<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>I've found a friend in Jesus, He's everything to me</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Praise of the Lord&amp;mdash;Satisfaction with Him</category>
  <numbers><english num="210"/><portuguese num="111"/><tagalog num="210"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="1838-1882" biolink="">Charles William Fry</author>
    <composer biodate="" biolink="">English melody</composer>
  </creators>
  <meter>Peculiar Meter.</meter>
  <hymncode>34556553121165</hymncode>
  <key>F Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - G7 | C - C/E - | F - C - | C - Am - | Dm - G7 - | C - C/E - | F - C - | C/G - G7 - | C - C7 - | F - - - | C - - - | Am - - - | Dm - G7 - | C - C/E - | F - C/E - | C/G - G7 - | C F/C C - |</chords>
  <melody>| 0 - - 3/( 4/) | 5/ 5/ 6/ 5/ 5/ 3 1/ | 2/ 1/ 1/ 6_./ 5_. 1/ 2/ | 3/ 3/ 3/ 3/ 6/ 5/ 5/ 3/ (break) | 2 - - 3/( 4/) | 5/ 5/ 6/ 5/ 5/( 3) 1/ | 2/ 1/ 1/ 6_./ 5_. 1/ 2/ | 3/ 5/ 3/ 1/ 2/ 4/ 3/ 2/ (break) | 1 - - 1 | 4/ 4/ 4/ 4/ 4/ 6 6/ | 6/ 5/ 5/ 3/ 5 3/( 2/) | 1/ 1/ 1/ 1/ 6/ 5/ 5/ 3/ (break) | 2 - - 3/ 4/ | 5/ 5/ 6/ 5/ 5/( 3) 1/ | 2/ 1/ 1/ 6_./ 5_. 1/ 2/ | 3/ 5/ 3/ 1/ 2/ 4/ 3/ 2/ | 1 - - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>I've found a friend in Je -- sus, He's ev -- ery -- thing to me, He's the fair -- est of ten thou -- sand to my soul; The Ap -- ple- -- tree of trees, in Him a -- lone I see All I need to cleanse and make me ful -- ly whole. In sor -- row He's my com -- fort, in trou -- ble He's my stay, He tells me ev -- ery care on Him to roll: He's the Ap -- ple- -- tree of trees, the Bright and Morn -- ing Star, He's the fair -- est of ten thou -- sand to my soul.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="group">hymnal-subj164.xml</link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midi location="h" length="46">e0210_i.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">I've found a friend in Jesus, He's everything to me,
  He's the fairest of ten thousand to my soul;
The Apple-tree of trees, in Him alone I see
  All I need to cleanse and make me fully whole.
In sorrow He's my comfort, in trouble He's my stay,
  He tells me every care on Him to roll:
He's the Apple-tree of trees, the Bright and Morning Star,
  He's the fairest of ten thousand to my soul.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">He all my griefs has taken, and all my sorrows borne;
  In temptation He's my strong and mighty tower;
I've all for Him forsaken, and all my idols torn
  From my heart, and now He keeps me by His power.
Though all the world forsake me, and Satan tempt me sore,
  Through Jesus I shall safely reach the goal:
He's the Apple-tree of trees, the Bright and Morning Star,
  He's the fairest of ten thousand to my soul.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">He'll never, never leave me, nor yet forsake me here,
  While I live by faith and do His blessed will;
A wall of fire about me, I've nothing now to fear,
  With His manna He my hungry soul shall fill.
Then sweeping up to glory to see His blessed face,
  Where rivers of delight shall ever roll:
He's the Apple-tree of trees, the Bright and Morning Star,
  He's the fairest of ten thousand to my soul.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
