<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Here, O my Lord, I see Thee face to face</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Praise of the Lord&amp;mdash;Remembrance of Him</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="180*"/><english num="225"/><korean num="180*"/><portuguese num="119"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="1808-1889" biolink="">Horatius Bonar</author>
    <composer biodate="1835-1909" biolink="">James Langran</composer>
  </creators>
  <meter>10.10.10.10.</meter>
  <hymncode>3123543321</hymncode>
  <key>F Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - - | C - C/E - | F - G7 - | C - F/C - | C - Am - | G/B - G - | C - D7 - | G - G7/F - | C/E - C - | G7/B - C - | C/E - F - | G - - - | C - C/E - | F - Dm - | C/G - G7 - | C - - - |</chords>
  <guitarChords>| C - - - | C - - - | G - G7 - | C - - - | C - - - | G - - - | D - D7 - | G - G7 - | C - - - | C - - - | C - - - | G - - - | C - - - | F - - - | G - G7 - | C - - - |</guitarChords>
  <melody>| 3 - 1 2 | 3 - 5 - | 4 3 3 2 | 1 - - - (break) | 3 - 3 2 | 5 - 2 - | 3 2 2 1 | 7_. - - - (break) | 1 - 1 1 | 4 - 3 - | 5. 3/ 2 1 | 7_. - - - (break) | 1 - 2 1 | 1 2 3 4 | 3 - 2 - | 1 - - - |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>Here, O my Lord, I see Thee face to face; Here faith can touch and han -- dle things un -- seen; Here would I grasp with firm -- er hand Thy grace, And all my wear -- i -- ness up -- on Thee lean.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="group">hymnal-subj163.xml</link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midi location="h" length="27">e0225_i.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Here, O my Lord, I see Thee face to face;
Here faith can touch and handle things unseen;
Here would I grasp with firmer hand Thy grace,
And all my weariness upon Thee lean.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Here would I feed upon the Bread of God;
Here drink with Thee the royal wine of heav'n;
Here would I lay aside each earthly load;
Here taste afresh the calm of sin forgiv'n.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">I have no help but Thine; nor do I need
Another arm save Thine to lean upon;
It is enough, my Lord, enough indeed;
My strength is in Thy might, Thy might alone.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">This is the hour of banquet and of song;
This is the heav'nly table spread for me;
Here let me feast, and, feasting, still prolong
The brief bright hour of fellowship with Thee.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">Too soon we rise; the symbols disappear;
The feast, though not the love, is past and gone;
The bread and wine remove, but Thou art here,
Nearer than ever still our Shield and Sun.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">Feast after feast thus comes and passes by,
Yet passing, points to the glad feast above,
Giving sweet foretastes of the festal joy,
The Lamb's great bridal-feast of bliss and love.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
