<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Abide with me! fast falls the eventide</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Longings&amp;mdash;For Fellowship with Christ</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="288"/><english num="370"/><korean num="288"/><portuguese num="187"/><russian num="74"/><tagalog num="370"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="1793-1847" biolink="">Henry Francis Lyte</author>
    <composer biodate="1823-1889" biolink="">William Henry Monk</composer>
  </creators>
  <meter>10.10.10.10.</meter>
  <hymncode>3321565543</hymncode>
  <key>E Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - G/B - | Am - C/E - | F - G7 - | C - - - | C - - - | F - C/E - | G/D - D7/A - | G - - - | C - G - | Am - C/E - | F - - - | Dm - - - | G - G7/B - | C - F - | C/G - G7 - | C - - - |</chords>
  <melody>| 3 - 3 2 | 1 - 5 - | 6 5 5 4 | 3 - - - (break) | 3 - 4 5 | 6 - 5 - | 4 2 3 4# | 5 - - - (break) | 3 - 3 2 | 1 - 5 - | 5 4 4 3 | 2 - - - (break) | 2 - 3 4 | 3 2 1 4 | 3 - 2 - | 1 - - - |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>A -- bide with me! fast falls the ev -- en -- tide; The dark -- ness deep -- ens; Lord, with me a -- bide! When oth -- er help -- ers fail and com -- forts flee, Help of the help -- less, oh, a -- bide with me.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="group">hymnal-subj129.xml</link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midi location="h" length="32">e0370_i.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Abide with me! fast falls the eventide;
The darkness deepens; Lord, with me abide!
When other helpers fail and comforts flee,
Help of the helpless, oh, abide with me.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Swift to its close ebbs out life's little day;
Earth's joys grow dim, its glories pass away;
Change and decay in all around I see;
O Thou who changest not, abide with me.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">Come not in terrors, as the King of kings;
But kind and good, with healing in Thy wings:
Tears for all woes, a heart for every plea;
Come, Friend of sinners, thus abide with me.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">I need Thy presence every passing hour:
What but Thy grace can foil the tempter's power?
Who like Thyself my guide and stay can be?
Through cloud and sunshine, oh, abide with me.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">I fear no foe, with Thee at hand to bless:
Ills have no weight, and tears no bitterness:
Where is death's sting? where, grave, thy victory?
I triumph still, if Thou abide with me.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
