<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>I take Thy promise, Lord, in all its length</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Experience of Christ&amp;mdash;Trusting Him</category>
  <numbers><english num="575"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="1853-1910" biolink="">Henry Legh Richmond Deck</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 1 - 2 3 | 4 - 3 - | 2 1 1 7_. | 1 - - - (break) | 3 - 4 5 | 6 - 5 - | 4 3 2 1 | 2 - - - (break) | 5 - 5 4 | 3 - 2 - | 3 5 5 4# | 5 - - - (break) | 3 - 2 1 | 7_. 1 2 4 | 3 - 2 - | 1 - - - |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>I take Thy prom -- ise, Lord, in all its length, And breadth and ful -- ness, as my dai -- ly strength; In -- to life's fu -- ture fear -- less I may gaze, For, Sav -- ior, Thou art with me all the days.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <copyright>Used by permission of Miss Elsie Deck</copyright>
  <links>
    <link type="group">hymnal-subj074.xml</link>
    <link type="relevant" category="nt" num="575"></link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midiref type="h" num="454"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">I take Thy promise, Lord, in all its length,
And breadth and fulness, as my daily strength;
Into life's future fearless I may gaze,
For, Savior, Thou art with me all the days.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Days may be coming fraught with loss and change,
New scenes surround my life and fancies strange;
I thank Thee that no day can ever break,
Savior, when Thou wilt leave me or forsake.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">There may be days of darkness and distress,
When sin has power to tempt, and care to press,
Yet in the darkest day I will not fear,
For, 'mid the shadows, Thou wilt still be near.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">Days there may be of joy and deep delight,
When earth seems fairest, and her skies most bright,
Then draw me closer to Thee, lest I rest
Elsewhere, my Savior, than upon Thy breast.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">And all the other days that make my life,
Marked by no special joy or grief or strife,
Days filled with quiet duties, trivial care,
Burdens too small for other hearts to share;</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">Spend Thou these days with me, all shall be Thine,
So shall the darkest hour with glory shine.
Then when these earthly years have passed away,
Let me be with Thee in the perfect day.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
