<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Resting on the faithfulness of Christ our Lord</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Experience of Christ&amp;mdash;Resting on Him</category>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="1836-1879" biolink="">Frances Ridley Havergal</author>
    <composer biodate="1849-1928" biolink="">Russell Kelso Carter</composer>
  </creators>
  <meter>11.11.11.11.</meter>
  <hymncode>5556543451166671176655</hymncode>
  <key>Bb Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - F/C - | C - C/E - | F - F/A - | C - G7 - | C - G/B - | Am - C/G - | F - G7 - | C F/C C - |</chords>
  <melody>| 5./ 5// 5./ 6// 5./ 4// 3./ 4// | 5 ._1 ._1 - (break) | 6./ 6// 6./ 7// ._1./ ._1// 7./ 6// | 6 5 5 - (break) | 5./ 5// 5./ 6// 5./ 4// 3./ 4// | 5 ._1 ._1 - (break) | ._3./ ._3// ._1./ ._1// ._2./ ._2// 7./ 7// | ._1 ._1 ._1 - |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>Rest -- ing on the faith -- ful -- ness of Christ our Lord, Rest -- ing on the ful -- ness of His own sure word, Rest -- ing on His wis -- dom, on His love and pow'r, Rest -- ing on His cov -- e -- nant from hour to hour.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="group">hymnal-subj072.xml</link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midi location="h" length="21">e0580_i.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Resting on the faithfulness of Christ our Lord,
Resting on the fulness of His own sure word,
Resting on His wisdom, on His love and pow'r,
Resting on His covenant from hour to hour.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Resting 'neath His guiding hand for untrack'd days,
Resting 'neath His shadow from the noontide rays,
Resting at the eventide beneath His wing,
In the glorious presence of our Savior King.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">Resting in the fortress while the foe is nigh,
Resting in the lifeboat while the waves roll high,
Resting in His chariot for the swift, glad race,
Resting, always resting, in His boundless grace.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">Resting in the pastures and beneath the Rock,
Resting by the waters where He leads His flock,
Resting, while we listen, at His glorious feet,
Resting in His very arms, oh, rest complete!</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">Resting and believing, let us onward press;
Resting on Himself, the Lord our righteousness;
Resting and rejoicing, let His saved ones sing,
Glory, glory, glory be to Christ our King!</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
