<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>What mystery, the Father, Son, and Spirit</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Experience of God&amp;mdash;By the Trinity</category>
  <numbers><cebuano num="608"/><chinese num="447"/><dutch num="76"/><english num="608"/><french num="124"/><german num="608"/><korean num="447"/><portuguese num="314"/><russian num="119"/><spanish num="287"/><tagalog num="608"/></numbers>
  <creators>
	<author biodate="1905-1997" biolink="www.witnesslee.org">Witness Lee</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 0 - 0/ 5/ 5/ 5/ | 3. 5/ 5/ 5/ 6/ 6/ | 4 6 0/ 6/ 6/ 6/ | 5. 3/ 5/ 5/ 4/ 4/ (break) | 3 - 0/ 5/ 5/ 5/ | 3. 5/ 5/ 5/ 6/ 6/ | 4 6 0/ 6/ 6/ 6/ | 5. 3/ 5/ 5/ 4/ 4/ (break) | 3 - 0/ (Chorus) 5/ 5/ ._1/ | ._3. ._2/ ._1/ 7/ ._1/ 6/ | 5 - 0/ ._1/ ._1/ 7/ | 2 - 0/ 4/ 6/ 5/ (break) | 3 - 0/ 5/ 5/ ._1/ | ._3. ._2/ ._1/ 7/ ._1/ 6/ | 5 - 0/ ._1/ 7/ ._1/ | ._2 - 0/ (.._3/ (.._4/ (.7/ | ._1 - 0 - |</melody>
  <layout>
	<singingstanza>What mys -- te -- ry, the Fath -- er, Son, and Spir -- it, In per -- son three, in sub -- stance all are one. How glo -- ri -- ous, this God our be -- ing en -- ters To be our all, thru Spir -- it in the Son! The Tri -- une God has now be -- come our all! How won -- der -- ful! How glo -- ri -- ous! This Gift di -- vine we nev -- er can ex -- haust! How ex -- cel -- lent! How mar -- vel -- ous!</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <links>
	<link type="group">hymnal-subj081.xml</link>
	<link type="lyrics" url="www.witness-lee-hymns.org/hymns/H0608.html">View Lyrics</link>
  </links>
  <music>
	<midiref type="h" num="17"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
	<stanza type="verse" number="1">What mystery, the Father, Son, and Spirit,
  In person three, in substance all are one.
How glorious, this God our being enters
  To be our all, thru Spirit in the Son!</stanza>
	<stanza type="chorus" number="">The Triune God has now become our all!
  How wonderful! How glorious!
This Gift divine we never can exhaust!
    How excellent! How marvelous!</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="2">How rich the source, the Father as the fountain,
  And all this wealth He wants man to enjoy!
O blessed fact, this vast exhaustless portion
  Is now for us forever to employ!</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="3">How wonderful, the Son is God's expression
  Come in the flesh to dwell with all mankind!
Redemption's work, how perfectly effective,
  That sinners we with God might oneness find.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="4">The Spirit is the Son's transfiguration
  Come into us as life the full supply.
Amazing fact, our spirit with the Spirit
  Now mingles and in oneness joins thereby!</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="5">How real it is that God is now the Spirit
  For us to touch, experience day by day!
Astounding fact, with God we are one spirit,
  And differ not in life in any way!</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
