<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>God the Lord has spoken, God has been unveiled</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Study of the Word&amp;mdash;The Function of the Word</category>
  <numbers><cebuano num="800"/><chinese num="580"/><english num="800"/><korean num="580"/><portuguese num="365"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="1905-1997" biolink="www.witnesslee.org">Witness Lee</author>
    <composer biodate="" biolink="">E. H. G. Sargent, adapted</composer>
  </creators>
  <meter>11.11.11.11.(T)</meter>
  <hymncode>33235323123</hymncode>
  <key>D Major</key>
  <time>6/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - G/B - - | Am - - C/G - - | F - - G - - | C - - - - - | C - - D7/A - - | G/B - - C - - | G/D - - D7 - - | G - - G7 - - | C/E - - F - - | C/E - - C - - | A/C# - - A7 - - | Dm - - Dm/C - - | G7/B - - G7 - - | C/E - - F - - | C/G - - G7 - - | C - - - - - |</chords>
  <melody>| 3 - 3 2# - 3 | 5 - 3 2 - 3 | 1 - - 2 - - | 3( - - 3) - - (break) | 3 - 4# 3 - 4# | 5 - 4# 5 - 6 | 7 - - 6 - - | 5( - - 5) - - (break) | ._1 - ._1 7 - 6 | 5 - 4 3 - 3 | 6 - - 5 - - | 4( - - 4) - - (break) | 4 - 4 3 - 2 | 5 - 3 1 - 2 | 3 - - 2 - - | 1( - - 1) - - |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>God the Lord has spok -- en, God has been un -- veiled; All His cha -- rac -- ter and per -- sons are ex -- pressed; Un -- to A -- dam's sons His mys -- tery is re -- vealed, Full -- y il -- lus -- trat -- ed and made man -- i -- fest.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="group">hymnal-subj192.xml</link>
    <link type="lyrics" url="www.witness-lee-hymns.org/hymns/H0800.html">View Lyrics</link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midi location="h" length="30">e0800_i.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">God the Lord has spoken, God has been unveiled;
All His character and persons are expressed;
Unto Adam's sons His mystery is revealed,
Fully illustrated and made manifest.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">God the Lord has spoken, and His heart disclosed,
That His Son should have pre-eminence in all,
That in His dear Son He might be glorified
Midst all His creation, either great or small.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">God the Lord has spoken, Christ has been revealed:
He is very God and yet is truly man;
He is all in all, in Him all things subsist,
Center and circumference of th' eternal plan.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">God the Lord has spoken, and His mystery shown,
Christ and His expression has His counsel willed:
Christ with all God's fulness as the glorious Head,
And the Church His Body, with His riches filled.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">God the Lord has spoken, and from heaven shown
That the triune God would blend with creature-man:
Father in the Son, the Son the Spirit is,
Dwelling in the Body to fulfill His plan.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">God the Lord has spoken, revelation giv'n
Of His vast creation and His lowly birth,
Of His great redemption and salvation full;
May His adoration ever fill the earth.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
