<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>In the stream! in the stream! let us work</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Service&amp;mdash;In the Stream</category>
  <numbers><cebuano num="909"/><chinese num="653"/><dutch num="45"/><english num="909"/><french num="169"/><german num="909"/><korean num="653"/><lsmyp num="266"/><portuguese num="423"/><russian num="431"/><spanish num="407"/><tagalog num="909"/></numbers>
  <creators>
	<author biodate="1905-1997" biolink="www.witnesslee.org">Witness Lee</author>
  </creators>
  <key>D Major</key>
  <melody>| 0 - - 3./ 4// | 5 5./ 5// 5 1/ 2/ | 3 3./ 3// 3 2/ 3/ | 4 4./ 3// 4 3/ 4/ (break) | 6 5./ 4#// (.5 3./ 4// | 5 5./ 5// 5 1/ 2/ | 3 3./ 3// 3 3/ 3/ | 2 5/ 5/ 4# 5/ 6/ (break) | 7 7./ 6// (.5 (Chorus) 3./ 4// | 5 - - ._1./ 3// | 2 - - 2./ 3// | 4 - - 5./ 4// (break) | 3 - - 3./ 4// | 5 - - ._1./ 7// | 6 - - 7 | ._1/ 5/ 6./ 4// 3 2 | 1 - - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
	<singingstanza>In the stream! in the stream! let us work for the Lord, By His mind, in His way, as re -- vealed in His Word; In the flow of His life let us work with His pow'r For His King -- dom and Church in the time of His hour. In the stream! in the stream! Let us work in the stream! In the stream! in the stream! We'll work as in the heav'n -- ly team!</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <links>
	<link type="lyrics" url="www.witness-lee-hymns.org/hymns/H0909.html">View Lyrics</link>
  </links>
  <music>
	<midiref type="h" num="895"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
	<stanza type="verse" number="1">In the stream! in the stream! let us work for the Lord,
By His mind, in His way, as revealed in His Word;
In the flow of His life let us work with His pow'r
For His Kingdom and Church in the time of His hour.</stanza>
	<stanza type="chorus" number="">In the stream! in the stream!
Let us work in the stream!
In the stream! in the stream!
  We'll work as in the heav'nly team!</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="2">In the stream! in the stream! let us work with the Lord
In the flow of the Spirit, as taught by His Word;
Never working by self, independent and free,
But in service related in full harmony.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="3">In the stream! in the stream! let us work in the Lord,
With the Church, with the saints, in the light of His Word;
Give the Word, life supply to the people in need,
Thus fulfilling God's plan, in His flow we'll proceed.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
