<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Christians, make haste, your mission high fulfilling</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Preaching of the Gospel&amp;mdash;Sending forth the Tidings</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="663"/><english num="918"/><korean num="663"/><tagalog num="918"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="1834-1923" biolink="">Mary Ann Thompson</author>
    <composer biodate="1837-1901" biolink="">James Walch</composer>
  </creators>
  <meter>11.10.11.10. with chorus.</meter>
  <hymncode>13455513221</hymncode>
  <key>Bb Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - - | C - - - | C - G - | Am - - - | F - - - | C/E - C - | G - G7/B - | C - - - | C - G7/D - | C/E - C - | E/B - E7 - | Am - - - | D - D7/C - | G/B - Em - | C - D7 - | G - - - | G7 - - - | C - - - | G7 - - - | C - - - | A7 - - - | Dm - Dm/F - | C/G - G7 - | C - - - |</chords>
  <melody>| ._1 - 3 4 | 5 - - 5 | 5 ._1 ._3 ._2 | ._2 - ._1 - | ._1 - 7 6 | 5 - - 5 | 7 6 5 4 | 3 - - - (break) | 3 - 4. 4#/ | 5 - - 5 | 5# 6 ._1 7 | 7 - 6 - | 6 - 7 ._1 | ._2 - 5 - | 7 6 5 4# | 5 - - - (break) | (Chorus) 7 - 6 5 | ._1 - 5 - | 7 - 6 5 | ._3 - - - | ._3 - ._4 ._3 | ._3( ._2) ._1 6 | 5 ._1 ._2. ._1/ | ._1 - 0 - |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>Christ -- ians, make haste, your mis -- sion high ful -- fill -- ing, To tell to all the world that God is Light, That He who made all na -- tions is not will -- ing One soul should pe -- rish, lost in shades of night. Pub -- lish glad tid -- ings, tid -- ings of peace; Tid -- ings of Je -- sus, re -- demp -- tion and re -- lease.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="group">hymnal-subj176.xml</link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midi location="h" length="40">e0918_i.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Christians, make haste, your mission high fulfilling,
  To tell to all the world that God is Light,
That He who made all nations is not willing
  One soul should perish, lost in shades of night.</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">Publish glad tidings, tidings of peace;
  Tidings of Jesus, redemption and release.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Behold how many thousands still are lying,
  Bound in the darksome prison-house of sin,
With none to tell them of the Savior's dying
  Or of the life He died for them to win.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">'Tis yours to save from peril of perdition
  The soul for whom the Lord His life laid down;
Beware lest, slothful to fulfill your mission,
  You lose one jewel that should deck His crown.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">Proclaim to every people, tongue, and nation
  That God, in whom they live and move, is love;
Tell how He stooped to save His lost creation,
  And died on earth that men He might approve.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">Give of your sons to bear the message glorious;
  Give of your wealth to speed them on their way;
Pour out your soul for them in prayer victorious,
  And all you spend our Savior will repay.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">He comes again; O brothers, ere you meet Him,
  Make known to every heart His saving grace;
Let none whom He hath ransomed fail to greet Him,
  Through your neglect unfit to see His face.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
