<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>I cannot tell why He, whom angels worship</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Preaching of the Gospel&amp;mdash;Myriads Won</category>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="1857-1932" biolink="">William Young Fullerton</author>
    <composer biodate="" biolink="">English tune</composer>
    <!--<composer biodate="" biolink="">Arranged by D. P. B.</composer>-->
  </creators>
  <meter>11.10.11.10.11.10.11.12.</meter>
  <hymncode>712323653216</hymncode>
  <key>C Major</key>
  <time>4/2</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - - C - - - | C - - - C - Am - | F - - - F - - - | Em - - - Am - C/G - | Dm/F - - - G7 - - - | C - - - C - C7 - | F - - - D7/F# - - - | C/G - Am - Dm - G7 - | C - F/C - C - G7 - | C - C/E - F - F/A - | C - - - C - G/B - | Am - C/G - F - Em - | Dm - D7/F# - G - G7/B - | C - C7/E - F - F/A - | C/G - Am - F - G7 - | C - Am - F - G7 - | C - F/C - C - - - |</chords>
  <guitarChords>| C - - - C - - - | C - - - C - - - | F - - - F - - - | C - - - C - - - | G - - - G - - - | C - - - C - C7 - | F - - - - - - - | C - - - G - - - | C - - - C - - - | C - - - F - - - | C - - - C - - - | C - - - F - - - | G - - - G - G7 - | C - - - F - - - | C - - - C - - - | C - - - G - G7 - | C - F - C - - - |</guitarChords>
  <melody>| 0 - - - 0 7_. 1 2 | 3 - - 2 3 6 5 3 | 2( 1) 6_. - - 1 3 4 | 5 - - 6 5 3 1 3 (break) | 2( - - - 2) 7_. 1 2 | 3 - - 2 3 6 5 3 | 2( 1) 6_. - - 7_. 1 2 | 3 - - 4 3 2 1 2 (break) | 1( - - - 1) 5 6 7 | ._1 - - 7 7 6 5 3 | 5( 3) 1 - - 5 6 7 | ._1 - - 7 7 6 5 3 (break) | 2( - - - 2) 5 5 5 | ._3 - - ._2 ._2 ._1 6 ._1 | 5( 3) 1 - - 7_. 1 2 | 3 (.6 5 3 2 1 6_. 7_. | 1( - - - 1) 0 - - |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>I can -- not tell why He, whom an -- gels wor -- ship, Should set His love up -- on the sons of men, Or why, as Sheph -- erd, He should seek the wan -- d'rers, To bring them back, they know not how or when. But this I know, that He was born of Ma -- ry, When Beth -- l'hem's man -- ger was His on -- ly home, And that He lived at Naz -- a -- reth and la -- bored, And so the Sav -- ior, Sav -- ior of the world, is come.</singingstanza>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <copyright>Used by permission of The Carey Kingsgate Press Ltd.</copyright>
  <music>
    <midi location="h" length="76">e0934_i.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">I cannot tell why He, whom angels worship,
  Should set His love upon the sons of men,
Or why, as Shepherd, He should seek the wand'rers,
  To bring them back, they know not how or when.
But this I know, that He was born of Mary,
  When Bethl'hem's manger was His only home,
And that He lived at Nazareth and labored,
  And so the Savior, Savior of the world, is come.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">I cannot tell how silently He suffered,
  As with His peace He graced this place of tears,
Or how His heart upon the Cross was broken,
  The crown of pain to three and thirty years.
But this I know, He heals the broken-hearted,
  And stays our sin, and calms our lurking fear,
And lifts the burden from the heavy laden,
  For yet the Savior, Savior of the world, is here.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">I cannot tell how He will win the nations,
  How He will claim His earthly heritage,
How satisfy the needs and aspirations
  Of east and west, of sinner and of sage.
But this I know, all flesh shall see His glory,
  And He shall reap the harvest He has sown,
And some glad day His sun shall shine in splendor
  When He the Savior, Savior of the world, is known.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">I cannot tell how all the lands shall worship,
  When, at His bidding, every storm is stilled,
Or who can say how great the jubilation
  When all the hearts of men with love are filled.
But this I know, the skies will thrill with rapture,
  And myriad, myriad human voices sing,
And earth to heaven, and heaven to earth, will answer:
  At last the Savior, Savior of the world, is King.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
