<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>God's Kingdom today is a real exercise</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>The Kingdom&amp;mdash;As an Exercise and a Reward</category>
  <numbers><cebuano num="947"/><chinese num="751"/><english num="947"/><german num="947"/><korean num="751"/><portuguese num="476"/><russian num="292"/><spanish num="431"/><tagalog num="947"/></numbers>
  <creators>
	<author biodate="1905-1997" biolink="www.witnesslee.org">Witness Lee</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 0 - 3./( 4//) | 5 5 6./( 7//) | ._1 ._1 7./( ._1//) | ._2 ._1 6 (break) | 5 - 5./ 5// | 5 6 7 | ._1 ._2 ._3 | ._3 ._2 ._1 (break) | ._2 - ._3./ ._2// | ._1 ._1 ._1./( 7//) | 6 6 6 | ._2 ._2 ._3 (break) | ._2 - ._2./ ._2// | ._3 ._2 ._3 | ._4 ._3 ._2 | ._1 7 ._2 | ._1 - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
	<singingstanza>God's King -- dom to -- day is a real ex -- er -- cise, But when Christ comes to reign it will be a great prize; It is wis -- dom di -- vine that we now may be trained That His plan be ful -- filled and His jus -- tice main -- tained.</singingstanza>
	<columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <links>
	<link type="lyrics" url="www.witness-lee-hymns.org/hymns/H0947.html">View Lyrics</link>
  </links>
  <music>
	<midiref type="h" num="162"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
	<stanza type="verse" number="1">God's Kingdom today is a real exercise,
But when Christ comes to reign it will be a great prize;
It is wisdom divine that we now may be trained
That His plan be fulfilled and His justice maintained.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="2">God's children, we're born to be kings with His Son,
And we need to be trained that we may overcome
And to know how to rule in His kingdom as kings,
That His kingship thru us be expressed o'er all things.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="3">Today we must learn to submit to His throne,
How to have a strict life and His government own;
His authority then we'll be able to share,
O'er the nations to rule with God's Son as the heir.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="4">With a life strict to self we must righteousness hold,
Kind to others in peace, and with God joyful, bold;
In the Kingdom's reality e'er to remain,
For its manifestation prepared thus to reign.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="5">Then Christ when He comes with the kingdom from God
Will to us grant His kingship to share as reward;
Thus the Lord will His righteousness thru us maintain
And His wisdom to heavenly powers make plain.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="6">For this the Apostle pressed on at all cost,
For the Kingdom assured that he would not be lost;
'Tis for this he charged others, Be true to the Lord.
That the Kingdom might be unto them a reward.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="7">O Lord, give us grace for Thy Kingdom to live,
To be trained that Thou may the reward to us give;
Make the Kingdom's reality our exercise,
That its manifestation may be our great prize.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
