<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>There are two lines to live by in our living today</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Experience of God&amp;mdash;As Life</category>
  <creators>
    <composer biodate="1879-1939" biolink="">Herbert Buffum</composer>
  </creators>
  <meter>Peculiar Meter.</meter>
  <hymncode>5533321135535</hymncode>
  <key>D Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - - | C - G/B - | Am - C/G - | F - Em - | Dm - G - | C - G - | C - F - | F/A - C - | G7 - C - | C - F/C - | C - - - | C - Am - | Dm - G - | C - G - | C - F - | F/A - C - | G7 - C - |</chords>
  <melody>| 0 - - 5/ 5/ | 3/ 3 3/ 2/ 1/ 1/ 3/ | 5/ 5 3/ 5 5/ 5/ | 6/ ._1 6/ 5/ 3/ 2/ 1/ (break) | 3/ 2 3/ 2 5/ 5/ | 3/ 3 3/ 2/ 1/ 1/ 3/ | 5 5 6 6/ 7/ | ._1/ ._1 6/ 5/ 3/ 2/ 1/ (break) | 3/ 3 2/ (.1 (Chorus) 5/ 5/ | ._1/ ._1 ._1/ 6/ 5/ 3/ 4/ | 5/ 5 6/ 5 5/ 5/ | ._1/ ._1 ._1/ 6/ 5/ 3/ 1/ (break) | 3/ 2 3/ 2 5/ 5/ | 3/ 3 3/ 2/ 1/ 1/ 3/ | 5 5 6 6/ 7/ | ._1/ ._1 6/ 5/ 3/ 2/ 1/ | 3/ 3 2/ 1 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>There are two lines to live by in our liv -- ing to -- day&amp;mdash; One the life line to bring us in -- to Christ all the way. But the oth -- er is know -- ledge which will make us die; We must be ver -- y care -- ful on which line we a -- bide. Oh, we'll stay on God's life line, nev -- er turn -- ing a -- side. We don't care for vain know -- ledge, which will cause us to die. Lord, we'll touch You by call -- ing on Your name each day; Liv -- ing in Your ap -- pear -- ing, in Your pre -- sence we'll stay.</singingstanza>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="group">hymnal-subj075.xml</link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midi location="h" length="40">e1194_i.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">There are two lines to live by in our living today&amp;mdash;
One the life line to bring us into Christ all the way.
But the other is knowledge which will make us die;
We must be very careful on which line we abide.</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">Oh, we'll stay on God's life line, never turning aside.
We don't care for vain knowledge, which will cause us to die.
Lord, we'll touch You by calling on Your name each day;
Living in Your appearing, in Your presence we'll stay.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Lord, we would be as Abel, fully contacting You;
Not by knowledge or concept, but by life fresh and new.
Just as Enosh began to call upon Your name,
And as Enoch who walked with You, we'll do just the same.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">Keep us living and walking as did old Abraham;
In Your holy appearing to be transfused like him.
As did Isaac and Jacob, Moses lived this way&amp;mdash;
So dependent upon Your presence with him each day.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">Full enjoyment had David, ate the life-giving tree.
Daniel prayed to his God and lived by Him constantly.
Jesus lived by the Father to be life complete;
Now as His living Body of the life tree we'll eat.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
