<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>When Noah worked upon the ark as God to</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>The Church&amp;mdash;As the Ark of Noah</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="ts:537"/><english num="1268"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="">Adapted</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 0 - - 0/ 5/ | ._3./ ._3// ._3./ ._2// ._1./ ._1// 7./ ._1// (break) | ._2./ ._1// 6./ ._1// 5. 5/ | ._3./ ._3// ._3./ ._2// ._1./ ._1// 7./ ._1// (break) | ._2./ ._2// ._2./ ._3// ._2. 5/ | ._3./ ._3// ._3./ ._2// ._1./ ._1// 7./ ._1// (break) | ._2./ ._1// 6./ ._1// 5. 5/ | 6./ 6// 7./ 7// ._1./ ._1// ._2./ ._2// (break) | ._3./ ._2// ._1./ 7// (.._1 (Chorus) 5 | ._1( - ._1./) 5// ._1./ 7// | 6 6 - 6 | ._2( - ._2./) 6// ._2./ ._1// (break) | 7 - - 5 | ._3( - ._3./) ._2// ._1./ 7// | ._2 ._1 7 6 | 5/ ._1. ._1 7 | ._1 - - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>When No -- ah worked up -- on the ark as God to him de -- creed. So man -- y oth -- ers watched, yet to his words they gave no heed. But No -- ah heard the voice of God and did His word o -- bey; His bus -- iness was to build the ark; he could -- n't waste a day. Now Je -- sus' test -- i -- mon -- y, we in the church -- es see The ark of test -- i -- mon -- y built in each lo -- cal -- i -- ty.</singingstanza>
    <globalstaffsize>15</globalstaffsize>
    <topmargin>0.25</topmargin>
    <bottommargin>0.25</bottommargin>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="ref">Genesis 6-8</link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midiref type="h" num="1152"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">When Noah worked upon the ark as God to him decreed.
So many others watched, yet to his words they gave no heed.
But Noah heard the voice of God and did His word obey;
His business was to build the ark; he couldn't waste a day.</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">Now Jesus' testimony, we in the churches see
  The ark of testimony built in each locality.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">The generation at that time was evil and perverse;
The wickedness upon the earth was waxing worse and worse.
But Noah stood against the age and ne'er the vision lost.
The ark of testimony must be built at any cost.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">There were at that time many men who said they worshipped God;
They served Him and they sacrificed and yet 'twas very odd,
The very thing that God desired they mocked and ridiculed.
Their heart was set upon this age and by the devil ruled.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">One day the ark was finished and eight souls were led aboard.
God shut the door and then the heavens opened and outpoured.
It rained, but Noah took no thought for he was safe inside.
When all the earth was flooded, he above it all did ride.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">The ark was just God's testimony on the earth that time.
For God had found a corporate man through whom His light could shine.
He needed something built through which He'd fully be expressed,
And now it is the local church where God is manifest.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">Be careful lest this age would lead you from God's heart's desire.
For Jesus' testimony must set all our hearts afire.
The local churches are the ark, God's testimony true.
For this we leave the age behind and give our hearts anew.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
