<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>We're the river-crossers, Hebrews is our name</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>The Church&amp;mdash;The Overcomers</category>
  <numbers><english num="1271"/><korean num="981"/><portuguese num="401"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="">Adapted</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 6_./ 7_./ 1/ 2/ 3 3 | 4/ 3/ 4/ 6/ 3 - | 2 2/ 3/ 1 1 | 7_./ 6_./ 7_./ 1/ 6_.. 0/ (break) | 6_./ 7_./ 1/ 2/ 3 3 | 4/ 3/ 4/ 6/ 3 - | 2 2/ 3/ 1 1 | 7_./ 6_./ 7_./ 1/ 6_. - (break) | 6_. 6/ 6/ 6 6 | 5/ 6/ 5/ 4/ 3 - | 6_. 6/ 6/ 6 6 | 5/ 6/ 5/ 4/ 3 - (break) | 2 2/ 3/ 1 1 | 2/ 3/ 4/ 6/ 3 - | 2 2/ 3/ 1 1 | 7_./ 6_./ 7_./ 1/ 6_. 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>We're the riv -- er- -- cross -- ers, He -- brews is our name; Crossed the Eu -- phrat -- es, i -- dols all are slain. En -- tered in -- to Ca -- naan, left the oth -- er side; Seek -- ing a ci -- ty, which shall e'er a -- bide. We are the He -- brews, that's our re -- al name; We've crossed the riv -- er, we are not the same. Build -- ing God's house that He may dwell on earth, Build -- ing God's house that He may dwell on earth.</singingstanza>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="group">hymnal-subj212.xml</link>
    <link type="relevant" category="nt" num="1271"></link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midiref type="h" num="1222"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">We're the river-crossers, Hebrews is our name;
Crossed the Euphrates, idols all are slain.
Entered into Canaan, left the other side;
Seeking a city, which shall e'er abide.
  We are the Hebrews, that's our real name;
  We've crossed the river, we are not the same.
  Building God's house that He may dwell on earth,
  Building God's house that He may dwell on earth.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">We were bound in Egypt, building for the foe;
God of the Hebrews said, "Let My people go!"
We have crossed the Red Sea, reached the other side;
Pharaoh, his army, perished in the tide.
  God of the Hebrews, speak again today;
  God of the Hebrews, lead us all the way.
  Save all Your people from this crooked age,
  Save all Your people from this crooked age.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">We're released, and now we build the house of God;
His tabernacle is our true abode.
Forty years of oldness left in Jordan's tide,
Fight we for Canaan on the kingdom side.
  Salvation's Captain sounds the trump of war;
  City by city, take we more and more,
  To gain His kingdom, enter into rest,
  To gain His kingdom, enter into rest.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">What was once God-given soon a form became;
Then John the Baptist did God's word proclaim&amp;mdash;
Make another crossing, God is going on;
Judaism's over; listen to My Son!
  Turn from the prophets, turn unto the Son;
  He's My Beloved, He and I are one;
  His Word will save you to the uttermost,
  His Word will save you to the uttermost.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">Now we're overcomers on the sea of glass;
This final crossing will forever last.
Sing the song of Moses, make the praise complete,
Look! All our enemies beneath our feet.
  We're overcomers, that's our real name.
  God has His city; Satan gets the shame.
  God is our portion for eternity,
  God is our portion for eternity.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
