<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>The wedding feast, the peak of man's enjoyment</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Gospel&amp;mdash;General</category>
  <numbers><english num="1329"/><german num="1329"/><korean num="933"/><lsmyp num="312"/><russian num="185"/></numbers>
  <creators>
	<author biodate="" biolink="">Adapted</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 0 - 0/ 3/ 3/ 2/ | 1. 2/ 3/ 5/ 6/ 3/ | 5 4. 4/ 4/ 3/ | 2. 3/ 4/ 5/ 2/ 4/ (break) | 3 - 0/ 1/ 1/ 1/ | 3b. 3b/ 3b/ 3b/ 2/ 1/ | 3 3 0/ 5/ ._1/ 3/ | 5. 3/ 4/ 4/ 3/ 2/ (break) | 1( - 1/) (Chorus) 5/ 6/ 3/ | 4. 5/ 7/ 6/ 5/ 4/ | 3 5 0/ 5/ 6/ 3/ | 4. 5/ 7/ 6/ 5/ 6/ (break) | 3( - 3/) 1/ 3/ 5/ | ._1. 3/ 3/ 3/ 4/ 5/ | 7 6. 6/ ._1/ 2/ | 5. 3/ 4/ 4/ 3/ 2/ | 1( - 1/) 0. |</melody>
  <layout>
	<singingstanza>The wed -- ding feast, the peak of man's en -- joy -- ment Was full of plea -- sure till the wine ran dry. The hu -- man life, like wine, is soon ex -- haust -- ed, Till Je -- sus comes, di -- vine life to sup -- ply. When Je -- sus comes, new wine is made from wa -- ter, When Je -- sus comes, the dark -- ness turns to light. He touch -- es death&amp;mdash; it's turned to life e -- ter -- nal, Weak -- ness to strength and blind -- ness in -- to sight.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <links>
	<link type="group">hymnal-subj098.xml</link>
	<link type="ref">John 2-11</link>
  </links>
  <music>
	<midiref type="h" num="1078"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
	<stanza type="verse" number="1">The wedding feast, the peak of man's enjoyment
Was full of pleasure till the wine ran dry.
The human life, like wine, is soon exhausted,
Till Jesus comes, divine life to supply.</stanza>
	<stanza type="chorus" number="">When Jesus comes, new wine is made from water,
When Jesus comes, the darkness turns to light.
He touches death&amp;mdash;it's turned to life eternal,
  Weakness to strength and blindness into sight.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="2">One night a moral righteous man, a ruler
To Jesus came, more teaching to pursue;
But teachings ne'er could change the fallen nature,
So Jesus said, "You must be born anew."</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="3">"I have no husband," sighed the thirsty sinner.
Indeed her many husbands left her dry.
Daily she came to draw the failing water
Till Jesus came, her thirst to satisfy.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="4">A man among the multitude lay helpless,
So weak while waiting till the water stirred.
Religion of the law could never heal him;
Then Jesus came and spoke the living word.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="5">Within the tomb, four days and nights he lay there,
Death's grip had come; they 'round the grave did weep.
Silent he lay, all bound and wrapped in grave clothes;
Then Jesus came, and woke him from his sleep.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="6">And still today, this Jesus is so living,
Able to save from death in any form.
Now open up your heart and call upon Him;
To you He'll come, in spirit you'll be born.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
