<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>The working of the Triune God</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Ultimate Manifestation&amp;mdash;God's Eternal Purpose</category>
  <melody>| 0 - 5_. | 1 1 2 | 3 3 2 | 1 2 7_. | 1 - 1 | 4 4 4 | 3 3 2 | 1 7_. 1 | 2 - 5_. (break) | 3 3 2 | 1 1 2/( 3/) | 4 4 3 | 2 - 2 | 5 5/( 4/) 3/( 4/) | 5 3 1 | 2( 1) 7_. | 1( - - | 1) - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>God's e -- co -- no -- my is to have God and man In -- cor -- po -- rat -- ed as one&amp;mdash; di -- vine- -- hu -- man, To build up His Bo -- dy&amp;mdash; an or -- ga -- ni -- sm, Which con -- sum -- mates the New Je -- ru -- sa -- lem.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <notes>Banner song for the 1997 Yearend West Malaysia Youth Training. Subject: "The Working of the Triune God on the Three Sections of the Life of a Corporate Person for the Fulfillment of His Eternal Economy."</notes>
  <links>
    <link type="relevant" category="h" num="278"></link>
    <link type="ref">Genesis 12-50</link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midiref type="h" num="278"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">God's economy is to have God and man
Incorporated as one&amp;mdash;divine-human,
To build up His Body&amp;mdash;an organism,
Which consummates the New Jerusalem.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">God the Father loves man and chooses man
In eternity past, in His great plan,
According to His purpose, and not of works
But of Him, in the section of Jacob.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">God the Father calls man and justifies man
In time, in the section of Abraham;
That man may live by faith, know grace from within
That man may live in fellowship with Him.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">God the Son gives man His rich inheritance,
And a life enjoying His abundance,
And a life in peace, totally without lack&amp;mdash;
Fully blessed, in the section of Isaac.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">God the Spirit transforms man and causes man
To be mature in life, enabling man
To bless and supply all, and rule o'er the earth,
In the section of Jacob with Joseph.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
