<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>The Lord has put me in the Body</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>The Church&amp;mdash;As Christ's Body</category>
  <hymncode>555556554</hymncode>
  <key>D Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>115</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - - | C - C/E - | F - - - | C - Am - | Dm - G7 - | C - C/E - | F - - - | C/G - G - | C - - - | G - G/B - | C - - - | G - G/B - | C - - - | G - G/B - | C - - - | G/D - D7 - | G - - - |</chords>
  <melody>| 0 - - 0/ 5/ | 5. 5/ 5/ 5/ 6/ 5/ | 5/ 4.( 4) - | 5/ 5/ 5/ 5/ 5/ 5/ 5/ 3/ | 2 - - 0/ 5/ | 5/ 5/ 5/ 5/ 5/ 5// 5// 6/ 5/ | 5/ 4.( 4.) 5/ | 5/ 5/ 5/ 3/ 2/ 2/ 3/ 2/ | 1 - - 0/ 3/ | 2/ 2/ 2/ 2/ 5/ 5/ 6/ 5/ | 5/ 3.( 3.) 3/ | 2/ 2/ 2/ 2/ 5/ 5/ 6/ 5/ | 3 - - 0/ 3/ | 2/ 2/ 2/ 2/ 5/ 5/ 6/ 5/ | 5/ 3.( 3.) 3/ | 2/ 2/ 2/ 2/ 4#/ 4#/ 5/ 6/ | 5 - - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>The Lord has put me in the Bod -- y, He has made a mem -- ber out of me; I'm leav -- ing all the things on the tree of knowl -- edge, And learn -- ing how to eat the liv -- ing tree. Well now I'm tak -- ing in much more of Je -- sus! He's put me on His farm here just to grow, We're on -- ly here be -- cause we love our Je -- sus, We stand as ONE so all the world will know.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midi location="ns" length="34">ns0076.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">The Lord has put me in the Body,
He has made a member out of me;
I'm leaving all the things on the tree of knowledge,
And learning how to eat the living tree.
Well now I'm taking in much more of Jesus!
He's put me on His farm here just to grow,
We're only here because we love our Jesus,
We stand as ONE so all the world will know.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">The Lord doesn't need more individuals,
He's got too many now, it's plain to see;
All He wants is One New Man forever,
And that doesn't leave any room for you and me.
The only way that we'll be one is Jesus!
The only way for Him to gather us,
Is by our EATING, DRINKING, BREATHING JESUS!
Until His riches overflow in us!</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">The Lord has put me in the church life,
Christ and the church, His image to express;
He's chosen me according to His purpose,
And won't be satisfied with something less.
The only way that we'll be one is Jesus!
The only way for Him to gather us,
Is by our EATING, DRINKING, BREATHING JESUS!
Until His riches overflow in us!</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
