<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Father, I know that all my life</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Experience of God&amp;mdash;Obedience to His Will</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="305"/><english num="ns:12"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="">Anna Laetitia Waring</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 0 - - 0 - 5_. | 3 - 3 3( 2) 3 | 4 - 2 7_. - 5_. | 1 - 1 1( 7_.) 1 (break) | 2( - - 2) - 2/ 2/ | 2 - 2 2( 3) 4 | 5 - 5 6_. - 2 | 1 - 1 2( 1) 2 (break) | 3( - - 3) - 3/ 3/ | 3( 2) 2 2( 3) 4 | 5 - ._1 6( 4) 2 | 1 - 1 3 - 2 | 1( - - 1) - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>Fa -- ther, I know that all my life is por -- tioned out for me, And the chang -- es that are sure to come I do not fear to see; But I ask Thee for a pre -- sent mind in -- tent on pleas -- ing Thee.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <notes>Very little is known about the author of this hymn, because of her remarkably retiring disposition. She was Anna Laetitia Waring, and was born in Neath, a town of South Wales, in 1820. In 1850 she published her "Hymns and Meditations," and in 1858 she published "Additional Hymns." It is believe that she was a Friend, and that her life was full of suffering and pain. Hymn #305 in the Chinese Hymnal is a translation of this hymn by Watchman Nee.</notes>
  <links>
    <link type="relevant" category="h" num="661"></link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midiref type="h" num="661"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Father, I know that all my life is portioned out for me,
And the changes that are sure to come I do not fear to see;
But I ask Thee for a present mind intent on pleasing Thee.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">I ask Thee for a thoughtful love, through constant watching wise,
To meet the glad with joyful smiles, and to wipe the weeping eyes;
And a heart at leisure from itself, to soothe and sympathize.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">I would not have the restless will that hurries to and fro,
Seeking for some great thing to do or secret thing to know;
I would be treated as a child, and guided where I go.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">Wherever in the world I am, in whatso'er estate,
I have a fellowship with hearts to keep and cultivate;
And a work of lowly love to do for the Lord on whom I wait.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">So I ask Thee for the daily strength, to none that ask denied,
And a mind to blend with outward life while keeping at Thy side;
Content to fill a little space, if Thou be glorified.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">And if some things I do not ask in my cup of blessing be,
I would have my spirit filled the more with grateful love to Thee,
More careful, not to serve Thee much, but to please Thee perfectly.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="7">There are briers besetting every path that call for patient care;
There is a cross in every lot, and an earnest need for prayer;
But a lowly heart that leans on Thee is happy anywhere.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="8">In a service which Thy will appoints there are no bonds for me;
For my inmost heart is taught "the truth" that makes Thy children "free"
And a life of self-renouncing love is a life of liberty.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
