<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Christ has come to be life</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Various Aspects of the Inner Life&amp;mdash;The Fellowship of Life</category>
  <numbers><english num="ns:149"/><lsmyp num="166"/><vsb num="33"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Philip Bradley">P. B.</author>
    <composer biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Philip Bradley">P. B.</composer>
  </creators>
  <hymncode>11653123334321</hymncode>
  <key>Bb Major</key>
  <time>6/8</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C. F/C. | C. F/C. | C. F/C. | C. F/C. | C. F/C. | C. F/C. | C. F/C. | C - - | G/B. G. | F. C. | G. G/B. | F. C. | F - - | Dm - - | D. D7/F#. | G. G7. | C. F/C. | C. F/C. | C. F/C. | C. F/C. | C. F/C. | C. F/C. | C. F/C. | C - - | Am. G/B. | C. Am. | F. G. | C. Am. | F. C. | G. F. | C/E. Dm. | G. Am. | F. C. | G7. C. | F/C. C. |</chords>
  <melody>| ._1. ._1. | 6/ 5/ 3/ 1 2/ | 3/ 3/ 3/ 4 3// 2// | 1 - - | ._1. ._1. | 6/ 5/ 3/ 1 2/ | 3/ 3/ 3/ 4/ 3/ 2/ | 1. 0/ 7/ ._1/ | ._2.( ._2/) ._3/ ._2/ | ._1// ._1./ ._1/ 5 7// ._1// | ._2/ ._2/ ._2/ ._2// ._3./ ._2/ | ._1/ ._1/ ._1/ 5 5/ | 6/ 6/ 6/ 6/ 6/ 6/ | 6.( 6) 6/ | 6/ 6/ 6/ 6/ 7/ ._1/ | ._2. ._3( ._2/) | ._1. 6. | ._1// ._1./ ._1/ 6 6// 7// | ._1/ ._1/ ._1/ ._2// ._1./ 7/ | ._1 - - | ._1. 6. | ._1// ._1./ ._1/ 6 6// 7// | ._1/ ._1/ ._1/ ._2// ._1./ 7/ (break) | ._1. 0/ (Chorus) ._1/ 7/ | 6. 5 4/ | 3. 3 3/ | 4 4/ 5 7/ | ._1. ._1. | ._1. ._1/ ._1/ ._2/ | ._2. ._1. | ._1. ._1/ ._1/ ._2/ | ._2 ._3// ._2// ._1.( | ._1) ._3// ._2// ._1/ ._1/ ._1/ | ._2/ ._1/( 7/) ._1.( | ._1) - - |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>Christ has come to be life, the pro -- cessed di -- vine Trin -- i -- ty. God the Fa -- ther's the source, a foun -- tain e -- merg -- ing to be. God the Son as a gush -- ing up spring, And the Spir -- it's a riv -- er for life im -- part -- ing Oh how can this mir -- a -- cle be? The Tri -- une God flow -- ing in me! Oh, I've got riv -- ers of life flow -- ing out of my in -- ner -- most being! I've got riv -- ers of life flow -- ing out of my in -- ner -- most being! As this life flows through me, I'm sup -- plied a -- bun -- dant -- ly. His life nul -- li -- fies sin! Power springs now from with -- in! To be free, o -- ver -- com -- ing spon -- ta -- neous -- ly.</singingstanza>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midi location="ns" length="79">ns0149.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Christ has come to be life, the processed divine Trinity.
God the Father's the source, a fountain emerging to be.
God the Son as a gushing up spring,
And the Spirit's a river for life imparting
Oh how can this miracle be? The Triune God flowing in me!
Oh, I've got rivers of life flowing out of my innermost being!
I've got rivers of life flowing out of my innermost being!</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">As this life flows through me, I'm supplied abundantly.
His life nullifies sin! Power springs now from within!
To be free, overcoming spontaneously.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Yet this life though it frees, is not meant for mere victory.
God is full of intent and never could flow aimlessly.
So this life has a totality, a consummate issue encompassing me.
Life moves and life grows, life shapes as it flows
Now I share in this life's destiny.
Oh, I've got rivers of life flowing out of my innermost being!
I've got rivers of life flowing out of my innermost being!</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">We'll abide mutually, God and man revealed to be
Lamb, Wife, Spirit, and Bride.
Come! Drink! And riverside, 
Grows the tree, our enjoyment for eternity!</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">So I've no cause to frown as one who's received this zoe.
I know life runs its course and triumphs inevitably.
I'm required just to stay in the flow, 
If I do the drinking then God gives the growth.
So there's joy in my heart, and a spring in my step, 
And a smile on my face as I sing,
Oh, I've got rivers of life flowing out of my innermost being!
I've got rivers of life flowing out of my innermost being!</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
