<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Two Greatest Prayers of Paul</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Prayer&amp;mdash;The Meaning</category>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Chao-Chun Liu">C. C. L.</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 0 - - 5/ 5/ | 3/ 3 3/ 2/ 1/ 1/ 3/ | 5/ 5 3/ 5 5/ 5/ | 6/ ._1 6/ 5/ 3/ 2/ 1/ (break) | 3/ 2 3/ 2 5/ 5/ | 3/ 3 3/ 2/ 1/ 1/ 3/ | 5 5 6 6/ 7/ | ._1/ ._1 6/ 5/ 3/ 2/ 1/ (break) | 3/ 3 2/ (.1 (Chorus) 5/ 5/ | ._1/ ._1 ._1/ 6/ 5/ 3/ 4/ | 5/ 5 6/ 5 5/ 5/ | ._1/ ._1 ._1/ 6/ 5/ 3/ 1/ (break) | 3/ 2 3/ 2 5/ 5/ | 3/ 3 3/ 2/ 1/ 1/ 3/ | 5 5 6 6/ 7/ | ._1/ ._1 6/ 5/ 3/ 2/ 1/ | 3/ 3 2/ 1 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>There are two great -- est pray -- ers we must pray ev -- ery -- day, For which Paul the a -- pos -- tle taught us in Eph -- e -- sians, One in chap -- ter one and the oth -- er, chap -- ter three, One for vi -- sion and the oth -- er for ex -- pe -- ri -- ence. Grant us spir -- it of wis -- dom and of rev -- e -- la -- tion, Strength -- en us, Lord, with pow -- er in -- to our in -- ner man, Your e -- con -- o -- my then may be -- come our vi -- sion, And You may make home in our hearts to ful -- fill Your plan.</singingstanza>
    <globalstaffsize>15</globalstaffsize>
    <topmargin>0.25</topmargin>
    <bottommargin>0.25</bottommargin>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="ref">Ephesians 1:17-23</link>
    <link type="ref">Ephesians 3:14-21</link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midiref type="h" num="1194"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">There are two greatest prayers we must pray everyday,
For which Paul the apostle taught us in Ephesians,
One in chapter one and the other, chapter three,
One for vision and the other for experience.</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">Grant us spirit of wisdom and of revelation,
Strengthen us, Lord, with power into our inner man,
Your economy then may become our vision,
And You may make home in our hearts to fulfill Your plan.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">We have prayed for our many concerns, worries, and plans,
We have prayed for our heart's desire and so many aims,
We have prayed for good meetings and our gospel friends,
Now let's rise up and pray prayers that would turn this age!</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">Two millennia have gone by Christians countless as sands,
God's economy yet a mystery hidden to man,
Many zealous yet with no vision, no restraint,
Who would kneel down and pray to see God's central vision?</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">What's God's calling and glory of His inheritance?
What's the surpassing greatness of His power fourfold?
What's the transmission of Christ as Head to the church?
What's His Body, His fullness while He fills all in all?</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">To see vision we need to pray for four elements,
Wisdom to know and revelation of the objects,
Light for illumination and our eyes opened,
God's economy then shall be a vision so clear.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">With the vision we must not be proud or be content,
Lest as Laodicea soon we lukewarm become,
Empty knowledge would only make you poor, blind, naked,
"Buy gold, garments and eyesalve!" &amp;mdash; this' how we overcome!</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="7">What're Christ's unsearchable riches Paul as gospel proclaimed?
What're the breadth, length, height, depth of Christ we shall apprehend?
What's the knowledge-surpassing love of Christ to know?
What's to be filled with all the fullness of God fore'er?</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="8">Thus we all must pursue to gain the experience,
E'en as Mary wouldn't let go till the Lord manifest'd,
Look how Paul ran his race to gain Christ till the end,
Let us forget all things and press on to Christ ahead.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="9">For experience we must pray to be strengthened always,
That from soul into spirit we would turn and remain,
Only when we're in spirit can Christ have a way,
From our spirit to make His home in our hearts through faith.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="10">Seeing the vision would help us walk on God-ordained way,
Being in spirit then God will build up His dwelling place,
Making home in our hearts is how Christ builds His church,
How His bride is prepared for Him to come end this age.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="11">Heav'nly vision must be renewed and ne'er disobeyed,
To experience Christ for His Body &amp;mdash; that's all we care!
Let's all pray these two greatest prayers day by day,
Hallelujah! We'll soon bring Him back &amp;mdash; no more delay!</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
