<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Jesus Lord, my best love Thou art</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Experience of Christ&amp;mdash;Loving Him</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="ts:345"/><english num="ns:351"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="2005" biolink="">FTTJ</author>
    <author biodate="" biolink="">Translated from Chinese</author>
    <composer biodate="2005" biolink="">FTTJ</composer>
  </creators>
  <hymncode>3231116565644325</hymncode>
  <key>C Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - - | C - - - | Em - - - | F - G7 - | C - C7/E - | F - - - | Em - Am - | Dm - F - | Gsus4 - G7 - | C - - - | Em - - - | F - G7 - | C - C7/E - | F - - - | Em - Am - | Dm - F - | Gsus4 - G7 - | C - - - | G/B - - - | Am - - - | Em/G - - - | F - - - | Em - Am - | F - D7/F# - | Gsus4 - G7 - | C - - - | E/B - E7 - | Am - - - | Em/G - Em - | F - - - | C G/B Am C/G | F - G7 - | C - - - |</chords>
  <melody>| 0 - - 3/ 2/ | 3. 1/ 1 1/ 6/ | 5 - - 6/ 5/ | 6. 4/ 4 3/ 2/ | 5 - - 6/ 5/ | 6. 1/ 1 4/ 6/ | 5 3/( 2/) 1 2/ 3/ | 4 3 2/ 1/( 1/) 6_./ | 2 - - 3/ 2/ | 3. 1/ 1 1/ 6/ | 5 - - 6/ 5/ | 6. 4/ 4 3/ 2/ | 5 - - 6/ 5/ | 6. 1/ 1 4/ 6/ | 5 3/( 2/) 1 4/ 3/ | 4 4 4/ 4/( 4/) 5/ | 5 - - (Chorus) ._3/ ._2/ | ._3. 5/ 5 ._1/ ._3/ | ._2 ._1 7 ._1/ 7/ | ._1. 3/ 3 6/ ._1/ | 7 ._2 5 6/ 5/ | 6. 1/ 1 6/ 6/ | 5 7 ._1 6/ 5/ | 6. ._1/ ._3/ ._2/( ._2/) ._1/ | ._2 - - ._3/ ._2/ | ._3. 5/ 5 ._1/ ._3/ | ._2 ._1 7 ._1/ 7/ | ._1. 3/ 3 6/ ._1/ | 7 ._2 5 6/ 5/ | 6. 1/ 1 6/ 6/ | 5 7 ._1 6/ 5/ | 6. 6/ 5/ 5/( 5/) 7/ | ._1 - - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>Je -- sus Lord, my best love Thou art, Thou hast ful -- ly cap -- tured my heart; There is none in heav'n nor on earth like Thee, With Thy beau -- ty none can com -- pete. When Thy voice first came to my ear, Whis -- p'ring in my heart words most dear, All past loves and aims lost their charm for me, All my boasts so vain now ap -- pear. Through -- out all the world, who com -- pares with Thee? Who so full of worth, who so fair and sweet?  On -- ly Thou art worth -- y my love to win, O Lord Je -- sus, how I love Thee! No more I who live, no more self- de -- ceived, No more in the self's world in -- dulged to be, Deep with -- in I know You're my on -- ly love, My best love is none else but Thee!</singingstanza>
    <globalstaffsize>16</globalstaffsize>
    <topmargin>0.25</topmargin>
    <bottommargin>0.25</bottommargin>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <videos>
    <video title="Orchestra" youtubeid="JlM0yRndVM0"/>
  </videos>
  <music>
    <midi location="ns" length="91">ns0351.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Jesus Lord, my best love Thou art,
Thou hast fully captured my heart;
There is none in heav'n nor on earth like Thee,
With Thy beauty none can compete.
When Thy voice first came to my ear,
Whisp'ring in my heart words most dear,
All past loves and aims lost their charm for me,
All my boasts so vain now appear.</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">Throughout all the world, who compares with Thee?
Who so full of worth, who so fair and sweet?
Only Thou art worthy my love to win,
O Lord Jesus, how I love Thee!

No more I who live, no more self-deceived,
No more in the self's world indulged to be,
Deep within I know You're my only love,
My best love is none else but Thee!</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Jesus Lord, my best love Thou art,
Rid all rocks that hide in my heart;
Gladly I Thy bondslave of love would be,
One heart, one will ever with Thee
Though my heart is oft not subdued,
Still Thy way alone it would choose;
All I yearn for is what Thy heart desires,
In Thy love alone peace I find.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">Jesus Lord, my best love Thou art,
Ne'er again from Thee I'd depart;
Never hide Thy dear, smiling face from me.
To none else I'd cling, Lord, but Thee.
To Thee, Lord, my all I outpour,
How Thy love my heart deeply fills,
My eternal portion, most precious Lord,
None but Thee I want evermore.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
