<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>The Uniqueness of the Lord's Recovery</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>The Church&amp;mdash;The Lord's Recovery</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="ts:540"/><english num="ns:321"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="">FTTT 14th term trainees</author>
    <author biodate="" biolink="">Translated from Chinese</author>
  </creators>
  <hymncode>155125524321717132</hymncode>
  <key>E Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>C - - - | G/B - G - | Dm - Dm7 - | F - G - | C - - - | G/B - G - | Dm - F - | C/G G7 C - | G - - - | C - - - | F - C/E - | Dm - G - | Dm - G7 - | E7 - Am - | F - C/E - | Dm7 G7 C - | C - - - | G/B - - - | Am - - - | Em/G - - - | F - - - | C/E - Am - | Dm - D7/F# - | G - G7/B - | C - - - | G/B - - - | Am - - - | Em - - - | F - - - | C E/B Am - | Dm - Dm7/F - | C/G - G7 - | C - F/C - | C - - - |</chords>
  <melody>1. 5_./ 5_. 1 | 2. 5_./ 5_. 2 | 4 3/ 2/ 1 7_. | 1/ 7_./ 1/ 3/ 2 - | 1. 5_./ 5_. 1 | 2. 5_./ 5_. 2 | 4 3/ 2/ 1 3/ 3/ | 3/ 2/ 1/ 7_./ 1 - (break) | 7_. 1 2 7_. | 1 2 3 1 | 6 6/ 6/ 5 1 | 4/ 3/ 2/ 1/ 2 - | 2 3 4 5 | 3 2 3 1 | 4 5/ 6/ 5 1 | 6_./ 1/ 1/ 7_./ (.1. (Chorus) 5_./ (break) | 3 2 3 4 | 5 2/ 2/( 2.) 7_./ | 1 7_. 1 2 | 3 7_./ 7_./( 7_.) - (break) | 6_. 7_. 1 6_. | 5_. 1 2 3 | 4 3 2 1 | 2/ 2/ 3/ 2/( 2.) 5_./ (break) | 3 2 3 4 | 5 2/ 2/( 2.) 7_./ | 1 2 3 4/ 4/ | 5 3/ 5/( 5.) 5/ | 6 6 7 ._1 | 5 3/ 2/ 1. 6_./ | 4 3 2 1 | 1 - 7_.. 1/ | 1( - - - | 1) - - 0 ||</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>Glo -- rious vi -- sion, I have seen it: My life is meant for God's e -- con -- o -- my! Earth -- ly bond -- age, I have left it: My heart out -- pours for the Lord's re -- cov -- er -- y! Di -- vine Trin' -- ty, Di -- vine d'spens -- ing: Christ to be life as Spir -- it real is He; Church -- es of God, Bod -- y of Christ, New Je -- ru -- sa -- lem&amp;mdash; how I long to see. O Lord, we give our -- selves a -- fresh, In -- to Your train -- ing hands to be, Mold -- ed, shaped, and worked on dai -- ly, To be ves -- sels of Your glo -- ry! May all my life and work de -- clare, U -- nique -- ness of Your re -- cov -- er -- y To build Your Bod -- y, pre -- pare Your bride, To bring You back, ful -- fill Your long -- ing!</singingstanza>
    <globalstaffsize>13.5</globalstaffsize>
    <topmargin>0.25</topmargin>
    <bottommargin>0.25</bottommargin>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midi location="ns" length="78">ns0321.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Glorious vision, I have seen it: My life is meant for God's economy!
Earthly bondage, I have left it: My heart outpours for the Lord's recovery!
Divine Trinity, Divine dispensing: Christ to be life as Spirit real is He;
Churches of God, Body of Christ, New Jerusalem&amp;mdash;how I long to see.</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">O Lord, we give ourselves afresh, Into Your training hands to be,
Molded, shaped, and worked on daily, To be vessels of Your glory!
May all my life and work declare, Uniqueness of Your recovery
To build Your Body, prepare Your bride, To bring You back, fulfill Your longing!</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Heav'n and earth shall have one living: God and man in organic union live,
Resurrection power supplying, Conformed to Christ's death, no longer I live!
Take His model, tread His footsteps, Go out the camp to live within the veil,
Walk with God, obey His headship, New man un'versal, God's kingdom to bring.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">As the members of one Body, Built up in love, support in spirit each,
Christ dispensing, Spirit minist'ring, Blending until we're all made one in Him.
Give our whole being, one soul to be, Vital groups forming, build up Body His,
Gospelize and truthize widely, Shepherd as God, New Revival to reach.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">Zion Highways, Our heart's longing, Though pass through Baca valley yet not cease,
All loss count we, Refuse, rubbish; Care for God's interests, vision ever heed.
My Lord shall be no more delayed, Be overcomers, pave the way for Him!
Conquering all foes, reigning with Him, How splendid, beauteous, Zion the High Peak!</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
