<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Christ is coming as a thief</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Hope of Glory&amp;mdash;Preparing for Christ's Return</category>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Sarah Olson">S. O.</author>
    <composer biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Sarah Olson">S. O.</composer>
  </creators>
  <hymncode>11111235111565</hymncode>
  <key>F Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - - | Am - - - | F - - - | G - - - | C - - - | Am - - - | F - - - | G - - - | Em - - - | Am - - - | Em - - - | Am - - - | F - - - | G - - - | F - G - | C - - - | C - - - | C - - - | Am - - - | F - - - | G - - - | C - - - | Am - - - | F - G7 - | C - - - ||</chords>
  <melody>| (startrepeat) 1 1/ 1/( 1) 1 | 1 2/ 3/( 3.) 5_./ | 1 1/ 1/( 1) 5_. | 6_. - 5_. - (break) | 1 1/ 1/( 1) 1 | 1 2/ 3/( 3.) 1/ | 4 3/ 2/( 2) 1 | 1.( 2/) 2. 5_./ (break) | 5 5/ 5/( 5) 3 | 2. 1/( 1.) 5_./ | 5 5/ 5/( 5) 3 | 2. 3/( 3.) 6_./ (break) | 4 3/ 2/( 2) 1 | 1.( 2/) 2. 5_./ | 6_. 1 7_. 2 | 2. 1/( 1)( - | 1) - - 0 (endrepeat)  (break) | (Chorus) 0. 5/ 5/ 5/ 5/ 5/ | 6. 5/( 5) - | 0 - 1/ 1/ 5 | 3.( 2/)( 2) - (break) | 0. 5/ 5/ 5/ 5/ 5/ | 6. 5/( 5) - | 0 1 1 7_. | 1 - - - ||</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>Christ is com -- ing as a thief to steal those who are faith -- ful, Those who are most val -- ua -- ble and in the night, so watch -- ful. I seek, Lord, to be pre -- cious; make me a cra -- zy lov -- er! In -- crease Your life with -- in me that I would be Your trea -- sure. Christ's com -- ing is His pres -- ence Spread -- ing in us. He's prom -- ised to come quick -- ly; Lord, grow in us!</singingstanza>
    <singingstanza2>2. Christ will come as a bride -- groom&amp;mdash; His per -- son most at -- trac -- tive&amp;mdash; Tak -- ing vir -- gins wise with Him&amp;mdash; those in pur -- suit so ac -- tive. I buy oil for my ves -- sel; may Thy life spread to my soul. When we'd meet I'd be burn -- ing and sa -- vor Your feast so full.</singingstanza2>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midi location="ns" length="84">ns0418.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Christ is coming as a thief to steal those who are faithful,
Those who are most valuable and in the night, so watchful.
I seek, Lord, to be precious; make me a crazy lover!
Increase Your life within me that I would be Your treasure.

Christ will come as a bridegroom&amp;mdash;His person most attractive&amp;mdash;
Taking virgins wise with Him&amp;mdash;those in pursuit so active.
I buy oil for my vessel; may Thy life spread to my soul.
When we'd meet I'd be burning and savor Your feast so full.</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">Christ's coming is His presence
Spreading in us.
He's promised to come quickly;
Lord, grow in us!</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Christ will be the morning star to those eagerly waiting,
Watching for Him everyday in darkness for His rising.
It's dark and most are sleeping; I rise for Your appearing.
Reward me every morning; I want Your gentle shining.

Christ is coming as a judge, all His people to meet.
All our work He'll test through fire before His judgement seat.
So burn in me today, Lord! I open to Your searching.
Burn the wood and fill with gold; I'm desperate for Your purging!</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">Christ is coming as a King to spread His kingdom on earth.
He will reign with all His saints who know His kingdom's worth.
Reign in all my life, dear King; I give You full permission.
Under Your authority, I'm given Your dominion.

Christ will come still as a Man&amp;mdash;the Son of Man forever.
First He was God's only Son, now He has many brothers.
The Father's Firstborn Son now has a pure duplication;
We truly match each other&amp;mdash;we are divine and human.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
