<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Let me love and not be respected</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>The Way of the Cross&amp;mdash;The Way of Following the Lord</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="ts:428"/><english num="ns:474"/><vsb num="190"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="1903-1972" biolink="www.watchmannee.org">Translated from Watchman Nee</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 0 - - 3_./ 3_./ | 6_.. 6_./ 1 7_./ 6_./ | 6_./ 5#_./( 5#_.) - 6_./ 7_./ | 1. 1/ 3 2/ 1/ (break) | 1/ 7_./( 7_.) - 1/ 7_./ | 6_./ 6_./( 6_./) 6_./ 1 7_./ 6_./ | 2/ 2/( 2) - 3/ 2/ | 1/ 6_./( 6_./) 1/ 7_. 6_./ 5#_./ (break) | 7_./ 6_./( 6_.) - 3_./ 3_./ | 6_./ 6_./( 6_.) 1 7_./( 6_./) | 6_./ 5#_./( 5#_.) - 6_./ 7_./ | 1/ 1/( 1) 3 2/( 1/) | 1/ 7_./( 7_.) - 1/ 7_./ | 6_./ 6_./( 6_./) 6_./ 1 7_./ 6_./ | 2/ 2/( 2) - 3/ 2/ | 1/ 6_./( 6_./) 1/ 7_. 6_./ 5#_./ (break) | 7_./ 6_./( 6_.) - 5_./ 5_./ | 1/ 1/( 1) 3 2/ 1/ | 7_./ 2/( 2) - 5_./ 5_./ | 2/ 2/( 2) 4 3/ 2/ (break) | 1/( 3/)( 3) - 3/ 4/ | 5/ 5. 5 4/ 3/ | 2/ 4/( 4) - 5/ 4/ | 3/ 5_./( 5_.) 4 3/ 2/ (break) | 2/ 1/( 1) - 1/ 2/ | 3 3 3 4/ 3/ | 3/ 2/ 2/ 1/ 7_. 6_./ 7_./ | 1 1 1 2/ 1/ | 7_./ 6_./ 5#_./ 6_./ (.7_. 1/ 7_./ | 6_. 7_. 1 7_./ 6_./ | 2 3 4 3/ 2/ | 1 2/ 1/ 7_./( 1/)( 1/) 2/ | 3 - - 4/ 3/ | 2 3 4 3/ 2/ | 1 2 3 1/ 6_./ | 7_. 7_./ 1/ 2 1/ 7_./ (break) | 6_. - - 5_. | 5 5 5 4/ 3/ | 2/ 1#/ 2/ 3/ 4 4 | 3 3 3 4/ 3/ | 2/ 1/ 7_./ 1/ (.2 1/ 7_./ | 6_./ 6_./( 6_./) 7_./ 1 7_./ 6_./ | 2/ 2/( 2/) 3/ 4 3/ 2/ | 1 2/ 1/ 7_./ 7_./ 1/ 2/ (break) | 3 - - 4/ 3/ | 2 3 4 3/ 2/ | 1 2 3 1/ 6_./ | 7_. 7_./ 1/ 2/ 2/ 1/ 7_./ | 6_. - - 4/ 3/ | 2 3 4 3/ 2/ | 1 2 3 1/ 6_./ | 7_. 7_./ 1/ 2/ 2/ 1/ 7_./ | 6_. - - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza end="-1">Let me love and not be re -- spect -- ed; Let me serve and not be re -- ward -- ed; Let me la -- bor and not be re -- mem -- bered; Let me suf -- fer and not be re -- gard -- ed. 'Tis the pour -- ing, not the drink -- ing; 'Tis the break -- ing, not the keep -- ing— A life suf -- f'ring to seek oth -- ers' bless -- ing, A life lov -- ing and true com -- fort giv -- ing. Not ex -- pect -- ing pi -- ty or con -- cern, Not ac -- cept -- ing so -- lace or praise; E -- ven lone -- ly, e -- ven for -- got -- ten; E -- ven word -- less, e -- ven for -- sak -- en. Tears and blood for the righ -- teous crown My price shall be; los -- ing all, My cost for a faith -- ful pil -- grim's life. 'Twas the life, O Lord, that You chose to live In those days when on earth You walked, Glad -- ly suf -- f'ring all in -- ju -- ries and loss So that all might draw near and re -- pose. I can -- not see how much far -- ther I shall go; Still I press on, know -- ing there is no re -- turn. Let me fol -- low Your pat -- tern, so per -- fect and true, Bear -- ing all grate -- ful -- ly with -- out com -- plaint. In this time of trial, O my Lord, I pray that You would wipe my hid -- den tears a -- way; Let me learn, O Lord, You are my re -- ward; Let me be oth -- ers' bless -- ing all my days.</singingstanza>
    <globalstaffsize>14</globalstaffsize>
    <topmargin>0.25</topmargin>
    <bottommargin>0.25</bottommargin>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="relevant" category="ns" num="19"/>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midiref type="ns" num="19"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="">Let me love and not be respected;
Let me serve and not be rewarded;
Let me labor and not be remembered;
Let me suffer and not be regarded.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="">'Tis the pouring, not the drinking;
'Tis the breaking, not the keeping—
A life suff'ring to seek others' blessing,
A life loving and true comfort giving.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="">Not expecting pity or concern,
Not accepting solace or praise;
Even lonely, even forgotten;
Even wordless, even forsaken.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="">Tears and blood for the righteous crown
My price shall be; losing all,
My cost for a faithful pilgrim's life.
'Twas the life, O Lord, that You chose to live
In those days when on earth You walked,
Gladly suff'ring all injuries and loss
So that all might draw near and repose.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="">I cannot see how much farther I shall go;
Still I press on, knowing there is no return.
Let me follow Your pattern, so perfect and true,
Bearing all gratefully without complaint.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="">In this time of trial, O my Lord,
I pray that You would wipe my hidden tears away;
Let me learn, O Lord, You are my reward;
Let me be others' blessing all my days.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
