<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Now I See</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Experience of Christ&amp;mdash;Loving Him</category>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Ferdinand Tuntomo">F. T.</author>
    <composer biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Ferdinand Tuntomo">F. T.</composer>
  </creators>
  <hymncode>5332212326443327717</hymncode>
  <key>Eb Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - - | G - - - | F - - - | G - - - | C - - - | Am - - - | Dm - - - | G - - - | C - - - | Am - - - | F - - - | G - - - | C - - - | Am - - - | Dm - - - | G - - - | C - F/C - | C - - - ||</chords>
  <melody>| 0 5/ 3/ 3/ 2/ 2/ 1/ | 2 3/ 2/( 2) - | 0 6/ 4/ 4/ 3/ 3/ 2/ | 7_./ 7_./ 1/ 7_./( 7_.) - (break) | 0 5/ 3/ 3/ 2/ 2/ 1/ | 1/ 1/ 2/ 6_./( 6_./) 6_./ 3/ 2/( | 2)( - 2/) 6_./ 3/ 2/( (break) | 2.) 1/ 1/( 2/) 3/ 5/( | 5) 5/ 3/ 3/ 2/ 2/ 1/ | 1 2/ 6_./( 6_./) 2/ 3/ 5/( (break) | 5) 5/ 3/ 3/ 2/ 2/ 1/ | 2 3/ 2/( 2/) 2/ 3/ 5/( | 5) 5/ 3/ 3/ 2/ 2/ 1/ (break) | 1 2/ 6_./( 6_./) 6_./ 3/ 2/( | 2)( - 2/) 6_./ 3/ 2/( | 2) - - 1 | 1( - - - | 1) - - 0 ||</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>Lord, You're with me when I'm by my -- self, Al -- ways com -- fort -- ing me when I'm lone -- ly, You're the One in whom I find my true rest, And You sat -- is -- fy me... And now I see... Lord, You are the on -- ly One for me. And I see... You're the Friend who's with me con -- stant -- ly. And I see... Lord, You're liv -- ing right in -- side of me. And I see, Lord You are for me.</singingstanza>
    <globalstaffsize>14</globalstaffsize>
    <topmargin>0.25</topmargin>
    <bottommargin>0.25</bottommargin>
    <columns>3</columns>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midi location="ns" length="45">ns0437.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Lord, You're with me when I'm by myself,
Always comforting me when I'm lonely,
You're the One in whom I find my true rest,
And You satisfy me...</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">And now I see...
Lord, You are the only One for me.
And I see...
You're the Friend who's with me constantly.
And I see...
Lord, You're living right inside of me.
And I see, Lord You are for me.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">You became a man to die for me,
You shed Your blood that I might be redeemed,
You loved me more than my words can ere tell,
And You attracted me...</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">And now I see...
Lord, You died and rose to save me to You.
And I see...
A divine romance with us human beings.
And I see...
You loved me before time ever began.
And I see You really love me.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">You're the One inside who cherishes me,
Feeding me with milk from Your holy Word,
Lord, You bring me just to feast upon You.
And You feed me richly...</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">And now I see...
You're the One who's always shepherding me.
And I see...
You're the One who's feeding, watering me.
And I see...
You're the One who loves me as Your sheep.
And I see, Lord, You shepherd me.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">Lord, I consecrate myself unto You,
My time, my life, my riches; future too,
You're the One on whom I'll pour everything,
That's because I love You...</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">And now I see...
You're the only One who's within my view.
And I see...
You're the One who I will give myself to.
And I see...
You're the only One who I will pursue.
'Cause I see, Lord, You are lovely.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">Lord, without You I just cannot go on,
You're the One in whom my life has meaning,
I am absolutely for Your purpose,
And I know why I live...</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">And now I see...
You're the only One who I truly need.
And I see...
I am living for Your economy.
And I see...
It's because Your being captivates me.
And I see I'm in love with You.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">Lord, I've set my feet upon the track,
Pressing onward just to fulfill Your dream,
And may I nevermore turn my head back,
'Cause I am just for You...</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">And now I see...
Lord, You've drawn me away to Yourself.
And I see...
I'm pursuing You, Lord, wholeheartedly.
And I see...
There is nothing else on earth for me.
And I see, Lord, You are my goal.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
