<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>What a Christ We Have</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Experience of Christ&amp;mdash;As the Good Land</category>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Ray Huff">R. H.</author>
    <composer biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Ray Huff">R. H.</composer>
  </creators>
  <hymncode>12311561165</hymncode>
  <key>F Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - - | C - - - | F - - - | C - - - | F/C - - - | C - - - | F - - - | G - - - | G - - - | F - - - | C - - - | F - - - | C - - - | F - - - | G - - - | C - - - | C - - - ||</chords>
  <melody>| 0 - - 1/ 2/ | 3 1 1 5_. | 6_. 1/ 1/( 1) 6_. | 5_.( - - - (break) | 5_.) - - 1/ 2/ | 3 1 1 5_. | 6_. 1/ 1/( 1) 2 | 2( - - - (break) | 2) - - 2/ 3/ | 4 4/ 3/( 3) 2 | 3 1/ 1/( 1) 5_. | 6_.. 7_./( 7_.) 1 (break) | 5_. - - 5_./ 5_./ | 6_. 1 1 1 | 2. 1/( 1) 7_. | 1( - - - | 1) - - 0 ||</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>What a Christ we have, the all -- in -- clu -- sive One, Our al -- lot -- ted por -- tion, set a -- part in light. In the king -- dom of the Son of God, the Son of God's love, Here He rules us in the light of His love.</singingstanza>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midi location="ns" length="23">ns0438.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">What a Christ we have, the all-inclusive One,
Our allotted portion, set apart in light.
In the kingdom of the Son of God, the Son of God's love,
Here He rules us in the light of His love.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Lift your eyes up and look from where you are.
When you see the Christ, our all-inclusive land,
Then we walk in this blessed land, enjoying all we see,
Getting saved eating milk and honey.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">See the wheat, the restricted Jesus Christ.
Incarnation was restriction in the flesh.
Limited outwardly, by God's power set free,
Resurrected as unlimited barley.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">See the vine trees, the sacrificing Christ.
He produced wine thus cheering God and man.
When we drink this new wine, we are so energized,
For the Lord to be a living sacrifice.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">See the fig trees, Christ's sweetness our supply.
To progress in the joy of all our faith,
Be a channel of supply so others experience Christ,
And be happy in the bountiful supply.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">See the pomegranates, fulness of His life;
The abundance and the beauty of this life.
As the olive tree the Spirit fills to honor God and man,
Bearing fruit as branches grafted into Christ.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="7">See our portion so available to take,
To be walked in and experienced in full.
Apprehending the unsearchable extent of this good land,
When we corporately enjoy Him with the saints.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
