<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>God's Dream</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>The Church&amp;mdash;As God's Dream</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="ns:476c"/><english num="ns:476"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Andrew Yu">Translated from A. Y.</author>
    <author biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Chao-Chun Liu">Translated by C. C. L.</author>
    <author biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Maryanna Cashmore">Translated by M. C.</author>
    <composer biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Andrew Yu">A. Y.</composer>
  </creators>
  <hymncode>532123444452</hymncode>
  <key>D Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>110</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - - | C - - - | Am - - - | Dm - - - | G - - - | C - - - | Am - - - | Dm - - - | G - - - | F - - - | C/E - - - | Dm - - - | G - - - | F - - - | C/E - - - | Dm - - - | G - - - | C - - - | Em - - - | F - - - | G7 - - - | C - F/C - | C - - - ||</chords>
  <melody>| 0 - - 5_. | 3 - - 2 | 1 - - 2/ 3/ | 4 4/ 4/( 4/) 4/ 5 (break) | 2 - - 5_. | 3 - - 2 | 1 - - 2/ 3/ | 4 4/ 4/( 4) 5 (break) | 5( - 5/) 1/ 1/ 6/ | 6( - 6/) 6/ 7/ ._1/ | ._1 - - 4/( 3/) | 4 - - 6 (break) | 5( - 5/) 1/ 1/ 6/ | 6( - 6/) 6/ 7/ ._1/ | ._1 - - 4/ 3/ | 4 - - 3 (break) | 2 - - 5_. | 3 - - 4 | 5 - - - | 1. 4/ 4 3 | 2 - 1 7_. | 1( - - - | 1) - - 0 ||</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>There's al -- ways been some -- thing hid -- den deep in Your heart, Yet I had not giv -- en it one sin -- gle thought, I on -- ly knew that I was wan -- d'ring, feel -- ing lost, Dream -- ing were You, and I was too, in the wil -- der -- ness, Un -- til one day You re -- vealed Your dream in my heart.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <music>
	<midi location="ns" length="48">ns0476.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">There's always been something hidden deep in Your heart,
Yet I had not given it one single thought,
I only knew that I was wand'ring, feeling lost,
Dreaming were You, and I was too, in the wilderness,
Until one day You revealed Your dream in my heart.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Your heart's desire is with man to mingle as one,
To dwell with man, an eternal bond to form,
'Twas for this dream You became man, uplifting man,
That God and man, heaven and earth, be joined for aye,
God's house, heav'n's gate, now descends, Your dream to attain.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">From heav'n You came as my bread of eternal life,
By eating You, I can now enjoy Your life,
Brought to His house, the Father's love for You is mine,
I'm joined, a branch, to You, the vine&amp;mdash;union divine,
By bearing fruit, this relationship multiplies.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">Abide in love, so His life in us may flow free,
By mutual love, His disciples we will be;
The more we're joined, the more we're built organically,
And by His word we're sanctified, not of the world,
As one new man, corporate God-man living we'll see.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">O Lord, I place myself on the altar for You,
For Your desire, that Your dream may become true.
As for my life, I'd gladly dwell in a lowly tent,
To be a drink off'ring outpoured for man
God's pillar, stand to fulfill God's eternal plan.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
