<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>The City and the Bride</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Ultimate Manifestation&amp;mdash;The New Jerusalem</category>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Steve A. Watts">S. A. W.</author>
    <composer biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Steve A. Watts">S. A. W.</composer>
  </creators>
  <hymncode>5333331217655</hymncode>
  <key>F Major</key>
  <time>2/4</time>
  <tempo>112</tempo>
  <chords>| C - | C - | Am - | F G | C - | C/E - | Am - | D - | G - | F - | C - | Am - | F - | F - | F - | C - | G G7 | C - | C - | C - | C - | F - | C - | C - | Am - | G G7 | C F/C | C - ||</chords>
  <melody>| 0 5_. | 3./ 3// 3./ 3// | 3 1 | 2./ 1// 7_../ 6_.// | 5_. 5_. (break) | 1./ 1// 1./ 1// | 3 1./ 3// | 2./ 2// 2./ 3// | 2 3 (break) | 4./ 4// 2./ 4// | 3 1./ 2// | 3./ 2// 1./ 7_.// | 6_.( - | 6_.) 3 (break) | 4./ 4// 2./ 4// | 3 1 | 3./ 2// 1./ 7_.// | 1( - (break) | 1) (Chorus) 3./ 4// | 5./ 5// 5( | 5)( 5./) 5// | 6./ 6// 5./ 4// | 5 3./ 4// (break) | 5 3./ 4// | 5 1 | 3./ 2// 1./ 7_.// | 1( - | 1) 0 ||</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>The New Je -- ru -- sa -- lem, the king -- dom with God's throne, Is Christ, the rul -- ing Head of God's house, the church, God's home; The life with -- in the church is the life of God Him -- self, The life that rules and reigns, and saves from sin and self. New Je -- ru -- sa -- lem! The ci -- ty and the bride! Build -- ed up, beau -- ti -- fied, and whol -- ly sanc -- ti -- fied!</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midi location="ns" length="33">ns0486.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <notes>Adapted from 2014 Spring ITERO, Message 2.</notes>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">The New Jerusalem, the kingdom with God's throne,
Is Christ, the ruling Head of God's house, the church, God's home;
The life within the church is the life of God Himself,
The life that rules and reigns, and saves from sin and self.</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">New Jerusalem! The city and the bride!
Builded up, beautified, and wholly sanctified!</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">The New Jerusalem is in reality
The church with Christ as Head in God's economy;
The content of the church must be the kingdom life,
Expressed through all the saints experiencing Christ.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">The New Jerusalem is builded in the Lord,
A company in Christ established in the Word;
As fellow citizens, God's kingdom manifest,
In spirit live and walk, and enter Sabbath rest.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">The New Jerusalem, the bride who is prepared,
Is beautified by Christ, to be His wife, matured;
In nature and in life she must in stature grow
And in the Body live, the Body-life to know.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">The New Jerusalem, eternal, builded bride,
From self she is delivered from independent pride;
Her righteousness is Christ yet in her daily life
She manifested God, and lived and worked in Christ.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">The New Jerusalem, the city and the bride,
Remains in God forever, forever to abide;
A city that is holy, in God one entity,
And shining forth with Christ unto eternity.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
