<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="yes"?>
<book name="1 Samuel">
    <info title="Author">Originally, 1 and 2 Samuel were one book in the Hebrew Scriptures. First Samuel 1-24 was written by Samuel ([link]1 Chron. 29:29[/link]; [link]1 Sam. 25:1[/link]). The remainder of 1 Samuel and all of 2 Samuel were written by Nathan the prophet and Gad the seer ([link]1 Chron. 29:29[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Time of Writing">The eleventh century B.C.</info>
    <info title="Place of Writing">Ephraim and Judah.</info>
    <info title="Time Period Covered">About 155 years, approximately 1171-1017 B.C.</info>
    <subject>The Illustrations of the Way to Enjoy the God-given Good Land</subject>
    <outlines>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="1" ref="1 Sam. 1:1-8:22">The history concerning Samuel</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="1:1-20">His origin and birth</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="1:21-2:11">His youth</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="2:12-7:17">His relationship with the stale and waning Aaronic priesthood</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="1" ref="2:12-26">Observing the deterioration of the degraded Aaronic priesthood</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="2" ref="2:27-3:21">Realizing God's severe judgment on the house of Eli</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="3" ref="4:1-7:2">Knowing the misfortune of the Ark of God under the superstition of the degraded and rotten Aaronic priesthood</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="4" ref="7:3-17">Serving as a priest and as a judge over Israel</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="4" ref="8:1-22">The ending of Samuel's ministry</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="2" ref="1 Sam. 9:1-15:35">The history concerning Saul</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="9:1-2">Saul's origin</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="9:3-10:27">God's anointing Saul as king</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="11:1-13">Saul's conquest of the Ammonites</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="4" ref="11:14-12:25">Samuel's reminder to Israel</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="5" ref="13:1-14:52">Saul's conquest of the Philistines</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="6" ref="15:1-35">Saul's disobedience in his conquest of the Amalekites</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="3" ref="1 Sam. 16:1-2 Sam. 24:25">The history concerning David</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="1 Sam. 16:1-2 Sam. 1:27">Prepared by God to be a man according to the heart of God</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="1" ref="1 Sam. 16:1-10">Chosen by God</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="2" ref="1 Sam. 16:11">Trained by God in humility</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="3" ref="1 Sam. 16:12-23">Anointed</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="4" ref="1 Sam. 17:1-58">Tested and approved in trusting God and defeating Goliath</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="5" ref="1 Sam. 18:1-2 Sam. 1:27">Persecuted and tried by Saul</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="1" ref="1 Sam. 18:1-5">Jonathan's love of David</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="2" ref="1 Sam. 18:6-9">Saul's envy of David</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="3" ref="1 Sam. 18:10-20:42">Saul's device to kill David</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="4" ref="1 Sam. 21:1-9">David's being supplied with the holy bread of the Presence and with the sword of Goliath by the priest Ahimelech</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="5" ref="1 Sam. 21:10-15">David's fleeing from Saul and going to Achish the king of Gath</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="6" ref="1 Sam. 22:1-5">David's staying in the cave of Adullam, in Mizpeh of Moab, and in the forest of Hereth of Judah</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="7" ref="1 Sam. 22:6-23">Saul's killing Ahimelech the priest and his family because of David</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="8" ref="1 Sam. 23:1-12">David's defeating the Philistines and staying in Keilah</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="9" ref="1 Sam. 23:13-28">David's remaining in the wilderness of Ziph</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="10" ref="1 Sam. 23:29-24:2">David's remaining in the strongholds of En-gedi</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="11" ref="1 Sam. 24:3-22">Saul's falling into the hand of David but David not killing him</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="12" ref="1 Sam. 25:1a">Samuel's death</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="13" ref="1 Sam. 25:1b-44">David's dealing with Nabal and Abigail</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="14" ref="1 Sam. 26:1-25">Jehovah's delivering Saul into the hand of David but David not killing him</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="15" ref="1 Sam. 27:1-28:2">David's escaping to and staying in the land of the Philistines</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="16" ref="1 Sam. 28:3-25">Saul's tragic ending pretold by Samuel</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="17" ref="1 Sam. 29:1-11">David's being sovereignly kept away by God from joining the Philistines' camp to fight against Israel</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="18" ref="1 Sam. 30:1-31">David's conquering the Amalekites and capturing their captives</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="19" ref="1 Sam. 31:1-13">Saul's end</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="20" ref="2 Sam. 1:1-27">David's reaction</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="2 Sam. 2:1-24:25">Crowned by the people to be the king for the kingdom of God on the earth</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="1" ref="2:1-5:25">Crowned by the people</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="1" ref="2:1-4:12">Crowned by the tribe of Judah</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="2" ref="5:1-5">Crowned by all the other tribes</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="3" ref="5:6-25">Established by God as king with his kingdom exalted for the sake of God's people Israel</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="2" ref="6:1-7:29">David's care for God's habitation on the earth</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="1" ref="6:1-23">Taking care of the habitation of the Ark of God</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="2" ref="7:1-29">Wanting to build a house for God</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="3" ref="8:1-10:19">David's conquest over his enemies for the strengthening of his kingdom</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="1" ref="8:1-14">David's conquests over the Philistines, Moab, Zobah, Syria, and Edom</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="2" ref="8:15-18">David's reign in justice and righteousness</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="3" ref="9:1-13">David showing kindness to Mephibosheth the son of Jonathan</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="4" ref="10:1-19">David's conquests over Ammon and Syria</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="4" ref="11:1-27">David's indulging sin</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="5" ref="12:1-15a">God's punishing condemnation</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="6" ref="12:15b-20:26">God's punishing judgment on David</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="1" ref="12:15b-23">The death of the child born of Uriah's wife</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="2" ref="12:24-25">The birth of Solomon</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="3" ref="12:26-31">David's conquest over the children of Ammon</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="4" ref="13:1-22">The incest of Amnon the son of David with his sister Tamar</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="5" ref="13:23-39">The murder of Amnon by Absalom the son of David</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="6" ref="14:1-24">Joab's device to bring Absalom back</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="7" ref="14:25-27">Absalom's beauty and his children</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="8" ref="14:28-33">Absalom's seeking to see his father David</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="9" ref="15:1-19:8a">Absalom's revolt</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="10" ref="19:8b-43">The peaceful settlements in David's kingdom after Absalom's revolt</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="11" ref="20:1-22">The rebellion of Sheba</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="12" ref="20:23-26">The re-establishment of the kingdom of David</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="7" ref="21:1-24:25">The last stage of David's kingship</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="1" ref="21:1-14">David's taking care of the famine for the people</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="2" ref="21:15-22">David's conquest over the Philistines</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="3" ref="22:1-51">David's thanking and praising to God in a song</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="4" ref="23:1-7">David's last words</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="5" ref="23:8-39">David's mighty men</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="6" ref="24:1-25">David's last sin</outline>
    </outlines>
    <chapters>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Now there was a certain man from Ramathaim-zophim, from the hill country of Ephraim, and his name was [xref]a[/xref]Elkanah, the son of Jeroham, the son of Elihu, the son of Tohu, the son of Zuph, an Ephrathite.</text>
        <note num="1">The content of 1 and 2 Samuel is the history of Samuel, Saul, and David, which continues the history of the judges and which is a crucial part of the central line of Israel's history. Samuel was a Levite by birth and a Nazarite by consecration, who became a priest, a prophet, and a judge. He initiated the prophethood to replace the waning priesthood in the speaking for God, terminated the judgeship, and brought in the kingship. Saul was a king among Israel in a negative way, and David was a king in a positive way.[br/][br/]The central thought of 1 and 2 Samuel is that the fulfillment of God's economy needs man's cooperation in the principle of incarnation, as illustrated by the history of Samuel's mother, Hannah, of Samuel, and of David, in the positive sense, and by the history of Eli and of Saul, in the negative sense. Such a cooperation is related to the personal enjoyment of the good land, which typifies the all-inclusive and all-extensive Christ (see note [link]7[sup]1[/sup] in Deut. 8[/link]). First and 2 Samuel, as a continuation of Joshua, Judges, and Ruth, give the details concerning the enjoyment of the God-given good land. The types in these two books show us how the New Testament believers can and should enjoy Christ as their God-allotted portion ([link]Col. 1:12[/link]) for the establishing of God's kingdom, which is the church ([link]Matt. 16:18-19[/link]; [link]Rom. 14:17[/link]). These types indicate that our being right with God is a condition for our enjoyment of Christ. In 1 and 2 Samuel the good land enjoyed by those who cooperated with God became the kingdom of God, in which the cooperators reigned as kings. Likewise, in our cooperation with God we need to enjoy Christ to such an extent that our enjoyment of Christ becomes the kingdom of God, in which we reign in life with Christ ([link]Rom. 5:17[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Chron. 6:34</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And he had two wives; the name of one was Hannah, and the name of the other was Peninnah. Now Peninnah had children, but Hannah had [xref]a[/xref]no children.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Gen. 16:1; 25:21; 29:31; Judg. 13:2; Luke 1:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And this man went up from his city [xref]a[/xref]year by year to worship and to sacrifice to Jehovah of hosts in [xref]b[/xref]Shiloh. And the two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, priests of Jehovah, were there.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Exo. 23:14; Deut. 16:16; Luke 2:41</xref>
        <xref num="b">Josh. 18:1; 1 Sam. 1:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And when the day came that Elkanah sacrificed, he would give portions to Peninnah his wife and to all her sons and her daughters.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>But he would give a double portion to Hannah, for it was Hannah whom he loved; but [note]1[/note]Jehovah had shut up her womb.</text>
        <note num="1">Under Eli the old Aaronic priesthood had become stale and waning ([link]2:12-29[/link]), and God desired to have a new beginning for the accomplishing of His economy. For Samuel's birth God initiated things behind the scenes. On the one hand, He shut up Hannah's womb; on the other hand, He prepared Peninnah to provoke Hannah ([link]vv. 5-7[/link]). This forced Hannah to pray that the Lord would give her a male child. Hannah's prayer, in which she made a vow to God ([link]vv. 10-11[/link]), was initiated not by Hannah but by God. God was pleased with Hannah's prayer and her promise and He opened her womb. Hannah conceived, bore a child, and named him Samuel ([link]v. 20[/link]). Hence, actually no human being was the origin of Samuel. God was the real origin, who motivated His people sovereignly and secretly.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And her rival provoked her bitterly to irritate her, because Jehovah had shut up her womb.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And so it happened year after year; when she went up to the house of Jehovah, [note]1[/note]the other provoked her this way; and she wept and would not eat.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., she.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And Elkanah her husband said to her, Hannah, why are you weeping, and why do you not eat? And why is your heart sad? Am I not better to you than ten sons?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Then after the eating and drinking in Shiloh, Hannah rose up. Now Eli the priest was sitting on his seat at the doorpost of the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]temple of Jehovah.</text>
        <note num="1">Some MSS read, house.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 3:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And she was bitter in soul and [note]1[/note]prayed to Jehovah and wept much.</text>
        <note num="1">On the human side, Samuel's origin was his God-worshipping parents, especially his God-seeking mother with her prayer (cf. note [link]5[sup]1[/sup][/link]). In the midst of the chaos of degraded Israel, Elkanah and Hannah remained in the line of life ordained by God for His eternal purpose (see note [link]9[sup]3[/sup], par. 2, in Gen. 2[/link]). The line of life is a line that brings forth Christ for the enjoyment of God's people (see note [link]18[sup]1[/sup] in Ruth 4[/link]), that on earth God may have His kingdom, which is the church as the Body of Christ ([link]Matt. 16:18-19[/link]; [link]Rom. 14:17[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:22b-23[/link]), the very organism of the Triune God. Because of God's moving in her, Hannah could not have peace until she prayed for a son. Hannah's prayer was an echo, a speaking out, of the heart's desire of God. It was a human cooperation with the divine move for the carrying out of God's eternal economy. God could motivate Hannah as a person who was one with Him in the line of life. As long as God can gain such a person, He has a way on earth.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And she made a [xref]a[/xref]vow and said, O Jehovah of hosts, if You will indeed [xref]b[/xref]look upon the affliction of Your female servant and remember me and not forget Your female servant, but give to Your female servant a male child, then I will give him to Jehovah for all the days of his life, and [xref]c[/xref]no [note]1[/note]razor will come upon his head.</text>
        <note num="1">Hannah's prayer indicates that God's move with His answer to Hannah's prayer ([link]vv. 19-20[/link]) was to produce a Nazarite who was absolute for the fulfilling of God's desire. A Nazarite is one who is consecrated to God absolutely, one who takes God as the Head, considering God his Husband, and one who has no interest in the enjoyment of worldly pleasures ([link]Num. 6:1-5[/link] and notes). Even before he was born, Samuel was consecrated by his mother to be such a person.</note>
        <xref num="a">Num. 6:2</xref>
        <xref num="b">Luke 1:48</xref>
        <xref num="c">Num. 6:5; Judg. 13:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And while she continued praying a long time before Jehovah, Eli watched her mouth.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And Hannah was speaking in her heart; only her lips moved, but her voice was not heard. So Eli thought that she was drunk.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And Eli said to her, How long will you be drunk? Put away your wine from you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And Hannah answered and said, No, my lord. I am a woman oppressed in spirit. I have drunk neither wine nor strong drink, but I have been pouring out my soul before Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Do not take your female servant for a worthless woman; for out of the greatness of my anxiety and provocation I have been speaking all this time.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Then Eli answered and said, Go in peace, and may the God of Israel grant your request that you have requested from Him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And she said, Let your servant find favor in your sight. And the woman went her way; and she ate, and her countenance was [i]sad[/i] no more.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And they rose up early in the morning and worshipped before Jehovah; and they returned and came to their house in Ramah. And Elkanah knew Hannah his wife, and Jehovah [xref]a[/xref]remembered her.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 30:22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And in due time Hannah conceived and bore a son; and she called his name [note]1[/note]Samuel, For, [i]she said,[/i] I asked for him of Jehovah.</text>
        <note num="1">Meaning [i]heard of God,[/i] or [i]asked for of God.[/i]</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And the man Elkanah went up with all his house to offer the yearly sacrifice to Jehovah and his vow.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>But Hannah did not go up, for she said to her husband, When the child is weaned, then I will [xref]a[/xref]bring him up, so that he may appear before Jehovah and stay there forever.</text>
        <xref num="a">Luke 2:22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>And Elkanah her husband said to her, Do what is good in your sight; stay until you have weaned him. Only, may Jehovah establish His word. So the woman stayed and nursed her son until she weaned him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And as soon as she weaned him, she brought him up with her, along with three bulls and one ephah of flour and a skin of wine; and she brought him to the house of Jehovah in [xref]a[/xref]Shiloh, although the child was young.</text>
        <xref num="a">Josh. 18:1; 1 Sam. 1:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>And they slaughtered the bull and brought the child to Eli.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>And she said, Oh, my lord, as your soul lives, my lord, I am the woman who stood here by you, praying to Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>It was for this child that I prayed, and Jehovah has granted me my request that I [xref]a[/xref]requested from Him.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 2:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>Therefore I, for my part, have [note]1[/note]lent him to Jehovah; all the days that he lives, he is lent to Jehovah. And he worshipped Jehovah there.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., made him a request to Jehovah. At the time of Eli, God was poor as far as the priesthood was concerned, so Hannah lent Samuel to the Lord. When the situation is abnormal, the Lord becomes poor with respect to His administration, and there is the need for someone to voluntarily lend himself to the Lord.</note>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]And Hannah prayed and said: / My heart exults in Jehovah; / My [xref]b[/xref]horn is exalted in Jehovah; / My mouth is enlarged against my enemies, / Because I rejoice in Your [note]1[/note][xref]c[/xref]salvation.</text>
        <note num="1">In her prayer Hannah praised God for His salvation accomplished through His marvelous deeds. Her prayer was related to God's move in His economy and indicated that she realized something concerning God's economy.</note>
        <xref num="a">vv. 1-10: cf. Luke 1:46-53</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 75:10; 92:10; 148:14; 18:2</xref>
        <xref num="c">Psa. 9:14; 35:9; Isa. 12:2-3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>There is none [xref]a[/xref]holy like Jehovah, / For there is none besides You; / Nor is there a [xref]b[/xref]rock like our God.</text>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 11:44; Rev. 15:4</xref>
        <xref num="b">Deut. 32:31; 2 Sam. 22:32</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Talk no more so very proudly; / Do not let arrogance go forth from your mouth; / For Jehovah is a God of [xref]a[/xref]knowledge, / [note]1[/note]And actions are [xref]b[/xref]weighed by Him.</text>
        <note num="1">Some MSS read, Though actions are not weighed.</note>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 139:1-6; Rom. 11:33</xref>
        <xref num="b">Dan. 5:27; Prov. 16:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>The bows of the mighty men are broken, / And those who stumbled are girded with strength.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Those who were full have hired themselves out for food, / And those who were [xref]a[/xref]hungry are not so any longer. / She who was [xref]b[/xref]barren has borne seven, / And she who had many children languishes.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 107:9; Luke 1:53</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 113:9; Isa. 54:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Jehovah kills and makes [xref]a[/xref]alive; / He brings down to Sheol and [xref]b[/xref]brings up.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 32:39; 2 Kings 5:7</xref>
        <xref num="b">Isa. 26:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Jehovah makes poor and makes rich; / He makes low and also [xref]a[/xref]lifts up.</text>
        <xref num="a">Job 5:11; Psa. 75:7; Luke 1:52</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]He raises the poor from the dust, / From the ash heap He lifts the needy, / That He may seat [i]them[/i] with princes / And cause [i]them[/i] to inherit the [xref]b[/xref]throne of glory. / For the pillars of the [xref]c[/xref]earth are Jehovah's, / And He has set the world upon them.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 113:7-8</xref>
        <xref num="b">James 2:5; cf. Rev. 3:21</xref>
        <xref num="c">Job 38:4-6; Psa. 24:2; 102:25</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>He will keep the feet of His faithful ones, / But the wicked will be silenced in darkness; / For not by [xref]a[/xref]strength shall any man prevail.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 33:16; cf. Zech. 4:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Those who strive with Jehovah will be shattered; / Against them He will thunder in heaven. / Jehovah will [xref]a[/xref]judge the ends of the earth; / And He will give strength to His king / And exalt the [xref]b[/xref]horn of His anointed.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 96:10, 13; 98:9</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 89:24; 1 Sam. 2:1; Luke 1:69</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And Elkanah went to Ramah to his house. And the child [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]ministered to Jehovah before [note]2[/note]Eli the priest.</text>
        <note num="1">Samuel was of the tribe of Levi ([link]1 Chron. 6:33-38[/link]) but was not of the house of Aaron, the family of the priests ordained by God. Samuel ministered to the Lord as one who was a priest not by birth but by the Nazarite vow. At the time of Samuel the priesthood of the house of Aaron was utterly fallen. God, however, foresaw the situation. Besides His ordaining the house of Aaron to be the priests, He made a supplement &amp;#8212; the Nazarite vow in [link]Num. 6[/link] &amp;#8212; in case there should be an inadequacy in the ordained priests. When the house of Aaron fell, this supplement was put into practical use. Samuel became a priest by being consecrated, separated, and lent to God ([link]1:11[/link], [link]28[/link]). See note [link]2[sup]1[/sup] in Num. 6[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Samuel grew up under the custody of the elderly Eli ([link]1:25[/link]). In his youth Samuel ministered to Jehovah before Eli ([link]vv. 11b[/link], [link]18-19[/link]), being taught by Eli the way to minister to God. While Samuel was learning, he observed the deterioration of the degraded Aaronic priesthood ([link]vv. 12-17[/link], [link]22-25[/link]). This did not weaken Samuel in his future Nazarite priesthood; rather, it became a constant warning to him throughout his priestly service.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 2:18; 3:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Now the sons of Eli were worthless men; they did not [xref]a[/xref]know Jehovah,</text>
        <xref num="a">Judg. 2:10; Jer. 2:8; Rom. 1:28</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Nor [i]did they regard[/i] the priests' rightful [xref]a[/xref]due with the people. When any man offered a sacrifice, the priest's attendant would come with a three-pronged fork in his hand while the flesh was boiling,</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 18:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And he would thrust [i]it[/i] into the pan or kettle or cauldron or pot; all that the fork brought up, the priest took with it. Thus they did in Shiloh to all the Israelites who came there.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Indeed before they burned the [xref]a[/xref]fat, the priest's attendant would come and say to the man sacrificing, Give some flesh to roast for the priest, for he will not accept boiled flesh from you, but only raw.</text>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 3:16; 7:23, 25, 31</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And if the man said to him, Let them burn up the fat first, then take as much as your soul desires; he would say, No, but you shall give [i]it[/i] now; otherwise, I will take [i]it[/i] by force.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And the sin of the young men was very great before Jehovah, for the men despised the offering of Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And Samuel ministered before Jehovah, as a boy wearing a linen [xref]a[/xref]ephod.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 28:4; 2 Sam. 6:14; 1 Chron. 15:27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And his mother would make him a little robe and bring [i]it[/i] up to him yearly when she went up with her husband to offer the yearly sacrifice.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And Eli would bless Elkanah and his wife and say, May Jehovah give you seed by this woman in place of the one she requested of Jehovah; and they would go back to their place.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>[note]1[/note]And Jehovah visited Hannah, and she conceived and bore three sons and two daughters. And the boy Samuel [xref]a[/xref]grew before Jehovah.</text>
        <note num="1">Many MSS read, for.</note>
        <xref num="a">Judg. 13:24; 1 Sam. 2:26; 3:19; Luke 1:80; 2:40</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Now Eli was very old, and he heard of all that his sons did to all Israel and how they lay with the women who were engaged in service at the entrance of the Tent of Meeting.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>And he said to them, [note]1[/note]Why do you do such things? For I hear of your evil dealings from all this people.</text>
        <note num="1">Eli attempted to say something to his sons ([link]vv. 23-25[/link]), but it seems that he was somewhat loose and that his exhortation was not very strong, faithful, desperate, and absolute ([link]v. 29[/link]). Eli's sons brought the curse upon themselves, and Eli did not restrain them ([link]3:13[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>No, my sons; for it is not a good report [note]1[/note]that I hear Jehovah's people spreading.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, that I hear; you are making Jehovah's people transgress.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>If one man sins against another man, God will arbitrate for him; but if a man sins against Jehovah, who will arbitrate for him? But they would not listen to the voice of their father, for Jehovah was pleased to kill them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>And the boy Samuel continued to [xref]a[/xref]grow in stature and in favor both with Jehovah and with men.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Luke 2:52</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>And a man of God came to Eli and said to him, Thus says Jehovah, I [xref]a[/xref]revealed Myself to the house of your father when they were in Egypt [note]1[/note]as slaves to Pharaoh's house.</text>
        <note num="1">Some MSS omit the words [i]as slaves.[/i]</note>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 3:2; 4:27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>And I chose him out of all the tribes of Israel to be My [xref]a[/xref]priest, to go up to My altar, to burn incense, [i]and[/i] to wear the ephod before Me. And I gave the house of your father all the offerings by fire of the children of Israel.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 28:1; Num. 18:1-7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>Why then do you kick at My sacrifice and My offering, which I have commanded in My habitation, and honor your sons more than Me by making yourselves fat with the best of all the offerings of Israel My people?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>Therefore Jehovah the God of Israel declares, I surely said that your house and the house of your father would walk before Me [xref]a[/xref]forever; but now Jehovah declares, Far be it from Me; for those who honor Me I will honor, and those who spurn Me will be lightly esteemed.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 27:21; 29:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>The days are now coming when I will [xref]a[/xref]cut off your arm and the arm of the house of your father, so that there will not be an old man in your house.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 4:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>And you shall see the [xref]a[/xref]distress of My habitation in the midst of all the good that [note]1[/note]I will do to Israel, and there shall not be an old man in your house forever.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., He.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 4:11; Psa. 78:59-64</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>And [i]that[/i] man of yours whom I do not cut off from My altar [i]shall be left[/i] to consume your eyes and to grieve your soul, and all the increase of your house shall die [note]1[/note]by the swords of men.</text>
        <note num="1">Some MSS read, as men.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>And this will be the sign to you, which will come upon your two sons, upon Hophni and Phinehas: In one day both of them shall die.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>And I will raise up for Myself a faithful [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]priest, who will do according to what is in My [note]2[/note]heart and in My [note]2[/note]mind; and I will build him a sure [xref]b[/xref]house; and [xref]c[/xref]he will [note]3[/note]go before My anointed continually.</text>
        <note num="1">Samuel was a priest not by birth but by God raising him up particularly. As a priest Samuel replaced and, in a sense, terminated the stale Aaronic priesthood. He did not rebel against the house of Aaron, and he did not usurp anything of the house of Aaron. As Samuel was growing, God arranged the environment to perfect him and to build up his capacity to do everything that was needed for God to change the age. God used Samuel to change the age not through rebellion but through the way of divine revelation. Samuel was a man of revelation ([link]3:21[/link]), and he did everything according to what he saw. Furthermore, he was a man according to God's heart &amp;#8212; a copy, a duplicate, of God's heart. As such a person, he would never do anything rebellious.</note>
        <note num="2">Samuel's whole being and person, not just his doing, living, and work, were according to God. Samuel's being and God's heart were one. For this reason it is not too much to say that Samuel, a man according to God, was the acting God on earth. God's mind was Samuel's consideration. He had no other thought, consideration, or thinking. His living and working were for the carrying out of whatever was in God's heart. As a consequence, Samuel was one who turned the age.</note>
        <note num="3">Samuel anointed Saul and David to be kings ([link]10:1[/link]; [link]16:1[/link], [link]13[/link]). This was according to God's ordination that Samuel should go before His anointed continually to supervise the king, observing what the king was doing. This indicates that Samuel, the acting God on earth, was greater than the king. Samuel could be qualified to such an extent because for many years God had been perfecting him uniquely for His economy.</note>
        <xref num="a">Heb. 2:17</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. 1 Sam. 25:28; 1 Kings 11:38</xref>
        <xref num="c">cf. Num. 27:21-22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
        <text>And everyone who is left of your house will come and bow down to him for a piece of silver and for a loaf of bread, and will say, Please put me in one of the priests' offices that I may eat a morsel of bread.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And the boy Samuel [xref]a[/xref]ministered to Jehovah before Eli. Now the word of Jehovah was [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]rare in those days; visions were not widespread.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]20[sup]1[/sup][/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 2:11, 18</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 3:7, 21; cf. Amos 8:11-12; Psa. 74:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And at that time Eli lay in his place, and his eyesight had begun to grow [xref]a[/xref]dim, so that he could not see.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 4:15; Gen. 27:1; cf. Deut. 34:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And the [xref]a[/xref]lamp of God had not yet gone out. And Samuel lay in the temple of Jehovah, where the Ark of God was.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 27:20-21; Lev. 24:2-3; 2 Chron. 13:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Then Jehovah called to Samuel. And he said, Here I am.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And he ran to Eli and said, Here I am, for you called me. And he said, I did not call. Go back [i]and[/i] lie down. And he went and lay down.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And Jehovah called yet again, Samuel. And Samuel rose up and went to Eli and said, Here I am, for you called me. And he said, I did not call, my son. Go back [i]and[/i] lie down.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Now Samuel did not yet know Jehovah, and the word of Jehovah had not yet been revealed to him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Then Jehovah called Samuel again, the third time. And he rose up and went to Eli and said, Here I am, for you called me. Then Eli perceived that it was Jehovah calling the boy.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And Eli said to Samuel, Go [i]and[/i] lie down, and if He calls you, you shall say, Speak, O Jehovah; for Your servant is listening. And Samuel went and lay down in his place.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Then Jehovah came and [xref]a[/xref]stood by and called as at the other times, Samuel! Samuel! And Samuel said, Speak, for Your servant is listening.</text>
        <xref num="a">Acts 23:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And Jehovah said to Samuel, [note]1[/note]I am about to do something in Israel which will make both ears of anyone who hears [i]of it[/i] [xref]a[/xref]tingle.</text>
        <note num="1">First, God's severe judgment on the house of Eli was prophesied by a man of God ([link]2:27-36[/link]). Then, this severe judgment was confirmed by the word of Jehovah spoken through Samuel ([link]vv. 4-18[/link]). God's purpose in telling Eli through Samuel of the coming judgment might have been to make an unforgettable impression on this young priestly boy. This was God's wisdom.</note>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 21:12; Jer. 19:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>On that day I will fulfill against Eli all that I have [xref]a[/xref]spoken concerning his house, from beginning to end.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 2:30-36</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>For I have told him that I am about to judge his house forever because of the iniquity which he knew; for his sons brought the curse upon themselves, and he did not restrain them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And therefore I have sworn to the house of Eli that the iniquity of the house of Eli shall not be expiated by sacrifice or by offering forever.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And Samuel lay down until the morning, when he opened the doors of the house of Jehovah. And Samuel was afraid to tell the vision to Eli.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>But Eli called Samuel and said, Samuel my son. And he said, Here I am.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And he said, What was the word that He spoke to you? Do not hide [i]it[/i] from me. May God do so to you, and even more, if you hide from me any of the word which He spoke to you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>So Samuel told him everything and did not hide [i]anything[/i] from him. And he said, He is Jehovah; let Him do what is good in His sight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And Samuel grew, and Jehovah was with him and let none of his words [xref]a[/xref]fall to the ground.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 2 Kings 10:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And all Israel, from Dan to Beer-sheba, knew that [xref]a[/xref]Samuel had been established as a [note]1[/note]prophet of Jehovah.</text>
        <note num="1">Samuel was established by God to speak the word of God to replace the teaching of the word of God by the old priesthood. In the priesthood the first thing that a priest should do is speak for God. The breastplate and the Urim and the Thummim worn by the high priest were the means used by God to speak to His people (see [link]Exo. 28:30[/link] and notes). In the degradation of the priesthood God's speaking was almost lost ([link]v. 1[/link]). Thus, God needed to raise up a living person, a prophet, to speak for Him. In God's ordination Samuel is counted as the first prophet because he brought in the prophethood for God's speaking ([link]Acts 3:24[/link]; [link]13:20[/link]; [link]Heb. 11:32[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Acts 13:20; 3:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And Jehovah continued to appear in [xref]a[/xref]Shiloh, for Jehovah revealed Himself to Samuel in Shiloh by the word of Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">Josh. 18:1; 1 Sam. 1:3</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And the word of Samuel came to all Israel. And Israel went forth against the Philistines in battle; and they encamped near Ebenezer, and the Philistines encamped in Aphek.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And the Philistines arrayed themselves against Israel; and when the battle spread, Israel was struck down before the Philistines. And they slew about four thousand men of the array in the field.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And when the people came to the camp, the elders of Israel said, Why has Jehovah struck us down today before the Philistines? Let us take for ourselves the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Ark of the Covenant of Jehovah from [xref]b[/xref]Shiloh that it may come into our midst, and [i]thus[/i] save us from the hand of our enemies.</text>
        <note num="1">In their degradation Israel was foolish because they did not trust in God directly. Rather, they trusted in the systems ordained by God. In their situation they should have repented, made a thorough confession, and returned to God from their idols, and they should have inquired of God as to what He wanted them to do. Instead, having no heart for God's desire or for His eternal economy, they exercised their superstition to trust in the Ark based on the past victories they had experienced through the move of the Ark ([link]Num. 10:35[/link]; [link]Josh. 6[/link]). But this time their situation was not right. In their degradation they offended God to the uttermost, and God left them. Eventually, instead of the Ark saving Israel, the Ark itself was captured ([link]v. 11a[/link]).[br/][br/]The Ark typifies Christ as the embodiment of God (see note [link]10[sup]1[/sup] in Exo. 25[/link]). It also signifies Christ as the presence of the Triune God with His people for the carrying out of His economy to establish His kingdom on earth. To bring out the Ark was to bring out the presence of God ([link]v. 4[/link]). The move of the Ark was a picture of God's move on the earth in Christ as His embodiment ([link]Num. 10:33-36[/link]; see note [link]1[sup]1[/sup] in Psa. 68[/link]). During Israel's fighting with the Philistines, God did not intend to move. The children of Israel had no thought of or concern for God's economy, and their bringing out the Ark indicated that they were usurping God, even forcing Him to go out with them for their safety, peace, rest, and profit. In principle, we do the same thing whenever we pray for our prosperity without any consideration of God's economy. Instead of usurping God, we should pray, live, and be persons according to God's heart and for His economy.</note>
        <xref num="a">Num. 10:33-35; Josh. 4:7; cf. Jer. 3:16</xref>
        <xref num="b">Josh. 18:1; 1 Sam. 1:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>So the people sent [i]men[/i] to Shiloh, and they took up from there the Ark of the Covenant of Jehovah of hosts who is enthroned [i]between[/i] the cherubim. And the two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, were there with the Ark of the Covenant of God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And when the Ark of the Covenant of Jehovah came into the camp, all Israel shouted with a great shout, and the earth resounded.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And the Philistines heard the sound of the shout and said, What does the sound of this great shout in the camp of the Hebrews mean? Then they found out that the Ark of Jehovah had come into their camp.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And the Philistines were afraid, for they said, God has come into their camp. And they said, Woe to us! For there has never been such a thing as this before.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Woe to us! Who will deliver us from the hand of these mighty gods? These are the gods that [xref]a[/xref]struck the Egyptians with every kind of plague in the wilderness.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 7:5; 9:14; Psa. 78:43-51</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Be strong and be men, O Philistines, lest you become servants to the Hebrews as they have been servants to you. Be men then and fight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And the Philistines fought, and they struck Israel; and every man fled to his tent. And there was a very great slaughter, for thirty thousand foot soldiers of Israel fell.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And the [xref]a[/xref]Ark of God was [note]1[/note]taken, and the two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, [xref]b[/xref]died.</text>
        <note num="1">At this point the Ark was separated from the tabernacle. This abnormal situation persisted for many years, until a full recovery was realized by the people of Israel. In the first stage of its history, the Ark was in the tabernacle ([link]Exo. 40:21[/link]); this is the normal situation. Then, due to Israel's degradation, the Ark was captured by the Philistines and was separated from the tabernacle ([link]4:11-6:1[/link]), leaving the tabernacle an empty vessel without the proper content. Later, the Ark was recovered and brought first to the house of Abinadab at Kiriath-jearim, where it remained for twenty years ([link]6:2-7:2[/link]), and then to the house of Obed-edom the Gittite, where it stayed for three months ([link]2 Sam. 6:1-11[/link]). Still, the Ark was apart from the tabernacle, which was at Shiloh ([link]1:24[/link]; [link]Josh. 18:1[/link]). David moved the Ark from Obed-edom's house to a tent that he had prepared for it in his own city, at Mount Zion, the choicest place in Jerusalem ([link]2 Sam. 6:12-19[/link]; [link]1 Chron. 15:1-16:1[/link]). This was an improved situation, but the Ark was still in an improper place; it had not been returned to the tabernacle. Finally, after Solomon finished the building of the temple in Jerusalem, the Ark was moved into the Holy of Holies in the temple ([link]1 Kings 8:1-11[/link]). This was a full recovery of the normal situation.[br/][br/]The history of the Ark and the tabernacle prefigures the history of the church. In the first stage of its history, the church was the expression of Christ, and Christ was the content of the church. This is the normal condition. However, in the second stage the church became degraded and lost the reality and presence of Christ (cf. [link]Rev. 3:20[/link]). It became an empty vessel, an outward expression without the inward reality. After this, beginning from the second century a number of "Obed-edoms" were raised up, who had the Lord's presence (the Ark) but did not have the proper church life as the expression of Christ (the tabernacle). Later, other believers who, like David, cared for God's interests attempted to practice the church life according to their own choice, not according to God's revelation. These believers had Christ, but they had Him with an improper practice of the church life (David's tent in Jerusalem). Today in His recovery the Lord is working to restore the normal condition of Christ within the proper church as His expression.</note>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 78:60-61</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 2:34; Psa. 78:64</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And a man of Benjamin ran from the array and came to Shiloh on the same day, with his clothes torn and earth upon his head.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And when he came, there was Eli, sitting on his seat by the roadside watching; for his heart trembled for the Ark of God. And when the man came to tell [i]the news[/i] to the city, the whole city cried out.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And when Eli heard the sound of the cry, he said, What does this sound of commotion mean? And the man hurried and came and told Eli.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Now Eli was ninety-eight years old; and his eyes were [xref]a[/xref]set, and he could not see.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 14:4; cf. 1 Sam. 3:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And the man said to Eli, I am he who has come from the array, and I fled from the array today. And he said, How did the matter go, my son?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And he who brought the news answered and said, Israel fled before the Philistines, and there was a great slaughter among the people; and even your two sons, Hophni and Phinehas, are dead; and the Ark of God has been taken.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And when he mentioned the Ark of God, [note]1[/note]Eli fell from off his seat backward by the side of the gate. And he broke his neck and [note]2[/note]died, for he was an old man and heavy. And he had judged Israel forty years.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., he.</note>
        <note num="2">As a priest Eli had the right to enjoy the top portion of all the good land allotted to the twelve tribes of Israel ([link]Num. 18[/link]). However, in his loose disciplining of his two evil sons ([link]2:28-29[/link]), Eli disregarded the priesthood. This caused the tragedy of the ending of his history, the terminating of his enjoyment of the good land, and the fading of the priesthood in the divine revelation, that is, in the speaking for God ([link]3:1[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And his daughter-in-law, the wife of Phinehas, was pregnant, about to deliver; and when she heard the report that the Ark of God had been taken and that her father-in-law and her husband had died, she bowed down and gave birth, for her pains came upon her.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And around the time that she died, the women who stood around her said, Do not fear, for you have borne a son. But she did not answer or pay attention.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And she named the child [note]1[/note]Ichabod, [note]2[/note]meaning, The glory has departed from Israel, because the Ark of God had been taken and because of her father-in-law and her husband.</text>
        <note num="1">Meaning [i]no glory.[/i] Glory is God Himself ([link]Acts 7:2[/link]). Because the Ark of Jehovah, which bore God's presence among His people, had been captured, the glory had departed from Israel ([link]Psa. 78:61[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Or, saying.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And she said, The glory has departed from Israel, for the Ark of God has been taken.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="5">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>When the Philistines took the Ark of God, they brought it from Ebenezer to Ashdod.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And the Philistines took the Ark of God and brought it into the house of Dagon, and they set it next to Dagon.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And when the Ashdodites arose early the next day, there was Dagon, fallen on his face to the ground, before the Ark of Jehovah. And they took Dagon and put him back in his place.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And when they arose early in the morning of the next day, there was Dagon, fallen on his face to the ground, before the Ark of Jehovah. And Dagon's head and the palms of his hands were cut off, [i]lying[/i] on the threshold; [note]1[/note]only Dagon's trunk was left to him.</text>
        <note num="1">Following the ancient versions; the Hebrew reads, only Dagon was left to him.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Because of this, neither the priests of Dagon nor any who enter the house of Dagon tread upon Dagon's threshold in Ashdod to this day.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>But the [xref]a[/xref]hand of [note]1[/note]Jehovah was heavy upon the Ashdodites, and He devastated them and struck them with tumors, even Ashdod and its borders.</text>
        <note num="1">Jehovah dealt heavily with the Philistines for the protection of His Ark ([link]vv. 1-12[/link]). For God to protect His Ark meant that He was protecting His holiness (cf. [link]6:19-20[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 7:4; 9:3; 1 Sam. 5:7, 9, 11; Psa. 32:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And when the men of Ashdod saw that it was so, they said, The Ark of the God of Israel cannot stay with us, for His hand is hard on us and on Dagon our god.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Therefore they sent for and gathered all the lords of the Philistines to themselves, and they said, What shall we do with the Ark of the God of Israel? And they said, Let the Ark of the God of Israel be brought around to Gath. And they brought the Ark of the God of Israel [i]there.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Then after they brought it [i]there,[/i] the [xref]a[/xref]hand of Jehovah was against the city, causing a very great panic. And He struck the men of the city, from small to great; and they broke out with tumors.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 2:15; 1 Sam. 7:13; 12:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Then they sent the Ark of God to Ekron. But when the Ark of God came to Ekron, the Ekronites cried out, saying, They have brought the Ark of the God of Israel around to us to kill us and our people.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And they sent for and gathered all the princes of the Philistines, and they said, Send away the Ark of the God of Israel; and let it return to its place, so that it does not kill us and our people. For the panic of death was throughout the whole city. The hand of God was very heavy there,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And the men who did not die were stricken with tumors. And the cry of the city went up to heaven.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="6">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Now the Ark of Jehovah was in the country of the Philistines seven months.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And the Philistines called for the priests and the diviners and said, What shall we do with the Ark of Jehovah? Make known to us how we should send it forth to its place.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And they said, If you send away the Ark of the God of Israel, do not send it away empty, but be sure to return Him a [xref]a[/xref]trespass offering. Then you will be healed, and it will be made known to you why His hand has not turned away from you.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Lev. 5:15-16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And they said, What is the trespass offering that we should return to Him? And they said, Five golden [note]1[/note]tumors and five golden mice, [i]according to[/i] the number of the lords of the Philistines; for one plague was upon you all and upon your lords.</text>
        <note num="1">The Philistines, who were very close neighbors of Israel, typify the people of the religious world. Their worldly way in handling the things of God is shown in the trespass offering that they offered to God and in their use of a cart and two milch cows to send the Ark back to Israel ([link]vv. 7-12[/link]). Cf. note [link]7[sup]2[/sup] in 2 Sam. 6[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Therefore you shall make images of your tumors and images of your mice that devastate the land, and you shall give glory to the God of Israel; perhaps He will lighten His [xref]a[/xref]hand on you and your gods and your land.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Sam. 5:6-7, 9, 11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Why then should you [xref]a[/xref]harden your hearts as the Egyptians and Pharaoh hardened their hearts? When He had dealt severely with them, did they not let [note]1[/note]the people go, and they went?</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., them.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. Exo. 7:13; 8:15; 9:34-35; 10:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>So now take and prepare a new [xref]a[/xref]cart and two milch cows on which the yoke has never come, and tie the cows to the cart, and bring their calves home, away from them.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 6:3; cf. 1 Chron. 15:2; 2 Chron. 35:3; Num. 7:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And take the Ark of Jehovah and put it on the cart; and in a box by the side of it, place the articles of gold which you are returning to Him as a trespass offering; and send it away that it may go.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Then watch: If it goes up toward its own border at Beth-shemesh, it is He who has done us this great harm. But if it does not, we will know that it was not His hand that struck us; it happened to us by chance.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And the men did so and took two milch cows and tied them to the cart and shut up their calves at home.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And they put the Ark of Jehovah on the cart with the box and the gold mice and the images of their tumors.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And the cows went straight in the way toward Beth-shemesh; they went on one road, lowing as they went; and they did not turn to the right or to the left. And the lords of the Philistines went after them as far as the border of Beth-shemesh.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>[i]Now the people of[/i] Beth-shemesh were reaping their wheat harvest in the valley. And when they lifted up their eyes and saw the Ark, they rejoiced to see [i]it.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And the cart came into the field of Joshua the Beth-shemeshite and stood still there. And there was a great stone there. And they split up the wood of the cart and offered up the cows as a burnt offering to Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Then the Levites took down the Ark of Jehovah and the box that was with it, in which were the articles of gold; and they placed them on the great stone. And the men of Beth-shemesh offered up burnt offerings and sacrificed sacrifices that day to Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And when the five lords of the Philistines saw [i]this,[/i] they returned to Ekron that day.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And these are the gold tumors that the Philistines returned to Jehovah as a trespass offering: for Ashdod, one; for Gaza, one; for Ashkelon, one; for Gath, one; for Ekron, one;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And the gold mice, [i]according to[/i] the number of all the cities of the Philistines that belonged to the five lords, both of fortified cities and country villages, as far as the [note]1[/note]great stone on which they rested the Ark of Jehovah, [i]which is there[/i] to this day, in the field of Joshua the Beth-shemeshite.</text>
        <note num="1">Some MSS read, great Abel.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And He struck the men of Beth-shemesh because they [xref]a[/xref]looked into the Ark of Jehovah; and He struck seventy men [note]1[/note]among the people. And the people mourned because Jehovah struck the people with a great slaughter.</text>
        <note num="1">Some MSS add, [i]and[/i] fifty thousand men.</note>
        <xref num="a">Num. 4:20; Exo. 19:21</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And the men of Beth-shemesh said, Who can stand before Jehovah, this holy God? And to whom shall He go up from us?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And they sent messengers to the inhabitants of [xref]a[/xref]Kiriath-jearim, saying, The Philistines have returned the Ark of Jehovah; come down [i]and[/i] take it up to you.</text>
        <xref num="a">Josh. 18:14; 1 Chron. 13:5-6</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="7">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And the men of Kiriath-jearim came and took up the Ark of Jehovah and brought it to the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]house of Abinadab on the hill, and they consecrated Eleazar his son to keep the Ark of Jehovah.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]11[sup]1[/sup], par. 1, in ch. 4[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 6:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And it was a long time from the day that the Ark began to abide in Kiriath-jearim, for it was twenty years. And all the house of Israel lamented after Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Then Samuel [note]1[/note]spoke to all the house of Israel, saying, If you are [xref]a[/xref]returning with all your heart to Jehovah, [xref]b[/xref]remove the foreign gods and the Ashtaroth from your midst, and direct your heart to Jehovah and [xref]c[/xref]serve only Him; and He will deliver you from the hand of the Philistines.</text>
        <note num="1">The picture in [link]vv. 2-6[/link] shows a people returning to God, and a man, Samuel, who was one with God on earth. As the acting God on earth, the representative of the very God in heaven to rule over His people on earth, Samuel began to minister.[br/][br/]Samuel, who was by nature a Levite born of one of the descendants of the great rebel Korah ([link]1 Chron. 6:33-38[/link]; cf. [link]Num. 16:1-33[/link]), ministered in five statuses: (1) as a Nazarite consecrated to God absolutely for God's fulfillment of His economy, a volunteer to replace any official and formal serving ones of God ([link]1:11[/link], [link]28a[/link]); (2) as a priest faithful to act on behalf of God, even to appoint and establish kings for the divine government on earth ([link]2:35[/link]); (3) as a prophet established by God ([link]3:20[/link]) to assist the kings appointed by him as a priest, to speak the word of God to replace the teaching of the word of God by the old priesthood; (4) as a judge ([link]vv. 15-17[/link]) established by God to carry out God's governmental administration, to replace the judging of the people by the old priesthood; and (5) as a man of prayer who prayed for God's elect, the children of Israel ([link]vv. 3-14[/link]; [link]8:6[/link]; [link]15:11b[/link]; cf. [link]12:23[/link]), that they would be kept in the way of God, would be one with God, would not be ensnared by the idols of the nations, and would enjoy God as Ebenezer ([link]v. 12[/link]) that God's desire in His will regarding His elect might be fulfilled. God admitted to Jeremiah that Samuel, like Moses, was a man standing before Him for His people ([link]Jer. 15:1[/link]). Moses was a priest ([link]Exo. 29[/link]), a prophet ([link]Deut. 18:15[/link], [link]18[/link]), and a judge ([link]Exo. 18:13[/link], [link]16[/link]), and he always prayed for God's people (e.g., [link]Exo. 32:11-13[/link], [link]31-32[/link]). In these matters Samuel was the same. In the Old Testament only Moses and Samuel were qualified to participate fully in the priesthood, the prophethood, and the judgeship.</note>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 30:2-10; 1 Kings 8:48; Isa. 55:7; Hosea 6:1; Joel 2:12</xref>
        <xref num="b">Gen. 35:2; Josh. 24:23; Judg. 10:16</xref>
        <xref num="c">Deut. 6:13; 10:20; 13:4; Matt. 4:10; Luke 4:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Then the children of Israel removed the Baals and the Ashtaroth, and served only Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And Samuel said, Gather all Israel to Mizpah, and I will pray to Jehovah for you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And they gathered at Mizpah and drew water and poured it out before Jehovah, and they fasted that day. And they said there, We have sinned against Jehovah. And Samuel judged the children of Israel at Mizpah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Now when the Philistines heard that the children of Israel gathered themselves at Mizpah, the lords of the Philistines went up against Israel. And when the children of Israel heard [i]of it,[/i] they were afraid of the Philistines.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And the children of Israel said to Samuel, Do not stop crying to Jehovah our God for us, so that He will save us from the hand of the Philistines.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And Samuel took a suckling lamb and offered it up as a whole burnt offering to Jehovah. And [xref]a[/xref]Samuel cried out to Jehovah for Israel, and Jehovah answered him.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 99:6; Jer. 15:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And while Samuel was offering up the burnt offering, the Philistines approached for battle against Israel. And Jehovah thundered with a great voice that day against the Philistines and threw them into a panic; and they were struck down before Israel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And the men of Israel went out from Mizpah and pursued the Philistines, and they struck them as far as below Beth-car.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Then Samuel took a stone and set [i]it[/i] between Mizpah and Shen; and he called its name [note]1[/note]Ebenezer and said, Thus far Jehovah has helped us.</text>
        <note num="1">Meaning the [i]stone of help.[/i]</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>So the Philistines were subdued, and they no longer came into the territory of Israel. And the [xref]a[/xref]hand of Jehovah was against the Philistines all the days of Samuel.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 5:9; 12:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And the cities which the Philistines had taken from Israel were returned to Israel, from Ekron to Gath; and Israel rescued their territory from the hand of the Philistines. And there was peace between Israel and the Amorites.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And Samuel judged Israel all the days of his life.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And he went year by year in circuit to Bethel and Gilgal and Mizpah, and he judged Israel in all those places.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Then he would return to Ramah, for his house was there. And he judged Israel there and built an altar to Jehovah there.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="8">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Now when Samuel was old, he made his sons [xref]a[/xref]judges over Israel.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Judg. 8:22-23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And the name of his firstborn son was Joel, and the name of his second was Abijah; they were judges in Beer-sheba.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>But his sons did [note]1[/note]not follow in his ways, but turned aside after unjust [xref]a[/xref]gain and took [xref]b[/xref]bribes and perverted justice.</text>
        <note num="1">The unjust ways of Samuel's sons were contrary to their father's pure and just way in his whole life ([link]12:3-5[/link]) and gave the people of Israel cause to ask Samuel to appoint a king to judge them like all the nations ([link]vv. 4-5[/link]). Hence, the sons of Samuel should not be reckoned judges among the people of Israel ([link]Acts 13:20[/link]), and their father Samuel should be considered the last judge.[br/][br/]The only defect in Samuel's history was that he appointed his two sons as judges among the children of Israel. Humanly, Samuel made a mistake in this matter, but this mistake helped God to manage the situation among His people by bringing in the kingship for the fulfillment of His economy.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. Exo. 18:21</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. Exo. 23:8; Deut. 16:19; Psa. 15:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Then all the elders of Israel gathered together and came to Samuel at Ramah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And they said to him, You are now old, and your sons do not follow in your ways. Appoint now for us a [xref]a[/xref]king to judge us like all the [note]1[/note]nations.</text>
        <note num="1">Israel had been chosen by God to be a particular people on earth; therefore, they should have been absolutely different in every respect from the nations. Yet they took the way of following the nations by rejecting God as their King.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. Deut. 17:14; 1 Sam. 8:19-20; Hosea 13:10; Acts 13:21</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>But the matter displeased Samuel when they said, Give us a king to judge us. Then Samuel prayed to Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And Jehovah said to Samuel, Listen to the voice of the people according to all that they have said to you; for it is [xref]a[/xref]not you whom they have rejected, but they have [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]rejected Me from being King over them.</text>
        <note num="1">By insisting on having a king, the elect of God turned from God to a man. In doing this they not only displeased Samuel ([link]v. 6[/link]) but also offended God by rejecting Him as their King and thus replacing Him ([link]v. 7[/link]; [link]12:12[/link]). This was a great wickedness, a great evil, in the sight of God ([link]12:17[/link], [link]19[/link]). Whatever we may do, no matter how good, "spiritual," and even scriptural it may be, it is evil in the sight of God if we reject Him as our Head, our Husband, and our King. It is not a matter of right or wrong; it is a matter of whether we take God as our King or reject Him. It is for this reason that Samuel as a Nazarite kept his hair long, covering his head with God Himself as his authority ([link]1:11[/link]; [link]Num. 6:5[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. Exo. 16:8</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 10:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Like all the deeds that they have done since the day that I brought them up out of Egypt to this very day by forsaking Me and serving other gods, so they do also to you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Now therefore listen to their voice, but you shall solemnly warn them and declare to them the [xref]a[/xref]practice of the king who will reign over them.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Sam. 8:11-18; 10:25</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>So Samuel spoke all the words of Jehovah to the people, who had asked him for a king.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And he said, This will be the practice of the king who will reign over you: He will take your [xref]a[/xref]sons and appoint them for himself to his chariots and as his horsemen, and they will run before his chariots;</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Sam. 14:52</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And he will appoint [i]them[/i] for himself as captains of thousands and as captains of fifties, and to plow his ground and reap his harvest, and to make his instruments of war and the equipment for his chariots.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And he will take your [xref]a[/xref]daughters to be perfumers and cooks and bakers.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Deut. 17:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And he will take your best [xref]a[/xref]fields and [xref]b[/xref]vineyards and olive groves, and give [i]them[/i] to his servants.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Ezek. 46:18</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Kings 21:6-7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And he will exact a tenth of your seed and of your vineyards, and give [i]it[/i] to his eunuchs and servants.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And he will take your male servants and your female servants and your best young men and your donkeys, and put [i]them[/i] to his work.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>He will exact a tenth of your flocks, and you will be his servants.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And you will cry out in that day on account of your king, whom you have chosen for yourselves; but Jehovah will not answer you in that day.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>But the people refused to listen to the voice of Samuel, and they said, No; but there will be a king over us,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>That we also may be like all the nations, and that our king may judge us and go out before us and fight our battles.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And Samuel heard all the words of the people, and he spoke them in the hearing of Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Then Jehovah said to Samuel, Listen to their voice, and [note]1[/note]appoint a [xref]a[/xref]king to them. And Samuel said to the men of Israel, Go, each one to his city.</text>
        <note num="1">Samuel turned the age in God's administration from the age of the priesthood to the age of the prophethood with the kingship. This was a great thing not only in the history of Israel but even in the history of mankind. Moses was a priest, and after him God's administration was centered on the priesthood (see note [link]21[sup]1[/sup] in Num. 27[/link]). The priesthood was to minister the word of God to His people and to exercise the authority of God over His people. The Aaronic priesthood failed God in these two things. At the waning of the God-ordained priesthood, God began a new age in raising up Samuel, a young Nazarite, as a faithful priest to replace the waning priesthood ([link]2:35[/link]). God ministered His word to His elect by establishing Samuel as a prophet in the uplifted prophethood ([link]3:20-21[/link]), and He exercised His authority over His elect by raising up Samuel as a judge ([link]7:15-17[/link]). Samuel, as the last judge, terminated the judgeship, and, as the new priest, brought in the kingship, which was strengthened by the uplifted prophethood, in which Samuel was established as the first prophet ([link]Acts 3:24[/link]; [link]13:20[/link]; [link]Heb. 11:32[/link]). Through Samuel God set up a governmental administration in His economy so that He could fulfill His promises to all the forefathers and accomplish His desire according to His economy, that is, to have a line of genealogy to bring Christ to the earth.[br/][br/]At the end of his ministry, by the time that Saul was raised up to be the king in Israel ([link]9:3-10:27[/link]), Samuel had reached the highest position, only God being above him. Thus, as God's representative, Samuel was the acting God. However, God did not have any intention to make a kingdom of Samuel. Rather, God determined to raise up David, through whom He intended to build up a kingdom ([link]2 Sam. 7:12-13[/link]). God had the intention that Christ would be born in the lineage of David. Hence, God raised up Samuel and prepared him for His use to do whatever was necessary to gain, through David, the proper genealogy of Christ. As a Nazarite according to his mother's vow, Samuel had no heart for anything other than God and His elect. He could be used by God to carry out His economy because he was a man according to God and God's heart, having no self-seeking nor any thought of self-gain.</note>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 13:11</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="9">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Now there was a man from Benjamin whose name was [xref]a[/xref]Kish, the son of Abiel, the son of Zeror, the son of Becorath, the son of Aphiah, a Benjaminite, a man of [note]1[/note]wealth.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, valor.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 14:51; 1 Chron. 8:33; 9:39; Acts 13:21</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And he had a son whose name was [note]1[/note]Saul, a choice and handsome man; and there was not a man among the children of Israel more handsome than he; from his shoulders and up he was taller than all the people.</text>
        <note num="1">Meaning [i]asked for.[/i]</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Now the donkeys of Kish, Saul's father, were lost; and Kish said to Saul his son, Take with you one of the servants, and rise up [i]and[/i] go to search for the donkeys.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And he passed through the hill country of Ephraim, and he passed through the land of Shalishah; but they did not find [i]them.[/i] Then they passed through the land of Shaalim, but they were not [i]there.[/i] Then he passed through the land of Benjamin, but they did not find [i]them.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>When they came to the land of Zuph, Saul said to his servant who was with him, Come, and let us return; otherwise, my father will stop [i]worrying[/i] about the donkeys and will worry about us.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>But he said to him, There is a [xref]a[/xref]man of God here in this city, and he is a man held in honor; all that he says happens without fail. Let us now go there; perhaps he will tell us about our journey that we have set out on.</text>
        <xref num="a">Judg. 13:6; 1 Sam. 2:27; 1 Kings 13:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And Saul said to his servant, But if we go, what will we bring the man? For the food is gone from our bags, and there is no present to bring the man of God. What do we have?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And the servant answered Saul again and said, Here in my hand is a quarter shekel of silver, and I can give [i]it[/i] to the man of God; then he will tell us our way.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>(Formerly in Israel a man spoke this way when he went to inquire of God, Come, and let us go to the [xref]a[/xref]seer; for today's prophet was formerly called a seer.)</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Chron. 29:29; 2 Kings 17:13; 2 Sam. 15:27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Then Saul said to his servant, Well said; come, let us go. So they went to the city where the man of God was.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>As they went up the ascent into the city, they found some girls coming out to draw water; and they said to them, Is the seer here?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And they answered them and said, He is; there he is ahead of you. Hurry now; for he has [i]just[/i] come to the city today, because the people have a sacrifice at the [xref]a[/xref]high place today.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 10:5; 1 Kings 3:2-4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Right when you enter the city, you will find him, before he goes up to the high place to eat. For the people will not eat until he comes, because he is the one who [xref]a[/xref]blesses the sacrifice. Right after that, those who have been invited will eat. Go up now then, for you will find him right away.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Tim. 4:5; Mark 6:41; Matt. 26:26</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>So they went up into the city. As they came into the midst of the city, there came Samuel out toward them, going up to the high place.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Now Jehovah had revealed [i]this[/i] to Samuel a day before Saul came, saying,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>At about this time tomorrow I will send to you a man from the land of Benjamin, and you shall [xref]a[/xref]anoint him ruler over My people Israel; and he will save My people from the hand of the Philistines, for I have looked upon My people because their [xref]b[/xref]cry has come to Me.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 15:1; cf. Acts 13:2</xref>
        <xref num="b">Exo. 2:23-24; 3:7, 9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And when Samuel saw Saul, Jehovah declared to him, [xref]a[/xref]Here is the man of whom I spoke to you. This man shall rule over My people.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Sam. 16:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And Saul approached Samuel in the gate and said, Tell me, please, where is the seer's house?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And Samuel answered Saul and said, I am the seer. Go up before me to the high place, for you shall eat with me today; and in the morning I will send you away, and I will tell you all that is in your heart.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And as for your donkeys that have now been lost three days, do not [i]even[/i] consider them; for they have been found. And for whom is all the desire of Israel? Is it not for you and for all your father's house?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And Saul answered and said, Am I not a [xref]a[/xref]Benjaminite, of the [xref]b[/xref]smallest of the tribes of Israel? And [i]is not[/i] my family the least of all the families of the tribe of Benjamin? Why then do you speak to me in this way?</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 68:27</xref>
        <xref num="b">Judg. 6:15; 1 Sam. 15:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And Samuel took Saul and his servant, and brought them to the hall, and put them in the chief place among those who had been invited; and there were about thirty men.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>And Samuel said to the cook, Bring the portion that I gave, concerning which I said to you, Set it by you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And the cook took up the [xref]a[/xref]thigh and what was attached to it, and set it before Saul. And [i]Samuel[/i] said, Here is what has been reserved. Set [i]it[/i] before you [i]and[/i] eat, because it has been kept for you for the appointed time, when I said I was inviting the people. So Saul ate with Samuel that day.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 29:22, 17; Lev. 7:32-33; Ezek. 24:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>And when they came down from the high place to the city, he spoke with Saul upon the roof.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>And they rose early; and around the break of dawn Samuel called to Saul on the roof, saying, Rise up, and I will send you away. So Saul rose up, and they both went outside, he and Samuel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>As they were going down to the end of the city, Samuel said to Saul, Tell the servant to go on ahead of us &amp;#8212; and [i]the servant[/i] went on &amp;#8212; but you stand here now, and I will let you hear the word of God.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="10">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Then Samuel took the vial of [xref]a[/xref]oil and poured [i]it[/i] upon his head, and he kissed him and said, [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]Jehovah anoints you ruler over His [xref]c[/xref]inheritance.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., Has not Jehovah anointed...? God's purpose in anointing Saul to be king was to discipline, to train, the children of Israel by means of a negative king, so that they would learn that replacing God with a king was not a matter of blessing ([link]v. 19[/link]; [link]12:17[/link], [link]19[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 9:16; 16:13; 2 Sam. 2:4; 1 Kings 1:34, 39; 2 Kings 9:1, 3, 6; Psa. 89:20</xref>
        <xref num="b">Acts 13:21</xref>
        <xref num="c">Deut. 32:9; Psa. 78:71</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>When you depart from me today, you will find two men by [xref]a[/xref]Rachel's tomb in the territory of Benjamin at Zelzah; and they will say to you, The donkeys that you went to look for have been found; and now your father has stopped worrying about the donkeys and is worried about you, saying, What shall I do about my son?</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 35:19-20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Then you will go on further from there and come to the terebinth of Tabor; and three men will meet you there, going up to God at Bethel, one carrying three kids, and another carrying three loaves of bread, and another carrying a skin of wine.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And they will greet you and give you two loaves of bread, and you will take [i]them[/i] from their hand.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>After that you will come to [note]1[/note]the hill of God, where the Philistines' garrison is. And as you come to the city there, you will encounter a group of prophets coming down from the [xref]a[/xref]high place, preceded by harp and tambourine and pipe and lyre; and they will be prophesying.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, Gibeah-haelohim.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 9:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And the [xref]a[/xref]Spirit of Jehovah will rush upon you; and you will [xref]b[/xref]prophesy with them and be turned into another man.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 16:13; cf. Num. 11:25; Judg. 3:10; 14:6, 19</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 19:23-24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And when these signs happen to you, do as you find occasion, for God is with you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And you shall go down before me to [xref]a[/xref]Gilgal; and behold, I will come down to you to offer up burnt offerings [i]and[/i] to sacrifice sacrifices of peace offerings. You shall wait [xref]b[/xref]seven days, until I come to you; then I will make known to you what you shall do.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 11:14-15; 13:4</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 13:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And so when he turned his back to depart from Samuel, God gave him another heart. And all these signs happened that day.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And when they came there to [note]1[/note]the hill, there was the group of prophets, [i]coming[/i] to meet him. And the [xref]a[/xref]Spirit of God rushed upon him, and he prophesied among them.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, Gibeah.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 11:6; 1 Chron. 12:18; 2 Chron. 24:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And when all who had known him previously saw that now he was prophesying with the prophets, the people said one to another, What is this that has happened to the son of Kish? Is Saul also [xref]a[/xref]among the prophets?</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 19:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And someone from there answered and said, And who is their father? Therefore it became a proverb, Is Saul also among the prophets?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And when he finished prophesying, he came to the high place.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And Saul's uncle said to him and his servant, Where did you go? And he said, To look for the donkeys; and when we saw that they were not to be found, we went to Samuel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And Saul's uncle said, Tell me then what Samuel said to you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And Saul said to his uncle, He told us clearly that the donkeys had been found. But he did not tell him about the matter of the kingdom that Samuel had spoken of.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Then Samuel gathered the people together to Jehovah at Mizpah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And he said to the children of Israel, Thus says Jehovah the God of Israel, I [xref]a[/xref]brought up Israel out of Egypt, and I delivered you from the hand of the Egyptians and from the hand of all the kingdoms that oppressed you.</text>
        <xref num="a">Judg. 6:8-9; 1 Sam. 12:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>But today you have rejected your God, who Himself saved you from all your calamities and distresses, and have said, [note]1[/note]No; but set a [xref]a[/xref]king over us. And now present yourselves [xref]b[/xref]before Jehovah according to your tribes and according to your thousands.</text>
        <note num="1">Some MSS read, to Him.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 8:5-6, 19-20; 12:12</xref>
        <xref num="b">Josh. 24:1; 1 Sam. 10:25</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>So Samuel brought all the [xref]a[/xref]tribes of Israel near, and the tribe of Benjamin was [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]taken.</text>
        <note num="1">Saul was made king by the casting of lots ([link]vv. 20-23a[/link]) to prove that he was chosen by God. Cf. note [link]2[sup]1[/sup] in Josh. 14[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Josh. 7:14-18; Num. 17:2</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 14:41-42</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And he brought the tribe of Benjamin near according to its families, and the family of Matri was taken. And Saul the son of Kish was taken. But when they sought him, he could not be found.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Therefore they [xref]a[/xref]asked of Jehovah again, Is there yet [i]another[/i] man coming here? And Jehovah said, There [i]he is;[/i] he has hidden himself among the baggage.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 23:2; Num. 27:21</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>And they ran and took him from there. And when he stood up among the people, he was taller than all the people from his shoulders and up.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And Samuel said to all the people, See him whom Jehovah has chosen, that there is none like him among all the people. And all the people shouted and said, Long live the king!</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Then Samuel told the people the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]practice of the kingdom, and he wrote it in a book and laid it before Jehovah. And Samuel sent all the people away, every man to his house.</text>
        <note num="1">Moses gave the law to the children of Israel, but before Samuel came they did not have a set of bylaws, a constitution. Samuel taught the people the bylaws, the constitution, the practice, the customs, the manners, the ordinances, and the rules of how to practice the kingdom of God on earth.</note>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 17:14-20; 1 Sam. 8:9, 11-18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>And Saul also went to his house at Gibeah, and the [i]men of[/i] valor, whose hearts God had touched, went with him;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>But some worthless men said, How can this man save us? And they despised him and brought him no present. But he kept silent.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="11">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Then [xref]a[/xref]Nahash the Ammonite went up and encamped against [xref]b[/xref]Jabesh-gilead. And all the men of Jabesh said to Nahash, Make a treaty with us, and we will serve you.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 12:12</xref>
        <xref num="b">Judg. 21:8; 1 Sam. 31:11; 2 Sam. 2:4-5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And Nahash the Ammonite said to them, On this condition I will make [i]a treaty[/i] with you, that all your right eyes be gouged out; and I will make it a reproach upon all Israel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And the elders of Jabesh said to him, Give us seven days' respite that we may send messengers throughout all the territory of Israel. And if there is no one to save us, we will come out to you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Then the messengers went to Gibeah of Saul, and they spoke these words in the hearing of the people. And all the people lifted up their voice and wept.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And Saul was just coming from the field after the oxen, and Saul said, What is wrong with the people that they weep so? And they related to him the words of the men of Jabesh.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And the [xref]a[/xref]Spirit of God rushed upon Saul as he heard these words, and his anger was greatly kindled.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 10:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And he took a yoke of oxen and cut them into [xref]a[/xref]pieces and sent [i]them[/i] throughout all the territory of Israel by means of the messengers, saying, Whoever does not come forth after Saul and after Samuel, so shall it be done to his oxen. And the dread of Jehovah fell upon the people, and they came forth as one man.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Judg. 19:29; 20:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And he mustered them in Bezek; and the children of Israel were three hundred thousand, and the men of Judah were thirty thousand.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And they said to the messengers who had come, Thus shall you say to the men of Jabesh-gilead, Tomorrow you will have deliverance by the time the sun is hot. So the messengers went and told [i]this[/i] to the men of Jabesh; and they were glad.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And the men of Jabesh said, Tomorrow we will come out to you, and you may do to us all that seems good in your sight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And on the next day Saul put the people into three companies, and they came into the midst of the camp at the morning watch. And they struck Ammon until the day was hot; and those who remained were so scattered that not two of them remained together.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And the people said to Samuel, Who said, [xref]a[/xref]Shall Saul reign over us? Bring the men that we may put them to death.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Sam. 10:27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>But Saul said, No man shall be put to death on this day, for today Jehovah has accomplished deliverance in Israel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Then Samuel said to the people, Come and let us go to [xref]a[/xref]Gilgal and there renew the [note]1[/note]kingdom.</text>
        <note num="1">Although Saul had been victorious over the Ammonites and appeared to be an attractive, humble person, Samuel's reminder to Israel ([link]11:14-12:25[/link]) indicates that according to Samuel's realization the nation of Israel was still not the kingdom of God on earth. Rather, it was Saul's personal monarchy. The kingdom of God came first under David, when God's throne was established in Jerusalem ([link]2 Sam. 7:12-16[/link]; cf. [link]Matt. 21:43[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 10:8; 13:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And all the people went to Gilgal. And there they made Saul king before Jehovah in Gilgal, and there they sacrificed peace offerings before Jehovah, and there Saul and all the men of Israel rejoiced greatly.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="12">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And Samuel said to all Israel, I have now listened to your voice according to all that you have [xref]a[/xref]said to me, and I have placed a king over you.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 8:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And now, here is the king who goes before you. But I am [xref]a[/xref]old and gray, and my sons are here with you, and I have gone before you from my youth until this day.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 8:1, 5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Here I am; testify against me before Jehovah and before His anointed. Whose ox have I taken? Or whose donkey have I taken? Or whom have I [xref]a[/xref]defrauded? Whom have I oppressed? Or from whose hand have I taken a bribe in order to blind my eyes with it? Then I will restore [i]it[/i] to you.</text>
        <note num="1">Samuel's reminder implies a comparison between Samuel and Saul. His reminding Israel of his integrity ([link]vv. 1-5[/link]) implied that Saul would pervert justice and take away many things from the people. Samuel had this kind of foresight concerning Saul.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. Num. 16:15; Acts 20:33; 2 Cor. 7:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And they said, You have not defrauded us or oppressed us or taken anything from anyone's hand.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And he said to them, Jehovah is Witness against you, and His anointed is witness this day, that you have not found anything in my hand. And they said, [i]He is[/i] witness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And Samuel said to the people, It is Jehovah who appointed Moses and Aaron and who [xref]a[/xref]brought your fathers up out of the land of Egypt.</text>
        <xref num="a">Micah 6:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Now therefore stand here, that I may plead with you before Jehovah concerning all the righteous acts of Jehovah, which He did to you and to your fathers.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>When Jacob went to [xref]a[/xref]Egypt, and your fathers [xref]b[/xref]cried out to Jehovah, Jehovah [xref]c[/xref]sent Moses and Aaron; and they [xref]d[/xref]brought your fathers out from Egypt and caused them to dwell in this place.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 46:5-7</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. Exo. 2:22-23; 3:9</xref>
        <xref num="c">Exo. 3:10; 4:14-16</xref>
        <xref num="d">Judg. 6:8; 1 Sam. 10:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>But they forgot Jehovah their God, and He sold them into the hand of [xref]a[/xref]Sisera, the captain of Hazor's army, and into the hand of the [xref]b[/xref]Philistines and into the hand of the king of [xref]c[/xref]Moab; and they fought against them.</text>
        <xref num="a">Judg. 4:2</xref>
        <xref num="b">Judg. 10:7; 13:1</xref>
        <xref num="c">Judg. 3:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Then they [xref]a[/xref]cried out to Jehovah and said, We have sinned, for we have forsaken Jehovah and have served the Baals and the Ashtaroth; but deliver us now from the hand of our enemies, and we will serve You.</text>
        <xref num="a">Judg. 3:9; 10:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And Jehovah sent [xref]a[/xref]Jerubbaal and [note]1[/note]Bedan and [xref]b[/xref]Jephthah and [xref]c[/xref]Samuel, and He delivered you from the hand of your enemies all around; and you dwelt securely.</text>
        <note num="1">The Septuagint and other ancient versions read, Barak.</note>
        <xref num="a">Judg. 6:14, 32</xref>
        <xref num="b">Judg. 11:1</xref>
        <xref num="c">1 Sam. 7:9-13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And when you saw that [xref]a[/xref]Nahash the king of the children of Ammon came against you, you said to me, [note]1[/note]No; but a king will reign over us, though Jehovah your God was your [xref]b[/xref]King.</text>
        <note num="1">Here Samuel was rebuking Israel for leaving God as her Husband and King. Because they wanted a king as a replacement for God, they would not have the proper enjoyment of the good land.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 11:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. 1 Sam. 8:7; Judg. 8:23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Now therefore here is the king whom [xref]a[/xref]you have chosen [i]and[/i] whom you have asked for. See then, Jehovah has set a [xref]b[/xref]king over you.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Sam. 10:24</xref>
        <xref num="b">Hosea 13:11; Acts 13:21</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>If you fear Jehovah and serve Him and listen to His voice and do not rebel against the commandment of Jehovah, and [i]if[/i] both you and the king who reigns over you follow Jehovah your God, [i]fine.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>But if you do not listen to the voice of Jehovah, but rebel against the commandment of Jehovah, then the hand of Jehovah will be against you, as [i]it was[/i] against your fathers.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Now therefore stand here and see this great thing that Jehovah will do before your eyes.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Is it not the wheat harvest today? I will call to Jehovah, that He send thunder and rain; and you will know and see that your wickedness which you have done in the sight of Jehovah by asking for a king for yourselves is great.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And Samuel called to Jehovah, and Jehovah sent [xref]a[/xref]thunder and rain on that day. And all the people feared Jehovah and Samuel greatly.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 9:23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Then all the people said to Samuel, Pray to Jehovah your God for your servants that we would not die, for we have added to all our sins the evil of asking for a king for ourselves.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And Samuel said to the people, Do not be afraid. You have done all this evil, yet do not turn away from following Jehovah, but serve Jehovah with all your heart.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And do not turn away, for [i]your turning away would be[/i] after [xref]a[/xref]vain [i]idols,[/i] which cannot profit or deliver [i]you,[/i] for they are vanity.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 32:21; Jer. 14:22; Acts 14:15; Hab. 2:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>For because of His great name Jehovah will not forsake His people, for Jehovah has been pleased to make you a [xref]a[/xref]people for Himself.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 7:6; 14:2; 1 Pet. 2:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Moreover as for me, far be it from me that I would [note]1[/note]sin against Jehovah by ceasing to pray for you, but I will instruct you in the good and right way.</text>
        <note num="1">Samuel considered that not praying for God's people was a sin against Jehovah. God's elect are His peculiar, personal possession as a treasure ([link]Exo. 19:5[/link]). This book shows that Samuel's heart was only for God's elect. Samuel's caring for God's elect was a crucial aspect of the history concerning Samuel, which was in sharp contrast to the history concerning Saul.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>Only, fear Jehovah and serve Him in truth with all your heart, for consider what great things He has done for you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>But if you still do wickedly, both you and your king will be consumed.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="13">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Saul [note]1[/note]was...years old when he began to reign; and he reigned over Israel two years.</text>
        <note num="1">The Hebrew text lacks the exact age of Saul; the Septuagint lacks the entire verse.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And Saul chose three thousand men from Israel for himself; and two thousand were with Saul in Michmash and in the hill country of Bethel, and one thousand were with Jonathan in Gibeah of Benjamin. And the rest of the people he sent away, every man to his tent.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And Jonathan struck the garrison of the Philistines that was in Geba, and the Philistines heard [i]of it.[/i] And Saul blew the trumpet throughout all the land, saying, Let the Hebrews hear!</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And when all Israel heard that Saul had struck the garrison of the Philistines and also that Israel had become odious to the Philistines, the people gathered themselves behind Saul at Gilgal.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And the Philistines assembled themselves for battle with Israel, thirty thousand chariots and six thousand horsemen and people like the sand that is on the seashore in multitude. And they came up and encamped in Michmash, east of Beth-aven.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>When the men of Israel saw that they were in distress (for the people were hard pressed), the people hid themselves in caves and in thickets and among rocks and in cellars and in pits.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And some Hebrews crossed over the Jordan into the land of Gad and Gilead; but Saul was still in Gilgal, and all the people trembled behind him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And he waited for [xref]a[/xref]seven days, until the time appointed by Samuel, but Samuel did not come to Gilgal. And the people scattered from him.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 10:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Then Saul said, Bring the [xref]a[/xref]burnt offering and the peace offerings to me. And he [note]1[/note]offered up the burnt offering.</text>
        <note num="1">Saul's disobedience was exposed in the matter of his sinful offering ([link]vv. 8-12[/link]). Saul was disobedient, yet he still offered something to God. In the war with the Philistines Saul's intention to act on his own for the building up of his own monarchy within the building up of God's kingdom was exposed. Saul's disobedience, which was observed by Samuel, meant that he had given up God; it resulted in his losing his kingship ([link]vv. 13-15a[/link]; [link]15:28[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Sam. 10:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And just as he finished offering up the burnt offering, there came Samuel; and Saul went out to meet him and greet him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And Samuel said, What have you done? And Saul said, When I saw that the people were scattered from me and that you had not come at the appointed time and that the Philistines assembled themselves at Michmash,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>I said, Now the Philistines will come down on me at Gilgal, and I have not entreated the favor of Jehovah. Therefore I forced myself to offer up the burnt offering.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Then Samuel said to Saul, You have acted foolishly; you have not kept the commandment of Jehovah your God, which He commanded you. For now Jehovah would have established your kingdom over Israel forever;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>But now your kingdom will not continue. Jehovah has [xref]a[/xref]sought a [note]1[/note]man according to His heart for Himself, and Jehovah has appointed [note]1[/note]him ruler over His people; for you have not kept that which Jehovah commanded you.</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to David, to whom God would shift the kingship ([link]16:1-13[/link]; [link]28:17[/link]). See note [link]22[sup]1[/sup] in Acts 13[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Acts 13:22; cf. 1 Sam. 15:28</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Then Samuel rose and went up from Gilgal to Gibeah of Benjamin. And Saul mustered the people who were with him, about six hundred men.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And Saul and Jonathan his son and the people who were with them dwelt in Geba of Benjamin, and the Philistines encamped in Michmash.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And the raiders came out from the camp of the Philistines in three companies. One company turned toward Ophrah, to the land of Shual;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And another company turned toward Beth-horon; and another company turned toward the border that overlooks the valley of Zeboim toward the wilderness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Now there was [xref]a[/xref]no smith to be found throughout all the land of Israel, for the Philistines had said, Lest the Hebrews make swords or spears;</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 2 Kings 24:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Therefore all Israel would go down to the Philistines so that each might sharpen his plowshare or his mattock or his ax or his hoe.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>[note]1[/note]And the price was two-thirds of a shekel for plowshares and for mattocks and for three-pronged forks and for axes and for setting the goads.</text>
        <note num="1">The form and meaning of the Hebrew text of this verse is uncertain.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>So on the day of the battle there was [note]1[/note]not a sword or spear to be found in the hand of any of the people who were with Saul and with Jonathan, but [i]such[/i] were found with Saul and Jonathan his son.</text>
        <note num="1">On the day of battle, only Saul and Jonathan his son had a sword and a spear. In such a poor situation, God was their unique weapon. Saul, Jonathan, and the people of Israel fought the battle by God.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>And the garrison of the Philistines went out to the pass of Michmash.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="14">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Now one day Jonathan the son of Saul said to the young man who carried his armor, Come and let us cross over to the garrison of the Philistines that is on the other side; but he did not tell his father.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And Saul was staying in the outskirts of Gibeah under the pomegranate tree that is in Migron; and the people with him were about six hundred men,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Including Ahijah the son of [xref]a[/xref]Ahitub, [xref]b[/xref]Ichabod's brother, the son of Phinehas, the son of Eli, the priest of Jehovah in [xref]c[/xref]Shiloh, wearing an [xref]d[/xref]ephod; and the people did not know that Jonathan went.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 22:9, 11, 20</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 4:21</xref>
        <xref num="c">Josh. 18:1</xref>
        <xref num="d">1 Sam. 2:28</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And in the pass by which Jonathan sought to cross over to the garrison of the Philistines, there was a rocky crag on one side, and another rocky crag on the other side; and the name of the one was Bozez, and the name of the other was Seneh.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>The one crag rose up on the north before Michmash; and the other, on the south before Geba.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And Jonathan said to the young man who carried his armor, Come and let us cross over to the garrison of these uncircumcised. Perhaps Jehovah will act on our behalf, for there is no constraint on Jehovah to save by many or by few.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And his armor bearer said to him, Do all that is in your heart. Go to it; I am here with you according to your heart.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And Jonathan said, Now we will cross over to the men and disclose ourselves to them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>If they say this to us, Wait until we come to you; then we will stand in our place and not go up to them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>But if they say this, Come up to us; then we will go up, for Jehovah will have delivered them into our hand, and this will be the sign [i]of it[/i] to us.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And both of them disclosed themselves to the garrison of the Philistines. And the Philistines said, The Hebrews are now coming out of the [xref]a[/xref]holes that they hid themselves in.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 13:6; 14:22; Judg. 6:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And the men of the garrison answered Jonathan and his armor bearer and said, Come up to us, and we will show you something. Then Jonathan said to his armor bearer, Come up after me, for Jehovah has delivered them into the hand of Israel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And Jonathan went up on his hands and feet with his armor bearer behind him; and [note]1[/note]the Philistines fell before Jonathan, and his armor bearer went behind him killing [i]them.[/i]</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., they.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And that first slaughter that Jonathan and his armor bearer made was of about twenty men in half a furrow of an acre of land.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And there was a panic in the camp, in the field, and among all the people; even the garrison and the raiders were in a panic; and the earth quaked. And there came to be a [note]1[/note]very great panic.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., panic of God.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And Saul's watchmen in Gibeah of Benjamin looked; and the multitude was just then melting away, and they were going here and there.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Then Saul said to the people who were with him, Call a muster, and see who has gone from us. And they called a muster, and Jonathan and his armor bearer were not there.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And Saul said to Ahijah, Bring the Ark of God here; for the [xref]a[/xref]Ark of God was at that time with the children of Israel.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 7:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And while Saul spoke to the priest, the tumult that was in the camp of the Philistines continued to increase. Then Saul said to the priest, Withdraw your hand.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And Saul and all the people who were with him gathered together and went into the battle. And each man's sword was against his companion; the tumult was very great.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And the [xref]a[/xref]Hebrews who had previously been with the Philistines [i]and[/i] who had gone up with them into the camp all around, they also [i]turned[/i] to be with the Israelites who were with Saul and Jonathan.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Sam. 29:3-4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Likewise, when all the men of Israel who had [xref]a[/xref]hidden themselves in the hill country of Ephraim heard that the Philistines had fled, even they followed them closely in the battle.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 13:6; 14:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Thus Jehovah saved Israel that day, and the battle crossed over beyond Beth-aven.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And the men of Israel were distressed that day; for Saul had laid an oath on the people, saying, Cursed be the man who eats any food before the evening, when I am avenged of my enemies. So none of the people [i]even[/i] tasted food.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>And all those from the land came upon a honeycomb, and there was [xref]a[/xref]honey on the surface of the ground.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 3:8; Deut. 8:8; cf. Judg. 14:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>And when the people came to the honeycomb, there was [xref]a[/xref]honey flowing; but no one put his hand to his mouth, for the people were afraid of the oath.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 3:8; Num. 13:27; Mark 1:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>But Jonathan had not heard his father charge the people with the oath; and he put forth the end of his staff that was in his hand and dipped it in the honeycomb, and he put his hand to his mouth, and his eyes brightened.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>Then someone from among the people responded and said, Your father sternly charged the people with an oath, saying, Cursed be the man who eats any food today; and so the people are faint.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>Then Jonathan said, My father has troubled the land. Look how my eyes lit up because I tasted a bit of this honey.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>How much more if today the people had eaten up the spoil from their enemies, which they found, for now the slaughter among the Philistines has not been great.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>Now they had struck down the Philistines that day from Michmash to Aijalon, and the people were very faint.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>And the people flew upon the spoil; and they took sheep and oxen and calves, and slew [i]them[/i] on the ground; and the people ate [i]them[/i] with the blood.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>And it was reported to Saul, saying, The people are now sinning against Jehovah by eating [i]the spoil[/i] with the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]blood. And he said, You have dealt treacherously. Roll a large stone to me today.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]17[sup]1[/sup] in Lev. 3[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. Lev. 3:17; 7:26-27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>And Saul said, Disperse yourselves among the people, and say to them, Let each man bring his ox here to me, and each his sheep; and slay [i]them[/i] here and eat; and do not sin against Jehovah by eating [i]these things[/i] with the blood. And all the people brought their oxen with them there that night and slew [i]them[/i] there.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>And Saul built an [xref]a[/xref]altar to Jehovah; it was the first altar that he built to Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Sam. 7:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
        <text>And Saul said, Let us go down after the Philistines by night and take spoil among them until the morning light, and let us not leave a man among them. And they said, Do all that is good in your sight. But the [xref]a[/xref]priest said, Let us draw near to God here.</text>
        <xref num="a">Num. 27:21</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
        <text>And Saul inquired of God, Shall I go down after the Philistines? Will You deliver them into the hand of Israel? But He did not answer him that day.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
        <text>Then Saul said, Come here, all you chiefs of the people; and find out how this sin has happened today.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
        <text>For as Jehovah lives, who saves Israel, even if it is with Jonathan my son, he shall surely be put to death. But there was no one among all the people who answered him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
        <text>And he said to all Israel, You shall be on one side, and I and Jonathan my son shall be on the other side. And the people said to Saul, Do what is good in your sight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
        <text>Then Saul said to Jehovah the God of Israel, Show perfectly. And Jonathan and Saul were taken [i]by [xref]a[/xref]lot,[/i] but the people escaped.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 10:20-21; Acts 1:24-26; cf. Josh. 7:16-18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
        <text>And Saul said, Cast [i]the lot[/i] between me and Jonathan my son. And Jonathan was taken.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
        <text>Then Saul said to Jonathan, Tell me what you have done. And Jonathan told him and said, I did indeed taste a bit of honey with the end of the staff that was in my hand. Here I am; I must die.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
        <text>And Saul said, God do so [note]1[/note]to me and more so, for you shall surely die, Jonathan.</text>
        <note num="1">Some MSS omit, to me.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
        <text>Then the people said to Saul, Shall Jonathan die, who has executed this great salvation in Israel? Far from it! As Jehovah lives, not a hair of his head shall fall to the ground; for he has worked with God this day. So the people rescued Jonathan so that he did not die.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
        <text>Then Saul went up from following the Philistines, and the Philistines went to their own place.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="47">
        <text>Now when Saul had taken the kingdom over Israel, he fought against all his enemies all around, against Moab and against the children of Ammon and against Edom and against the kings of Zobah and against the Philistines. And wherever he turned, he did [i]them[/i] harm.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="48">
        <text>And he performed valiantly and struck the Amalekites and delivered Israel from the hand of those who had plundered them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="49">
        <text>Now the sons of Saul were [xref]a[/xref]Jonathan and Ishvi and Malchi-shua. And the names of his two daughters were these: The name of the firstborn was [xref]b[/xref]Merab, and the name of the younger was [xref]c[/xref]Michal.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Chron. 8:33; 9:39; cf. 1 Sam. 31:2</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 18:17, 19</xref>
        <xref num="c">1 Sam. 18:20, 27; 19:12, 17; 2 Sam. 6:20-21, 23; 21:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="50">
        <text>And the name of Saul's wife was Ahinoam the daughter of Ahimaaz. And the name of the captain of his army was [xref]a[/xref]Abner the son of Ner, Saul's uncle.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 2:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="51">
        <text>And Kish was Saul's father; and Ner, the father of Abner, was the son of Abiel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="52">
        <text>And there was severe war against the Philistines all the days of Saul; and when Saul saw any mighty man or any valiant man, he [xref]a[/xref]took him for himself.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 8:11</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="15">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And Samuel said to Saul, Jehovah sent me to [xref]a[/xref]anoint you king over His people, over Israel. Now therefore listen to the voice of the words of Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 9:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Thus says Jehovah of hosts, I will punish the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Amalekites [i]for[/i] what they did to Israel when they set themselves against them in the way as they came up out of Egypt.</text>
        <note num="1">In typology the Amalekites signify the flesh &amp;#8212; the fallen man ([link]Exo. 17:8-16[/link]; [link]Gen. 6:3a[/link]; [link]Rom. 3:20a[/link]). God created man, not the flesh, but man became fallen and eventually became flesh. In the entire universe God's unique enemy, in a practical sense, is not Satan but the flesh ([link]Rom. 8:7[/link]). The flesh, the fallen man, is altogether one with Satan ([link]Matt. 16:23[/link]) and is used by Satan to fight against God ([link]Gal. 5:17[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 17:8-16; Deut. 25:17-19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Go now and strike the Amalekites; and [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]utterly destroy all that they have, and do not spare them, but kill both man and woman, infant and suckling, oxen and sheep, camel and donkey.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., devote (i.e., to destruction). So throughout this chapter. In charging Saul to utterly destroy the Amalekites, God wisely put Saul in a situation in order to test him.</note>
        <xref num="a">Num. 21:2; Josh. 6:21</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And Saul summoned the people and mustered them in Telaim, two hundred thousand footmen and ten thousand men of Judah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And Saul came to the city of the Amalekites and set an ambush in the river valley.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And Saul said to the [xref]a[/xref]Kenites, Go, depart; go down from among the Amalekites; otherwise, I will destroy you with them; for you showed kindness to all the children of Israel when they came up out of Egypt. And the Kenites departed from among the Amalekites.</text>
        <xref num="a">Judg. 1:16; 4:11; 1 Sam. 27:10; 30:29</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Then Saul struck the Amalekites from Havilah as you go toward Shur, which is opposite Egypt.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And he captured [xref]a[/xref]Agag the king of the Amalekites alive and utterly destroyed all the people with the edge of the sword.</text>
        <xref num="a">Num. 24:7; Esth. 3:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>But Saul and the people [note]1[/note]spared Agag and the best of the sheep and of the oxen and of the fatlings, and the lambs and all that was good, and would not utterly destroy them; but everything that was despised and worthless, this they utterly destroyed.</text>
        <note num="1">Saul and the people's sparing the best of the things that should have been utterly destroyed portrays the fact that, experientially, we treasure the good aspects of our flesh, our natural life, and do not wish to destroy them. Whatever we do apart from God's grace and apart from depending on Him and trusting in Him is of the flesh. Every aspect of the flesh, whether good or evil, is in opposition to grace and God's kingship and keeps us from enjoying Christ (cf. [link]Gal. 3:3[/link]; [link]5:2-4[/link], and notes). Therefore, we must hate every aspect of the flesh and be absolute in destroying the flesh.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And the word of Jehovah came to Samuel, saying,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>I [xref]a[/xref]repent that I made Saul king, for he has turned back from following Me and has not fulfilled My words. And Samuel was angry, and he [xref]b[/xref]cried to Jehovah all night long.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 6:6; 1 Sam. 15:35</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. 1 Sam. 15:35; 16:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Then Samuel rose early to meet Saul in the morning. And it was told Samuel, saying, Saul went to Carmel and has now set up a [note]1[/note]monument [xref]a[/xref]for himself, and he has returned and passed on down to Gilgal.</text>
        <note num="1">Saul built this monument not for the kingdom of God but for the remembrance of himself because of the victory that made both him and his monarchy rich. This was a strong indication that Saul's intention was to build up his monarchy within God's kingdom.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Sam. 14:52</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And Samuel came to Saul, and Saul said to him, Blessed are you of Jehovah! I have fulfilled the word of Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And Samuel said, What then is this bleating of sheep in my ears and the lowing of oxen that I hear?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And Saul said, They have been brought from the Amalekites; for the people spared the best of the sheep and oxen to [note]1[/note]sacrifice to Jehovah your God, and the rest we have utterly destroyed.</text>
        <note num="1">God did not want the best of the cattle to be used as a sacrifice to Him. In His eyes, such a thing was evil ([link]v. 19[/link]). Anything presented and sacrificed to God that has its source in the flesh is evil in His sight. To offer something to God according to our own will is presumptuous and is sinful. See [link]Gen. 4:5[/link] and note; [link]Matt. 7:22-23[/link] and note [link book="Matt." chapter="7"]23[sup]1[/sup][/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Then Samuel said to Saul, Stop, and I will tell you what Jehovah spoke to me last night. And he said to him, Speak.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And Samuel said, Though you are [xref]a[/xref]small in your own eyes, are you not the head of the tribes of Israel? And Jehovah has anointed you king over Israel.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Sam. 9:21</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And Jehovah sent you on a journey and said, Go and utterly destroy the sinners, the Amalekites, and fight against them until they are consumed.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Why then did you not obey the voice of Jehovah, but flew upon the spoil and did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And Saul said to Samuel, I surely did obey the voice of Jehovah, and I went on the journey that Jehovah sent me on. And I have brought Agag the king of the Amalekites and have utterly destroyed the Amalekites.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>But of the spoil the people took sheep and oxen, the chief of those things devoted to destruction, to sacrifice to Jehovah your God in Gilgal.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And Samuel said, / Does Jehovah delight in [xref]a[/xref]burnt offerings and sacrifices / As much as in obeying the voice of Jehovah? / Behold, to obey is better than sacrifice, / [i]And[/i] to heed, than the fat of rams.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 50:8-9; Isa. 1:11-13; Jer. 7:22-23; Micah 6:6-8; Hosea 6:6; Matt. 9:13; Mark 12:33; Heb. 10:6-9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>For [note]1[/note]rebellion is [i]like[/i] the sin of divination, / And insubordination is [i]like[/i] idolatry and teraphim. / Because you have rejected the word of Jehovah, / He has also [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]rejected you from being king.</text>
        <note num="1">Doing good according to our own will is actually an act of rebellion against God's throne and His economy (see note [link]16[sup]1[/sup] in Exo. 17[/link]). Saul's disobedience exposed him as being a rebel against God and an enemy of God (see note [link]17[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 22[/link]). What Saul did was as evil as contacting an evil spirit for the purpose of carrying out the intention of that spirit, not God's intention. Samuel's word in this verse indicates that sparing the good aspects of our flesh involves us with evil spirits and idolatry.</note>
        <note num="2">If we are not absolute in dealing with our flesh, we, like Saul, will lose our kingship. This account of Saul's disobedience is a warning, indicating that we should not do anything in the kingdom of God by our flesh. In everything we must crucify our flesh with its passions and its lusts ([link]Gal. 5:24[/link]; [link]Rom. 8:13[/link]) and faithfully exercise our spirit to follow the Lord, who is the life-giving, consummated Spirit indwelling our spirit and who is one with us ([link]1 Cor. 15:45[/link]; [link]6:17[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 4:22[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:16[/link], [link]25[/link]). Then the kingdom of God, the church as the intrinsic Body of Christ ([link]Matt. 16:18-19[/link]; [link]Rom. 14:17[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:22-23[/link]), which will consummate in the New Jerusalem ([link]Rev. 21:2[/link]), will be built up.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 13:14; 15:26</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And Saul said to Samuel, I have sinned; for I have transgressed the commandment of Jehovah and your words, because I feared the people and obeyed their voice.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Now therefore pardon my sin, I beg you, and return with me so that I may worship Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>But Samuel said to Saul, I will not return with you, for you have rejected the word of Jehovah, and Jehovah has rejected you from being king over Israel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>And when Samuel turned around to go, [note]1[/note]Saul seized the corner of his cloak, and it tore.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., he.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>And Samuel said to him, Jehovah has [xref]a[/xref]torn the kingdom of Israel away from you today and has given it to an [note]1[/note]associate of yours, who is better than you.</text>
        <note num="1">This associate was David ([link]16:1-13[/link]; [link]28:17[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 28:17-18; cf. 1 Kings 11:30-31</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>Moreover the Eminence of Israel does not lie nor [xref]a[/xref]repent, for He is not a man that He should repent.</text>
        <xref num="a">Num. 23:19; Ezek. 24:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>Then [note]1[/note]Saul said, I have sinned. Honor me now, I beg you, before the elders of my people and before Israel, and return with me so that I may worship Jehovah your God.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., he.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>So Samuel returned after Saul, and Saul worshipped Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>Then Samuel said, Bring Agag the king of the Amalekites near to me. And Agag came to him cheerfully, for Agag said, Surely the bitterness of death has turned.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>And Samuel said, Just as your sword has made women childless, so shall your mother be childless among women. And Samuel hewed Agag to pieces before Jehovah in Gilgal.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>And Samuel went to Ramah, and Saul went up to his house in Gibeah of Saul.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>And Samuel never again saw Saul unto the day of his death, though Samuel [xref]a[/xref]mourned for Saul. And Jehovah [xref]b[/xref]repented that He had made Saul king over Israel.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 16:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 15:11</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="16">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And Jehovah said to Samuel, How long will you [xref]a[/xref]mourn for Saul, though I have [xref]b[/xref]rejected him from being king over Israel? Fill your horn with [xref]c[/xref]oil, and [note]1[/note]go; I will send you to [xref]d[/xref]Jesse the [xref]e[/xref]Bethlehemite; for I have [note]2[/note]selected for Myself a king among his sons.</text>
        <note num="1">God had abandoned Saul, rejecting him from being king over Israel ([link]15:23[/link]). Immediately thereafter God sent Samuel to contact a youth, David, who was perhaps only fifteen years old. This shows that while Saul was usurping and even abusing the God-given kingship in order to build up his own monarchy, God was aware of the situation and was doing something marvelous to prepare the right person. God went secretly to David, the great grandson of Boaz and Ruth ([link]Ruth 4:21-22[/link]).[br/][br/]David was created and prepared by God to be a man according to the heart of God ([link]13:14a[/link]). Otherwise, he could not have been such a man. However, as shown in [link]chs. 16-17[/link], he still needed to pass through the process of being chosen, trained, anointed, tested, and approved. David was thirty years old when he began to reign ([link]2 Sam. 5:4[/link]). After David was anointed by Samuel, he was tested for about fifteen years. In particular, he was bothered and troubled by Saul. Eventually, David passed the test and was approved by God.</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., seen.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 15:35</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 15:23, 26</xref>
        <xref num="c">1 Sam. 10:1</xref>
        <xref num="d">1 Sam. 16:11-13; 17:12; Ruth 4:22; 1 Chron. 28:4; Matt. 1:6</xref>
        <xref num="e">1 Sam. 20:6; Micah 5:2; Luke 2:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And Samuel said, How can I go? If Saul hears [i]of it,[/i] he will kill me. And Jehovah said, Take a heifer with you, and say, I have come to sacrifice to Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Then call Jesse to the sacrifice, and I will make known to you what you shall do. And you shall anoint for Me the one whom I name to you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>So Samuel did what Jehovah said and came to Bethlehem. And the elders of the city came trembling to meet him, and they said, Do you come peaceably?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And he said, Peaceably. I have come to sacrifice to Jehovah. [xref]a[/xref]Sanctify yourselves and come with me to the sacrifice. And he sanctified Jesse and his sons and called them to the sacrifice.</text>
        <xref num="a">Num. 11:18; Josh. 3:5; 7:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And when they came, he saw [xref]a[/xref]Eliab and said, Surely Jehovah's anointed is [i]now[/i] before Him.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 17:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>But Jehovah said to Samuel, Do not regard his [xref]a[/xref]appearance and the height of his stature, because I have rejected him. For [i]it is[/i] not how man sees [i]that matters;[/i] for man looks on the outward appearance, but Jehovah looks on the [xref]b[/xref]heart.</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 22:16; James 2:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Kings 8:39; 1 Chron. 28:9; Psa. 7:9; Prov. 21:2; Jer. 11:20; 17:10; 20:12; Luke 16:15; Acts 1:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Then Jesse called [xref]a[/xref]Abinadab and had him pass before Samuel; and [note]1[/note]Samuel said, Jehovah has not chosen this one either.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., he.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 17:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And Jesse had Shammah pass by; and he said, Jehovah has not chosen this one either.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And Jesse had [note]1[/note]seven of his sons pass before Samuel; and Samuel said to Jesse, Jehovah has not chosen these.</text>
        <note num="1">David was the eighth son of Jesse ([link]17:12[/link], [link]14[/link]), the number eight signifying resurrection. In the scriptural sense, David was one who was in resurrection; hence, he was the one whom God could use.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Then Samuel said to Jesse, Are these all the young men [i]you have?[/i] And he said, There is still the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]youngest, but he is now tending the [xref]b[/xref]sheep. And Samuel said to Jesse, Send for [i]him,[/i] and bring him; for we will not sit down until he comes here.</text>
        <note num="1">After being chosen by God ([link]vv. 1-10[/link]), David was trained by God in humility through his circumstances. God purposely caused him to be born as the youngest one, the last one, to make him humble. Furthermore, David was assigned the lowly task of going to the field to take care of the sheep.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 17:14</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. 2 Sam. 7:8; Psa. 78:70-71</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>So he sent for [i]him[/i] and brought him in. Now he was [xref]a[/xref]ruddy [i]and[/i] had beautiful eyes and a handsome appearance. And Jehovah said, Arise; anoint him, for this is he.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 17:42</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And Samuel took the horn of oil and [xref]a[/xref]anointed him in the midst of his brothers, and the [xref]b[/xref]Spirit of Jehovah [note]1[/note]rushed [xref]c[/xref]upon [note]2[/note]David from that day forward. Then Samuel rose up and went to Ramah.</text>
        <note num="1">The rushing of the Spirit upon David was a confirmation of Samuel's anointing David with oil. It was related not to life for salvation but to power for outward activities (see notes [link]49[sup]3[/sup] in Luke 24[/link] and [link]2[sup]1[/sup] in Acts 2[/link]). The Spirit of Jehovah departing from Saul and an evil spirit from Jehovah terrorizing him ([link]v. 14[/link]) were a further confirmation that God had chosen someone other than him.</note>
        <note num="2">Meaning [i]beloved.[/i]</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Sam. 10:1; Psa. 89:20</xref>
        <xref num="b">Judg. 3:10; 1 Sam. 10:6, 10; cf. Isa. 61:1; Luke 4:18</xref>
        <xref num="c">cf. Isa. 11:1-2; 42:1; Matt. 3:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And the Spirit of Jehovah [xref]a[/xref]departed from Saul, and an evil spirit from Jehovah terrorized him.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 18:12; 28:15-16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And Saul's servants said to him, See now, an evil spirit from God is terrorizing you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Let our lord speak. Your servants are before you; they will seek out a man who is skilled in playing the lyre. And when the evil spirit from God is upon you, he will [xref]a[/xref]play [i]it[/i] by hand, and you will be well.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 16:23; 18:10; 19:9; cf. 2 Kings 3:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And Saul said to his servants, Select for me a man who can play well, and bring [i]him[/i] to me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And one of the attendants answered and said, I have just seen a son of Jesse the Bethlehemite, who is skilled in playing and a mighty man of valor and a man of war and prudent in speech and of good presence, and Jehovah is with him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>So Saul sent messengers to Jesse and said, Send me [note]1[/note]David your son, who is among the [xref]a[/xref]sheep.</text>
        <note num="1">Under God's sovereignty David was selected to become an attendant of Saul. God put these two together to live and work together very closely. Eventually, however, the closer they became, the more Saul hated David. Simply by being put together, Saul and David became a test to each other. Saul was exposed as a person who was opposite to God's will, and David was manifested to be a man according to God's heart ([link]13:14a[/link]). This was God's sovereignty.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 16:11; 17:15, 34</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And Jesse took a donkey [i]laden[/i] with bread and a skin of wine and a kid, and sent [i]them[/i] by David his son to Saul.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And David came to Saul and [note]1[/note]entered his service. And [note]2[/note]Saul loved him greatly, and he became his armor bearer.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., stood before him. So also in the next verse.</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., he.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And Saul sent [i]word[/i] to Jesse, saying, Let David enter my service, for he has found favor in my sight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>So whenever the evil spirit from God was upon Saul, David took his lyre and [xref]a[/xref]played [i]it[/i] by hand, and Saul was refreshed and was well; and the evil spirit departed from him.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 16:16</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="17">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And the Philistines assembled their armies for battle, and they assembled in Socoh, which belongs to Judah. And they encamped between Socoh and Azekah in Ephes-dammim.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And Saul and the men of Israel were assembled, and they encamped in the valley of Elah. And they set the battle in array against the Philistines.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And the Philistines stood on one mountain on one side, and Israel stood on another mountain on the other side; and the valley was between them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And a champion came forth from the camps of the Philistines. His name was [xref]a[/xref]Goliath, from Gath, and he was six cubits and a span tall.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 17:23; 21:9; cf. 2 Sam. 21:19; 1 Chron. 20:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And there was a bronze helmet upon his head; and he was clothed with scaled armor, and the weight of the armor was five thousand bronze shekels.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And he had bronze greaves upon his legs and a bronze javelin [i]slung[/i] between his shoulders.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And the shaft of his spear was like a weaver's beam, and the head of his spear weighed six hundred iron shekels; and his shield bearer went before him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And he stood and called out to the ranks of Israel and said to them, Why do you come out to set the battle in array? Am I not a Philistine, and you, Saul's servants? Choose a man for yourselves, and let him come down to me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>If he is able to fight with me and strike me down, we will be your servants; but if I prevail against him and strike him down, you will be our servants and serve us.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And the Philistine said, I defy the ranks of Israel this day. Give me a man, and let us fight together.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Now when Saul and all Israel heard these words of the Philistine, they were dismayed and greatly afraid.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Now David was the son of that Ephrathite from Bethlehem-judah, named [xref]a[/xref]Jesse, who had [xref]b[/xref]eight sons. And the man was an old man in the days of Saul, advanced [i]in years[/i] among men.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 16:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 16:10-11; cf. 2 Chron. 2:13-15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And the three oldest sons of Jesse had gone after Saul to the battle. And the names of his three sons who had gone into the battle were [xref]a[/xref]Eliab the firstborn and the second to him Abinadab and the third Shammah;</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 16:6, 8-9; cf. 1 Chron. 2:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And David was the [xref]a[/xref]youngest. And the three oldest went after Saul,</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 16:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>But David went back and forth from Saul to tend his father's [xref]a[/xref]sheep at Bethlehem.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 16:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And the Philistine approached morning and evening, and he presented himself [xref]a[/xref]forty days.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Matt. 4:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And Jesse said to David his son, Take an ephah of this parched grain for your brothers and these ten loaves, and take them quickly to your brothers' camp.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Also bring these ten cheeses to the captain of [i]their[/i] thousand; and see how your brothers are doing, and take some token from them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Now Saul and they and all the men of Israel were in the valley of Elah, fighting with the Philistines.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And David rose early in the morning and left the sheep with a keeper. And he took up [i]the goods[/i] and went, as Jesse had commanded him. And he came to the entrenchment as the army was going forth to the battle line and shouting for the battle.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And Israel and the Philistines set the battle in array, array against array.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And David left the things he had in the hand of the keeper of the equipment, and he ran to the array and went and greeted his brothers.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>And just as he was speaking with them, the champion, whose name was [xref]a[/xref]Goliath, the Philistine from Gath, came up out of the ranks of the Philistines, and he spoke according to the same words; and David heard.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 17:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And all the men of Israel, when they saw the man, fled from before him; and they were very afraid.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>And the men of Israel said, Have you seen this man who has come up? Surely he comes up to defy Israel. But as for the man who strikes him down, the king will make him rich with great riches; and he will give him his daughter and make the house of his father [note]1[/note]free in Israel.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., free from tax and duty.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>Then David spoke to the men who were standing with him, saying, What shall be done for the man who strikes down this Philistine and turns away reproach from Israel? For who is this [xref]a[/xref]uncircumcised Philistine that he should defy the ranks of the [xref]b[/xref]living God?</text>
        <xref num="a">Judg. 14:3; 1 Sam. 14:6; 17:36</xref>
        <xref num="b">Deut. 5:26; Josh. 3:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>And the people spoke to him according to these words, saying, Thus shall it be done to the man who strikes him down.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>And Eliab his oldest brother heard him speaking to the men; and Eliab's anger was kindled against David, and he said, Why have you come down? And with whom have you left those few sheep in the wilderness? I know your pride and the evil of your heart, that you came down to see the battle.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>And David said, What have I done now? Is there no cause?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>And he turned around from him to another and spoke according to the same words, and the people responded to him according to the first words.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>And when the words that David spoke were heard, they were reported to Saul; and he had him brought.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>And David said to Saul, Let no man's heart fail because of him; your servant will go and fight with this Philistine.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>But Saul said to David, You are not able to go against this Philistine to fight with him, for you are [i]but[/i] a youth and he has been a man of war since his youth.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>And David said to Saul, Your servant has been tending his father's sheep; and when a lion or a bear came and took a lamb from the flock,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>I would go out after it and strike it and deliver [i]the lamb[/i] from its mouth. And when it rose up against me, I would seize [i]it[/i] by its beard and strike it and kill it.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
        <text>Both the lion and the bear did your servant strike; and this uncircumcised Philistine will be like one of them, for he has defied the ranks of the living God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
        <text>And David said, Jehovah, who [xref]a[/xref]delivered me from the paw of the lion and from the paw of the bear, He will deliver me from the hand of this Philistine. And Saul said to David, Go, and may Jehovah be with you.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 2 Tim. 4:17; Heb. 11:33</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
        <text>And Saul put his own garment on David, and he placed a bronze helmet on his head and put [i]his[/i] armor on him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
        <text>And David girded his sword over his garment and tried to go, for he had not tried [i]the armor.[/i] Then David said to Saul, I cannot go in these because I have not tried [i]them.[/i] And David took them off.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
        <text>Then he took his staff in his hand, and he chose for himself five smooth stones from the brook and put them into the shepherd's bag that he had, that is, in his pouch; and his sling was in his hand. And he drew near to the Philistine.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
        <text>And the Philistine came on and approached David, and the man who bore the shield was before him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
        <text>And when the Philistine looked and saw David, he scorned him; for he was [i]but[/i] a [xref]a[/xref]youth and ruddy and handsome in appearance.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 17:33; 16:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
        <text>And the Philistine said to David, Am I a dog, that you come to me with staves? And the Philistine cursed David by his gods.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
        <text>And the Philistine said to David, Come to me, and I will give your flesh to the birds of heaven and to the beasts of the field.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
        <text>Then David said to the Philistine, You come to me with sword and spear and javelin, but I come to you in the [xref]a[/xref]name of Jehovah of hosts, the God of the ranks of Israel, whom you have defied.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 20:5-7; 124:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
        <text>On this day Jehovah will deliver you up into my hand, and I will strike you and remove your head from you. And I will give the corpses of the camp of the Philistines to the birds of heaven and to the animals of the earth on this day. And all the earth will [xref]a[/xref]know that there is a God in Israel;</text>
        <xref num="a">Josh. 4:24; 1 Kings 18:36</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="47">
        <text>And all this congregation will know that it is not by sword or spear that Jehovah [xref]a[/xref]saves, for the battle is Jehovah's and He will deliver you into our hand.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 14:6; 2 Chron. 14:11; 20:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="48">
        <text>And when the Philistine rose up and came and drew near to meet David, David hurried and ran toward the battle line to meet the Philistine.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="49">
        <text>And David put forth his hand into his bag and took a stone from there. And he slung [i]it[/i] and struck the Philistine in his forehead. And the stone sank into his forehead, and he fell on his face to the ground.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="50">
        <text>Thus David [xref]a[/xref]prevailed over the Philistine with a sling and a stone, and struck the Philistine and killed him; but there was no sword in David's hand.</text>
        <xref num="a">Heb. 11:34</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="51">
        <text>Then David ran and stood beside the Philistine, and he took [note]1[/note]the Philistine's [xref]a[/xref]sword and drew it out of its sheath and made certain he was dead by striking off his head with it. And when the Philistines saw that their mighty man was dead, they fled.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., his.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 21:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="52">
        <text>And the men of Israel and Judah rose up and shouted and pursued the Philistines until you come to Gai and to the gates of Ekron. And the Philistines lay slain along the way to Shaaraim as far as Gath and Ekron.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="53">
        <text>And the children of Israel returned from chasing the Philistines, and they plundered their camps.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="54">
        <text>And David took the head of the Philistine and brought it to Jerusalem, but he put his armor in his tent.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="55">
        <text>Now when Saul saw David going forth to meet the Philistine, he said to Abner the captain of the army, Whose son is this youth, Abner? And Abner said, As your soul lives, O king, I do not know.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="56">
        <text>And the king said, Inquire whose son this young man is.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="57">
        <text>So when David returned from striking down the Philistine, Abner took him and brought him before Saul; and the Philistine's head was in his hand.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="58">
        <text>And Saul said to him, Whose son are you, young man? And David said, The son of your servant [xref]a[/xref]Jesse the Bethlehemite.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 16:1</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="18">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Now when he had finished speaking to Saul, the soul of Jonathan became knit with the soul of David; and Jonathan [xref]a[/xref]loved him like his own soul.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 19:1; 20:17; 2 Sam. 1:26</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And Saul took him that day and would not let him return to his father's house.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Then Jonathan and David made a [xref]a[/xref]covenant, because he loved him like his own soul.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 20:8; 23:18; 2 Sam. 21:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And Jonathan stripped himself of the robe that was upon him, and he gave it to David, as well as his armor and even his sword and his bow and his belt.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And David went forth; on every [i]mission[/i] that Saul sent him he acted prudently. Therefore Saul set him over the men of battle, and it was good in the sight of all the people and also in the sight of Saul's servants.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>But when the men came [i]home,[/i] as David returned from striking the Philistines, the women came out of all the towns of Israel singing and dancing to meet Saul the king, with tambourines and joyful songs and stringed instruments.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And the women sang to one another as they played, and they said,[br/][xref]a[/xref]Saul has struck down his thousands; / But David, his ten thousands.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 21:11; 29:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And Saul was very [note]1[/note]angry, for this saying displeased him. And he said, They ascribe ten thousands to David, but to me they ascribe only thousands. And what more can he have except the kingdom?</text>
        <note num="1">Saul became angry and envious of David, showing that he was a person fully in the flesh and absolutely for himself. In contrast to Saul, David knew only to behave and to have his being according to God's heart. He had no feeling for himself; rather, he knew only to labor and conduct himself for God's people and God's kingdom.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>So Saul eyed David from that day on.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Then on the next day an [xref]a[/xref]evil spirit from God rushed upon Saul; and he [xref]b[/xref]prophesied in the midst of the house while David played [i]the lyre[/i] by hand, as he had day by day. And the spear was in Saul's hand.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 16:14; 19:9</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. 1 Sam. 19:23-24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Then Saul threw the spear; for he said, I will [xref]a[/xref]strike David even to the wall. But David [note]1[/note]fled from him twice.</text>
        <note num="1">When Saul attempted to kill him, David did not fight or do anything to avenge himself (cf. [link]Rom. 12:19[/link]; [link]Eph. 4:26[/link]); he only fled. Avenging and fighting back are matters of the flesh. Those who practice the things of the flesh have no share in the kingdom of God ([link]Gal. 5:21[/link]). In the kingdom of God the flesh must be crucified ([link]Gal. 5:24[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 19:10; 20:33</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And Saul was afraid of David, for Jehovah was [xref]a[/xref]with him and had departed from Saul.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 16:13, 18; 18:28</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>So Saul removed him from [i]being[/i] with him and made him the captain of a thousand. And he [xref]a[/xref]went out and came in before the people.</text>
        <xref num="a">Num. 27:17; Deut. 31:2; 1 Sam. 18:16; 2 Sam. 5:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And David acted prudently in all his campaigns, and Jehovah was with him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And when Saul saw that he acted very prudently, he stood in awe of him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And all Israel and Judah loved David, for he went out and came in before them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And Saul said to David, See, my oldest daughter Merab I will give to you as [xref]a[/xref]wife; only be valiant for me and fight Jehovah's [xref]b[/xref]battles. For Saul said, Let not my hand be upon him, but let the hand of the Philistines be upon him.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 17:25</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 25:28</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And David said to Saul, Who am [xref]a[/xref]I, and what is my life [i]or[/i] my father's family in Israel, that I should be a son-in-law to the king?</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 7:18; cf. Exo. 3:11; Judg. 6:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>But at the time when [xref]a[/xref]Merab the daughter of Saul was to be given to David, she was given to Adriel the Meholathite as wife.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 21:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Now Michal the daughter of Saul loved David, and it was told Saul; and the matter pleased him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And Saul said, I will give her to him that she may be a snare to him and that the hand of the Philistines may be upon him. Therefore Saul said to David, For the second time, you may be my son-in-law today.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Then Saul commanded his servants, Speak to David privately, saying, See, the king is pleased with you, and all his servants love you. So now become the king's son-in-law.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>And Saul's servants spoke these words in David's ears. And David said, Is it such a light thing in your sight [i]for me[/i] to become a son-in-law to the king, since I am a poor man and lightly esteemed?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And Saul's servants told him, saying, This is what David said.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Then Saul said, Thus shall you say to David, The king has no desire for a dowry but for a hundred Philistine foreskins, that he may be avenged of the king's enemies. For Saul planned to have David fall by the [xref]a[/xref]hand of the Philistines.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 18:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>So when his servants told David these things, David was pleased to become the king's son-in-law. And when the time had not [i]yet[/i] expired,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>David rose up and went, he and his men; and he struck down two hundred Philistine men. And David brought their foreskins, and they gave them in full number to the king, that he might become the king's son-in-law. And Saul gave him [xref]a[/xref]Michal his daughter as wife.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 3:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>And Saul saw and knew that Jehovah was with David. And Michal the daughter of Saul loved him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>And Saul was even more afraid of David, and Saul was David's enemy from then on.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>Then the princes of the Philistines went forth; and as often as they went forth, David succeeded more than all the servants of Saul. So his name was very highly esteemed.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="19">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And Saul told Jonathan his son and all his servants to kill David. But Jonathan, Saul's son, took great [xref]a[/xref]delight in David.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 18:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And [note]1[/note]Jonathan told David, saying, Saul my father is seeking to kill you. Now therefore be on guard in the morning, and stay in some secret place, and hide yourself.</text>
        <note num="1">As Saul was seeking to kill David, Jonathan and Michal helped him flee ([link]20:1-42[/link]; [link]19:11-18[/link]). In everything related to David, God was sovereign. As the sovereign One, God is above everything, behind everything, and in everything. In His sovereignty God prepared David to be a man according to His heart for His kingdom. He also prepared Saul to perfect David by testing him and putting him on trial, and He prepared Jonathan, the son of Saul, and Michal, the daughter of Saul who became David's wife, to help David to flee from Saul. Apart from the help rendered by Jonathan and Michal, David could not have endured being persecuted and tried by Saul. Both Jonathan and Michal typify Christ as God's provision for us to suffer God's trial and God's testing.[br/][br/]When David was persecuted by Saul, he did not react in a negative way, nor did he complain, condemn, criticize, or oppose. Using the New Testament term, he was always under the cross. He bore the cross every day under any kind of situation ([link]Luke 9:23[/link]). The strength for us to bear the cross is the power of Christ's resurrection ([link]Phil. 3:10[/link]), which is Christ Himself as the resurrection ([link]John 11:25[/link]). Christ as the resurrection lives in us to bear the cross within us ([link]Gal. 2:20[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And I will go out and stand by my father's side in the field where you are. And I will speak about you to my father; and if I learn anything, I will tell you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>So Jonathan spoke well about David to Saul his father and said to him, May the king not sin against his servant David, because he has not sinned against you, and because his deeds have been very good for you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>For he risked his life when he [xref]a[/xref]struck down the Philistine, and Jehovah accomplished a great salvation for all Israel. You saw [i]it[/i] and rejoiced. Why then will you sin against innocent blood by having David killed without cause?</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Sam. 17:49-51</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And Saul listened to the voice of Jonathan; and Saul swore, As Jehovah lives, he shall not be put to death.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Then Jonathan called David, and Jonathan told him all these things. And Jonathan brought David to Saul, and he was in his presence as before.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And there was war again. And David went out and fought against the Philistines. And he struck them with a great slaughter, and they fled from before him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Then there came an [xref]a[/xref]evil spirit from Jehovah upon Saul, and he sat in his house with his spear in his hand while David played [i]the lyre[/i] by hand.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 16:14; 18:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And Saul sought to [xref]a[/xref]strike David even to the wall with the spear, but he slipped away from Saul's presence. And [note]1[/note]Saul struck the wall with his spear, but David fled and [xref]b[/xref]escaped that night.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., he.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 18:11; 20:33</xref>
        <xref num="b">Heb. 11:34</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Then Saul sent messengers to David's house to watch him and kill him in the morning. And Michal, David's wife, told him, saying, If you do not save your life tonight, in the morning you will be killed.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>So Michal let David [xref]a[/xref]down through the window, and he went away and fled and escaped.</text>
        <xref num="a">Josh. 2:15; Acts 9:25; 2 Cor. 11:33</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Then Michal took the [xref]a[/xref]teraphim and laid [i]it[/i] in the bed. And she put a net of goats' hair on its head and covered [i]it[/i] with clothing.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 31:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And when Saul sent messengers to take David, she said, He is sick.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And Saul sent the messengers to see David, saying, Bring him up to me on his bed that I may kill him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And when the messengers went in, there was the teraphim in the bed with a net of goats' hair on its head.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Then Saul said to Michal, Why have you deceived me like this and let my enemy go so that he has slipped away? And Michal said to Saul, He said to me, Let me go; why should I kill you?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>So David fled and slipped away and came to [xref]a[/xref]Samuel at Ramah, and he told him all that Saul had done to him. And he and Samuel went and dwelt at Naioth.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 7:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Then it was told Saul, saying, David is now at Naioth in Ramah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>So Saul sent messengers to seize David; and when they saw the company of prophets prophesying and Samuel standing [i]and[/i] presiding over them, the [xref]a[/xref]Spirit of God came upon Saul's messengers, and they also prophesied.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Sam. 10:10; 11:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And it was told Saul, and he sent other messengers, and they also prophesied. And Saul again sent messengers the third time, and they also prophesied.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Then he himself went to Ramah. And he came to the great well that is in Secu; and he asked and said, Where are Samuel and David? And someone said, They are now at Naioth in Ramah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>So he went there, toward Naioth in Ramah. And the Spirit of God came upon him as well, and he went on and [xref]a[/xref]prophesied until he came to Naioth in Ramah.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 10:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And he also stripped off his clothes and also prophesied before Samuel, and he lay naked all that day and all that night. Therefore they say, Is Saul also [xref]a[/xref]among the prophets?</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 10:11-12</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="20">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Then David fled from Naioth in Ramah and came and said to Jonathan, What have I done? What is my iniquity, or what is my sin before your father, that he is seeking my life?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And he said to him, Far from it! You shall not die. My father does nothing great or small that he does not disclose to me. So why should my father hide this matter from me? Such would not happen.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Then David swore again and said, Your father fully knows that I have found favor in your sight; so he says, Do not let Jonathan know about this; otherwise, he will be grieved. But truly as Jehovah [xref]a[/xref]lives and as your soul lives, there is [i]but[/i] a step between me and death.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ruth 3:13; 1 Sam. 20:21; 25:26; 2 Kings 2:2, 4, 6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And Jonathan said to David, Whatever you say, I will do for you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And David said to Jonathan, It is the [xref]a[/xref]new moon tomorrow, and I am to sit with the king at the meal. But let me go, and I will hide myself in the field until the following evening.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 20:18; cf. Num. 10:10; 28:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>If your father misses me at all, you shall say, David earnestly asked leave of me to run to [xref]a[/xref]Bethlehem his city, for it is the yearly sacrifice there for all his family.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 16:1, 4; Micah 5:2; Luke 2:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>If he says in this way, Fine; [i]then[/i] your servant will have peace. But if he becomes angry at all, know that evil has been determined by him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Deal kindly then with your servant, for you have brought your servant into a [xref]a[/xref]covenant of Jehovah with you. But if there is any iniquity in me, you kill me. Why then should you bring me to your father?</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 18:3; 20:16; 2 Sam. 21:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And Jonathan said, Far be it from you! For if I knew at all that evil has been determined by my father to come upon you, would I not tell it to you?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Then David said to Jonathan, Who will tell me whether or not your father has responded to you harshly?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And Jonathan said to David, Come and let us go out into the field. And they both went out into the field.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And Jonathan said to David, By Jehovah, the God of Israel: When I search out my father about this time tomorrow, [i]or[/i] on the following day, and if he is good toward David, I will surely send [i]word[/i] to you and disclose [i]it[/i] to you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>May Jehovah do so to Jonathan, and even more, if it pleases my father to do you evil, and I do not disclose [i]it[/i] to you and send you away to go in peace. And may Jehovah be [xref]a[/xref]with you as He was with my father.</text>
        <xref num="a">Josh. 1:5, 17; 1 Sam. 17:37</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And while I am still alive, do show me the [xref]a[/xref]lovingkindness of Jehovah, that I may not die;</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 9:1, 3, 7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And never cut off your lovingkindness from my house, not even when Jehovah has cut off David's enemies to the man from the face of the earth.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>So Jonathan made [i]a covenant[/i] with the house of David, [i]saying,[/i] And Jehovah will require [i]it[/i] at the hand of David's enemies.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And Jonathan made David swear again by his love for him, for he [xref]a[/xref]loved him as he loved his own soul.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 18:1-3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Then Jonathan said to him, Tomorrow is the new moon; and you will be missed, for your seat will be empty.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And when you have waited three days, you shall go far down and come to the place where you hid yourself while [i]all this[/i] was happening; and you shall remain at the stone Ezel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And I will shoot three arrows to its side, as though I were shooting at a mark.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And just then I will send a boy, [i]saying,[/i] Go; find the arrows. If I say to the boy, The arrows are there to this side of you; gather them; then come, for you have peace and there is no problem, as Jehovah lives.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>But if I speak in this way to the young man, The [xref]a[/xref]arrows are there beyond you; then go, for Jehovah has sent you away.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 20:37</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>And concerning this matter that I and you have spoken of, it is Jehovah who is [xref]a[/xref]between me and you forever.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 20:42</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>So David hid himself in the field. And when the new moon came, the king sat at the meal to eat.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>And the king sat on his seat as at other times, on his seat near the wall; and Jonathan rose up, and Abner sat down beside Saul, but David's place was empty.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>But Saul said nothing that day [i]about it,[/i] for he thought, Something has happened [i]to him;[/i] he is [xref]a[/xref]not clean; surely [i]he is[/i] not clean.</text>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 7:21; 11:24-28; 15:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>And on the day after the new moon, the second day, David's place was empty. And Saul said to Jonathan his son, Why has the son of Jesse come neither yesterday nor today to the meal?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>And Jonathan answered Saul, David asked leave of me earnestly [i]to go[/i] to [xref]a[/xref]Bethlehem.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 20:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>And he said, Let me go, I beg you; for our family has a sacrifice in that city, and my brother commanded me [i]to be there.[/i] So now if I have found favor in your sight, let me slip away to see my brothers. Therefore he has not come to the king's table.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>And Saul's anger burned against Jonathan, and he said to him, You son of a perverse, rebellious woman! Do I not know that you have chosen the son of Jesse to your own shame and to the shame of your mother's nakedness?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>For as long as the son of Jesse is alive on the earth, you and your kingdom will not be established. Now therefore send [i]someone[/i] and bring him to me, for he is as good as dead.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>And Jonathan answered Saul his father and said to him, Why must he be put to death? What has he done?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>But Saul threw his spear at him in order to [xref]a[/xref]strike him down. So Jonathan knew that it was determined by his father to put David to death.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 18:11; 19:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>And Jonathan rose up from the table in burning anger and did not eat any food on the second day of the new moon, for he was grieved about David because his father had shamed him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>Then in the morning Jonathan went forth to the field for the appointment with David, and a small boy was with him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
        <text>And he said to his boy, Run [i]and[/i] find the arrows that I am shooting. While the boy was running, he shot the [xref]a[/xref]arrow beyond him.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 20:22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
        <text>And when the boy came to the place of the arrow that Jonathan had shot, Jonathan called out after the boy and said, The arrow is there beyond you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
        <text>And Jonathan called out to the boy, Hurry up quickly; do not stay there. And Jonathan's boy gathered the arrows and came to his master.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
        <text>And the boy knew nothing; only Jonathan and David knew the matter.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
        <text>Then Jonathan gave his equipment to his boy and said to him, Go; bring [i]them[/i] to the city.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
        <text>[i]And[/i] when the boy went, David rose up from [i]his hiding place[/i] toward the south and fell on his face to the ground; and he bowed himself three times. And they kissed each other; and they wept for each other, but David more greatly.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
        <text>And Jonathan said to David, Go in peace, because both of us have sworn in the name of Jehovah, saying, May Jehovah be [xref]a[/xref]between me and you and between my seed and your seed forever. Then [note]1[/note]David rose up and left, and Jonathan went into the city.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., he.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 20:23</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="21">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]And David went to [xref]b[/xref]Nob to Ahimelech the priest. And Ahimelech came trembling to meet David and said to him, Why are you alone, and no one with you?</text>
        <xref num="a">vv. 1-6: Matt. 12:3-4; Mark 2:25-26; Luke 6:3-4</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 22:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And David said to Ahimelech the priest, The king has charged me with some matter, and he said to me, Let no man know anything about the matter that I have sent you on and charged you with. So I have made an appointment with my young men at such and such a place.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Now then what do you have on hand? Give five loaves of bread into my hand, or whatever there is to be found.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And the priest answered David and said, There is no common bread on hand; yet there is holy [xref]a[/xref]bread, but only if the young men have kept themselves from women.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 25:30; Lev. 24:5-9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And David answered the priest and said to him, Women have indeed been kept from us, as previously when I went forth; and the vessels of the young men were holy, even if it was a common journey. How much more then today will their vessels be holy!</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>So the priest gave him what was holy, for there was no bread there except the [note]1[/note]bread of the Presence, which was taken from before Jehovah, to be replaced by hot bread at the time it was taken.</text>
        <note num="1">See [link]Matt. 12:1-4[/link] and note [link]3[sup]2[/sup][/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Now one of Saul's servants was there that day, detained before Jehovah. His name was [xref]a[/xref]Doeg the Edomite, the chief of the shepherds that belonged to Saul.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 22:9, 22; Psa. 52 title</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And David said to Ahimelech, And is there not a spear or a sword here on hand? For I have brought neither my sword nor my equipment with me, for the king's matter was urgent.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And the priest said, The [xref]a[/xref]sword of Goliath the Philistine, whom you struck down in the valley of Elah, is here, wrapped in a cloth behind the ephod. If you will take it, take [i]it;[/i] for there is no other here but that one. And David said, There is none like it; give it to me.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 17:51</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Then David rose up and fled that day from before Saul, and he went to [xref]a[/xref]Achish the king of Gath.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 27:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>But the servants of Achish said to him, Is this not David the king of the land? Is this not him of whom they sang to one another in dances, saying,[br/][xref]a[/xref]Saul has struck down his thousands; / But David, his ten thousands?</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 18:7; 29:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And David took these words to heart and feared Achish the king of Gath greatly.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>So he disguised his sanity in their sight and acted like a [xref]a[/xref]madman before them, and he made marks on the doors of the gate and let his spittle run down his beard.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 34 title</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And Achish said to his servants, Look, you see that the man is mad. Why have you brought him to me?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Do I lack madmen that you have brought this one to me to be a madman before me? Shall this one come into my house?</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="22">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Then David went from there and escaped to the [xref]a[/xref]cave of Adullam. And when his brothers and all his father's house heard [i]of it,[/i] they went down to him there.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 23:13; 1 Chron. 11:15; Psa. 57 title; 142 title; Heb. 11:38</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And everyone who was in distress and everyone who was in debt and everyone who was discontented gathered to him, and he became captain over them. And with him were about four hundred men.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And David went from there to Mizpeh of [xref]a[/xref]Moab. And he said to the king of Moab, Let my father and mother go forth [i]and be[/i] with you until I know what God will do for me.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Ruth 1:1-4; 4:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And he brought them before the king of Moab, and they remained with him all the time that David was in the stronghold.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And [xref]a[/xref]Gad the prophet said to David, Do not stay in the stronghold; depart and go into the land of Judah. So David departed and went into the forest of Hereth.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 24:11, 18-19; 1 Chron. 21:9-19; 29:29; 2 Chron. 29:25</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Then Saul heard that David and the men with him had been discovered. Now Saul was sitting in Gibeah, under the tamarisk tree on the height; and his spear was in his hand, and all his servants were standing around him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And Saul said to his servants standing around him, Hear now, you Benjaminites: Will the son of Jesse give every one of you [xref]a[/xref]fields and vineyards, will he make every one of you captains of thousands and captains of hundreds,</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Sam. 8:11-14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>That every one of you has conspired against me, so that no one discloses [i]it[/i] to me when my son makes [i]a [xref]a[/xref]covenant[/i] with the son of Jesse, and none of you is sorry for me or discloses [i]it[/i] to me when my son stirs up my servant against me to ambush [i]me[/i] as on this day?</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 18:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Then [xref]a[/xref]Doeg the Edomite, who was set over Saul's servants, answered and said, I saw the son of Jesse coming to Ahimelech the son of Ahitub at Nob.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 21:7; Psa. 52 title</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And he [xref]a[/xref]inquired of Jehovah for him and gave him provisions, and he gave him the sword of Goliath the Philistine.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 21:1-9; cf. 1 Sam. 23:2, 4; 30:8; 2 Sam. 5:19, 23; Num. 27:21</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Then the king sent [i]men[/i] to call Ahimelech the priest, the son of Ahitub, and all his father's house, the priests who were in Nob. And all of them came to the king.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And Saul said, Hear now, you son of Ahitub. And he said, Here I am, my lord.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And Saul said to him, Why have you conspired against me, you and the son of Jesse, in that you have given him food and a sword, and have inquired of God for him, so that he rises up against me to ambush [i]me[/i] as on this day?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And Ahimelech answered the king and said, And who among all your servants is as faithful as David, who is the king's son-in-law and has access to your council and is honored in your house?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Was it [i]just[/i] today that I began to inquire of God for him? Far be it from me! May the king not impute anything to his servant [i]nor[/i] to all my father's house, for your servant knows nothing of this matter, small or great.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>But the king said, You shall surely die, Ahimelech, you and all your [xref]a[/xref]father's house.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Sam. 2:31-33; 3:13-14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Then the king said to the runners who were standing around him, Turn, and [note]1[/note]kill the priests of Jehovah, because their hand is also with David, and because they knew that he was fleeing and they did not disclose it to me. But the king's servants would not put forth their hand to attack the priests of Jehovah.</text>
        <note num="1">Saul's killing of Ahimelech and his family ([link]vv. 6-23[/link]; cf. [link]Psa. 52[/link], title) shows that Saul was utterly rebellious toward God. He had no subordination to God, nor did he take God as his King and Head. He was constituted with rebellion, which is as evil as the worship of idols ([link]15:23[/link]). All rebellion is a matter of presumption, a matter of daring to do things without God.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And the king said to Doeg, You turn, and attack the priests. And Doeg the Edomite turned, and he attacked the priests. And on that day he killed eighty-five men who wore the linen ephod.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And he struck Nob, the city of the priests, with the edge of the sword, both men and women, infants and sucklings, and oxen and asses and sheep, with the edge of the sword.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>But one of the sons of Ahimelech the son of Ahitub escaped, whose name was [xref]a[/xref]Abiathar, and he fled after David.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 23:6, 9; 2 Sam. 15:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And Abiathar told David that Saul had slain the priests of Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And David said to Abiathar, I knew on that day when Doeg the Edomite was there that he would surely tell Saul. I am responsible for all the lives of your father's house.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Remain with me, [i]and[/i] do not be afraid; for he who seeks my life seeks your life, for you will be kept safe with me.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="23">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And some told David, saying, The Philistines are now fighting against Keilah and robbing the threshing floors.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And David [xref]a[/xref]inquired of Jehovah, saying, Shall I go and strike these Philistines? And Jehovah said to David, Go and strike the Philistines, and save Keilah.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 22:10; 30:8; 2 Sam. 2:1; 5:19, 23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And David's men said to him, Here we are, afraid here in Judah; how much more if we go to Keilah against the ranks of the Philistines!</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>So David inquired yet again of Jehovah. And Jehovah answered him and said, Rise up; go down to Keilah, for I have delivered the Philistines into your hand.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Then David and his men went to Keilah and fought against the Philistines and carried off their cattle and struck them down with a great slaughter. And David saved the inhabitants of Keilah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Now it so happened that when Abiathar the son of Ahimelech fled to David at Keilah, he came down with an [xref]a[/xref]ephod in his hand.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 14:3; 30:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Then it was told Saul that David had come to Keilah. And Saul said, God has [note]1[/note]delivered him into my hand; for he is shut in, because he has entered a city with gates and bars.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., alienated; the meaning of the Hebrew text is uncertain.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And Saul summoned all the people to battle, to go down to Keilah, to besiege David and his men.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>But when David learned that Saul was planning evil against him, he said to Abiathar the priest, Bring the ephod here.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And David said, O Jehovah the God of Israel, Your servant has heard for certain that Saul is seeking to come to Keilah in order to destroy the city on my account.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Will the men of Keilah deliver me into his hand? Will Saul come down, as Your servant has heard? O Jehovah the God of Israel, do tell Your servant. And Jehovah said, He will come down.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And David said, Will the men of Keilah deliver me and my men into the hand of Saul? And Jehovah said, They will deliver [i]you.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>So David and his men, about six hundred men, rose up and went forth from Keilah; and they went about wherever they could. And when it was told Saul that David had slipped away from Keilah, he ceased [i]his[/i] going forth.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And David remained in the wilderness in strongholds, and he remained in the hill country in the [xref]a[/xref]wilderness of Ziph. And Saul sought him every day, but God did not deliver him into his hand.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 63 title; Heb. 11:38</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And David saw that Saul went forth to seek his life, and David was in the wilderness of Ziph at Horesh.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Then Jonathan the son of Saul rose up and went to David at Horesh, and he strengthened his hand in God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And he said to him, Do not be afraid, for the hand of Saul my father will not find you; and you will become [xref]a[/xref]king over Israel, and I will be second to you; and even Saul my father knows that.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 15:28; 20:31; 24:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And the two of them made a [xref]a[/xref]covenant before Jehovah. And David remained in Horesh, and Jonathan went to his house.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 18:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Then some [xref]a[/xref]Ziphites went up to Saul at Gibeah, saying, David is indeed hiding among us in the strongholds at Horesh, on the [xref]b[/xref]hill of Hachilah, which is south of the desert!</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 26:1; Psa. 54 title</xref>
        <xref num="b">Heb. 11:38</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Now then, O king, come down, according to all your soul's desire to come down; and we will deliver him into the hand of the king.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And Saul said, Blessed are you of Jehovah, for you have had compassion on me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Go now, and make sure once more; and find out and look into his place, where he sets foot, who has seen him there; for I am told that he is very cunning.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>And look about and learn of all his hiding places where he lurks, and come back to me with sure information; then I will go with you, and if he is in the land, I will search him out among all the thousands of Judah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And they rose up and went to Ziph before Saul. And David and his men were in the wilderness of Maon, in the Arabah to the south of the desert.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>And Saul and his men went to seek [i]him.[/i] And when some told David [i]this,[/i] he went down to the rock and remained in the wilderness of Maon. And when Saul heard [i]of it,[/i] he pursued after David in the wilderness of Maon.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>And Saul went on one side of the mountain, while David and his men [i]went[/i] on the other side of the mountain. And David hurried to get away from Saul, while Saul and his men were closing in on David and his men in order to capture them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>Then a messenger came to Saul, saying, Hurry and come, for the Philistines have raided the land.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>So Saul returned from pursuing after David, and he went to meet the Philistines; therefore they call that place the Rock of Escape.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>And David went up from there and remained in the strongholds of En-gedi.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="24">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And when Saul returned from following the Philistines, some told him, saying, David is now in the [xref]a[/xref]wilderness of En-gedi.</text>
        <xref num="a">Heb. 11:38</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And Saul took three thousand choice men from all Israel and went to seek David and his men upon the Rocks of the Wild Goats.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And he came to the sheepfolds along the way, and a cave was there. And Saul went in to relieve himself. Now David and his men were sitting in the innermost part of the [xref]a[/xref]cave.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 57 title; 142 title</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And David's men said to him, The day is here of which Jehovah said to you, I am about to [xref]a[/xref]give your enemy into your hand. Do then to him according to what seems good in your sight. So David rose up and cut off a corner of Saul's cloak without being noticed.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 24:10; 26:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>But afterward David's heart [xref]a[/xref]smote him because he had cut off a corner of Saul's [i]cloak.[/i]</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 24:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And he said to his men, [note]1[/note]Jehovah forbid that I should do such a thing to my lord, Jehovah's [xref]a[/xref]anointed, as stretch out my hand against him; for he is Jehovah's anointed.</text>
        <note num="1">David feared God and did not dare to overthrow the divine order arranged by God. In God's kingdom there is a divine order of authority. Saul was not a self-appointed king; he was the king appointed and anointed by God ([link]10:1[/link]). Saul was therefore the divine authority, and David feared God in this. David kept the God-ordained order of authority among God's elect. By so doing, David laid a good foundation for himself to be the king of God's elect in the coming days. If he had rebelled against Saul, he would have been to the people an example of rebellion against the God-ordained, appointed king. Cf. notes [link]25[sup]1[/sup] in Gen. 9[/link] and [link]9[sup]3[/sup] in Jude[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 12:3; 26:9-11; 2 Sam. 1:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>So David checked his men with these words and would not allow them to rise up against Saul. And Saul rose up out of the cave and went on his way.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Then David rose up afterward and came out of the cave. And he called after Saul, saying, My lord the king. And when Saul looked behind him, David bowed with his face to the ground and paid [i]him[/i] homage.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And David said to Saul, Why do you listen to men's words that say, David now seeks your harm?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Just this day your eyes have seen that Jehovah gave you into my hand today in the cave. And though some told [i]me[/i] to kill you, [note]1[/note]I spared you and said, I will not stretch out my hand against my lord, for he is Jehovah's anointed.</text>
        <note num="1">Following some ancient versions; the Hebrew text reads, it (my eye) spared you. What David did here was exactly what the New Testament teaches concerning not repaying evil for evil but overcoming evil with good ([link]Rom. 12:17[/link], [link]21[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Now my father, look, indeed, look at the corner of your cloak in my hand; for in that I cut off the corner of your cloak and did not kill you, know and see that there is no harm or transgression in my hand. And though I have not sinned against you, you [xref]a[/xref]hunt after my life in order to take it.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 23:14, 23; 26:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>May Jehovah [xref]a[/xref]judge between me and you, and may Jehovah avenge me of you; but my hand will not be against you.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 16:5; Judg. 11:27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>As the proverb of the ancients says, Out of the wicked comes forth wickedness; but my hand will not be against you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>After whom does the king of Israel come out? Whom do you pursue? A dead dog; a single [xref]a[/xref]flea.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 26:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>May Jehovah then be Judge and decide between me and you. And may He see and plead my cause and release me through His judgment out of your hand.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And when David finished speaking these words to Saul, Saul said, Is this your voice, my son David? And Saul lifted up his voice and [note]1[/note]wept.</text>
        <note num="1">David's God-fearing and God-honoring life subdued the reckless Saul and stopped Saul from pursuing him ([link]vv. 16-22[/link]). In his relationship with Saul, David is a very good pattern for the New Testament believers in the church life as God's kingdom ([link]Rom. 14:17[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And he said to David, You are more righteous than I; for you have repaid me with good, while I have repaid you with evil.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And you have declared today how you did good to me, because Jehovah delivered me up into your hand, but you would not kill me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>For if a man finds his enemy, will he send him away safely? May Jehovah therefore reward you with good for what you have done to me this day.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And now I indeed know that you will surely be [xref]a[/xref]king and that the kingdom of Israel will be established in your hand.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 23:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Now therefore [xref]a[/xref]swear to me by Jehovah that you will not cut off my seed after me and that you will not destroy my name from my father's house.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 21:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>So David swore to Saul. And Saul went to his house, and David and his men went up to the stronghold.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="25">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Then [xref]a[/xref]Samuel [note]1[/note]died, and all Israel gathered together and [xref]b[/xref]mourned for him; and they buried him at his house in Ramah.[br/]And David rose up and went down into the wilderness of Paran.</text>
        <note num="1">Samuel died a peaceful death after he had properly and fully enjoyed his portion in the God-promised good land. Because he was faithful in all his statuses and offices (see note [link]3[sup]1[/sup], par. 2, in ch. 7[/link]), Samuel enjoyed the good land, a type of Christ (see note [link]7[sup]1[/sup] in Deut. 8[/link]), in every way and in every sense throughout his entire life. His enjoyment of the land exceeded that of everyone else in the Old Testament.[br/][br/]Samuel became a priest, a prophet, and a judge to usher in the Davidic kingdom for the accomplishing of God's economy on the earth. He therefore established the kingdom of God and wrote all the regulations concerning the kingdom of God ([link book="1 Sam."]10:25[/link]). Although Samuel was disappointed with Saul's kingship ([link]15:35[/link]), he died with the encouraging expectation of the Davidic kingdom, a type of the kingdom of God. This was a comfort to him.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 28:3</xref>
        <xref num="b">Gen. 50:10; Num. 20:29; Deut. 34:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Now there was a man in Maon, whose possessions were in Carmel. And the man was very wealthy: He had three thousand sheep and a thousand goats. And [i]at that time[/i] he was shearing his sheep in Carmel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And the man's name was Nabal, and his wife's name was Abigail. And the woman had good discernment and was beautiful in appearance. But the man was hard, and he was evil in [i]his[/i] doings; and he was a Calebite.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And David heard in the wilderness that Nabal was shearing his sheep.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>So David sent ten young men; and David said to the young men, Go up to Carmel, and go to Nabal and greet him in my name.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And thus shall you say, Live long; and peace be to you, and [xref]a[/xref]peace be to your house, and peace be to all that you have.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Chron. 12:18; Matt. 10:13; Luke 10:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Now therefore I hear that you have shearers; your shepherds have now been with us, and we have not harmed them, nor has there been anything missing from them, all the time they were in Carmel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Ask your young men, and they will tell you. Therefore let these young men find favor in your sight, for we come in a good time. Give whatever you may have on hand to your servants and to your son David.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>So David's young men went and spoke to Nabal according to all these words in the name of David; then they waited.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>But Nabal answered David's servants and said, Who is David, or who is the son of Jesse? There are many [xref]a[/xref]servants today who break away from their masters.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 22:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Shall I then take my food and my water and my meat that I have slaughtered for my shearers, and give it to men who come from I do not know where?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Then David's young men turned back on their way. And they returned and came and told him all these things.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And David said to his men, Each man gird on his sword. And each man girded on his sword, and David also girded on his sword. And they went up after David, about four hundred men. And two hundred remained [xref]a[/xref]with the baggage.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 30:10, 24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>But one of the young men told Abigail, Nabal's wife, saying, David has just sent messengers from the wilderness to greet our master, but he shouted insultingly at them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>But the men were very good to us; and we were not harmed, nor did we miss anything all the time we went with them when we were in the fields.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>They were a [xref]a[/xref]wall to us both by night and by day all the time we were with them tending the sheep.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Job 1:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Now therefore know and consider what you will do, because evil has been determined against our master and against all his house; for he is so worthless a man that no one can speak to him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Then Abigail hurried and took [xref]a[/xref]two hundred loaves of bread and two skins of wine and five sheep ready dressed and five measures of parched grain and one hundred clusters of raisins and two hundred cakes of figs, and she put them on her donkeys.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 2 Sam. 16:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And she said to her young men, Go on before me; I am coming right behind you. But she did not tell her husband Nabal.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And as she rode on her donkey and came down under the cover of the mountain, David and his men at that moment came down toward her; and she met them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Now David had said, [note]1[/note]It was certainly in vain that I guarded all that this fellow has in the wilderness, so that nothing was missed of all that he has; for he has repaid me evil for good.</text>
        <note num="1">David's word here indicates that he was offended by Nabal. In this matter David did not pass the test. He bore the bigger cross under the persecution by Saul (see note [link]2[sup]1[/sup], par. 2, in ch. 19[/link]), but in this small cross involving Nabal he failed. It is often through the small crosses that the flesh is exposed.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>May God do so to David's enemies, and even more, if I [xref]a[/xref]leave so much as a male child of all that he has until morning.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 25:34</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>And when Abigail saw David, she hurried and got down from her donkey and fell on her face before David; and she bowed herself to the ground.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And she fell at his feet and said, Upon me alone, my lord, be this iniquity; and let your female servant speak in your hearing, and hear the words of your female servant.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>May my lord not take this worthless man Nabal to heart. For as his name is, so he is: [note]1[/note]Nabal is his name, and folly is with him. But I your female servant did not see my lord's young men, whom you sent.</text>
        <note num="1">Meaning [i]fool.[/i]</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>And now, my lord, as Jehovah lives and as your soul lives, since Jehovah has [xref]a[/xref]withheld you from entering into bloodshed and from [xref]b[/xref]avenging yourself by your own hand, now therefore let your enemies and those who seek harm against my lord be like Nabal.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 25:33-34, 39; cf. 2 Sam. 12:9; Gen. 20:6</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. Rom. 12:19; Heb. 10:30</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>And now this present which your servant has brought to my lord, let [i]it[/i] be given to the young men who follow my lord.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>Please forgive the transgression of your female servant, for Jehovah will no doubt make a [xref]a[/xref]sure house for my lord, because my lord [xref]b[/xref]fights the battles of Jehovah; and no evil will be found in you throughout your days.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 11:38; 1 Sam. 2:35</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 18:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>And though men rise up to pursue you and to seek your life, my lord's life will be [xref]a[/xref]bound up in the bundle of the living with Jehovah your God; and the lives of your enemies He will sling out, as from the hollow of the sling.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 66:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>And when Jehovah has done to my lord according to all the good He has spoken concerning you and has appointed you [xref]a[/xref]ruler over Israel,</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 13:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>This will not be a qualm of conscience to you or a stumbling block in heart to my lord, that you shed blood without cause or that my lord has avenged himself. And when Jehovah has dealt well with my lord, may you remember your female servant.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>And David said to Abigail, Blessed be Jehovah, the God of Israel, who sent you this day to meet me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>And blessed be your discretion; and blessed be you, who have kept me this day from entering into bloodshed and from avenging myself by my own hand.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>For surely as Jehovah the God of Israel lives, who has [xref]a[/xref]withheld me from harming you, unless you had hurried and come to meet me, indeed there would not have been [xref]b[/xref]left to Nabal even a male child until morning's light.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 25:26</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 25:22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>So David took from her hand what she brought to him. And he said to her, Go up in peace to your house. See, I have listened to your voice and have accepted your person.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
        <text>And Abigail went to Nabal. And just then he was having a feast in his house, like the feast of a king. And Nabal's heart was merry within him, and he was extremely drunk; therefore she told him nothing, small or great, until the light of morning.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
        <text>And in the morning, when the wine had left Nabal, his wife told him these things. And his heart died within him, and he became like a stone.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
        <text>And about ten days later Jehovah struck Nabal, and he died.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
        <text>And when David heard that Nabal was dead, he said, Blessed be Jehovah, who has pleaded the cause of my reproach at the hand of Nabal and who has [xref]a[/xref]withheld His servant from evildoing; and Jehovah has returned the evildoing of Nabal upon his own head. And David sent [i]men[/i] to propose to Abigail, that he might take her to himself as [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]wife.</text>
        <note num="1">In David's taking Abigail and Ahinoam ([link]v. 43[/link]) as his wives, David's weakness in the matter of sex was manifested. The root of his later failure in murdering Uriah and taking Bath-sheba ([link]2 Sam. 11[/link]) was manifested here. See note [link]4[sup]1[/sup] in 2 Sam. 11[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 25:26</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. 1 Sam. 25:43-44</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
        <text>And when David's servants came to Abigail at Carmel, they spoke to her, saying, David has sent us to you, to take you to himself as wife.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
        <text>And she rose up and fell on her face to the ground. And she said, Here is your female servant, as a slave to wash the feet of my lord's servants.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
        <text>And Abigail hurried and rose up; and she rode on a donkey, with her five young women following her. And she went after the messengers of David, and she became his wife.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
        <text>David also took [xref]a[/xref]Ahinoam of Jezreel; and both of them became his [xref]b[/xref]wives.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 3:2-3; 1 Chron. 3:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 27:3; 30:5; 2 Sam. 2:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
        <text>Now Saul had given [xref]a[/xref]Michal his daughter, David's wife, to Palti the son of Laish, who was from Gallim.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 3:13-14</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="26">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And the [xref]a[/xref]Ziphites came to Saul at Gibeah, saying, David is hiding himself on the hill of Hachilah, which is opposite the desert!</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 23:19; Psa. 54 title</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And Saul rose up and went down to the wilderness of Ziph, with him [xref]a[/xref]three thousand choice men of Israel, to seek David in the wilderness of Ziph.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 24:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And Saul encamped on the hill of Hachilah, which is opposite the desert, by the road. And David remained in the wilderness, but he saw that Saul had come into the wilderness after him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And David sent spies and knew for certain that Saul had come.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>So David rose up and went to the place where Saul encamped. And David looked on the place where Saul and [xref]a[/xref]Abner the son of Ner, the captain of his army, lay. Now Saul was lying within the entrenchment, and the people were encamped around him.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 14:50; 17:55; 2 Sam. 2:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And David responded and spoke to Ahimelech the Hittite and [xref]a[/xref]Abishai the son of Zeruiah, the brother of Joab, saying, Who will go down with me to Saul at the camp? And Abishai said, I will go down with you.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 2:18; 3:30; 16:9; 19:21; 1 Chron. 2:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>So David and Abishai went to the people by night; and there lay Saul, sleeping within the entrenchment, and his [xref]a[/xref]spear was stuck in the ground by his head. And Abner and the people lay around him.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 26:11, 16; cf. 1 Sam. 18:10-11; 19:9-10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And Abishai said to David, God has [xref]a[/xref]delivered your enemy into your hand today. Now therefore let me strike him with the spear even to the ground with one stroke, and I will not do it twice.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 24:4, 18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>But David said to Abishai, Do not destroy him; for who can stretch out his hand against Jehovah's [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]anointed and be guiltless?</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]6[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 24[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 24:6, 10; 26:11, 16, 23; 2 Sam. 1:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And David said, As Jehovah lives, Jehovah will strike him down, or his day will come to die, or he will go down in battle and perish.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Jehovah forbid that I should stretch out my hand against Jehovah's anointed. Now therefore take the spear that is by his head and the water jug, and let us go.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>So David took the spear and the water jug by Saul's head, and they went away. And no one saw [i]it[/i] or knew about [i]it,[/i] nor did anyone awake, for all of them were sleeping; for a [xref]a[/xref]deep sleep from Jehovah had fallen upon them.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Isa. 29:10; Gen. 2:21; 15:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And David crossed over to the other side and stood on the top of the hill far off; a great distance was between them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And David called out to the people and to Abner the son of Ner, saying, Will you not answer, Abner? And Abner answered and said, Who are you that calls out to the king?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And David said to Abner, Are you not a man? Who is like you in Israel? Why then have you not guarded your lord the king? For one of the people came in to destroy the king your lord.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>This thing is not good that you have done. As Jehovah lives, you are as good as dead because you did not guard your lord, Jehovah's anointed. Now therefore, see where the king's spear and the water jug that were by his head are.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And Saul recognized David's voice; and he said, Is this your voice, my son David? And David said, It is my voice, my lord, O king.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And he said, Why does my lord pursue after his servant? For what have I done? Or what evil is in my hand?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Now therefore let my lord the king hear the words of his servant. If it is Jehovah who has stirred you up against me, let Him accept an offering; but if it is the sons of men, let them be cursed before Jehovah; for they have [note]1[/note]driven me out today, so that I cannot share in Jehovah's [xref]a[/xref]inheritance, saying, Go, serve other gods.</text>
        <note num="1">David considered that to remain in the good land was the greatest blessing and that to be driven out of the good land and to go to another land to serve other gods was a curse. David expected to remain in the good land and share in Jehovah's inheritance and serve Him. His sincere trust in God and his faithful walk with God qualified him fully to enjoy the good land to a high level, even up to the kingship according to God's heart with a kingdom that became the kingdom of God on the earth. David was one with God. He and God had only one kingdom (cf. note [link]16[sup]1[/sup] in 2 Sam. 7[/link]). Such a one enjoyed the good land, a type of Christ (see note [link]7[sup]1[/sup] in Deut. 8[/link]), to the uttermost.</note>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 14:16; 20:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Now therefore do not let my blood fall to the ground apart from the presence of Jehovah; for the king of Israel has come forth to seek a single [xref]a[/xref]flea, as one might hunt a partridge in the mountains.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 24:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And Saul said, I have sinned. Return, my son David; for I will not harm you anymore, because my life was precious in your sight this day. I have indeed acted foolishly and have made a very great mistake.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And David answered and said, Here is the spear, O king. Let one of the young men cross over and get it.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>And Jehovah will repay to each man his righteousness and faithfulness: Because Jehovah has [xref]a[/xref]delivered you into my hand today, and I would not stretch out my hand against Jehovah's anointed;</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 26:8, 11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>Then just as great as your life was in my eyes this day, so great may my life be in Jehovah's eyes that He would deliver me from all distress.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>And Saul said to David, Blessed are you, my son David. You shall most certainly both do and prevail. And David went on his way, and Saul returned to his place.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="27">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And David said in his heart, I will now one day perish at the hand of Saul. There is nothing better for me than to escape into the land of the Philistines; then Saul will despair of seeking me any longer within all the territory of Israel. Thus I will escape from his hand.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>So David rose up and [note]1[/note]crossed over, he and the six hundred men who were with him, to [xref]a[/xref]Achish the son of Maoch, the king of Gath.</text>
        <note num="1">David was the most skillful and experienced fighter and could have been useful to Saul in utterly destroying the Philistines, but because of Saul's selfishness and envy, Saul would not use David to accomplish this but instead persecuted David. Because Saul wanted to do away with him, David was forced to flee to the country that was Israel's greatest enemy.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 21:10; cf. 1 Kings 2:39-40</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And David and his men remained with Achish in Gath, he and his men, each man with his household: David and his two [xref]a[/xref]wives, Ahinoam the Jezreelite and Abigail the wife of Nabal, the Carmelite.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 25:42-43</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And it was told Saul that David had fled to Gath, so he no longer sought him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And David said to Achish, If now I have found favor in your sight, let me be given a place in one of the country towns; and I will dwell there. For why should your servant dwell in the royal city with you?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>So Achish gave him [xref]a[/xref]Ziklag that day; therefore Ziklag belongs to the kings of Judah to this day.</text>
        <xref num="a">Josh. 15:31; 1 Sam. 30:1; 1 Chron. 12:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And the length of time that David remained in the country of the Philistines was a year and four months.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Now David and his men went up and attacked the [xref]a[/xref]Geshurites and the Girzites and the [xref]b[/xref]Amalekites, for they were the inhabitants of the land from of old, as you go to Shur and unto the land of Egypt.</text>
        <xref num="a">Josh. 13:2</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 15:7-8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And David struck the land; and he left neither man nor woman alive but took the sheep and the oxen and the asses and the camels and the clothing. Then he returned and came to Achish.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Then Achish said, [note]1[/note]Against whom have you conducted an attack today? And David said, Against the south of Judah and against the south of the Jerahmeelites and against the south of the Kenites.</text>
        <note num="1">Some MSS read, Have you not; others, Where have you.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Now David left neither man nor woman alive to be brought to Gath, for he said, Perhaps they will tell of us, saying, Thus did David do. And such was his custom as long as he dwelt in the country of the Philistines.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And Achish trusted David, saying, He has made himself utterly odious to his people Israel; therefore he shall be my servant forever.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="28">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Then in those days the Philistines gathered their camps together for war to fight against Israel. And Achish said to David, Know assuredly that you shall go out with me into the camp, you and your men.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And David said to Achish, This being so, you will know what your servant can do. And Achish said to David, Therefore I will make you my bodyguard for life.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Now [xref]a[/xref]Samuel was dead, and all Israel had mourned for him; and they had buried him in Ramah, that is, in his own city. And Saul had the [xref]b[/xref]mediums and the soothsayers put out of the land.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 25:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">Lev. 19:31; 20:27; Deut. 18:10-11; 1 Sam. 28:9; cf. 2 Kings 21:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And the Philistines gathered together, and they came and encamped in Shunem; and Saul gathered all Israel together, and they encamped in Gilboa.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And when Saul saw the camp of the Philistines, he was afraid, and his heart trembled greatly.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And Saul [xref]a[/xref]inquired of Jehovah; but Jehovah did not answer him, not by dreams or by the [xref]b[/xref]Urim or by the prophets.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 14:37</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. Exo. 28:30; Num. 27:21; Deut. 33:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Then said Saul to his servants, Seek for me a woman who is a [note]1[/note]medium that I may go to her and inquire of her. And his servants said to him, There is now a woman who is a medium at En-dor.</text>
        <note num="1">Samuel had warned Saul that his rebellion was like the sin of divination ([link]15:23[/link]). Here Saul practiced divination, which involves contact with evil spirits and is worse than idol worship.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Then Saul disguised himself and put on other clothes. And he and two men with him went, and they came to the woman by night. And he said, [xref]a[/xref]Consult a departed spirit for me, and bring up to me the one whom I tell you.</text>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 19:31; Deut. 18:11; Acts 16:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>But the woman said to him, Look, you know what Saul has done, that he has cut off the mediums and the soothsayers from the land. Why then do you lay a snare for my life to make me die?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Then Saul swore to her by Jehovah, saying, As Jehovah lives, no punishment shall happen to you for this thing.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>So the woman said, Whom shall I bring up to you? And he said, Bring up Samuel to me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Now when the woman saw Samuel, she cried out with a loud voice; and the woman spoke to Saul, saying, Why have you deceived me? For you are Saul.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And the king said to her, Do not be afraid. But what do you see? And the woman said to Saul, I see [note]1[/note]some divine being coming up out of the earth.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, a god; Heb. [i]elohim.[/i]</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And he said to her, What is his appearance? And she said, An old man is coming up; and he is wrapped in a cloak. Then Saul knew that it was Samuel, and he bowed with [i]his[/i] face to the ground and paid [i]him[/i] homage.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And Samuel said to Saul, Why have you disturbed me by bringing me up? And Saul said, I am greatly distressed; for the Philistines wage war against me, and God has [xref]a[/xref]turned away from me and answers me no more, neither through the prophets nor by dreams. Therefore I have called you, that you may make known to me what I shall do.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 16:14; 18:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And Samuel said, Why then have you inquired of me? For Jehovah has turned away from you and become your adversary.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And Jehovah has done for Himself just as He spoke through me, for [xref]a[/xref]Jehovah has torn the kingdom out from your hand and given it to an associate of yours, to David.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 15:28</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Because you did [xref]a[/xref]not listen to the voice of Jehovah and did not execute His burning anger upon the Amalekites, therefore Jehovah has done this thing to you this day.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 15:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And Jehovah will also give Israel with you into the hand of the Philistines, and tomorrow [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]you and your sons will be with me; Jehovah will also give the camp of Israel into the hand of the Philistines.</text>
        <note num="1">On Saul's tragic end ([link]31:1-5[/link]), see note [link]6[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 31[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Sam. 31:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Then immediately Saul fell his full length to the ground, and he was very afraid because of Samuel's words. And there was no strength in him, for he had not eaten food all day and all night.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And the woman came to Saul and saw that he was very troubled. And she said to him, Indeed, your servant has listened to your voice; and I have put my life in my hand and have listened to your words which you spoke to me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Now therefore, you listen also to the voice of your servant, and let me set a morsel of bread before you; and eat, that you may have strength when you go on your way.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>But he refused and said, I will not eat. Then his servants, as well as the woman, compelled him, and he listened to their voice; and he rose up from the ground and sat on the bed.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And the woman had a [xref]a[/xref]fattened calf in the house; and she hurried and killed it, and took flour and kneaded [i]it,[/i] and baked unleavened bread with it.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 18:7-8; Luke 15:23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>And she brought [i]it[/i] before Saul and his servants, and they ate. And they rose up and went away that night.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="29">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And the Philistines [xref]a[/xref]gathered all their camps together at Aphek; and Israel encamped by the spring that is in Jezreel.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 28:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And the lords of the Philistines passed on by hundreds and by thousands; and David and his men passed on at the rear with Achish.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And the princes of the Philistines said, What are these Hebrews [i]doing here?[/i] And Achish said to the princes of the Philistines, Is this not David, the servant of Saul the king of Israel, who has been with me these days, or [i]even[/i] these [xref]a[/xref]years? And I have found nothing [i]wrong[/i] in him since the day he deserted [i]to me[/i] to this day.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 27:7; 28:1-2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>But the princes of the Philistines were angry with him. And the princes of the Philistines said to him, [note]1[/note]Make the man go back, that he may return to his place that you have assigned him, so that he does not go down with us into the battle and does not become our adversary in the battle. For with what might this man reconcile himself to his master? Will it not be with the heads of these men?</text>
        <note num="1">In this chapter David was sovereignly kept by God from joining the Philistines' camp to fight against Israel. Thus, he was not involved in the destruction of Saul, his sons (including Jonathan), and the men of Israel ([link]31:1-5[/link]). His returning to the land of the Philistines also enabled him to rescue his two wives and the families of his men, who had been captured by the Amalekites ([link]ch. 30[/link]).[br/][br/]All the small things in this record show that God was working in a detailed way to carry out His economy. God exercised His sovereignty to rescue David from his dilemma. God did this not only for David's sake but also for the sake of His economy. Jesus Christ is called [i]the son of David[/i] ([link]Matt. 1:1[/link]), indicating that David was very much related to God's becoming a man to fulfill what had been determined in eternity past ([link]Micah 5:2[/link]). Without David there would not have been the genealogy through which Christ as God became a man to be one with mankind and to thereby accomplish God's economy.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Is this not David, of whom they sang to one another in dances, saying,[br/][xref]a[/xref]Saul has struck down his thousands; / But David, his ten thousands?</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 18:7; 21:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And Achish called David and said to him, [i]As[/i] Jehovah lives, you are upright, and it is acceptable in my sight that you go forth and come in with me in the camp; for I have not found evil in you since the day you came to me to this day. But you are not acceptable to the lords.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Now therefore return and go in peace, so that you do not do anything displeasing to the lords of the Philistines.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And David said to Achish, But what have I done? And what [i]wrong[/i] have you found in your servant since the day I began to be with you to this day, that I should not go and fight against the enemies of my lord the king?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And Achish answered and said to David, I know that you are as acceptable to me as an [xref]a[/xref]angel of God; nevertheless the princes of the Philistines have said, He shall not go up with us into the battle.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 14:17, 20; 19:27; Zech. 12:8; Gal. 4:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Now therefore rise up early in the morning with your master's servants who came with you; indeed rise up early in the morning, and when you have daylight, go.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>So David rose up early, he and his men, to go in the morning, to return into the land of the Philistines. And the Philistines went up to Jezreel.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="30">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And when David and his men came to [xref]a[/xref]Ziklag on the third day, the [xref]b[/xref]Amalekites had made a raid upon the south and upon Ziklag; and they had struck Ziklag and burned it with fire.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 27:6</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 15:2-3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And they had taken the women [i]and all[/i] who were in it captive, both small and great; they had killed none, but had carried [i]them[/i] off, and had gone on their way.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And David and his men came to the city; and there it was, burned with fire. And their wives and their sons and their daughters had been taken captive.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And David and the people who were with him lifted up their voice and wept until they had no strength to weep.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And David's two [xref]a[/xref]wives had been taken captive, Ahinoam the Jezreelite and Abigail the wife of Nabal the Carmelite.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 25:42-43</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And David was very distressed because the people spoke of [xref]a[/xref]stoning him, for the soul of all the people was bitter, every man because of his sons and his daughters. But David strengthened himself in Jehovah his God.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 17:4; Num. 14:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And David said to [xref]a[/xref]Abiathar the priest, the son of Ahimelech, Bring the ephod to me. So Abiathar brought the ephod to David.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 23:6, 9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And David [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]inquired of Jehovah, saying, Shall I pursue after this band? Will I overtake them? And He said to him, Pursue, for you will certainly overtake [i]them,[/i] and you will certainly deliver [i]them.[/i]</text>
        <note num="1">David was a person who trusted in God and walked according to God's sovereignty in all his trials ([link]17:36-37[/link]; [link]23:14-16[/link]). While he was under trial, he sought God's leading ([link]vv. 6b-10[/link]). He was one with God and behaved according to God.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 23:2; 2 Sam. 5:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>So David went, he and the six hundred men who were with him; and they came to the brook Besor, where those who were left stayed behind.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And David pursued, he and four hundred men; for two hundred stayed behind, who were too exhausted to cross over the brook Besor.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And they found an Egyptian in the field and brought him to David. And they gave him food, and he ate; and they gave him water to drink.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And they gave him a piece of fig cake and two raisin cakes; and he ate, and his [xref]a[/xref]spirit returned to him; for he had eaten no food and had drunk no water for three days and three nights.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Judg. 15:19; Luke 8:55</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And David said to him, To whom do you belong and where are you from? And he said, I am a young man of Egypt, the servant of an Amalekite man; and my master abandoned me because I fell sick three days ago.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>We attacked the south of the Cherethites and what belongs to Judah and the south of Caleb; and we burned Ziklag with fire.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And David said to him, Can you lead me down to this band? And he said, Swear to me by God that you will neither kill me nor deliver me into the hand of my master, and I will lead you down to this troop.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And he led him down; and there they were, spread over the whole land, eating and drinking and celebrating because of all the great spoil that they had taken from the land of the Philistines and from the land of Judah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And David struck them from twilight until the evening of the next day; and not a man of them escaped except for four hundred young men, who rode upon camels and fled.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And David delivered all that the Amalekites had taken; and David delivered his two wives.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And nothing was missed by them, neither small nor great, neither sons nor daughters, neither spoil nor anything that they had taken; David brought everything back.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And David took all the flocks and the herds, [i]which[/i] they drove before the other cattle and [i]of which[/i] they said, This is David's [note]1[/note]spoil.</text>
        <note num="1">By fighting the Amalekites David gained many rich spoils. While he was becoming rich, Saul was being defeated. David was flourishing, but Saul was diminishing, even to death ([link]31:1-5[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Then David came to the [xref]a[/xref]two hundred men who had been too exhausted to follow David and who had been left behind at the brook Besor. And they went forth to meet David and to meet the people who were with him; and David came near to the people and greeted them.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 30:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And all the wicked and worthless men among the men that had gone with David responded; and they said, Because they did not go with us, we will not give them anything of the spoil that we have delivered, except every man his wife and his children that they may lead [i]them[/i] off and go away.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Then said David, You shall not do so, my brothers, with that which Jehovah has given us, who has kept us and given this band that came against us into our hand.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And who will listen to you in this matter? For as his share is who goes down to the battle, so shall his share be who [xref]a[/xref]stays by the baggage; they shall [xref]b[/xref]share alike.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 25:13</xref>
        <xref num="b">Num. 31:27; Josh. 22:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>And from that day forward he made it a statute and an ordinance for Israel unto this day.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>And David came to Ziklag, and he sent some of the spoil to the elders of Judah, to his companions, saying, Here is a present for you from the spoil of the enemies of Jehovah:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>For those in Bethel, and for those in Ramoth of the south, and for those in Jattir,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>And for those in Aroer, and for those in Siphmoth, and for those in Eshtemoa,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>And for those in Racal, and for those in the cities of the Jerahmeelites, and for those in the cities of the Kenites,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>And for those in Hormah, and for those in Bor-ashan, and for those in Athach,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>And for those in Hebron, and for all the places where David himself and his men had gone about.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="31">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Now the Philistines were fighting against Israel; and the men of Israel fled from before the Philistines and fell down slain on Mount Gilboa.</text>
        <xref num="a">vv. 1-13: 1 Chron. 10:1-12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And the Philistines chased Saul and his sons; and the Philistines struck down [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Jonathan and Abinadab and Malchi-shua, Saul's sons.</text>
        <note num="1">Jonathan realized that David would be the king ([link]23:17[/link]), but instead of going to follow David according to God's will, Jonathan remained with his father because of his natural affection toward his father. In type, Jonathan's following David would have signified our following Christ and our giving Him the preeminence ([link]Col. 1:18[/link]). Because of his failure Jonathan suffered the same fate as his father and died with him in the battle. Thus, Jonathan lost the proper and adequate enjoyment of his portion in the good land promised by God.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Sam. 14:49; 1 Chron. 8:33</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And the battle bore heavily against Saul, and the archers hit him; and he was badly wounded by the archers.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Then Saul said to his armor bearer, Draw your sword, and thrust me through with it, lest these uncircumcised come and thrust me through and abuse me. But his armor bearer would not, for he was very [xref]a[/xref]afraid. So Saul took his sword and fell on it.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 2 Sam. 1:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And when his armor bearer saw that Saul was dead, he likewise fell on his sword and died with him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>So [xref]a[/xref]Saul and his three sons and his armor bearer, as well as all his men, [note]1[/note]died that day together.</text>
        <note num="1">Saul's tragic end was altogether due to his not being properly related to God's economy. God, wanting to build up His kingdom among His chosen people, had brought Saul into His economy, but instead of participating in God's economy and cooperating with it, Saul was selfish and usurped God's kingdom to build up his own monarchy. With David the situation was entirely different. When David was anointed by Samuel, he had a clear understanding that he had been assigned by God to be the king, but he did not have any thought about kingship. After Saul was appointed to be the king, he was immediately filled with thoughts of the kingship, including how his son would succeed him ([link]20:31[/link]). In this, Saul was selfish and wrong to the uttermost. Eventually, God gave Saul up and cut him off, tearing the kingdom away from him ([link]15:28[/link]). Because Saul was given up by God, he was left alone, like an orphan, having no provision of help when trouble came. Because of Saul's selfishness, the people of Israel suffered defeat and were slaughtered in the fight against the Philistines, and Saul and his sons were killed. Saul's ambition to have the kingdom for himself and for his son, with his jealousy of David, annulled and ended his enjoyment of the good land promised by God. The collective death of Saul, his three sons, and his armor bearer was God's fair judgment on the one who had rebelled against Him, had usurped Him, and had become His enemy ([link]1 Chron. 10:13-14[/link]).[br/][br/]From Saul's tragic end we should learn the lesson of crucifying our flesh and denying our selfishness &amp;#8212; our self-interest and self-seeking ([link]Gal. 5:24[/link]; [link]Matt. 16:24[/link]; [link]Phil. 2:3[/link]). The record of Saul's terrible end is a strong warning to all who serve in the kingdom of God not to do a separate work within the kingdom of God or to abuse anything in the kingdom. We should not be like Saul, trying to build up a "monarchy" for ourselves; rather, we should all do one unique work to build up the kingdom of God, the Body of Christ.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 28:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And when the men of Israel who were on the other side of the valley and who were on the other side of the Jordan saw that the men of Israel had fled and that Saul and his sons were dead, they forsook the cities and fled; and the Philistines came and dwelt in them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And the next day the Philistines came to strip the slain, and they found Saul and his three sons fallen on Mount Gilboa.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And they cut off his head and stripped off his armor; and they sent [i]them[/i] all around, throughout the land of the Philistines in order to announce the good news in the houses of their idols and to the people.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And they put his armor in the house of Ashtaroth; and they fastened his body to the wall of [xref]a[/xref]Beth-shan.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 21:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And when the inhabitants of [xref]a[/xref]Jabesh-gilead heard what the Philistines had done to Saul,</text>
        <xref num="a">Judg. 21:8; 1 Sam. 11:1; 2 Sam. 2:4-5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>All the valiant men rose up and went all night and took the body of Saul and the bodies of his sons from the wall of Beth-shan; and they came to Jabesh and burned them there.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And they took their bones and buried them under the tamarisk at Jabesh, and they fasted seven days.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    </chapters>
</book>
