<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book name="2 Peter" description="THE SECOND EPISTLE OF PETER" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="..\bible.xsd">
    <info title="Author">Peter, a slave and apostle of Jesus Christ ([link]1:1[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Time of Writing">Probably around A.D. 69, after Paul's martyrdom (cf. [link]3:15-16[/link]) and before the destruction of Jerusalem in A.D. 70, as indicated by the allusions to the decline of the church; close to the time of Peter's martyrdom ([link]1:14[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Place of Writing">Perhaps Rome, where the tradition in church history places Peter's martyrdom.</info>
    <info title="Recipients">The Jewish believers in dispersion in the Gentile world (see [link]1:1[/link] and note 3).</info>
    <subject>The Divine Provision and the Divine Government</subject>
    <outlines>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="1" ref="1:1-2">Introduction &amp;#8212; To the Believers, Who Have Been Allotted Equally Precious Faith</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="2" ref="1:3-21">The Divine Provision</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="vv. 3-11">The Impartation of the Divine Power</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="1" ref="vv. 3-4">All Things Which Relate to Life and Godliness, with the Divine Nature</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="2" ref="vv. 5-11">Growth and Development by Life unto the Rich Entrance into the Eternal Kingdom</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="vv. 12-21">The Shining of the Divine Truth</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="1" ref="vv. 12-18">By the Glory of the Apostles' Witnessing</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="2" ref="vv. 19-21">By the Light of the Prophetic Word</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="3" ref="2:1-3:16">The Divine Government</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="2:1-3">God's Judgment on the False Teachers</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="2:4-9">God's Judgment on Both Angels and Men</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="2:10-22">The Evils of the False Teachers and Their Punishment under God's Judgment</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="4" ref="3:1-9">God's Judgment on the Heretical Mockers</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="5" ref="3:10-12">God's Judgment on the Heavens and the Earth</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="6" ref="3:13">Expectation of the New Heavens and the New Earth Filled with God's Righteousness</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="7" ref="3:14-16">Preparation for the Coming Judgment</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="1" ref="v. 14">To Be Found by Him in Peace</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="2" ref="vv. 15-16">To Be Saved from Destruction</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="4" ref="3:17-18">Conclusion &amp;#8212; Be on Guard and Grow in the Grace and Knowledge of the Lord</outline>
    </outlines>
    <chapters>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Simon Peter, a [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]slave and [xref]c[/xref]apostle of Jesus Christ, to [note]3[/note]those who have been [note]4[/note]allotted [note]5[/note][xref]d[/xref]faith [note]6[/note]equally precious as [note]7[/note]ours [note]8[/note]in the [note]9[/note]righteousness of our [note]10[/note]God and Savior, Jesus Christ:</text>
        <note num="1">Simon, Peter's old name, refers to his old man by birth; Peter, his new name given by the Lord ([link]John 1:41-42[/link]), refers to his new man by regeneration. Here the two names are combined as one, signifying that the old man Simon had become the new man Peter.</note>
        <note num="2">[i]Slave[/i] indicates Peter's submission to the Lord, and [i]apostle,[/i] the Lord's commission to him.</note>
        <note num="3">Referring to the Jewish believers in dispersion in the Gentile world ([link]1 Pet. 1:1[/link]).</note>
        <note num="4">As the children of Israel were allotted a piece of the good land ([link]Josh. 13:6[/link]; [link]14:1-5[/link]; [link]19:51[/link]). This implies that the "all things which relate to life and godliness" ([link]v. 3[/link]), including the divine nature ([link]v. 4[/link]) partaken of by the believers through the equally precious faith according to the precious and exceedingly great promises, are the real inheritance given to the believers by God in the New Testament.</note>
        <note num="5">Faith is the substantiation of the substance of the truth ([link]Heb. 11:1[/link]), which is the reality of the contents of God's New Testament economy. The contents of God's New Testament economy are composed of the "all things which relate to life and godliness" ([link]v. 3[/link]), that is, the Triune God dispensing Himself into us as life within and godliness without (see points 1, 2, 4, and 5 and the last paragraph of note [link]1[sup]1[/sup] in 1 Tim. 1[/link]). The equally precious faith, allotted to us by God through the word of God's New Testament economy and the Spirit, responds to the reality of such contents and ushers us into the reality, making its substance the very element of our Christian life and experience. Such a faith is allotted to all the believers in Christ as their portion, which is equally precious to all who have received it. As such a portion from God, this faith is objective to us in the divine truth. But it brings all the contents of its substantiation into us, thus making them all, with itself (faith), subjective to us in our experience. This can be compared to the scenery (truth) and the seeing (faith) being objective to the camera (us). But when the light (the Spirit) brings the scenery to the film (our spirit) within the camera, both the seeing and the scenery become subjective to the camera.</note>
        <note num="6">The Greek word means [i]of[/i] equal value or honor; hence, equally precious. Equal not in measure but in value and honor to all those who receive it.</note>
        <note num="7">Referring to the apostle Peter and all the other believers in the Jewish land. All the believers in the Gentile world share with all those in the Jewish land the same precious faith, which enables them to substantiate the blessing of life of the New Testament as their common portion allotted to them by God.</note>
        <note num="8">In the sphere of.</note>
        <note num="9">Our God is righteous. Through His righteousness He has allotted the precious faith as a divine portion equally to all believers in Christ, both Jewish and Gentile, without respect of persons. And now He is not only our God but also our Savior. Thus, His righteousness now is not the righteousness only of God nor only of Christ, but the righteousness of both our God and our Savior, Jesus Christ. In that the Lord is our Savior, His righteousness is His righteous act, His death on the cross in absolute obedience ([link]Phil. 2:8[/link]), by which He accomplished redemption for us ([link]Heb. 9:12[/link]), enabling us to be justified by God ([link]Rom. 5:18[/link]). In that the Lord is our God, His righteousness is His justice, since, based on the righteous act, the redemption of our Savior Jesus Christ ([link]Rom. 3:24-25[/link]), He justifies all the believers in Christ ([link]Rom. 3:26[/link]), both Jewish and Gentile ([link]Rom. 3:30[/link]). In and by such a twofold righteousness, the righteousness of both our God and our Savior, Jesus Christ, the precious faith, the precious substantiation of the New Testament blessing, has been allotted equally to all believers among all nations.</note>
        <note num="10">Jesus Christ is both our God and our Savior. This indicates that Jesus Christ is God being our Savior. He is the very God whom we worship, and He became our Savior to save us. At Peter's time this designated the believers in Christ and separated them from the Jews, who did not believe that Jesus Christ was God, and from the Romans, who believed that Caesar, not Jesus Christ, was God.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 15:14[/link]; [link]Luke 5:8[/link]; [link]John 13:6[/link]; [link]20:2[/link]; [link]21:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 1:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 3:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Pet. 1:5[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:7[/link], [link]9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Grace to you and peace be [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]multiplied [note]3[/note]in the full [note]4[/note][xref]b[/xref]knowledge of God and of [note]5[/note]Jesus our Lord;</text>
        <note num="1">Or, Grace and peace be multiplied to you.</note>
        <note num="2">Grace and peace came to us through the God-allotted faith, which substantiates the life-blessing of the New Testament ([link]v. 1[/link]). This faith was infused into us through the word of God, which conveys to us the real knowledge of God and of Jesus our Lord. In the sphere of the full knowledge of God and of Jesus our Lord, and by means of this increasing and increased knowledge, the grace and peace that we have received will be multiplied.</note>
        <note num="3">In the sphere of, by means of.</note>
        <note num="4">This refers to a thorough, experiential knowledge. The full knowledge of the Triune God is for our participation in and enjoyment of His divine life and divine nature. It is in contrast to the killing knowledge of the human logic of philosophy, which invaded the church in its apostasy.</note>
        <note num="5">Some MSS read, Jesus Christ our Lord.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Pet. 1:2[/link]; [link]Jude 2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 1:3[/link], [link]8[/link]; [link]2:20[/link]; [link]3:18[/link]; [link]John 17:3[/link]; [link]Phil. 3:8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Seeing that His [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]divine power has [note]2[/note]granted to us [note]3[/note]all things which relate to [note]4[/note][xref]b[/xref]life and [note]5[/note][xref]c[/xref]godliness, [note]6[/note]through the [note]7[/note]full knowledge of [note]8[/note]Him who has [xref]d[/xref]called us [note]9[/note]by His own [note]10[/note][xref]e[/xref]glory and [note]11[/note][xref]f[/xref]virtue,</text>
        <note num="1">Chapter two shows that this Epistle, like 2 Timothy, 2 John, 3 John, and Jude, was written in the time of the church's degradation and apostasy. Hence, apostasy was the background of this book. The burden of the writer was to inoculate the believers against the poison of apostasy. God's salvation is to impart Himself in His Trinity into the believers that He may be their life and life supply. This is God's economy, God's plan. The apostasy distracted the believers from the economy of God by leading them into the human logic of puzzling philosophies. This did not lead them to partake of the tree of life, which gives life, but to participate in the tree of knowledge, which brings in death (Gen. [link]2:9[/link], [link]16-17[/link]). Thus the serpent deceived and seduced Eve ([link]Gen. 3:1-6[/link]). In order to inoculate against this death-poison, in his healing Epistle the apostle first prescribed the divine power as the strongest and most effective antidote. This provides the believers with all things related to the generating and supplying divine life (not the killing knowledge) and the God-expressing godliness (not the show of human wisdom). This rich divine provision, which is covered in detail in the succeeding verses (to [link]v. 11[/link]), is more than sufficient to enable the believers to live a proper Christian life and overcome the satanic apostasy.[br][br][i]Divine[/i] denotes the eternal, unlimited, and almighty divinity of God. Hence, divine power is the power of the divine life, which is related to the divine nature.</note>
        <note num="2">I.e., imparted, infused, and planted into us by the all-inclusive life-giving Spirit, who regenerates us and indwells us ([link]2 Cor. 3:6[/link], [link]17[/link]; [link]John 3:6[/link]; [link]Rom. 8:11[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">"All things which relate to life and godliness" are the various aspects of the divine life, typified by the riches of the produce of the good land in the Old Testament. They are the substance of our faith's substantiation allotted to us by God as our portion for our inheritance.</note>
        <note num="4">Life is within, enabling us to live, and godliness is without as the outward expression of the inward life. Life is the inward energy, the inward strength, to bring forth the outward godliness, which leads to and results in glory.</note>
        <note num="5">See note [link]2[sup]2[/sup] in 1 Tim. 2[/link].</note>
        <note num="6">The imparting into us of all the things of life is through the full knowledge of God, which is conveyed and revealed to us through His word. This becomes the faith (objective), in which our faith (subjective) is produced.</note>
        <note num="7">This refers to a thorough, experiential knowledge.</note>
        <note num="8">Referring to God, who is our Savior and our Lord Jesus Christ ([link]vv. 1-2[/link]). He called us to His glory and virtue by His glory and virtue. His disciples saw His glory and virtue ([link]v. 16[/link]; [link]John 1:14[/link]) and were attracted by them. Then by this glory and virtue He called them to this glory and virtue. It is the same with all believers in Christ.</note>
        <note num="9">Or, to.</note>
        <note num="10">I.e., the expression of God, God expressed in splendor.</note>
        <note num="11">Lit., excellency (see note [link]8[sup]7[/sup] in Phil. 4[/link]), denoting the energy of life that enables us to overcome all obstacles and to carry out all excellent attributes. Glory is the divine goal; virtue is the energy and strength of life that enable us to reach the goal. This virtue, with all things relating to life, has been given to us by the divine power, but it needs to be developed on the way to glory.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Rom. 1:20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Gen. 2:9[/link]; [link]Psa. 36:9[/link]; [link]John 1:4[/link]; [link]3:16[/link]; [link]10:10[/link]; [link]14:6[/link]; [link]1 John 1:2[/link]; [link]5:12[/link]; [link]Titus 1:2[/link]; [link]Acts 11:18[/link]; [link]Rom. 5:10[/link], [link]17[/link], [link]21[/link]; [link]6:4[/link]; [link]Col. 3:4[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 6:12[/link], [link]19[/link]; [link]Rev. 2:7[/link], [link]10[/link]; [link]22:1-2[/link], [link]14[/link], [link]19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 1:6[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 2:2[/link]; [link]3:16[/link]; [link]4:6-7[/link]; [link]6:3[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 3:12[/link]; [link]Titus 1:1[/link]; [link]2:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Pet. 2:9[/link]; [link]3:9[/link]; [link]5:10[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 2:12[/link]; [link]2 Thes. 2:14[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 1:9[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 1:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Rom. 1:23[/link]; [link]3:23[/link]; [link]5:2[/link]; [link]6:4[/link]; [link]8:18[/link]; [link]9:23[/link]; [link]John 17:22[/link], [link]24[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:17[/link]; [link]3:16[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 2:7[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 4:17[/link]; [link]Col. 1:27[/link]; [link]3:4[/link]; [link]Heb. 2:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]1 Pet. 2:9[/link]; cf. [link]2 Pet. 1:5[/link]; [link]Phil. 4:8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Through [note]2[/note]which He has granted to us precious and [note]3[/note]exceedingly great [xref]a[/xref]promises that through [note]4[/note]these you might become [xref]b[/xref]partakers of the divine nature, [note]5[/note]having [xref]c[/xref]escaped the [note]6[/note]corruption which is in the [xref]d[/xref]world [note]7[/note]by [xref]e[/xref]lust.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, on account of, on the basis of. The Greek word has an instrumental sense, but it also denotes cause here.</note>
        <note num="2">Referring to glory and virtue in [link]v. 3[/link]. Through and on the basis of the Lord's glory and virtue, by and to which we have been called, He has given us His precious and exceedingly great promises, such as in [link]Matt. 28:20[/link]; [link]John 6:57[/link]; [link]7:38-39[/link]; [link]10:28-29[/link]; [link]14:19-20[/link], [link]23[/link]; [link]15:5[/link]; and [link]16:13-15[/link]. All these promises are being carried out in His believers by His life-power as the excellent virtue, unto His glory.</note>
        <note num="3">Lit., greatest.</note>
        <note num="4">Through the precious and exceedingly great promises we, the believers in Christ, who is our God and Savior, have become partakers of His divine nature in an organic union with Him, into which we have entered through faith and baptism ([link]John 3:15[/link]; [link]Gal. 3:27[/link]; [link]Matt. 28:19[/link]). The virtue (energy of life) of this divine nature carries us into His glory (godliness becoming the full expression of the Triune God).</note>
        <note num="5">In his first Epistle the apostle told the believers that Christ had redeemed them from their vain manner of life ([link]1 Pet. 1:18-19[/link]) and that they should, thus, abstain from fleshly lusts ([link]1 Pet. 2:11[/link]) and no longer live in the flesh in the lusts of men ([link]1 Pet. 4:2[/link]). Here, in his second Epistle, he unveiled to them the energy, the strength, by which they were enabled to escape the corruption in lust, and the result of that escape. The energy is the virtue of the divine life, and the result is that the believers partake of the divine nature of God and thus enjoy all the riches of what the Triune God is. In our partaking of the divine nature and in our enjoying of all that God is, all the riches of the divine nature will be fully developed, as described in [link]vv. 5-7[/link]. Having escaped the corruption of lust in the world and having thus removed the barriers to the growth of the divine life in us, we are freed to become partakers of the divine nature and to enjoy its riches to the fullest extent in its development by the virtue of God unto His glory.</note>
        <note num="6">See note [link]1[sup]5[/sup], point 3, in ch. 2[/link].</note>
        <note num="7">Or, in.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Cor. 7:1[/link]; cf. [link]2 Pet. 3:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 12:10[/link]; [link]6:4[/link]; [link]3:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 2:18[/link], [link]20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Pet. 2:20[/link]; [link]1 John 2:15-17[/link]; [link]5:4[/link], [link]19[/link]; [link]James 4:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]2 Pet. 2:10[/link], [link]18[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 4:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And for this very reason also, [note]1[/note]adding all [xref]a[/xref]diligence, [note]2[/note]supply bountifully in your [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]faith [note]4[/note][xref]c[/xref]virtue; and in virtue, [note]5[/note][xref]d[/xref]knowledge;</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., bringing in beside. Beside, along with, the precious and exceedingly great promises given to us by God, we should bring in all diligence to cooperate with the enabling of the dynamic divine nature for the carrying out of God's promises.</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]19[sup]3[/sup] in Phil. 1[/link]. What the divine power has given us in [link]vv. 3-4[/link] is developed in [link]vv. 5-7[/link]. To supply virtue in faith is to develop virtue in the exercise of faith. This applies to all the other items.</note>
        <note num="3">This is the equally precious faith allotted to us by God ([link]v. 1[/link]) as the common portion of the New Testament blessing of life for the initiation of the Christian life. This faith needs to be exercised that the virtue of the divine life may be developed in the succeeding steps and reach maturity.</note>
        <note num="4">Lit., excellency (see note [link]8[sup]7[/sup] in Phil. 4[/link]); denoting the energy of the divine life, which issues in vigorous action (cf. note [link]3[sup]11[/sup][/link]).</note>
        <note num="5">Virtue, the vigorous action, needs the bountiful supply of the knowledge of God and of Jesus our Lord ([link]vv. 2-3[/link], [link]8[/link]) regarding all things that relate to the divine life and godliness and the partaking of the divine nature ([link]vv. 3-4[/link]) for our enjoyment in the subsequent development.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 1:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 1:1[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:6[/link]; [link]James 2:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Phil. 4:8[/link]; cf. [link]2 Pet. 1:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Pet. 1:2[/link], [link]3[/link], [link]8[/link]; [link]3:18[/link]; [link]Phil. 1:9[/link]; [link]3:8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And in knowledge, [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]self-control; and in self-control, [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]endurance; and in endurance, [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]godliness;</text>
        <note num="1">Or, temperance; the exercise of control and restraint over one's self in its passions, desires, and habits. This needs to be supplied and developed in knowledge for the proper growth in life.</note>
        <note num="2">To exercise self-control is to deal with ourselves; to exercise endurance is to bear with others and with circumstances.</note>
        <note num="3">A living that is like God and that expresses God. As we exercise control over our self and bear with others and with circumstances, godliness needs to be developed in our spiritual life, that we may be like God and express Him.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 24:25[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:23[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 3:2[/link], [link]11[/link]; [link]Titus 2:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 5:3[/link]; [link]Heb. 10:36[/link]; [link]James 1:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 1:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And in godliness, [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]brotherly love; and in brotherly love, [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]love.</text>
        <note num="1">The Greek word is composed of [i]to have affection for[/i] and [i]a brother;[/i] hence, a brotherly affection, a love characterized by delight and pleasure. In godliness, which is the expression of God, this love needs to be supplied for the brotherhood ([link]1 Pet. 2:17[/link]; [link]3:8[/link]; [link]Gal. 6:10[/link]), for our testimony to the world ([link]John 13:34-35[/link]), and for the bearing of fruit ([link]John 15:16-17[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word is used in the New Testament for the divine love, which God is in His nature ([link]1 John 4:8[/link], [link]16[/link]). It is nobler than human love. It adorns all the qualities of the Christian life ([link]1 Cor. 13[/link]; [link]Rom. 13:8-10[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:13-14[/link]). It is stronger in ability and greater in capacity than human love ([link]Matt. 5:44[/link], [link]46[/link]), yet a believer who lives by the divine life ([link]v. 3[/link]) and partakes of the divine nature ([link]v. 4[/link]) can be saturated with it and express it in full. Such a love needs to be developed in brotherly love to govern it and flow in it for the full expression of God, who is this love. Faith can be considered the seed of life, and this nobler love, the fruit ([link]v. 8[/link]) in its full development. The six steps of development in between are the stages of its growth unto maturity.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Pet. 1:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Thes. 3:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>For [note]1[/note]these things, [note]2[/note]existing in you and [note]3[/note]abounding, [note]4[/note]constitute [i]you[/i] neither [note]5[/note]idle nor [note]6[/note][xref]a[/xref]unfruitful [note]7[/note]unto the full [note]8[/note][xref]b[/xref]knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ.</text>
        <note num="1">All the virtues covered in [link]vv. 5-7[/link], from faith to love.</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word denotes that certain things exist in and belong to a person from the beginning, thus becoming his rightful possession to the present. This indicates that all the virtues mentioned above are the possession of the believers and exist in them forever through their experience of partaking of the divine nature in all its riches.</note>
        <note num="3">The divine virtues not only exist in and are possessed by the believers but also abound and multiply in them in the development and growth of the divine life.</note>
        <note num="4">This indicates that the virtues of the divine life and divine nature are the constituents of our spiritual constitution, our spiritual being, making us persons who do not have the elements of idleness and unfruitfulness.</note>
        <note num="5">Lit., unworking; hence, idle. One who is not idle may still be unfruitful. To be fruitful requires more growth in life and more supply of life. Idleness and unfruitfulness are constituents of our fallen being; working, the energizing of life, and fruitfulness are the constituents of our being that is growing in the divine life.</note>
        <note num="6">This indicates that what is covered in [link]vv. 5-7[/link] is the development of the growth of the divine life unto its maturity.</note>
        <note num="7">The constitution that has the spiritual virtues as its constituents advances in many steps toward the full knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ, with a view to the full realization of the all-inclusive embodiment of the Triune God. In this section of the Word, three prepositions are used regarding the relationship between the experience of life and spiritual knowledge: [i]in,[/i] in [link]v. 2[/link], referring to the sphere of the knowledge; [i]through,[/i] in [link]v. 3[/link], referring to the channel of the knowledge; and [i]unto,[/i] in [link]v. 8[/link], referring to the knowledge in view as a goal.</note>
        <note num="8">See note [link]2[sup]4[/sup][/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Titus 3:14[/link]; [link]John 15:2-5[/link]; [link]Jude 12[/link]; cf. [link]2 Cor. 9:10[/link]; [link]Rom. 1:13[/link]; [link]6:22[/link]; [link]7:4[/link]; [link]15:28[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:22[/link]; [link]Eph. 5:9[/link]; [link]Phil. 1:22[/link]; [link]4:17[/link]; [link]Col. 1:6[/link], [link]10[/link]; [link]Heb. 12:11[/link]; [link]13:15[/link]; [link]James 3:18[/link]; [link]Rev. 22:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 1:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>For he in whom [note]1[/note]these things are not present is [xref]a[/xref]blind, being [note]2[/note]shortsighted, [note]3[/note]having forgotten the [xref]b[/xref]cleansing of his past sins.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]8[sup]1[/sup][/link].</note>
        <note num="2">From the root word that means [i]to close the eyes[/i] (because of strong light); hence, to be shortsighted. To be thus shortsighted is to be spiritually blind, unable to see something further in the divine life and divine nature of the Triune God dispensed into the believers as their bountiful supply.</note>
        <note num="3">The Greek phrase has the sense of [i]willing to forget,[/i] i.e., willing to forget the experience of the cleansing of our past sins. That cleansing took place so that we could go on in the divine life by partaking of the divine nature to reach the maturity of life. This is not to deny the faithful profession we made when we believed in Christ and were baptized into Him, or to lose the assurance of salvation that we received at that time, but to neglect what the initiation of salvation meant to us.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Deut. 28:28-29[/link]; [link]Isa. 59:10[/link]; [link]Zeph. 1:17[/link]; [link]1 John 2:11[/link]; [link]Rev. 3:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Titus 2:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Therefore, brothers, be the more [xref]a[/xref]diligent to [note]2[/note]make your [xref]b[/xref]calling and [xref]c[/xref]selection [xref]d[/xref]firm, for doing [note]3[/note]these things you shall by no means ever [xref]e[/xref]stumble.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, Therefore rather, brothers, be diligent...</note>
        <note num="2">I.e., to develop the spiritual virtues in the divine life, to advance in the growth of the divine life. This makes God's calling and selection of us firm.</note>
        <note num="3">See note [link]8[sup]1[/sup][/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 1:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 1:3[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:18[/link]; [link]4:1[/link], [link]4[/link]; [link]Heb. 3:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Pet. 1:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Pet. 1:19[/link]; [link]3:17[/link]; [link]Heb. 3:6[/link], [link]14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]1 Pet. 2:8[/link]; [link]Jude 24[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>For in this way the [xref]a[/xref]entrance into the [note]1[/note]eternal [xref]b[/xref]kingdom of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ will be richly [i]and[/i] [xref]c[/xref]bountifully [note]2[/note]supplied to you.</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to the kingdom of God, which was given to our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ ([link]Dan. 7:13-14[/link]) and which will be manifested at His coming back ([link]Luke 19:11-12[/link]). It will be a reward to His faithful believers, who pursue the growth in His life unto maturity and the development of the virtues of His nature that in the millennium they may participate in His kingship in God's glory ([link]2 Tim. 2:12[/link]; [link]Rev. 20:4[/link], [link]6[/link]). To enter thus into the eternal kingdom of the Lord is related to entering into God's eternal glory, to which God has called us in Christ ([link]1 Pet. 5:10[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 2:12[/link] and notes 2 and 3).</note>
        <note num="2">The bountiful supply that we enjoy in the development of the divine life and divine nature ([link]vv. 3-7[/link]) will bountifully supply us a rich entrance into the eternal kingdom of our Lord. It will enable and qualify us to enter into the coming kingdom by all the riches of the divine life and divine nature as our excellent virtues (energy) unto the splendid glory of God. This is not merely to be saved but, after being saved, to pursue the growth and maturity in the divine life and thereby receive the kingdom reward. See note [link]28[sup]1[/sup] in Heb. 12[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Matt. 5:20[/link]; [link]7:21[/link]; [link]25:21[/link], [link]23[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 14:22[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 6:9-10[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:21[/link]; [link]Eph. 5:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Phil. 1:19[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Therefore I will be ready always to [xref]a[/xref]remind you concerning these things, even though you know [i]them[/i] and have been [xref]b[/xref]established in the [note]1[/note]present [xref]c[/xref]truth.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., the truth that is present with the believers, which they have already received and now possess. In the first section of this chapter, [link]vv. 3-11[/link], Peter used the provision of the divine life for the proper Christian life to inoculate against the apostasy. In the second section, [link]vv. 12-21[/link], he used the revelation of the divine truth, as the second antidote, to inoculate against the heresy in the apostasy, a heresy similar to today's modernism. The provision of life and the revelation of truth are the antidotes used by Peter in dealing with the apostasy.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 3:1[/link]; [link]Jude 5[/link]; [link]Rom. 15:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Thes. 3:2[/link]; [link]Rom. 1:11-12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Tim. 2:4[/link]; [link]4:3[/link]; [link]6:5[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 2:18[/link]; [link]Titus 1:1[/link], [link]14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And I consider it [xref]a[/xref]right, as long as I am in this [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]tabernacle, to [xref]c[/xref]stir you up by a reminder,</text>
        <note num="1">The temporal body ([link]2 Cor. 5:1[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Phil. 1:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Cor. 5:1-4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 3:1[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Knowing that the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]putting off of my tabernacle is imminent, even as [note]2[/note]also our Lord Jesus Christ has made clear to me.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., to put off the body, to be unclothed of the body ([link]2 Cor. 5:4[/link]), to leave the body, to die physically. Peter, like Paul ([link]2 Tim. 4:6[/link]), knew that he would leave the world by martyrdom, and he was now ready for it.</note>
        <note num="2">Peter remembered the Lord's word to him concerning his death, given at the time the Lord charged him to feed His sheep ([link]John 21:15-19[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]2 Tim. 4:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Moreover I will also be diligent that you may be able, after my [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]exodus, to [xref]b[/xref]bring these things to mind at all times.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, departure; i.e., to leave the world. The same word is used in [link]Luke 9:31[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Luke 9:31[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Jude 17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>For we did not [note]1[/note]follow [xref]a[/xref]cleverly devised [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]myths when we made known to you the [xref]c[/xref]power and [note]3[/note][xref]d[/xref]coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, but we became [note]4[/note][xref]e[/xref]eyewitnesses of that One's [note]5[/note]majesty.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., follow out.</note>
        <note num="2">Myths were the superstitious stories cleverly devised in Greek philosophy, which was related to the apostasy.</note>
        <note num="3">The Greek word means [i]presence.[/i]</note>
        <note num="4">"'Admitted into immediate vision of the glory,' a word used for full initiation into the mysteries" (Darby). Peter realized that he, James, and John had been admitted into the highest degree of initiation at the Lord's transfiguration, admitted to be the initiated spectators of His majesty. He considered the transfiguration of the Lord a figure of His second coming, even as the Lord did in [link]Luke 9:26-36[/link]. The Lord's transfiguration in glory was a fact, and he was in it. The Lord's coming back in glory also will be a fact, as real as the Lord's transfiguration, and he will be in it as well. This was not a cleverly devised myth told to the believers by the apostles.</note>
        <note num="5">I.e., magnificence, greatness in splendor, honor, and glory, even magnificent glory ([link]v. 17[/link]), as that which appeared to the eyes of Peter and the other two disciples in the Lord's transfiguration ([link]Matt. 17:1-2[/link]; [link]Luke 9:32[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 2:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 1:4[/link] and note 1; [link]Titus 1:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Mark 5:30[/link]; [link]Luke 6:19[/link]; [link]8:46[/link]; [link]24:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Pet. 3:4[/link]; [link]Matt. 24:3[/link] and note 3</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]1 John 1:1[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>For He received from God the Father honor and glory, a [xref]a[/xref]voice such as this being [note]1[/note]borne to Him by the [note]2[/note]magnificent glory: This is My Son, My Beloved, in whom I delight.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, carried along. So also in [link]vv. 18[/link] and [link]21[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">The overshadowing cloud at the Lord's transfiguration ([link]Luke 9:34-35[/link]), like the shekinah glory that overshadowed the expiation cover ([link]Exo. 25:20[/link]; [link]40:34[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Matt. 17:5[/link]; [link]3:17[/link]; [link]Mark 9:7[/link]; [link]Luke 9:35[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And this voice we heard being borne out of heaven while we were with Him in the [xref]a[/xref]holy [xref]b[/xref]mountain.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 3:5[/link]; [link]Josh. 5:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Matt. 17:1[/link]; [link]Mark 9:2[/link]; [link]Luke 9:28[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>[note]1[/note]And we have the [xref]a[/xref]prophetic word [i]made[/i] more [xref]b[/xref]firm, to which you do well to give heed as to a [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]lamp shining in a [note]3[/note]dark place, until the [note]4[/note][xref]d[/xref]day dawns and the [xref]e[/xref]morning star rises in your hearts;</text>
        <note num="1">[i]And[/i] indicates that in addition to the truth of the Lord's transfiguration, covered in the preceding verses as the inoculation against superstitious myths, the truth of the prophetic word is used for a more sure confirmation.</note>
        <note num="2">Peter likened the word of prophecy in the Scripture to a lamp shining in a dark place. This indicates that (1) this age is a dark place in the dark night ([link]Rom. 13:12[/link]), and all the people of this world are moving and acting in darkness; and (2) the prophetic word of the Scripture, as the shining lamp to the believers, conveys spiritual light that shines in their darkness (not merely knowledge in letters for their mental apprehension), guiding them to enter into a bright day, even to pass through the dark night until the day of the Lord's appearing dawns. Before the Lord as the sunlight appears, we need this word as light to shine over our footsteps.</note>
        <note num="3">Or, murky place, a place that is squalid, dry, and neglected. This is a metaphor illustrating the darkness in the apostasy.</note>
        <note num="4">A metaphor illustrating a coming time that will be full of light, as a bright day dawning, with the morning star rising, before its dawning, in the hearts of the believers, who are illuminated and enlightened by giving heed to the shining word of prophecy in the Scripture. In the time of apostasy the believers do well to give heed in this matter, that the prophetic word, as a lamp, may shine through the darkness of apostasy until such a day dawns upon them. This will cause and encourage them to earnestly seek the Lord's presence and be watchful so that they will not miss the Lord in the secret part of His coming (parousia), when He will come as a thief (see notes [link]27[sup]1[/sup] in Matt. 24[/link] and [link]8[sup]3[/sup] in 2 Thes. 2[/link]). Hence, this metaphor must allude to the coming age, the age of the kingdom, as a day that will dawn at the appearing (the coming) of the Lord ([link]v. 16[/link]) as the Sun of righteousness ([link]Mal. 4:2[/link]), whose light will shine to break through the gloom of the dark night of this age. Preceding this, in the darkest hour of the night the Lord will appear as the morning star ([link]Rev. 2:28[/link]; [link]22:16[/link]) to those who are watchful and looking for His dear appearing ([link]2 Tim. 4:8[/link]). They have been enlightened by the shining of the prophetic word, which is able to lead them to the dawning day.[br][br]If we give heed to the word in the Bible, which shines as a lamp in a dark place, we will have His rising in our hearts to shine in the darkness of apostasy where we are today, before His actual appearing as the morning star.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Pet. 1:10[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 3:2[/link]; [link]Luke 1:70[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 1:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Psa. 119:105[/link]; [link]John 5:35[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">cf. [link]Rom. 13:12[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 5:4-5[/link], [link]8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Rev. 2:28[/link]; [link]22:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Knowing this first, that no prophecy of [xref]a[/xref]Scripture is of [note]1[/note]one's own [note]2[/note]interpretation;</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to the prophet who spoke the prophecy or to the writer who wrote the prophecy.</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., loosening, untying; hence, disclosure, explanation, exposition. [i]One's own interpretation[/i] means the prophet's or writer's own explanation or exposition, which would not be inspired by God through the Holy Spirit. The thought here is that no prophecy of Scripture is of the prophet's or writer's own concept, idea, or understanding; no prophecy comes from that source, the source of man; no prophecy originates from any prophet's or writer's private and personal thought. This is confirmed and explained by the succeeding verse.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 3:16[/link]; [link]Acts 1:16[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 3:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>[note]1[/note]For no prophecy was ever [note]2[/note]borne by the will of man, but men spoke from God while being [note]2[/note]borne by the Holy [xref]a[/xref]Spirit.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]For[/i] introduces an explanation of the preceding verse. No prophecy of Scripture is of the prophet's or writer's exposition, for no prophecy was ever borne, or carried along, by the will of man. Rather, men spoke from God while being borne by the Holy Spirit.</note>
        <note num="2">In Greek the same word as in [link]vv. 17[/link], [link]18[/link]. No prophecy was ever borne by the will of man. Man's will, desire, and wish, with his thought and exposition, were not the source from which any prophecy came; the source was God, by whose Holy Spirit men were borne, as a ship is borne by the wind, to speak out the will, desire, and wish of God.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Sam. 23:2[/link]; [link]Ezek. 3:12[/link], [link]14[/link]; [link]8:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[note]1[/note]But there arose also [xref]a[/xref]false prophets among the people, as also among you there will be [xref]b[/xref]false teachers, who will [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]secretly bring in destructive [note]3[/note]heresies, even [xref]d[/xref]denying the [note]4[/note][xref]e[/xref]Master who [xref]f[/xref]bought them, bringing upon themselves swift [note]5[/note]destruction.</text>
        <note num="1">After presenting to the believers (in [link]ch. 1[/link]) the rich provision of the divine life and the shining enlightenment of the divine truth, thus providing for the maintenance of life and inoculating against the poison of the apostasy, in this chapter the apostle faithfully indicated as a warning to the believers the awful contents of the apostasy and its dreadful result. This warning is a close parallel to the warning given in [link]Jude 4-19[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Or, bring in by smuggling. Lit., to bring in alongside, to bring in sideways. It means to introduce a new subject for which the hearers are not prepared. Here it denotes the false teachers' bringing in and introducing their false teachings alongside the true ones.</note>
        <note num="3">The Greek word means [i]choices of opinion (of doctrine) different from that usually accepted,[/i] "self-chosen doctrines, alien from the truth" (Alford). Such doctrines cause division and produce sects. This word is used also in [link]Acts 5:17[/link]; [link]15:5[/link]; [link]24:5[/link], [link]14[/link]; [link]26:5[/link]; [link]28:22[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 11:19[/link]; and [link]Gal. 5:20[/link]; and in [link]Titus 3:10[/link] in the adjective form, [i]heretical[/i] (there rendered [i]factious).[/i] Here it denotes the false and heretical doctrines brought in by the false teachers, the heretics. Such doctrines are like those of today's modernism.</note>
        <note num="4">This implies the Lord's person and His redemptive work. The false teachers at Peter's time, like today's modernists in their apostasy, denied both the person of the Lord as the Master and His redemption, by which the Lord purchased the believers.</note>
        <note num="5">In this Epistle, Peter used three different Greek words concerning the consequence of the apostasy under God's governmental judgment:[br][br](1) [i]Apollumi[/i] signifies [i]to destroy utterly;[/i] in the middle voice, [i]to perish,[/i] as in [link]3:6[/link]. The thought is not extinction but ruin, loss (not of being but of well-being). In [link]Matt. 10:28[/link]; [link]22:7[/link]; [link]Mark 12:9[/link]; [link]Luke 17:27[/link], [link]29[/link]; [link]John 3:16[/link]; [link]10:28[/link]; [link]17:12[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 10:9-10[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 2:15[/link]; [link]4:3[/link]; [link]2 Thes. 2:10[/link]; and [link]Jude 5[/link], [link]11[/link], this word unveils more concerning God's governmental judgment. In [link]3:9[/link] it denotes the punishment of God's governmental discipline.[br][br](2) [i]Apoleia,[/i] akin to [i]apollumi,[/i] indicates loss (of well-being, not of being), ruin, destruction, or (physical, spiritual, or eternal) perdition. It is rendered [i]destructive[/i] and [i]destruction[/i] in [link]2:1[/link], and [i]destruction[/i] in [link]2:3[/link]; [link]3:7[/link], [link]16[/link]. The same word is used to denote the different results of God's varied judgments (see note [link]17[sup]2[/sup], par. 2, in 1 Pet. 1[/link]). In cases such as those described in [link]2:1[/link], [link]3[/link]; [link]3:7[/link]; [link]John 17:12[/link]; [link]Rom. 9:22[/link]; [link]Phil. 1:28[/link]; [link]3:19[/link]; [link]2 Thes. 2:3[/link]; and [link]Rev. 17:8[/link], [link]11[/link], it denotes eternal perdition. In cases such as those described in [link]3:16[/link] (see note 4) and [link]Heb. 10:39[/link] (see note 2), it denotes the punishment of God's governmental discipline, not eternal perdition. In [link]Matt. 7:13[/link] and [link]1 Tim. 6:9[/link] it denotes a principle used for any case.[br][br](3) [i]Phthora,[/i] denoting corruption unto destruction, the destruction that comes with corruption, a destroying by means of corrupting (in reference to morality, soul, and body). It is rendered [i]corruption[/i] in [link]1:4[/link] and [link]2:19[/link], and [i]destruction[/i] and [i]corrupting[/i] in [link]2:12[/link]; its verb form is used in the future passive voice and is rendered [i]will be destroyed[/i] in [link]2:12[/link], and in the present passive voice, rendered [i]are being corrupted,[/i] in [link]Jude 10[/link]. Its significance can be further seen in [link]Rom. 8:21[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 3:17[/link] and notes 1 and 2; [link]15:33[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 7:2[/link]; [link]11:3[/link]; [link]Gal. 6:8[/link]; [link]Rev. 11:18[/link]; and [link]19:2[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Deut. 13:1[/link]; [link]1 Kings 18:19[/link], [link]22[/link], [link]40[/link]; [link]22:6[/link], [link]10[/link], [link]20-23[/link]; [link]Jer. 14:14[/link]; [link]27:9-10[/link], [link]16[/link]; [link]Matt. 7:15[/link]; [link]24:11[/link]; [link]1 John 4:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. [link]2 Cor. 11:13[/link], [link]26[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Gal. 2:4[/link]; [link]Jude 4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Matt. 10:33[/link]; [link]26:34-35[/link], [link]69-75[/link]; [link]Luke 12:9[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 2:12[/link]; [link]1 John 2:22-23[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Jude 4[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 2:21[/link]; [link]Rev. 6:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]Acts 20:28[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 6:20[/link]; [link]7:23[/link]; [link]Rev. 5:9[/link]; [link]14:3-4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And many will [note]1[/note]follow their [xref]a[/xref]licentiousness, because of whom the [note]2[/note]way of the truth will be [xref]b[/xref]reviled.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., follow out.</note>
        <note num="2">I.e., the path of the Christian life according to the truth, which is the reality of the contents of the New Testament ([link]1 Tim. 2:4[/link]; [link]3:15[/link]; [link]4:3[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 2:15[/link], [link]18[/link]; [link]Titus 1:1[/link]). It is designated by other titles according to its various virtues, such as the straight way ([link]v. 15[/link] and note 1; cf. [link]Heb. 12:13[/link]), the way of righteousness ([link]v. 21[/link] and note; [link]Matt. 21:32[/link]), the way of peace ([link]Luke 1:79[/link]; [link]Rom. 3:17[/link]), the way of salvation ([link]Acts 16:17[/link]), the way of God ([link]Matt. 22:16[/link]; [link]Acts 18:26[/link]), the way of the Lord ([link]John 1:23[/link]; [link]Acts 18:25[/link]), and the Way ([link]Acts 9:2[/link]; [link]19:9[/link], [link]23[/link]; [link]22:4[/link]; [link]24:22[/link]). It is slandered as the way of heresy ([link]Acts 24:14[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 2:7[/link], [link]18[/link]; [link]Jude 4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Pet. 3:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And in [xref]a[/xref]covetousness, with [xref]b[/xref]fabricated [xref]c[/xref]words, they will [xref]d[/xref]make merchandise of you, for whom the [note]1[/note][xref]e[/xref]judgment [note]2[/note]of old is not idle, and their [note]3[/note]destruction does not slumber.</text>
        <note num="1">First Peter stresses God's governmental judgment ([link]1 Pet. 4:17-18[/link]). This is continued in 2 Peter. Under God's government the fallen angels were caught and are being kept for judgment ([link]v. 4[/link]), and the age of the deluge and the cities of Sodom and Gomorrah were all judged ([link]vv. 5-9[/link]). But God will mete out especially serious judgment to the New Testament heretics ([link]v. 10[/link]). And all the ungodly will be judged and destroyed in the day when the heavens and the earth are burned by fire ([link]3:7[/link]). Because of this, the God of justice and holiness has begun His governmental judgment from His own household &amp;#8212; the believers. See note [link]17[sup]2[/sup], par. 2, in 1 Pet. 1[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">I.e., from ancient times, as illustrated in [link]vv. 4-9[/link].</note>
        <note num="3">See note [link]1[sup]5[/sup][/link], point 2.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 2:14[/link]; [link]Acts 20:33[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 2:5[/link]; [link]Titus 1:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 1:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rom. 16:18[/link]; [link]Col. 2:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Jude 16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Jude 4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>For if God did not spare the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]angels who sinned but delivered [i]them[/i] to gloomy [xref]b[/xref]pits, having cast them down to [note]2[/note]Tartarus, they being [xref]c[/xref]kept [note]3[/note]for [note]4[/note]judgment;</text>
        <note num="1">The fallen angels (see notes [link]19[sup]3[/sup] in 1 Pet. 3[/link] and [link]4[sup]1[/sup] in Rev. 12[/link]), who, according to the sequence of historical facts recorded in this chapter, were the first fallen ones in the universe.</note>
        <note num="2">A deep and gloomy pit, where the fallen angels are detained as in a prison. See note [link]19[sup]4[/sup] in 1 Pet. 3[/link].</note>
        <note num="3">Or, until.</note>
        <note num="4">The judgment of the great day ([link]Jude 6[/link]), which probably will be the judgment of the great white throne, executed upon all the dead and the demons, and probably also upon the fallen angels ([link]Rev. 20:11-15[/link]). It is logical that all the angels, demons, and men who have joined Satan in his rebellion will be judged at the same time, in the same way, and with the same result, immediately after their evil leader is judged and cast into the lake of fire ([link]Rev. 20:10[/link]), into which they also will be cast. See note [link]17[sup]2[/sup], par. 2, in 1 Pet. 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Jude 6[/link]; [link]Matt. 25:41[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. [link]Luke 8:31[/link]; [link]Rev. 9:1[/link], [link]2[/link], [link]11[/link]; [link]20:1[/link], [link]3[/link]; [link]Rom. 10:7[/link] and note 1</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 2:9[/link]; [link]3:7[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And did not spare the ancient [xref]a[/xref]world but guarded [xref]b[/xref]Noah, a herald of [note]1[/note][xref]c[/xref]righteousness, with seven others, when He brought a flood upon the world of the [xref]d[/xref]ungodly;</text>
        <note num="1">Whether one is righteous and godly or unrighteous and ungodly is crucial in regard to God's governmental judgment ([link]vv. 5-9[/link]). To be righteous is to be right with man before God, and to be godly is to express God before man. This was the manner of life that Noah and Lot lived, a manner of life that spared them from God's governmental judgment according to His righteousness.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 3:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Gen. 7:1[/link], [link]7[/link], [link]23[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 3:20[/link]; [link]Heb. 11:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Gen. 6:9[/link]; [link]7:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Pet. 3:7[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 1:9[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 2:16[/link]; [link]Titus 2:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And having reduced to ashes the cities of [xref]a[/xref]Sodom and Gomorrah, condemned [i]them[/i] to [note]1[/note]ruin, having set [i]them as[/i] an [xref]b[/xref]example to those who intend to [note]2[/note]live an ungodly life,</text>
        <note num="1">Or, overthrow.</note>
        <note num="2">I.e., to live in the flesh in the lusts of men, not in the will of God; to carry out the desire of the Gentiles ([link]1 Pet. 4:2-3[/link]) and to have a vain, ungodly manner of life ([link]1 Pet. 1:18[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 19:24[/link]; [link]Deut. 29:23[/link]; [link]Jude 7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. [link]Num. 26:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And rescued righteous [xref]a[/xref]Lot, who had been oppressed by the [xref]b[/xref]licentious [note]1[/note]manner of life of the [note]2[/note]lawless</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]6[sup]2[/sup][/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Unprincipled; a Greek word different from that for [i]lawless[/i] in [link]v. 8[/link]. [i]Lawless[/i] here denotes especially those who violate the law of nature and conscience.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 19:15-23[/link], [link]29[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 2:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>(For that righteous man, who settled down among them, in seeing and hearing [xref]a[/xref]tormented [i]his[/i] righteous soul day after day with [i]their[/i] lawless works);</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Psa. 119:136[/link]; [link]Ezek. 9:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>The Lord knows how to deliver the [note]1[/note]godly out of [xref]a[/xref]trial and how to [xref]b[/xref]keep the [note]2[/note]unrighteous under punishment [note]3[/note]for the [note]4[/note][xref]c[/xref]day of [note]5[/note]judgment,</text>
        <note num="1">Those who, like Noah and Lot ([link]vv. 5[/link], [link]7[/link]), live a godly life, in contrast to those who live an ungodly life ([link]v. 6[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">People who, like those in Noah's time and those in Sodom and Gomorrah ([link]vv. 5-7[/link]), live an unrighteous life, in the licentious manner of the lawless.</note>
        <note num="3">Or, until.</note>
        <note num="4">The day of the final judgment, the judgment at the great white throne (see notes [link]7[sup]4[/sup] in ch. 3[/link], [link]4[sup]4[/sup] in ch. 2[/link], and [link]6[sup]4[/sup] in Jude[/link]).</note>
        <note num="5">See note [link]17[sup]2[/sup], par. 2, in 1 Pet. 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Pet. 4:12[/link]; [link]Dan. 3:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 2:4[/link]; [link]3:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Jude 6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And especially [note]1[/note]those who go after the flesh in the [xref]a[/xref]lust for [xref]b[/xref]defilement and despise [note]2[/note]lordship. Daring, [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]self-willed, they do not tremble while reviling [note]4[/note]dignities;</text>
        <note num="1">From here to the end of the chapter the exposure returns to the false teachers and their followers, who were exposed initially in [link]vv. 1-3[/link]. In God's governmental dealing they, especially, will be kept under punishment for the day of judgment because they go after the flesh, indulging for pleasure in the lust for defilement and in corrupting luxury, and despise the Lord's government, rebelling against the Lord's authority ([link]vv. 10[/link], [link]13-14[/link], [link]18[/link]). Thus, they become persons who are like (1) animals without reason ([link]v. 12[/link]); (2) spots and blemishes among the believers, who are God's treasure ([link]v. 13[/link]); (3) Balaam, forsaking the straight way for unrighteous gain ([link]v. 15[/link]); (4) springs without water and mists driven by a storm ([link]vv. 17-19[/link]); and (5) dogs and sows, becoming defiled both inwardly and outwardly ([link]vv. 20-22[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Referring, in general, to all those who have authority to rule, including, of course, the Lord Christ, who was anointed and set up by God and who is the center of the divine government, dominion, and authority ([link]Acts 2:36[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:21[/link]; [link]Col. 1:16[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">Self-pleasing, seeking pleasure for self.</note>
        <note num="4">Lit., glories; referring generally to both angels and men in power and authority ([link]v. 11[/link]; [link]Jude 9[/link]; [link]Titus 3:1-2[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Pet. 4:2[/link]; [link]Jude 16[/link]; [link]1 John 2:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Jude 8[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 2:20[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 7:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Titus 1:7[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Whereas [note]1[/note]angels, though they are greater in strength and power, [note]2[/note]do not bring a reviling judgment against [note]1[/note]them before the Lord.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Angels[/i] and [i]them,[/i] referring to [i]dignities[/i] in [link]v. 10[/link], are mentioned here in a general way; but in [link]Jude 9[/link], regarding the same case, the archangel Michael and the devil are singled out.</note>
        <note num="2">This is to keep the order of authority in God's government.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>But [xref]a[/xref]these, like [note]1[/note]animals [note]2[/note]without reason, born natural [note]3[/note]for capture and [note]4[/note]destruction, reviling in things of which they are ignorant, will also in their corrupting [i]of others[/i] be [note]5[/note]destroyed;</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., living creatures (including man); indicating men who are living like animals.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, irrational, having no sense regarding moral issues. The highest sense within man is his spirit, of which the conscience is the leading part. Since man's fall, the conscience has governed man under God's government. Some men are past feeling ([link]Eph. 4:19[/link] and note), having given up the consciousness of their conscience through their denial of God ([link]Rom. 1:23-32[/link]). The first century heretics, such as the Sadducees in ancient Judaism ([link]Acts 23:8[/link]), and the modernists in today's Christianity are all in this category. They have denied the Lord to the uttermost so that their conscience is seared and has lost its consciousness ([link]1 Tim. 4:2[/link] and note 2), as if they do not even have a spirit ([link]Jude 10[/link], cf. [link]19[/link]). Thus, they become like animals without reason, like creatures of instinct, born natural to be captured, through their lust, by Satan, the destroyer of man, that they may be corrupted unto destruction. The portrayal here shows us that fallen men can be like animals without reason!</note>
        <note num="3">Lit., unto; indicating that they are destined to be captured for destruction, to be made slaves of corruption ([link]v. 19[/link]). By the supply of life through the divine provision ([link]1:3-4[/link]) we are able to escape this corruption that brings in destruction. See note [link]1[sup]5[/sup][/link], point 3.</note>
        <note num="4">The same Greek word as for [i]corruption.[/i]</note>
        <note num="5">The same Greek word as for [i]corrupted,[/i] referring to destruction caused by corruption.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Jude 10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Suffering unrighteousness as the [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]wages of unrighteousness; considering luxury in the day [i]to be[/i] [xref]b[/xref]pleasure; [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]spots and blemishes, reveling in their deceits while [xref]d[/xref]feasting together with you;</text>
        <note num="1">Some MSS read, Receiving the wages of unrighteousness.</note>
        <note num="2">I.e., wages of unrighteous doing.</note>
        <note num="3">The lust-indulging heretics are to genuine believers, who are God's treasure, as spots and blemishes are to precious gems.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 2:15[/link]; [link]Acts 1:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Luke 8:14[/link]; [link]Titus 3:3[/link]; [link]James 4:3[/link]; [link]5:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 3:14[/link]; [link]Eph. 5:27[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Jude 12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Having eyes full of [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]adultery and not [xref]b[/xref]ceasing from sin; [xref]c[/xref]enticing [xref]d[/xref]unstable souls, having a heart exercised for [xref]e[/xref]covetousness, [xref]f[/xref]children of [xref]g[/xref]curse.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., an adulteress.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 4:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Pet. 4:1[/link]; cf. [link]Rom. 6:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 2:18[/link]; [link]James 1:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Pet. 3:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]2 Pet. 2:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]Eph. 2:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="g">[link]Rom. 9:3[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 16:22[/link]; [link]Gal. 1:8-9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Forsaking the [note]1[/note]straight way, they have [xref]a[/xref]gone astray, [note]2[/note]following the way of [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]Balaam, the [i]son[/i] of Beor, who loved the [xref]c[/xref]wages of unrighteousness</text>
        <note num="1">To take the straight way, such as the way of the truth ([link]v. 2[/link] and note 2) and the way of righteousness ([link]v. 21[/link] and note 1), is to live an upright life without crookedness and bias, without unrighteousness.</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., following out.</note>
        <note num="3">Balaam was a genuine Gentile prophet, not a false one, but he loved the wages of unrighteousness ([link]Num. 22:5[/link], [link]7[/link]; [link]Deut. 23:4[/link]; [link]Neh. 13:2[/link]; [link]Rev. 2:14[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Ezek. 14:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Num. 22:5[/link], [link]7[/link]; [link]Deut. 23:4[/link]; [link]Neh. 13:2[/link]; [link]Jude 11[/link]; [link]Rev. 2:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 2:13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>But had reproof for his own transgression: a dumb [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]beast of burden, uttering with a man's voice, restrained the madness of the prophet.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., donkey.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Num. 22:21-30[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>These are [note]1[/note]springs [xref]a[/xref]without water and mists driven by a storm, for whom the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]gloom of darkness is kept.</text>
        <note num="1">The dried up heretical teachers are springs without water and mists driven by a storm, that is, waterless clouds being carried off by winds ([link]Jude 12[/link]), having nothing of life to meet the need of the thirsty ones.</note>
        <note num="2">This also is God's governmental dealing.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Jude 12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Jude 13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>For uttering great [xref]a[/xref]swelling [i]words[/i] of [xref]b[/xref]vanity, they [xref]c[/xref]entice by [xref]d[/xref]lusts of the flesh, with licentiousness, those who are barely [xref]e[/xref]escaping from them who [note]1[/note]live in error;</text>
        <note num="1">Or, behave, conduct themselves.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Jude 16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Pet. 1:18[/link]; [link]Rom. 1:21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 2:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Pet. 2:11[/link]; [link]4:2[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 2:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]2 Pet. 2:20[/link]; [link]1:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Promising [xref]a[/xref]freedom to them, while they themselves are [xref]b[/xref]slaves of [note]1[/note]corruption; for by whom anyone has been defeated, [note]2[/note]by this one he has been enslaved.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]1[sup]5[/sup][/link], point 3.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, to.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Pet. 2:16[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:1[/link], [link]13[/link]; [link]James 1:25[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]John 8:34[/link]; [link]Rom. 6:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>For if, having [xref]a[/xref]escaped the [xref]b[/xref]defilements of the [xref]c[/xref]world by the [xref]d[/xref]knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ but having again been [xref]e[/xref]entangled in these, they are defeated, the last state has become [xref]f[/xref]worse for them than the first.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 2:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 2:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 1:4[/link]; [link]1 John 2:15-17[/link]; [link]5:19[/link]; [link]James 4:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Pet. 1:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]2 Tim. 2:4[/link]; [link]Heb. 12:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]Matt. 12:45[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>For it would be better for them not to have known the [note]1[/note]way of righteousness than, knowing [i]it,[/i] to [xref]a[/xref]turn back from the [xref]b[/xref]holy commandment delivered to them.</text>
        <note num="1">To take the way of righteousness is to live a life that is right with both God and man; it is another aspect of the way of the truth ([link]v. 2[/link] and note 2) and the straight way ([link]v. 15[/link] and note 1). This is the way of living a life according to God's righteousness, a way that can receive His governmental judgment ([link]vv. 3[/link], [link]9[/link]) for His kingdom of righteousness ([link]Rom. 14:17[/link]; [link]Matt. 5:20[/link]). Peter in his Epistles stressed both the manner of life and the way of life because his writings are based on the governmental point of view of God's administration. To correspond with the government of Him who is holy and righteous, God's people need to have a manner of life that is holy, pure, good, and excellent ([link]1 Pet. 1:15[/link]; [link]3:16[/link], [link]2[/link]; [link]2:12[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 3:11[/link]), not licentious and vain ([link]v. 7[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:18[/link]), in His straight way of righteousness and truth.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Ezek. 18:24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 7:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>It has happened to them according to the true proverb: The [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]dog has turned [note]2[/note]to its own vomit, and the washed sow to wallowing in the mud.</text>
        <note num="1">Dogs and sows are unclean animals according to the ordinances of God's holiness ([link]Lev. 11:27[/link], [link]7[/link]; [link]Matt. 7:6[/link] and note 2). Dogs are accustomed to eating filthy things. They vomit what they eat and turn to their own vomit, becoming filthy inwardly. Sows wallow in the mud, making themselves filthy outwardly. The God-denying heretics eventually become like these dirty animals, making themselves filthy both inwardly and outwardly. (What serious judgment they deserve according to God's righteousness in His governmental administration!) Hence, they are very contagious, and the believers are prohibited from having contact with them ([link]2 John 9-11[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., upon.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Prov. 26:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>This second letter, beloved, I now write to you; in them [i]both[/i] I [xref]a[/xref]stir up your sincere mind with a [xref]b[/xref]reminder,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 1:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 1:12[/link]; [link]Jude 5[/link]; [link]Rom. 15:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>So that you would [xref]a[/xref]remember the [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]words spoken before by the holy [xref]c[/xref]prophets and the commandment of the Lord and Savior [i]preached[/i] by your [xref]d[/xref]apostles;</text>
        <note num="1">The words spoken by the prophets are the contents of the Old Testament, the Scriptures ([link]v. 16[/link]; [link]1:20[/link]), and the commandments preached by the apostles are the contents of the New Testament, the apostles' teaching ([link]Acts 2:42[/link]). Peter used both to confirm and strengthen his writings as an inoculation against the heretical teachings in the apostasy. In his first Epistle, concerning the full salvation of God, he referred to both the prophets and the apostles ([link]1 Pet. 1:9-12[/link]). Then in the second Epistle, concerning the shining of the divine truth, he again referred to both ([link]1:12-21[/link]). Here, for the third time, he did the same.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Jude 17[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 1:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 3:5[/link], [link]7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Luke 1:70[/link]; [link]Acts 3:21[/link]; [link]Heb. 1:1[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:10[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 1:19-21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Pet. 1:1[/link]; [link]Jude 17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Knowing this first, that in the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]last of days [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]mockers will come with mocking, going on according to their own [xref]c[/xref]lusts</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]1[sup]2[/sup] in 2 Tim. 3[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">They may be the false teachers mentioned in [link]2:1[/link]. Their mocking was a part of the apostasy.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Pet. 1:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Jude 18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Pet. 4:2[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 1:4[/link]; [link]James 1:14-15[/link]; [link]4:1[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And saying, [xref]a[/xref]Where is the [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]promise of His [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]coming? For since the [xref]d[/xref]fathers fell [xref]e[/xref]asleep, all things continue in this way from the [xref]f[/xref]beginning of [xref]g[/xref]creation.</text>
        <note num="1">The promise of the Lord's coming was given to the fathers by the holy prophets ([link]v. 2[/link]) in the Old Testament ([link]Psa. 72:6-17[/link]; [link]110:1-3[/link]; [link]118:26[/link]; [link]Dan. 7:13-14[/link]; [link]Zech. 14:3-9[/link]; [link]Mal. 4:1-3[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word means [i]presence.[/i]</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Jer. 17:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 3:9[/link], [link]13[/link]; [link]1:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 1:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Rom. 15:8[/link]; [link]9:5[/link]; [link]Acts 13:32[/link]; [link]26:6[/link]; [link]Heb. 1:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Acts 7:60[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]Mark 10:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="g">[link]Gen. 1:1[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>For [note]1[/note]this escapes them by their own choosing, that by the [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]word of God the [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]heavens [xref]c[/xref]were of old and the [note]3[/note]earth was [note]4[/note]compacted out of water and through [xref]d[/xref]water,</text>
        <note num="1">Or, this is hidden from them by their own willfulness. I.e., they are willfully ignorant of this; hence, this escapes their notice. The heretical mockers ignore willfully and deny purposely the word of God spoken by the prophets in the Scriptures. So Peter reminded the believers to remember the holy words spoken by both the Old Testament prophets and the New Testament apostles ([link]vv. 1-2[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">The promise concerning the Lord's coming ([link]v. 4[/link]) is the word of God. The mockers should not ignore that it was by the word of God that the heavens and the earth came into existence ([link]Heb. 11:3[/link]) and that it is by the same word that the heavens and the earth are being kept ([link]Heb. 1:3[/link]) for the day of judgment and destruction of ungodly men ([link]v. 7[/link]). So the mockers should be assured that by the word of God all the material universe, which includes them, will be judged by the coming of the Lord.</note>
        <note num="3">In the beginning, that is, of old, the heavens and the earth were created by God ([link]Gen. 1:1[/link]). By the word of God ([link]Psa. 33:6[/link]) first the heavens came into existence and then the earth ([link]Job 38:4-7[/link]).</note>
        <note num="4">Lit., standing together, standing with (in juxtaposition, side by side). First, in [link]Gen. 1:1[/link] the earth came into existence, and then, in [link]Gen. 1:9[/link], also by the word (the speaking) of God ([link]Psa. 33:9[/link]), the earth began to be compacted out of water and through water, that is, to stand together with water in juxtaposition, emerging partly from the water and remaining partly submerged under water.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 3:2[/link], [link]7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Zech. 12:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]John 1:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Psa. 24:2[/link]; [link]136:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Through [note]1[/note]which the [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]world [note]3[/note]then, being [note]4[/note][xref]b[/xref]flooded with water, [note]5[/note][xref]c[/xref]perished.</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to [i]water[/i] in [link]v. 5[/link]. The earth was compacted out of water and through water in an orderly condition. But through the same water it was judged and destroyed by the flood at Noah's time ([link]Gen. 7:17-24[/link]), indicating that all things did not continue in the same way from the beginning of creation.</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word means [i]order, a system,[/i] referring here to the world with its inhabitants. The earth in the preceding verse became the world in this verse &amp;#8212; not merely the earth, but the earth with its inhabitants in a system. This refers to the world in Noah's age, which was judged by God with the flood because of the sinfulness and ungodliness of that age ([link]Gen. 6:5-7[/link], [link]11-13[/link], [link]17[/link]). This book is concerned mainly with the divine government and all its judgments. The first judgment on the world was the one executed by the flood in Noah's day, which cleared up that ungodly world. This must have been Peter's thought while he was writing this verse, implying that this age of apostasy will also be judged on the day of the Lord's appearing, as in the day of Noah ([link]Matt. 24:37-39[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">[i]Then[/i] refers to the age of Noah.</note>
        <note num="4">Referring to the flood of Noah's time ([link]2:5[/link]), which caused the earth to be destroyed ([link]Gen. 6:13[/link], [link]17[/link]; [link]9:11[/link]). The earth then did not remain the same but experienced a cataclysm by being flooded with water, and was destroyed. Here Peter argued strongly with the heretical mockers. They said that "all things continue in this way from the beginning of creation" ([link]v. 4[/link]). But actually a cataclysm did come upon the earth because of the ungodliness of its inhabitants. This implies that the present world will not continue in the same way but will experience another cataclysm through the Lord's coming with His judgment upon the rebellious, including the false teachers and the heretical mockers in the apostasy.</note>
        <note num="5">I.e., was destroyed, demolished, laid waste ([link]Gen. 6:13[/link], [link]17[/link]). See note [link]1[sup]5[/sup], point 1, in ch. 2[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 2:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Gen. 7:18-19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 3:9[/link]; [link]Jude 11[/link]; cf. [link]1 Pet. 1:7[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>But the [xref]a[/xref]heavens and the earth [note]1[/note]now, by the [note]2[/note]same [xref]b[/xref]word, have been [xref]c[/xref]stored up for [note]3[/note][xref]d[/xref]fire, being [xref]e[/xref]kept unto the [xref]f[/xref]day of [note]4[/note]judgment and [note]5[/note][xref]g[/xref]destruction of [note]6[/note][xref]h[/xref]ungodly men.</text>
        <note num="1">In contrast to [i]then[/i] in [link]v. 6[/link] and referring to the present heavens and earth, which remain by the word of God ([link]Gen. 8:22[/link]) and will not be destroyed again by water, according to the covenant God made with Noah ([link]Gen. 9:11[/link]), but will be burned by fire on the day of judgment and destruction of ungodly men.</note>
        <note num="2">[i]The same word[/i] refers to the word of God mentioned in [link]v. 5[/link], which is included in the words of the prophets in the Old Testament. The false and heretical teachings in the apostasy are a deviation from the word of God spoken by the prophets in the Old Testament and the apostles in the New Testament. Hence, the antidote administered through Peter's inoculation against the poison of the apostate teachings was the holy word with the divine revelation, which Peter stressed repeatedly.</note>
        <note num="3">The fire that will burn up the heavens and the earth ([link]v. 10[/link]) at the end of the millennium when the judgment of the great white throne comes ([link]Rev. 20:11[/link]). God's initial judgment upon the universe was by water ([link]v. 6[/link]), but His consummate judgment will be by fire. Water only washes away the filthiness from the surface, but fire changes the nature of the entire substance. This is another indication that the heavens and the earth will not remain the same as they are but will be cleared up by fire, and that the ungodly false teachers ([link]2:1[/link]) and mockers ([link]v. 3[/link]) will be judged and destroyed under the divine government.</note>
        <note num="4">The judgment of the great white throne, which will take place after the millennium and will precede the new heaven and new earth ([link]Rev. 20:11-21:1[/link]). Through that judgment all the ungodly will be cast into the lake of fire for destruction (see note [link]3[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 2[/link]). Since it will be the final judgment upon men and the demons ([link]Rev. 20:13[/link] and note), it is of the greatest relevance to the government of God in the universe. See note [link]17[sup]2[/sup], par. 2, in 1 Pet. 1[/link].[br][br]Here Peter skipped over the millennium of one thousand years, going directly from the Lord's coming to the judgment of the great white throne. To him, as to the Lord, that one thousand years will be like one day ([link]v. 8[/link]), a short time. He was dealing here with God's governmental judgment. In God's economy the millennium is not for that purpose.</note>
        <note num="5">See note [link]1[sup]5[/sup], point 2, in ch. 2[/link].</note>
        <note num="6">Including the false teachers ([link]2:1[/link]) and the heretical mockers ([link]v. 3[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rev. 20:11[/link]; [link]21:1[/link]; [link]Heb. 1:10-12[/link]; [link]Matt. 24:35[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 3:2[/link], [link]5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 2:4[/link], [link]9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Pet. 3:10[/link], [link]12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]2 Pet. 2:4[/link], [link]9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]2 Pet. 2:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="g">[link]1 Thes. 5:3[/link]; [link]2 Thes. 1:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="h">[link]2 Pet. 2:5[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>But do not let this one thing [note]1[/note]escape you, beloved, that with the Lord [note]2[/note]one day is like a thousand years and a [xref]a[/xref]thousand years like one day.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, be hidden from you; i.e., escape your notice.</note>
        <note num="2">With the Lord God, who is eternal, the sense of time is compressed a thousandfold compared with man's sense of time. Hence, for the fulfillment of His word, especially the word of His promise, the crucial matter is not the time but the fact. Whatever He has promised will sooner or later become a fact. We should not be troubled by the sense of delay according to our reckoning of time.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 90:4[/link]; [link]Rev. 20:4[/link], [link]6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>The Lord [note]1[/note]does not [xref]a[/xref]delay regarding the [xref]b[/xref]promise, as [note]2[/note]some count [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]delay, but is [note]4[/note][xref]d[/xref]long-suffering toward you, not intending that any [note]5[/note][xref]e[/xref]perish but that [note]6[/note][xref]f[/xref]all advance to [note]7[/note][xref]g[/xref]repentance.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, is not tardy.</note>
        <note num="2">These must be the mockers ([link]v. 3[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">Or, tardiness.</note>
        <note num="4">The Lord's heart is set not on the time of the fulfillment of His promise but on His people, whom He possesses peculiarly as a treasure ([link]1 Pet. 2:9[/link]; [link]Titus 2:14[/link] and note 3). His desire is that none of us, His precious redeemed ones, would be punished by His governmental judgment but would have a prolonged season to repent that we may be spared from His punishment.</note>
        <note num="5">Or, be destroyed. See note [link]1[sup]5[/sup], point 1, in ch. 2[/link]. Since [i]you[/i] in this verse refers to the believers in Christ, [i]perish[/i] refers not to the eternal perdition of the unbelievers but to the punishment of God's governmental disciplining of the believers ([link]1 Pet. 4:17-18[/link] and note [link]18[sup]2[/sup][/link]; [link]1 Thes. 5:3[/link], [link]8[/link] and note 3).</note>
        <note num="6">Referring to the believers.</note>
        <note num="7">Repentance unto salvation ([link]v. 15[/link]), which is to repent for not being watchful for the day of the Lord's coming ([link]v. 10[/link]) and not living a life in a holy manner and godliness ([link]v. 11[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Hab. 2:3[/link]; [link]Heb. 10:37[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 3:4[/link], [link]13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Ezek. 12:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Pet. 3:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]2 Pet. 3:6[/link]; [link]Jude 5[/link], [link]11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">cf. [link]1 Tim. 2:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="g">[link]Rev. 2:5[/link], [link]16[/link], [link]22[/link]; [link]3:3[/link], [link]19[/link]; cf. [link]Ezek. 18:23[/link], [link]32[/link]; [link]33:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>But the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]day of the Lord will [note]2[/note]come as a [xref]b[/xref]thief, in [note]3[/note]which the [note]4[/note][xref]c[/xref]heavens will pass away with a [note]5[/note]roar, and the [note]6[/note]elements, burning with intense heat, will be [note]7[/note][xref]d[/xref]dissolved, and the [xref]e[/xref]earth and the [note]8[/note]works in it will be [note]7[/note]burned up.</text>
        <note num="1">Mainly in the sense of judgment ([link]1 Thes. 5:2[/link] and note 2) for God's government.</note>
        <note num="2">The day of the Lord for His judgment ([link]1 Thes. 5:3-4[/link]) will come before the millennium ([link]Rev. 18:1[/link]; [link]19:11[/link]; [link]20:4-6[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">Referring to the day of the Lord.</note>
        <note num="4">This will take place after the millennium ([link]Rev. 20:7[/link], [link]11[/link]). This indicates again that Peter skipped over the one thousand years of the millennium (see note [link]7[sup]4[/sup][/link]).</note>
        <note num="5">I.e., a rushing sound or noise. It may be a proclamation of a great change in the universe from the old to the new.</note>
        <note num="6">The physical elements that compose the heavens.</note>
        <note num="7">Compare [i]dissolved[/i] and [i]burned up[/i] with [i]roll them up[/i] and [i]changed[/i] in [link]Heb. 1:12[/link], [i]fled away[/i] and [i]no place was found for them[/i] in [link]Rev. 20:11[/link], and [i]passed away[/i] in [link]Rev. 21:1[/link]. The burning with intense heat to dissolve the heavens and the earth is the procedure God will use to roll up the heavens and the earth and put them away that they may be changed from the old to the new ([link]v. 13[/link]; [link]Rev. 21:1[/link]). This will be God's final and consummate dealing with His creation in His government. In God's final dealing all the material things will pass away, but His eternal word will abide forever ([link]Matt. 24:35[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:25[/link]). The word of His prophecy will remain and be fulfilled at His appointed time for the accomplishing of His eternal will, regardless of the change that will occur in the physical universe.</note>
        <note num="8">This may refer to both God's works of nature and man's works of art.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 1:8[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 1:14[/link]; [link]Phil. 1:6[/link], [link]10[/link]; [link]2:16[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 1:12[/link], [link]18[/link]; [link]4:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Matt. 24:43[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 5:2[/link]; [link]Rev. 3:3[/link]; [link]16:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Psa. 102:26[/link]; [link]Isa. 34:4[/link]; [link]51:6[/link]; [link]Matt. 24:35[/link]; [link]Heb. 1:11[/link]; [link]Rev. 6:14[/link]; [link]20:11[/link]; [link]21:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">cf. [link]Micah 1:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">cf. [link]Nahum 1:5[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Since [note]1[/note]all these things [note]2[/note]are to be thus dissolved, what kind of persons ought you to be [note]3[/note]in [xref]a[/xref]holy manner of life and [xref]b[/xref]godliness,</text>
        <note num="1">All things, both in the heavens and on the earth, have been defiled by the rebellion of Satan and the fall of man. Although all things, whether on the earth or in the heavens, have been reconciled to God through Christ by His blood ([link]Col. 1:20[/link] and note 4) &amp;#8212; even the heavenly things having been purified by the blood of Christ ([link]Heb. 9:23[/link] and note 1) &amp;#8212; they will still need to be cleared up by being burned up in God's governmental dealing, that they may become new in nature and appearance in God's new universe ([link]v. 13[/link]). Thus, what kind of persons ought we, the children of the holy God, to be in holy manner of life and godliness; that is, what kind of transformation ought we to experience in order to live a life in the manner of God's holy nature and godliness to express Him, that we may be qualified to match His holy government?</note>
        <note num="2">Some MSS read, therefore are to be dissolved.</note>
        <note num="3">The divine power has provided us with all things that are needed to live a life in a holy manner and godliness ([link]1:3[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Pet. 1:15[/link]; [link]Heb. 12:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 2:2[/link]; [link]4:7-8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>[note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Expecting and hastening the [note]2[/note]coming of the [note]3[/note]day of God, on account of [note]4[/note]which the heavens, being on [xref]b[/xref]fire, will be dissolved, and the elements, burning with intense heat, are to be melted away?</text>
        <note num="1">While we live a transformed life in a holy and godly manner, we are expecting, awaiting, and hastening the coming of the day of God.</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word means [i]presence.[/i]</note>
        <note num="3">The day of God is the day of the Lord ([link]v. 10[/link]), and to the children of Israel in the Old Testament, the day of the Lord is the day of Jehovah ([link]Isa. 2:12[/link]; [link]Joel 1:15[/link]; [link]2:11[/link], [link]31[/link]; [link]3:14[/link]; [link]Amos 5:18[/link], [link]20[/link]; [link]Obad. 15[/link]; [link]Zeph. 1:7[/link], [link]14[/link], [link]18[/link]; [link]2:2-3[/link]; [link]Zech. 14:1[/link]; [link]Mal. 4:1[/link], [link]5[/link]). In such expressions, [i]day[/i] is used mainly in the sense of judgment for governmental dealing. Before the Lord comes, it is "man's day," in which man judges until the Lord comes ([link]1 Cor. 4:3-5[/link]). Then, it will be "the day of the Lord," which will begin with the Lord's parousia (presence &amp;#8212; [link]Matt. 24:3[/link] and note 3) with all its judgments and will end with the judgment upon men and the demons at the great white throne ([link]Rev. 20:11-15[/link] and notes). The Lord's parousia (presence) will begin when the overcoming saints are raptured to the throne of God in the heavens before the great tribulation of three and a half years ([link]Rev. 12:5-6[/link]; [link]14:1[/link]). Then, all the supernatural calamities of the sixth seal and the first four trumpets will be meted out to smite the earth with the things on it and the heavens with their heavenly bodies ([link]Rev. 6:12-17[/link]; [link]8:7-12[/link]). This will be the beginning of the great tribulation. The great tribulation, which will consist mainly of the woes of the last three trumpets, including the plagues of the seven bowls, will last for three and a half years ([link]Matt. 24:21-22[/link], [link]29[/link]; [link]Rev. 8:13-9:21[/link]; [link]11:14[/link]; [link]15:5-16:21[/link]). That will be a time of trial for the inhabitants of the whole earth ([link]Rev. 3:10[/link]), including the Jews ([link]Isa. 2:12[/link]; [link]Zech. 14:1-2[/link]; [link]Mal. 4:1[/link], [link]5[/link]; [link]Joel 1:15-20[/link]; [link]2:1[/link], [link]11[/link], [link]31[/link]) and the believers in Christ who are left in the tribulation ([link]Rev. 12:17[/link]). At the end of the great tribulation, Christ's parousia (presence), with the overcomers, will come to the air ([link]Rev. 10:1[/link]), and the dead saints will be resurrected and raptured together with the majority of the living believers, who will have passed through the great tribulation, to meet with the Lord in the air ([link]1 Cor. 15:52[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 4:16-17[/link]; [link]Rev. 14:14-16[/link]). After this, all the believers will be judged by the Lord at His judgment seat in the air ([link]2 Cor. 5:10[/link]). Then the Lord will have His wedding feast with the overcoming saints ([link]Rev. 19:7-8[/link]). Immediately after this, the Lord with His bride, composed of the overcoming saints as His army, will come to the earth ([link]Zech. 14:4-5[/link]; [link]Jude 14[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 3:13[/link]) to fight and defeat Antichrist and his army; they will seize Antichrist and his false prophet and cast them alive into the lake of fire ([link]Rev. 19:11-21[/link]). At approximately that time, Babylon the Great will be destroyed ([link]Rev. 17:1-19:3[/link]). At the same time, the Lord will deliver, gather, and restore the children of Israel ([link]Zech. 12:2-14[/link]; [link]Rom. 11:26[/link]; [link]Matt. 24:31[/link]; [link]Acts 1:6[/link]). Following this, Satan will be bound and cast into the abyss, the bottomless pit ([link]Rev. 20:1-3[/link]). Then the Lord will judge the nations (the living &amp;#8212; [link]Matt. 25:31-46[/link]; [link]Joel 3:2[/link]). After this, the millennial kingdom will come ([link]Rev. 20:4-6[/link]). After the thousand years, Satan will be loosed from the abyss and will instigate certain of the nations, Gog and Magog in the north of the eastern hemisphere, to carry out the last rebellion against God. They will be subdued and burned, and the deceiving devil will be cast into the lake of fire ([link]Rev. 20:7-10[/link]). Following this, the heavens and the earth will be fully cleared up by being burned up ([link]vv. 7[/link], [link]10[/link]). Then will come the final judgment upon men (the dead) and the demons, and probably also upon the fallen angels ([link]2:4[/link] and note 4), at the great white throne ([link]Rev. 20:11-15[/link]). That will be God's consummate dealing with His old creation in His universal government and will be in addition to so many judgments and dealings executed within the day of the Lord to clear up the old universe. Then a new universe will begin with the new heaven and new earth for eternity ([link]Rev. 21:1[/link]), in which there will be no more judgment related to God's governmental dealing, for no unrighteousness will dwell there. Therefore, not counting the one thousand years, the day of the Lord will be very short, probably not more than seven years. This will be the main part of the last week (seven years) of the seventy weeks in [link]Dan. 9:24-27[/link]. It is unscriptural to consider the day of God and the day of the Lord two different days: the day of the Lord ends with the millennial kingdom, and the day of God begins with the burning of the heavens and the earth, followed by the judgment of the great white throne. Actually, since the judgment of the great white throne will be executed by the Lord Jesus ([link]Acts 10:42[/link]; [link]17:31[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 4:1[/link]), it too will be in the day of the Lord. God does not judge anyone; He has given all judgment to the Lord ([link]John 5:22[/link]).</note>
        <note num="4">Referring to the coming of the day of God, which is for executing judgment upon every part of the old creation to clear it up. On account of the coming of such a day, the heavens will no longer be able to stand and remain as they have been, but will be dissolved, their elements melting away in the intense heat of the burning fire.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 8:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 3:7[/link], [link]10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>But according to His [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]promise we are expecting [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]new heavens and a new earth, in which [note]3[/note]righteousness [note]4[/note]dwells.</text>
        <note num="1">After all the material things are dissolved, God's promise as His everlasting word will still exist for His redeemed people to trust in and stand upon with the expectation of a new universe. We should set our hope not on the visible elements but on what the word of God promises for our destiny, that is, the new heavens and new earth, which have not yet come into our view.</note>
        <note num="2">The new heavens and new earth are the old heavens and old earth renewed and transformed through the burning of God's judging fire, just as the new man is our old man renewed and transformed ([link]Col. 3:9-10[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 3:18[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">Righteousness is the main factor based on which God's governmental judgment is meted out to all creatures in His old creation. Hence, in these two books concerning God's government, this matter is stressed repeatedly ([link]1 Pet. 2:23-24[/link]; [link]3:12[/link], [link]14[/link]; [link]4:18[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 1:1[/link]; [link]2:5[/link], [link]7-8[/link], [link]21[/link]; [link]3:13[/link]). The main matter seen in John's writings is the love of God expressed in His life; in Paul's writings, the grace of God distributed in His economy; and in Peter's writings, the righteousness of God maintained in His government. God's life, economy, and government are the basic structures of the ministry of the three apostles. Life is of love, economy is through grace, and government is based on righteousness. This righteousness will dwell in the new heavens and new earth, saturating God's new universe prevailingly and thus maintaining it absolutely under God's righteous order, so that no further judgment will ever be needed.</note>
        <note num="4">Or, makes its home.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 3:4[/link], [link]9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Isa. 65:17[/link]; [link]66:22[/link]; [link]Rev. 21:1[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Therefore, [xref]a[/xref]beloved, since you expect these things, be diligent to be [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]found by Him in [xref]c[/xref]peace [note]2[/note]without spot and [xref]d[/xref]without blemish;</text>
        <note num="1">To be found by the Lord in peace is to be found righteous, right, having no problem in His eyes with either God or man at His coming. Since this book stresses righteousness for God's governmental dealing (see note [link]13[sup]3[/sup][/link]), it charges the believers, who are walking in the ways of righteousness (cf. [link]2:21[/link]), to pursue a living that is in peace, that they may be prepared for the Lord's coming with judgment.</note>
        <note num="2">The heretics, who forsake the straight way and follow the way of unrighteousness ([link]2:15[/link]), are spots and blemishes among the believers (see note [link]13[sup]3[/sup] in ch. 2[/link]); but the believers, who are pursuing to live in peace in God's government, should be without spot and without blemish, like the Lord, who is the Lamb without blemish and without spot ([link]1 Pet. 1:19[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 3:17[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 15:58[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Phil. 3:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Pet. 3:11[/link]; [link]5:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Eph. 5:27[/link]; [link]Phil. 2:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And [note]1[/note]count the [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]long-suffering of our Lord [i]to be[/i] [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]salvation, even as [note]4[/note]also our beloved brother [xref]c[/xref]Paul, according to the [xref]d[/xref]wisdom given to him, wrote to you,</text>
        <note num="1">The mockers count the Lord's long-suffering toward the believers as delay, tardiness, or slackness ([link]v. 9[/link]). This is their twisting of the Lord's word spoken by the prophets in the Scriptures and by the apostles in their teachings ([link]v. 16[/link]). Hence, Peter charged the believers to count the Lord's long-suffering as salvation instead of delay, and not to twist the prophets' prophecies or the apostles' teachings, including his own and also Paul's, that they might not be judged unto destruction as the heretics will be at the Lord's coming. It is by doing this and being diligent to be found by the Lord in peace, without spot and without blemish ([link]v. 14[/link]), that the believers prepare themselves for the Lord's coming with judgment.</note>
        <note num="2">The Lord's long-suffering in the delay regarding His promise should be counted as a prolonged opportunity for the believers to repent unto salvation ([link]v. 9[/link] and note 4).</note>
        <note num="3">Not salvation in its initial stage but salvation in its completing stage (see note [link]5[sup]5[/sup] in 1 Pet. 1[/link]). The Lord's intention in delaying His coming is to prevent many of His elect from missing the topmost portion of His full salvation.</note>
        <note num="4">It was not only Peter, as one of the apostles ([link]v. 2[/link]), who taught, with the confirmation of the prophets' prophecy ([link]v. 2[/link]), that the Lord's long-suffering should be counted as salvation instead of delay. Paul, as another of the apostles, taught the same thing in his writings, based on the prophetic word of the Old Testament. Peter referred to this fact to strengthen his writing.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 3:9[/link]; [link]Rom. 2:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Pet. 1:5[/link], [link]9[/link]; [link]2:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Acts 15:2[/link], [link]12[/link], [link]25[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Cor. 2:6-8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>As also in [note]1[/note]all [i]his[/i] letters, speaking in them concerning [note]2[/note]these things, in which some things are [xref]a[/xref]hard to understand, which the unlearned and [xref]b[/xref]unstable [note]3[/note]twist, as also the [note]2[/note]rest of the [xref]c[/xref]Scriptures, to their own [note]4[/note]destruction.</text>
        <note num="1">Since Peter's antidote to inoculate against the heretical teachings of the apostasy is the holy word spoken by the Old Testament prophets and the New Testament apostles, he could not omit the writings of the apostle Paul, which are the greatest part of the apostles' teaching for the constituting of the New Testament. In both his Epistles, which also are a part of the apostles' teaching and are constituents of the New Testament, Peter referred repeatedly to the Old Testament prophets and the New Testament apostles ([link]1 Pet. 1:10-12[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 1:12-21[/link]; [link]3:2[/link]). Here he referred to the apostle Paul in the strongest way, saying that Paul in all his writings spoke some things that are hard to understand, concerning the things of which Peter spoke in his writing, and that to twist Paul's writings is equivalent to twisting the Scriptures as the heretics do, which results in destruction, that is, in being judged by the Lord at His coming back. This is a strong warning to both the believers and the heretics in the apostasy.</note>
        <note num="2">In his two Epistles, comprising only eight chapters, Peter covered the entire economy of God, from eternity past before the foundation of the world ([link]1 Pet. 1:2[/link], [link]20[/link]) to the new heavens and new earth in eternity future ([link]2 Pet. 3:13[/link]). He unveiled the crucial things related to God's economy, concerning which things the prophets prophesied and the apostles preached ([link]1 Pet. 1:10-12[/link]), from four sides:[br][br](1) From the side of the Triune God:[br][br]God the Father chose a people in eternity according to His foreknowledge ([link]1 Pet. 1:1-2[/link]; [link]2:9[/link]) and called them into His glory ([link]1 Pet. 5:10[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 1:3[/link]). Christ, foreknown by God before the foundation of the world but manifested in the last times ([link]1 Pet. 1:20[/link]), has redeemed and saved God's chosen people ([link]1 Pet. 1:18-19[/link], [link]2[/link]) by His vicarious death ([link]1 Pet. 2:24[/link]; [link]3:18[/link]) through His resurrection in life and ascension in power ([link]1 Pet. 1:3[/link]; [link]3:21-22[/link]). The Spirit, sent from heaven, has sanctified and purified those whom Christ has redeemed ([link]1 Pet. 1:2[/link], [link]12[/link], [link]22[/link]; [link]4:14[/link]). (The angels long to look into these things &amp;#8212; [link]1 Pet. 1:12[/link].) The Triune God's divine power has provided the redeemed ones with all things that relate to life and godliness ([link]1:3-4[/link]) to guard them unto full salvation ([link]1 Pet. 1:5[/link]). God also disciplines them ([link]1 Pet. 5:6[/link]) by some of His varied governmental judgments ([link]1 Pet. 1:17[/link]; [link]2:23[/link]; [link]4:5-6[/link], [link]17[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 2:3-4[/link], [link]9[/link]; [link]3:7[/link]), and He will perfect, establish, strengthen, and ground them by His all grace ([link]1 Pet. 5:10[/link]). The Lord is long-suffering toward them that they all may have opportunity to repent unto salvation ([link]vv. 9[/link], [link]15[/link]). Then, Christ will appear in glory with His full salvation for His lovers ([link]1 Pet. 1:5[/link], [link]7-9[/link], [link]13[/link]; [link]4:13[/link]; [link]5:4[/link]).[br][br](2) From the side of the believers:[br][br]The believers, as God's possession, were chosen by God ([link]1 Pet. 1:1-2[/link]; [link]2:9[/link]), called by His glory and virtue ([link]1 Pet. 2:9[/link]; [link]3:9[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 1:3[/link], [link]10[/link]), redeemed by Christ ([link]1 Pet. 1:18-19[/link]), regenerated by God through His living word ([link]1 Pet. 1:3[/link], [link]23[/link]), and saved through the resurrection of Christ ([link]1 Pet. 3:21[/link]). They now are being guarded by the power of God ([link]1 Pet. 1:5[/link]), are being purified to love one another ([link]1 Pet. 1:22[/link]), are growing by feeding on the milk of the word ([link]1 Pet. 2:2[/link]), are developing in life the spiritual virtues ([link]2 Pet. 1:5-8[/link]), and are being transformed and built up into a spiritual house, a holy priesthood to serve God ([link]1 Pet. 2:4-5[/link], [link]9[/link]). They are God's chosen race, royal priesthood, holy nation, and peculiar people for His private possession to express His virtues ([link]1 Pet. 2:9[/link]). They are being disciplined by His governmental judgment ([link]1 Pet. 1:17[/link]; [link]2:19-21[/link]; [link]3:9[/link], [link]14[/link], [link]17[/link]; [link]4:6[/link], [link]12-19[/link]; [link]5:6[/link], [link]9[/link]), are living a holy life in an excellent manner and in godliness to glorify Him ([link]1 Pet. 1:15[/link]; [link]2:12[/link]; [link]3:1-2[/link]), are ministering as good stewards of His varied grace for His glorification through Christ ([link]1 Pet. 4:10-11[/link]) (under the elders' exemplary shepherding &amp;#8212; [link]1 Pet. 5:1-4[/link]), and are expecting and hastening the coming of the Lord ([link]1 Pet. 1:13[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 3:12[/link]) in order to be richly supplied with an entrance into the eternal kingdom of the Lord ([link]1:11[/link]). Further, they are expecting the new heavens and new earth, in which righteousness dwells, in eternity ([link]v. 13[/link]), and they are growing continually in the grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ ([link]v. 18[/link]).[br][br](3) From the side of Satan:[br][br]Satan is the believers' adversary, the devil, who as a roaring lion is walking about, seeking someone to devour ([link]1 Pet. 5:8[/link]).[br][br](4) From the side of the universe:[br][br]The fallen angels were condemned and are awaiting eternal judgment ([link]2:4[/link]); the ancient ungodly world was destroyed by a flood ([link]2:5[/link]; [link]3:6[/link]); the ungodly cities were reduced to ashes ([link]2:6[/link]); the false teachers and heretical mockers in the apostasy and mankind in his evil living will all be judged unto destruction ([link]2:1[/link], [link]3[/link], [link]9-10[/link], [link]12[/link]; [link]3:3-4[/link], [link]7[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 4:5[/link]); the heavens and the earth will be burned up ([link]vv. 7[/link], [link]10-11[/link]); and all the dead men and the demons will be judged ([link]1 Pet. 4:5[/link]). Then the new heavens and new earth will come as a new universe, in which God's righteousness will dwell for eternity ([link]v. 13[/link]).[br][br]Paul in his writings also spoke concerning "these things" (except for the new heavens and new earth). Hence, Peter referred to Paul's writings to strengthen his own writings, especially concerning God's governmental and disciplinary judgment upon the believers. Paul strongly and repeatedly emphasized this matter in his writings ([link]1 Cor. 11:30-32[/link]; [link]Heb. 12:5-11[/link]; [link]2:3[/link]; [link]4:1[/link]; [link]6:8[/link]; [link]10:27-31[/link], [link]39[/link]; [link]12:29[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 3:13-15[/link]; [link]4:4-5[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 5:10[/link]; [link]Rom. 14:10[/link]). This must be the reason Peter highly commended Paul's writings.[br][br]What beauty and excellency are in this commendation! Although the Corinthians attempted to divide Peter and Paul according to their divisive preferences ([link]1 Cor. 1:11-12[/link]), Peter commended Paul, saying that Paul, like him, taught "these things" and that Paul's writings should not be twisted but should be regarded like "the rest of the Scriptures" and should receive the same respect as the Old Testament. For Peter to make such a commendation was not a small thing, for it was he who was rebuked to his face by Paul regarding the New Testament faith ([link]Gal. 2:11-21[/link]). This indicates that Peter was bold in admitting that the early apostles, such as John, Paul, and himself, although their style, terminology, utterance, certain aspects of their views, and the way they presented their teachings differed, participated in the same, unique ministry, the ministry of the New Testament ([link]2 Cor. 3:8-9[/link]; [link]4:1[/link]). Such a ministry ministers to people, as its focus, the all-inclusive Christ as the embodiment of the Triune God, who, after passing through the process of incarnation, human living, crucifixion, resurrection, and ascension, dispenses Himself through the redemption of Christ and by the operation of the Holy Spirit into His redeemed people as their unique portion of life and as their life supply and everything, for the building up of the church as the Body of Christ, which will consummate in the full expression, the fullness, of the Triune God, according to the eternal purpose of the Father.</note>
        <note num="3">This indicates that the mockers ([link]v. 3[/link]) and their followers must have twisted, not merely ignored ([link]v. 5[/link]), the Scriptures and the apostles' teaching.</note>
        <note num="4">See note [link]1[sup]5[/sup], point 2, in ch. 2[/link]. According to the context, [i]destruction[/i] here refers not to eternal perdition but to the punishment of the divine governmental discipline. See notes [link]18[sup]2[/sup] in 1 Pet. 4[/link] and [link book="2 Pet." chapter="3"]9[sup]5[/sup][/link] in this chapter.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 5:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 2:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 1:20[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 3:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>You therefore, beloved, since you know [i]these things[/i] beforehand, [note]1[/note]be on your guard lest being [note]2[/note]carried away by the error of the [note]3[/note]lawless, you [note]4[/note][xref]a[/xref]fall from your own [xref]b[/xref]steadfastness.</text>
        <note num="1">Be on your guard because of the apostasy, the heretical teachings, which may carry you away to destruction by twisting the apostles' writings or the Scriptures ([link]v. 16[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">The same word as that used in [link]Gal. 2:13[/link] concerning Peter, Barnabas, and other Jewish believers.</note>
        <note num="3">See note [link]7[sup]2[/sup] in ch. 2[/link]. [i]The lawless[/i] must refer to the false teachers and mockers ([link]2:1[/link]; [link]3:3[/link]), who were the early heretics.</note>
        <note num="4">This is to become unstable ([link]v. 16[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gal. 5:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 1:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>But [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]grow in the [note]2[/note]grace and [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ. [note]4[/note]To Him be the [xref]c[/xref]glory both now and unto the day of eternity. Amen.</text>
        <note num="1">This indicates that what Peter wrote in his two Epistles is a matter of life. To grow in grace is to grow by the bountiful supply of eternal life provided by the divine power ([link]1:3-4[/link]), and to grow in the knowledge of the Lord is to grow by the realization of what Christ is. This is to grow by the enjoyment of grace and the realization of truth ([link]John 1:14[/link] and note 6, [link book="John" chapter="1"]17[/link] and note 1).</note>
        <note num="2">See notes [link]14[sup]6[/sup] in John 1[/link], [link]10[sup]1[/sup] in 1 Cor. 15[/link], and [link]14[sup]1[/sup] in 2 Cor. 13[/link].</note>
        <note num="3">The realization of the knowledge of our Lord equals truth, the reality of all that He is, as in [link]John 1:14[/link], [link]17[/link] (see note [link book="John" chapter="1"]17[sup]1[/sup][/link] there). Peter charged the believers to grow not only in grace but also in this truth.</note>
        <note num="4">Referring to our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ. Since such a praise is one that is rendered to our God ([link]Rom. 11:36[/link]; [link]16:27[/link]), it indicates that our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ is God.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Pet. 2:2[/link]; [link]Eph. 4:15[/link]; [link]Col. 2:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 1:2[/link], [link]3[/link], [link]5[/link], [link]8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Tim. 4:18[/link]; [link]Rev. 1:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    </chapters>
</book>
