<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book name="2 Timothy" description="THE SECOND EPISTLE OF PAUL TO TIMOTHY" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="..\bible.xsd">
    <info title="Author">The apostle Paul ([link]1:1[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Time of Writing">Approximately A.D. 67, during Paul's second imprisonment, near the time of his martyrdom ([link]4:6[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Place of Writing">A Roman prison ([link]1:16-17[/link]).</info>
    <subject>Inoculation against the Decline of the Church</subject>
    <outlines>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="1" ref="1:1-2">Introduction</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="2" ref="1:3-14">The Divine Provisions for the Inoculation &amp;#8212; A Pure Conscience, Unfeigned Faith, the Divine Gift, a Strong Spirit, Eternal Grace, Incorruptible Life, the Healthy Word, and the Indwelling Spirit</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="3" ref="1:15-18">The Basic Factor of the Decline &amp;#8212; Forsaking the Apostle and His Ministry</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="4" ref="2:1-15">The Inoculator &amp;#8212; A Teacher, a Soldier, a Contender, a Farmer, and a Workman</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="5" ref="2:16-26">The Spreading of the Decline &amp;#8212; Like That of Gangrene</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="6" ref="3:1-13">The Worsening of the Decline &amp;#8212; Becoming Grievous Times of Deceiving</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="7" ref="3:14-17">The Antidote of the Inoculation &amp;#8212; The Divine Word</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="8" ref="4:1-8">The Incentive to the Inoculator &amp;#8212; The Coming Reward</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="9" ref="4:9-18">The Issue of the Decline &amp;#8212; Loving the Present Age and Doing Many Evils</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="10" ref="4:19-22">Conclusion</outline>
    </outlines>
    <chapters>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus through the [xref]a[/xref]will of God [xref]b[/xref]according to the [note]1[/note][xref]c[/xref]promise of [xref]d[/xref]life, which is in Christ Jesus,</text>
        <note num="1">This book was written at a time when the churches established through the apostle's ministry in the Gentile world were in a trend of degradation and the apostle himself was confined in a remote prison. Many had turned away from him and forsaken him ([link]v. 15[/link]; [link]4:16[/link]), including even some of his co-workers ([link]4:10[/link]). It was a discouraging and disappointing scene, especially to his young fellow worker and spiritual child, Timothy. Because of this, in the opening of this encouraging, strengthening, and establishing Epistle, he confirmed to Timothy that he was an apostle of Christ not only through the will of God but also according to the promise of life, which is in Christ. This implies that though the churches may become degraded and many of the saints may backslide in unfaithfulness, the eternal life, the divine life, the uncreated life of God, promised by God in His holy writings and given to the apostle and all the believers, remains forever the same. With and upon this unchanging life the firm foundation of God was laid and stands unshaken through all the tide of degradation ([link]2:19[/link]). By such a life those who seek the Lord out of a pure heart are able to stand the test of the church's decline. This life, which the apostle in 1 Timothy charged Timothy and others to lay hold on ([link]1 Tim. 6:12[/link], [link]19[/link]), must have been an encouragement and strengthening to the apostle in perilous times.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 1:1[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 1:1[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:1[/link]; [link]Col. 1:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. [link]1 Tim. 1:1[/link]; [link]Titus 1:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Titus 1:2[/link]; [link]Rom. 1:2[/link]; [link]Eph. 3:6[/link]; [link]Heb. 9:15[/link]; [link]Acts 13:23[/link]; [link]Gal. 3:29[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Tim. 1:10[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 1:16[/link]; [link]6:12[/link], [link]19[/link]; [link]Titus 1:2[/link]; [link]3:7[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>To Timothy, beloved [xref]a[/xref]child: Grace, [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]mercy, peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.</text>
        <note num="1">Only in 1 and 2 Timothy, among all his Epistles, did the apostle include God's mercy in the opening greeting. God's mercy reaches farther than His grace. In the degraded situation of the churches, God's mercy is needed. This mercy brings in God's rich grace, which is sufficient to deal with any degradation.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 1:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 1:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>I thank God, whom I [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]serve [note]2[/note]from [i]my[/i] [xref]b[/xref]forefathers in a [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]pure conscience, while unceasingly I have remembrance concerning you in my petitions [xref]d[/xref]night and day,</text>
        <note num="1">To serve God in worship to Him ([link]Acts 24:14[/link]; [link]Phil. 3:3[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Following in the footsteps of his forefathers to serve God in a pure conscience.</note>
        <note num="3">See note [link]9[sup]2[/sup] in 1 Tim. 3[/link]. In a time of degradation a pure conscience is needed for one to serve God.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 24:14[/link]; [link]Rom. 1:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Gal. 1:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Tim. 3:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Thes. 3:10[/link]; [link]Acts 26:7[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Longing to see you, remembering your [xref]b[/xref]tears, that I may be [xref]c[/xref]filled with joy;</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Phil. 1:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Luke 19:41[/link]; [link]John 11:35[/link]; [link]Heb. 5:7[/link]; [link]Acts 20:19[/link], [link]37[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 2:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Phil. 2:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Having been reminded of the [xref]a[/xref]unfeigned faith in you, which [note]1[/note]dwelt first in your grandmother Lois and your [xref]b[/xref]mother Eunice, and I am persuaded [i]dwells[/i] also in you.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., indwelt.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 1:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 16:1[/link]; cf. [link]2 Tim. 3:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>For which cause I remind you to [note]1[/note]fan into flame the [xref]a[/xref]gift of God, which is in you through the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]laying on of my hands.</text>
        <note num="1">This was written to encourage and strengthen Timothy in his ministry for the Lord, which might have been enfeebled by Paul's imprisonment and the degraded situation of the churches.</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]14[sup]4[/sup] in 1 Tim. 4[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 4:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 4:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>For God has not given us a [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]spirit of [xref]b[/xref]cowardice, but [note]2[/note]of [xref]c[/xref]power and of [xref]d[/xref]love and of [xref]e[/xref]sobermindedness.</text>
        <note num="1">The spirit here denotes our human spirit, regenerated and indwelt by the Holy Spirit ([link]John 3:6[/link]; [link]Rom. 8:16[/link]). To fan into flame the gift of God ([link]v. 6[/link]) is related to our regenerated spirit.</note>
        <note num="2">[i]Of power[/i] refers to our will, [i]of[/i] love to our emotion, and [i]of[/i] sobermindedness to our mind. This indicates that having a strong will, a loving emotion, and a sober mind has very much to do with having a strong spirit for the exercise of the gift of God that is in us.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 4:22[/link]; [link]Rom. 8:15[/link], [link]16[/link]; [link]12:11[/link]; [link]John 3:6[/link]; [link]4:24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]John 14:27[/link]; [link]Rev. 21:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Eph. 3:16[/link]; [link]6:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Gal. 5:13-14[/link]; [link]Col. 3:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]1 Tim. 3:2[/link]; [link]Titus 1:8[/link]; [link]2:2[/link], [link]6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Therefore do [note]2[/note]not be [xref]a[/xref]ashamed of the [xref]b[/xref]testimony of our Lord nor of me [xref]c[/xref]His prisoner; but [xref]d[/xref]suffer evil with the [note]3[/note][xref]e[/xref]gospel [note]4[/note]according to the [xref]f[/xref]power of God;</text>
        <note num="1">This was the reason Paul charged Timothy in [link]vv. 6-7[/link] to fan into flame by a strong spirit the gift of God that was in him.</note>
        <note num="2">Not to be ashamed of the testimony of our Lord is to stand against the downward current in the declining churches.</note>
        <note num="3">Since the gospel, personified here (cf. note [link]2[sup]2[/sup] in Rev. 6[/link]), was suffering persecution, Timothy needed to suffer evil along with the gospel.</note>
        <note num="4">Our suffering of persecution along with the gospel must be to the extent that the power of God, not our natural strength, can endure.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 1:12[/link], [link]16[/link]; [link]Mark 8:38[/link]; [link]Rom. 1:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Cor. 1:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Philem. 1[/link], [link]9[/link]; [link]Eph. 3:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Tim. 2:3[/link], [link]9[/link]; [link]4:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Mark 8:35[/link]; [link]10:29[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]Eph. 3:7[/link], [link]20[/link]; [link]Col. 1:29[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Who has saved us and [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]called us with a holy calling, not according to our [xref]b[/xref]works but according to His own [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]purpose and [xref]d[/xref]grace, which was given to us in Christ Jesus [note]3[/note]before the [xref]e[/xref]times of the ages</text>
        <note num="1">God not only saved us to enjoy His blessing but also called us with a holy calling, a calling for a particular goal, in order to fulfill His purpose.</note>
        <note num="2">God's purpose is His plan according to His will to put us into Christ and make us one with Him to share His life and position that we may be His testimony. Grace is God's provision in life given to us that we may live out His purpose.</note>
        <note num="3">I.e., before the world began. The grace given to us in Christ was bestowed on us before the world began. This is a sure and unshakable foundation that stands firm against the downward current and exposes the utter powerlessness of the enemy's efforts to counter the eternal purpose of God. In order to strengthen Timothy, the apostle identified their ministry with this.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 6:12[/link]; [link]Heb. 3:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 9:11[/link]; [link]Eph. 2:9[/link]; [link]Titus 3:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Eph. 1:9[/link], [link]11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Tim. 1:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Titus 1:2[/link]; [link]Rom. 16:25[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>But now has been [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]manifested through the [xref]b[/xref]appearing of our Savior Christ Jesus, who [note]2[/note]nullified [xref]c[/xref]death and brought [note]3[/note][xref]d[/xref]life and [note]4[/note][xref]e[/xref]incorruption to light through the gospel,</text>
        <note num="1">God's grace was given to us in eternity, but it was manifested and applied to us through our Lord's first coming, in which He nullified death and brought life to us.</note>
        <note num="2">Christ nullified death, making it of none effect, through His devil-destroying death ([link]Heb. 2:14[/link]) and death-swallowing resurrection ([link]1 Cor. 15:52-54[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">The eternal life of God, which is given to all believers in Christ ([link]1 Tim. 1:16[/link]) and which is the main element of the divine grace given to us ([link]Rom. 5:17[/link], [link]21[/link]). This life has conquered death ([link]Acts 2:24[/link]) and will swallow up death ([link]2 Cor. 5:4[/link]). It was according to the promise of such a life that Paul was an apostle ([link]v. 1[/link]). This life and the incorruption that is its consequence have been brought to light and made visible to men through the preaching of the gospel.</note>
        <note num="4">Life is the divine element, even God Himself, imparted into our spirit; incorruption is the consequence of life's saturating of our body ([link]Rom. 8:11[/link]). This life and incorruption are able to counter the death and corruption brought in by the decline among the churches.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Titus 2:11[/link]; [link]Rom. 16:26[/link]; [link]Col. 1:26[/link]; [link]Titus 1:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:26[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Cor. 15:26[/link], [link]54[/link]; [link]Heb. 2:14[/link], [link]15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Tim. 1:1[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 1:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Rom. 2:7[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>For [note]1[/note]which I was [xref]a[/xref]appointed a [note]2[/note]herald and an apostle and a teacher.</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to the gospel of divine grace and eternal life, corresponding with the gospel in grace and life presented by the apostle John ([link]John 1:4[/link], [link]16-17[/link]). For such a gospel Paul was appointed a herald, an apostle, and a teacher.</note>
        <note num="2">A herald announces and proclaims the gospel, an apostle sets up and establishes the churches for God's administration, and a teacher gives instructions to the churches with all the saints. See note [link]7[sup]1[/sup] in 1 Tim. 2[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 1:12[/link]; [link]2:7[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>For which [note]1[/note]cause also I [xref]a[/xref]suffer these things; but I am [note]2[/note]not [xref]b[/xref]ashamed, for I know [note]3[/note]whom I have [xref]c[/xref]believed, and I am persuaded that He is able to [xref]d[/xref]guard [note]4[/note]my [xref]e[/xref]deposit unto [note]5[/note][xref]f[/xref]that day.</text>
        <note num="1">The apostle suffered for a cause, a cause on the highest plane &amp;#8212; the proclaiming of the glad tidings of the gospel of grace and life to establish the churches, and the directing of the saints. Such a cause must have been an encouragement and strengthening to Timothy as he faced the deterioration of the declining churches.</note>
        <note num="2">So Timothy should not have been ashamed either ([link]v. 8[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">The apostle believed not a thing or a matter but a living person, Christ, the Son of the living God, who is the embodiment of divine grace and eternal life. The eternal life in Him is powerful; it is more than able to sustain to the end the one who suffers for His sake, and to preserve him for the inheritance of the coming glory. The grace in Him was more than sufficient to provide His sent one with all he needed for finishing the course of his ministry unto a reward in glory ([link]4:7-8[/link]). Hence, He was able to guard that which the apostle had committed unto Him for the day of His return. Such an assurance must also have been an encouragement and strengthening to the enfeebled and sorrowful Timothy.</note>
        <note num="4">Or, that which I have committed [i]unto Him.[/i] The apostle committed his entire being with his glorious future unto the One who was able, through His life and grace, to guard his deposit for the day of His second appearing.</note>
        <note num="5">The day of Christ's second appearing.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 2:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Tim. 1:8[/link], [link]16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Titus 3:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">cf. [link]2 Tim. 1:14[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 6:20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]1 Pet. 4:19[/link]; [link]Psa. 10:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]2 Tim. 1:18[/link]; [link]4:8[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 1:8[/link]; [link]3:13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Hold a [note]1[/note]pattern of the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]healthy words that you have [xref]c[/xref]heard from me, in the [note]3[/note][xref]d[/xref]faith and love which are in Christ Jesus.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, example. The word in [link]v. 12[/link] is a pattern, an example, of healthy words.</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]3[sup]2[/sup] in 1 Tim. 6[/link].</note>
        <note num="3">See note [link]14[sup]2[/sup] in 1 Tim. 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Titus 1:9[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 1:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 6:3[/link]; [link]1:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Tim. 2:2[/link]; [link]Rev. 3:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Tim. 1:14[/link]; [link]2:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Guard the good [note]1[/note]deposit through the Holy [xref]b[/xref]Spirit who [note]2[/note]dwells in us.</text>
        <note num="1">This is the deposit the Lord entrusted to us, in contrast to the deposit we entrusted to Him, mentioned in [link]v. 12[/link]. According to [link]v. 13[/link], the deposit here must refer to the deposit of healthy words, including the riches of life in His word, which the Lord has stored in us. See note [link]20[sup]1[/sup] in 1 Tim. 6[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., is indwelling. The Holy Spirit dwells in our spirit ([link]Rom. 8:16[/link]). Hence, for us to guard the good deposit through the Holy Spirit requires that we exercise our spirit.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 6:20[/link]; cf. [link]2 Tim. 1:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Titus 3:5[/link]; [link]Rom. 8:9[/link], [link]11[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 3:16[/link]; [link]6:19[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>This you know, that all who are in [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Asia [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]turned away from me, of whom are [note]3[/note]Phygelus and Hermogenes.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., the province of Asia. The phrase [i]all who are in Asia[/i] points to the general situation among the believers in Asia and does not include every particular believer; for Onesiphorus is mentioned as one from Asia who often refreshed Paul and sought him out ([link]vv. 16-18[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">This indicates that the believers in Asia who had formerly received the apostle's ministry now forsook him. In spite of such desertion, the apostle grew stronger in the grace that was in Christ, who is the same and will never change. Not being discouraged, he exhorted his son in faith to persevere steadily in the ministry in the midst of the failure and ruin of the churches.</note>
        <note num="3">These two must be the ones who took the lead to desert the apostle because of his imprisonment (cf. [link]v. 8[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 2:9[/link]; [link]19:10[/link]; [link]20:18[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 1:8[/link]; [link]Rev. 1:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Tim. 4:10[/link], [link]16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>May the Lord grant [xref]a[/xref]mercy to the house of [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]Onesiphorus, for he often [xref]c[/xref]refreshed me and was not [xref]d[/xref]ashamed of my [xref]e[/xref]chain;</text>
        <note num="1">He was an overcomer who surmounted the general trend and stood against the downward current to refresh the Lord's ambassador in spirit, soul, and body, not being ashamed of the apostle's imprisonment on behalf of the Lord's commission.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 1:18[/link], [link]2[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 1:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Tim. 4:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Philem. 7[/link], [link]20[/link]; [link]Rom. 15:32[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 16:18[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 7:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Tim. 1:8[/link], [link]12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Acts 28:20[/link]; [link]Phil. 1:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>But being in [xref]a[/xref]Rome, he sought me out diligently and found [i]me.[/i]</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 28:14[/link], [link]16[/link], [link]17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>May the Lord grant him to find [xref]a[/xref]mercy from the Lord in [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]that day. And in how many things he served [i]me[/i] in [xref]c[/xref]Ephesus, you know best.</text>
        <note num="1">The day of the Lord's victorious appearing to reward His overcomers ([link]4:8[/link]; [link]Rev. 22:12[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 1:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Tim. 1:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Acts 18:19[/link]; [link]19:1[/link], [link]26[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 1:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>You therefore, my [xref]a[/xref]child, be [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]empowered in the [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]grace which is in Christ Jesus;</text>
        <note num="1">The apostle himself had experienced the empowering of grace in life ([link]1:9-12[/link]). Now he exhorted Timothy to be empowered in the same grace.</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]9[sup]2[/sup] in ch. 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 1:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Tim. 1:7[/link]; [link]4:17[/link]; [link]Eph. 6:10[/link]; [link]Phil. 4:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Tim. 1:9[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 1:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And the [note]1[/note]things which you have [xref]a[/xref]heard from me through many [xref]b[/xref]witnesses, these [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]commit to [note]3[/note][xref]d[/xref]faithful men, who will be competent to [xref]e[/xref]teach others also.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., the healthy words ([link]1:13[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">The healthy words, after being committed to faithful men, become the good deposit in them ([link]1:14[/link]). This word indicates that if someone in a local church has a deposit of the Lord's healthy words, he should train the faithful ones that they too may have a good deposit from the Lord and be competent to teach others.</note>
        <note num="3">Trustworthy.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 1:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 6:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Tim. 1:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Matt. 24:45[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]2 Tim. 2:24[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 3:2[/link]; [link]5:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Suffer evil with [i]me[/i] as a good [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]soldier of Christ Jesus.</text>
        <note num="1">The apostle considered their ministry a warfare for Christ, just as the priestly service was considered a military service, a warfare, in [link]Num. 4:23[/link], [link]30[/link], [link]35[/link] (lit.).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 1:8[/link]; [link]4:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 1:18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>No one serving as a soldier [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]entangles himself with the [xref]b[/xref]affairs of this [note]2[/note]life, that he may please the one who enlisted [i]him.[/i]</text>
        <note num="1">To fight a good fight ([link]4:7[/link]) for the Lord's interests on this earth, we must clear away all earthly entanglements.</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word ([i]bios[/i]) denotes the physical life in this age.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 12:1[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 2:20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. [link]Luke 14:18-20[/link]; [link]Matt. 13:22[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And also if anyone [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]contends [i]in the games,[/i] he is not [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]crowned unless he contends lawfully.</text>
        <note num="1">Here Timothy is likened to an athlete contending in the games.</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]25[sup]1[/sup] in 1 Cor. 9[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 9:25[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Tim. 4:8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>The laboring [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]farmer must be the first to partake of the fruit.</text>
        <note num="1">Here the apostle likened Timothy to a farmer. A soldier must win the victory, an athlete must receive the crown, and a farmer must partake of the fruits, the food.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 9:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Consider what I say, for the Lord will give you understanding in all things.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Remember Jesus Christ, [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]raised from the dead, of the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]seed of David, according to [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]my gospel,</text>
        <note num="1">Indicating Christ's victory over death by His divine life with its resurrection power.</note>
        <note num="2">Indicating Christ's dignified human nature, which was exalted and glorified along with His divine nature.</note>
        <note num="3">The apostle's gospel is the glad tidings of the living person, Christ, who possesses both the divine nature and the human nature, who was incarnated to be the Son of Man and resurrected to be the Son of God, as related in the parallel portion, [link]Rom. 1:1-4[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 2:24[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 15:4[/link], [link]20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Matt. 1:1[/link]; [link]22:42[/link], [link]45[/link]; [link]John 7:42[/link]; [link]Rom. 1:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rom. 2:16[/link]; [link]16:25[/link]; [link]Gal. 1:11[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 1:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>In which I [xref]a[/xref]suffer evil unto [xref]b[/xref]bonds as a [xref]c[/xref]criminal; but the [xref]d[/xref]word of God is [note]1[/note]not bound.</text>
        <note num="1">In spite of all the opposition by human efforts that were instigated by the enemy, Satan, the bonds of the apostle caused the word of God to be released, to be preached by men freely and to become more prevailing.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 1:8[/link], [link]12[/link]; [link]Acts 9:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Phil. 1:7[/link]; [link]Col. 4:3[/link], [link]18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Luke 22:37[/link]; [link]23:32[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Thes. 1:8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Therefore I [xref]a[/xref]endure all things for the sake of the [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]chosen ones, that they themselves also may obtain the [xref]c[/xref]salvation which is in Christ Jesus [note]2[/note]with [xref]d[/xref]eternal glory.</text>
        <note num="1">The believers in Christ, who were chosen by God the Father before the foundation of the world ([link]Eph. 1:4[/link]) and selected from among mankind for salvation. The apostle endured all sufferings for the sake of us, the chosen ones, that we too may obtain salvation, as he did.</note>
        <note num="2">It is not salvation [i]and[/i] eternal glory but salvation [i]with[/i] eternal glory. Eternal glory is the ultimate goal of God's salvation ([link]Rom. 8:21[/link]); God's salvation leads us into His glory ([link]Heb. 2:10[/link]). This encourages us to endure sufferings for the gospel ([link]Rom. 8:17[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 13:7[/link]; [link]Heb. 10:36[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Titus 1:1[/link]; [link]Col. 3:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Thes. 5:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Pet. 5:10[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 4:17[/link]; [link]Heb. 2:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Faithful is the word: [note]1[/note]For if we [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]died with [i]Him,[/i] we will also [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]live with [i]Him;[/i]</text>
        <note num="1">The portion from here to the end of [link]v. 13[/link] might have been a hymn. This passage corresponds with [link]Rom. 6:8[/link] and [link]8:17[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">In Christ's crucifixion, as symbolized by baptism ([link]Rom. 6:3-8[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">In Christ's resurrection ([link]Rom. 6:5[/link], [link]8[/link]; [link]John 14:19[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 1:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 6:8[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 4:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Thes. 5:10[/link]; [link]John 14:19[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>If we [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]endure, we will also [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]reign with [i]Him;[/i] if we [xref]c[/xref]deny [i]Him,[/i] He also will [note]3[/note]deny us;</text>
        <note num="1">In this age.</note>
        <note num="2">In the coming age.</note>
        <note num="3">Not acknowledge us ([link]Matt. 10:33[/link]; [link]Luke 12:9[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Thes. 1:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rev. 20:4[/link], [link]6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Matt. 10:33[/link]; [link]Luke 12:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>If we are [xref]a[/xref]faithless, He remains [note]1[/note]faithful, for He [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]cannot deny Himself.</text>
        <note num="1">Faithful to His own word.</note>
        <note num="2">If we become faithless toward Him, though He remains faithful, He cannot accept us as faithful by making Himself unfaithful, i.e., by denying Himself (His nature and His being).</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Rom. 3:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Titus 1:2[/link]; [link]Num. 23:19[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Remind [i]them[/i] of these things, solemnly [xref]a[/xref]charging [i]them[/i] before God not to have [xref]b[/xref]contentions of words, [i]which is[/i] [xref]c[/xref]useful for nothing, to the [note]1[/note]ruin of those who hear.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, overthrowing. Lit., catastrophe.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 4:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 6:4[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 2:23[/link]; [link]Titus 3:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Titus 3:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Be diligent to [xref]a[/xref]present yourself [xref]b[/xref]approved to God, an unashamed workman, [note]1[/note]cutting straight the [xref]c[/xref]word of the [note]2[/note][xref]d[/xref]truth.</text>
        <note num="1">As in carpentry. It means to unfold the word of God in its various parts rightly and straightly without distortion.</note>
        <note num="2">See notes [link]4[sup]2[/sup] in 1 Tim. 2[/link] and [link]15[sup]5[/sup] in 1 Tim. 3[/link]. Contentions of words ([link]v. 14[/link]), profane, vain babblings ([link]v. 16[/link]), the word that eats away like gangrene ([link]v. 17[/link]), and foolish questionings and those arising from an untrained mind ([link]v. 23[/link]) are often used by the devil ([link]v. 26[/link]) in the downward current among the churches to beget contentions ([link]v. 23[/link]), to ruin the hearers ([link]v. 14[/link]), to promote ungodliness ([link]v. 16[/link]), and to overthrow people's faith ([link]v. 18[/link]). Hence, there is the need of the word of the truth, rightly unfolded, to enlighten the darkened people, inoculate against the poison, swallow up the death, and bring the distracted back to the proper track.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 6:13[/link]; [link]12:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Phil. 2:22[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 11:19[/link]; [link]Rom. 5:4[/link]; cf. [link]2 Tim. 3:8[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 9:27[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 13:5[/link], [link]6[/link]; [link]Heb. 6:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Eph. 1:13[/link]; [link]James 1:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Tim. 2:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>But [xref]a[/xref]avoid [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]profane, [xref]c[/xref]vain babblings, for they will advance to more [note]2[/note][xref]d[/xref]ungodliness,</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]7[sup]1[/sup] in 1 Tim. 4[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Contrary to godliness. See note [link]2[sup]2[/sup] in 1 Tim. 2[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Titus 3:9[/link]; cf. [link]1 Tim. 6:20[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 3:5[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 6:11[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 2:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 4:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Tim. 6:20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Tim. 1:9[/link]; [link]Titus 2:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And their word will [note]1[/note]spread like [note]2[/note]gangrene, of whom are [xref]a[/xref]Hymenaeus and Philetus,</text>
        <note num="1">Or, feed, eat. Lit., have pasture; cf. [link]John 10:9[/link]. The word for [i]pasture[/i] in Greek is the medical term for the consuming progress of a mortifying disease (Alford). Hence, here the Greek phrase is rendered [i]spread.[/i]</note>
        <note num="2">An eating sore, a cancer.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 1:20[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Who concerning the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]truth have [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]misaimed, saying that the [xref]c[/xref]resurrection has [note]3[/note]already taken place, and overthrow the [note]4[/note][xref]d[/xref]faith of some.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]15[sup]5[/sup] in 1 Tim. 3[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">I.e., missed the mark, swerved, deviated.</note>
        <note num="3">I.e., that there will be no resurrection. This is a serious heresy that denies the divine power in life ([link]1 Cor. 15:52[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 4:16[/link]; [link]Rev. 20:4[/link], [link]6[/link]).</note>
        <note num="4">This is the subjective faith, i.e., the act of believing; it is very much related to the resurrection of Christ ([link]Rom. 10:9[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 2:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 1:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Cor. 15:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Tim. 1:14[/link]; [link]19a[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>However the firm [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]foundation of God stands, having this [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]seal, The Lord [xref]c[/xref]knows those who are His, and, Let everyone who [xref]d[/xref]names the name of the Lord depart from unrighteousness.</text>
        <note num="1">[link]Verses 14-18[/link] give instruction concerning how to deal with heresies, on the negative side, and handle the truth, on the positive side. According to the context of [link]vv. 15[/link], [link]18[/link], and 25, the foundation here does not refer to Christ as the foundation of the church ([link]1 Cor. 3:11[/link]) but to the church as the foundation of the truth. This corresponds with the base of the truth, which holds the truth (1 Tim. [link]3:15[/link]), especially the truth of the resurrection of Christ ([link]Acts 4:33[/link]).[br][br]The church is built with the divine life in Christ, a life that is indestructible, unconquerable ([link]Heb. 7:16[/link]; [link]Acts 2:24[/link]), and able to withstand deathly decline originating from any source. Hence, the church is the firm foundation of God that stands forever against any heresy.</note>
        <note num="2">The seal has two sides. On the Lord's side it is: "The Lord knows those who are His." This is based on the Lord's divine life, which He has given to all His believers and which has brought them into an organic union with Him, making them one with Him and causing them to become His. On our side it is: "Let everyone who names the name of the Lord depart from unrighteousness." This is the issue of the divine life &amp;#8212; it enables us to depart from unrighteousness and keeps us blameless in His holy name. The church as the firm foundation in the divine life bears such a two-sided seal, testifying that the Lord's divine life has made us His and has kept us from things that are contrary to His righteous way.[br][br][link]Verse 19[/link] indicates definitely that the ones exposed in [link]vv. 16-18[/link] are not the Lord's. Their evildoings are a strong proof of this.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 3:15[/link]; cf. [link]Isa. 28:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Eph. 1:13[/link]; [link]4:30[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 1:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Num. 16:5[/link]; [link]Nahum 1:7[/link]; [link]John 10:14[/link], [link]27[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Isa. 26:13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>[note]1[/note]But in a [note]2[/note]great house there are not only [note]3[/note]gold and silver vessels but also [note]4[/note]wooden and earthen; and some are unto [xref]a[/xref]honor, and some unto dishonor.</text>
        <note num="1">In contrast to the definition in [link]v. 19[/link] concerning genuine believers.</note>
        <note num="2">The house of God defined in [link]1 Tim. 3:15-16[/link] is the genuine church in its divine nature and essential character as the foundation of the truth; whereas the great house here refers to the deteriorated church in its mixed character, as illustrated by the abnormally large tree in [link]Matt. 13:31-32[/link] (see note [link]32[sup]1[/sup] in Matt. 13[/link]). In this great house there are not only precious vessels but also base ones.</note>
        <note num="3">Honorable vessels are constituted of both the divine nature (gold) and the redeemed and regenerated human nature (silver). These, like Timothy and other genuine believers, constitute the sure foundation that holds the truth.</note>
        <note num="4">Dishonorable vessels are constituted of the fallen human nature (wood and earth). Hymenaeus, Philetus, and other false believers belong to this category.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 9:21[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>If therefore anyone [note]1[/note]cleanses himself from [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]these, he will be a [xref]b[/xref]vessel [note]3[/note]unto honor, [xref]c[/xref]sanctified, [xref]d[/xref]useful to the master, [xref]e[/xref]prepared unto every good work.</text>
        <note num="1">This is to depart from unrighteousness ([link]v. 19[/link]), as an outward evidence of the inward divine nature.</note>
        <note num="2">Referring to vessels unto dishonor, including those mentioned in [link]vv. 16-18[/link].</note>
        <note num="3">[i]Unto honor[/i] is a matter of nature, [i]sanctified[/i] a matter of position, [i]useful[/i] a matter of practice, and [i]prepared[/i] a matter of training.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 2:16-18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 9:21[/link], [link]23-24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rom. 6:19[/link], [link]22[/link]; [link]15:16[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Philem. 11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]2 Tim. 3:17[/link]; [link]Titus 3:1[/link], [link]8[/link], [link]14[/link]; [link]Heb. 13:21[/link]; [link]Eph. 2:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>But [xref]a[/xref]flee youthful [note]1[/note]lusts, and [xref]b[/xref]pursue [note]2[/note]righteousness, faith, love, peace with those who [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]call on the Lord out of a [note]4[/note][xref]d[/xref]pure heart.</text>
        <note num="1">Timothy had to be wary not only of outward corruption among the churches but also of inward lusts within himself. He had to avoid the outward corruption and flee the inward lusts.</note>
        <note num="2">Righteousness is toward oneself, faith is toward God, and love is toward others; peace is the issue of these three virtues.</note>
        <note num="3">This is to name the name of the Lord ([link]v. 19[/link]) in our prayer and praise to Him. The Lord's seekers must be His callers.</note>
        <note num="4">See note [link]5[sup]3[/sup] in 1 Tim. 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 6:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 6:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rom. 10:12[/link]; [link]Acts 9:14[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 1:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Tim. 1:5[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>But [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]foolish [xref]b[/xref]questionings and those arising from an [note]2[/note]untrained mind refuse, knowing that they beget contentions.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, stupid.</note>
        <note num="2">Uneducated, undisciplined, unlearned, i.e., not subject to God but following one's own mind and will (Darby).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Titus 3:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 1:4[/link]; [link]6:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>But a [xref]a[/xref]slave of the Lord ought [xref]b[/xref]not to contend but be gentle toward all, apt to [xref]c[/xref]teach, bearing with wrong;</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 1:1[/link]; [link]Gal. 1:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 3:3[/link]; [link]Titus 3:2[/link]; [link]Matt. 12:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Tim. 2:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>In [xref]a[/xref]meekness correcting those who [xref]b[/xref]oppose, if perhaps God may give them [note]1[/note][xref]c[/xref]repentance unto the [note]2[/note][xref]d[/xref]full knowledge of the truth,</text>
        <note num="1">This indicates that with the opposers of the truth it is the heart and conscience that are in question. The truth is the revelation of the living God and His economy, His heart's desire. To receive the divine revelation, the heart and conscience need to be rightly exercised toward God. The heart should be turned to Him, directed solely to Him, and the conscience must be pure and void of offense before Him. Otherwise, one may be carried away as a captive by the devil and thus fall into his snare ([link]v. 26[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]4[sup]2[/sup] in 1 Tim. 2[/link]. This word proves that the opposers lack adequate knowledge of the divine revelation.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Titus 3:2[/link]; [link]Gal. 6:1[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 3:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Tim. 3:8[/link]; [link]Titus 1:9[/link]; [link]2:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Acts 5:31[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Tim. 2:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>And they may [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]return to soberness out of the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]snare of the [note]3[/note]devil, having been caught alive by him, unto [note]4[/note][xref]c[/xref]His will.</text>
        <note num="1">Become sober again, awake out of a drunken stupor (Vincent).</note>
        <note num="2">This indicates that the opposers of the truth have been captured and kept in a snare by the devil. The enemy of God occupies their reprobate mind with error and shuts God out, just as he did with the Pharisees ([link]John 8:42-45[/link]). Such opposers need to turn to God in their heart and have a thorough dealing in their conscience.</note>
        <note num="3">See note [link]10[sup]1[/sup] in Rev. 2[/link].</note>
        <note num="4">I.e., for God's will, to do God's will.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 15:34[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 3:7[/link]; [link]6:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rom. 12:2[/link]; [link]Eph. 5:17[/link]; [link]Col. 1:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[note]1[/note]But know this, that in the [note]2[/note]last days [note]3[/note]difficult [xref]a[/xref]times will come.</text>
        <note num="1">In contrast to the hope expressed at the end of the preceding chapter.</note>
        <note num="2">Denoting the present age ([link]2 Pet. 3:3[/link]; [link]Jude 18[/link]), which began with Christ's first coming ([link]1 Pet. 1:20[/link]) and will last until His second appearing. That this period was to be lengthy was not revealed to the apostles ([link]Matt. 24:36[/link]); they expected the Lord to return in their generation.</note>
        <note num="3">Or, hard times, grievous times, perilous times.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 4:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>For [note]1[/note]men will be [note]2[/note]lovers of self, [xref]a[/xref]lovers of money, [xref]b[/xref]boasters, [note]3[/note]arrogant, [note]4[/note][xref]c[/xref]revilers, [xref]b[/xref]disobedient to parents, [note]5[/note]unthankful, [xref]d[/xref]unholy,</text>
        <note num="1">The prophetic picture presented in [link]vv. 2-5[/link] portrays not the evil condition of the non-Christian society but the corrupted situation of the great house mentioned in [link]2:20[/link], which is Christianity in decline. This is proved by the phrase [i]having an outward form of godliness[/i] in [link]v. 5[/link]. Non-Christians do not have even the outward form of godliness.</note>
        <note num="2">In 1 and 2 Timothy and Titus seven kinds of lovers are mentioned: (1) lovers of self, (2) lovers of money ([link]v. 2[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 6:10[/link]), (3) lovers of pleasure, (4) lovers of God ([link]v. 4[/link]), (5) lovers of good ([link]Titus 1:8[/link]), (6) lovers of husbands, and (7) lovers of children ([link]Titus 2:4[/link]). Also, two kinds of nonlovers are mentioned: (1) nonlovers of good, and (2) nonlovers of God ([link]vv. 3-4[/link]). Whatever one loves, his whole heart, even his entire being, is set on and occupied and possessed by. This is crucial! Whether there would be a day of glory in the church's victory or grievous days of the church's decline depends altogether on what kind of lovers we are. History tells us that the root of the church's decline was the loss of her first love toward the Lord ([link]Rev. 2:4[/link]). To maintain the victorious standard of the church, we must be lovers of God and lovers of the good that pertains to God's economy.</note>
        <note num="3">Or, haughty.</note>
        <note num="4">Lit., blasphemers; as in [link]1 Tim. 1:13[/link]. Here, however, it does not refer to blasphemers of God but to revilers or railers, those who speak evilly and injuriously against men.</note>
        <note num="5">Or, ungrateful.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 6:10[/link]; [link]Heb. 13:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 1:30[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 2:10-12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Tim. 1:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Without natural affection, [note]1[/note]implacable, [xref]b[/xref]slanderers, [xref]c[/xref]without self-control, savage, [xref]c[/xref]not lovers of good,</text>
        <note num="1">Or, irreconcilable.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 1:31[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 3:11[/link]; [link]Titus 2:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">cf. [link]Titus 1:8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>[note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Traitors, [note]2[/note]reckless, [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]blinded with pride, [note]4[/note]lovers of [xref]c[/xref]pleasure rather than [xref]d[/xref]lovers of God,</text>
        <note num="1">Or, betrayers.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, headstrong.</note>
        <note num="3">See note [link]6[sup]2[/sup] in 1 Tim. 3[/link].</note>
        <note num="4">In this picture there are three kinds of lovers &amp;#8212; lovers of self, lovers of money, and lovers of pleasure &amp;#8212; and two kinds of nonlovers &amp;#8212; nonlovers of good and nonlovers of God.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]John 6:71[/link]; [link]Acts 7:52[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 3:6[/link]; [link]6:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Titus 3:3[/link]; [link]James 5:5[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 2:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Mark 12:30[/link]; [link]1 John 4:21[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Having an [note]1[/note]outward [xref]a[/xref]form of [xref]b[/xref]godliness, though [xref]c[/xref]denying its [note]2[/note]power; from these also [xref]d[/xref]turn away.</text>
        <note num="1">Merely an outward semblance without the essential reality.</note>
        <note num="2">The real and practical virtue with a living influence to express God.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 2:20[/link]; cf. [link]Matt. 7:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 2:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Tim. 5:8[/link]; [link]Titus 1:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Tim. 6:20[/link]; cf. [link]1 Tim. 6:11[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 2:22[/link], [link]16[/link]; [link]Titus 3:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>For of these are those who [xref]a[/xref]creep into [xref]b[/xref]houses and take captive silly women heaped with sins, who are led by [xref]c[/xref]various desires</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Jude 4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Titus 1:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Titus 3:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>[i]And[/i] are always learning yet never able to come to the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]full knowledge of the truth.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]4[sup]2[/sup] in 1 Tim. 2[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 2:25[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 2:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And in the manner that [note]1[/note]Jannes and Jambres opposed Moses, so these also [xref]a[/xref]oppose the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]truth; men [xref]c[/xref]corrupted in mind, [note]3[/note][xref]d[/xref]disapproved concerning the [note]4[/note][xref]e[/xref]faith.</text>
        <note num="1">According to Jewish tradition, these two were the Egyptian magicians who opposed Moses in [link]Exo. 7:11[/link], [link]22[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]15[sup]5[/sup] in 1 Tim. 3[/link]. In the decline among the churches, truth is the target of the enemy's attack. Hence, truth is also the remedy for and the rescue from the diseased and ruined situation.</note>
        <note num="3">Or, reprobate.</note>
        <note num="4">See note [link]1[sup]4[/sup] in 1 Tim. 4[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 2:25[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 2:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Tim. 6:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Titus 1:16[/link]; cf. [link]1 Cor. 9:27[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 13:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]1 Tim. 1:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>But they will not [xref]a[/xref]advance farther, for their [note]1[/note]folly will be completely manifest to all, as also the [i]folly[/i] of [note]2[/note]those became.</text>
        <note num="1">The lack of intelligence and the senselessness in their doings.</note>
        <note num="2">Jannes and Jambres, who were defeated and brought to nothing ([link]Exo. 8:18[/link]; [link]9:11[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]2 Tim. 2:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>But you have [xref]a[/xref]closely followed my teaching, [note]1[/note]conduct, [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]purpose, faith, long-suffering, love, endurance,</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., manner of life.</note>
        <note num="2">This Greek word is used in Paul's Epistles in relation to the purpose of God ([link]Rom. 9:11[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 4:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 11:23[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Persecutions, sufferings, such as befell me in [xref]b[/xref]Antioch, in [xref]c[/xref]Iconium, in [note]1[/note][xref]d[/xref]Lystra. Such persecutions I bore, and out of them all the Lord [xref]e[/xref]delivered me.</text>
        <note num="1">The city where Timothy lived ([link]Acts 16:1-2[/link]), near Iconium and Pisidian Antioch.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 13:50[/link]; [link]14:2[/link], [link]5[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 12:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 13:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Acts 14:1-2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Acts 14:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]2 Tim. 4:17-18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And indeed all who [note]1[/note]desire to [note]2[/note]live [xref]a[/xref]godly in Christ Jesus will be [xref]b[/xref]persecuted.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, determine.</note>
        <note num="2">I.e., live a life of godliness. See notes [link]2[sup]2[/sup] in 1 Tim. 2[/link], and [link book="1 Tim." chapter="3"]16[sup]2[/sup][/link], [link]16[sup]3[/sup] in 1 Tim. 3[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Titus 2:12[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 2:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]John 15:20[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 4:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>But evil men and [note]1[/note]impostors will grow worse and worse, [xref]a[/xref]deceiving and being deceived.</text>
        <note num="1">Juggling impostors. This verse indicates that the decline of the church will become worse.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Titus 1:10[/link]; [link]3:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>But you, [note]1[/note]continue in the [note]2[/note]things which you have learned and have been assured of, knowing from which ones you have learned [i]them[/i]</text>
        <note num="1">Or, abide.</note>
        <note num="2">The things that Timothy learned from the apostle and was assured of constituted the vital portion of the content of the New Testament, a portion that completed the divine revelation ([link]Col. 1:25[/link]). Hence, he had practical apprehension of a great part of the New Testament.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>[note]1[/note]And that [xref]a[/xref]from a babe you have known the [xref]b[/xref]sacred writings, which are able to make you [xref]c[/xref]wise unto [xref]d[/xref]salvation through the [note]2[/note]faith which is in Christ Jesus.</text>
        <note num="1">In addition to his knowledge of the New Testament, Timothy had, from his childhood, a good foundation in the knowledge of the Old Testament. He was one who was fully perfected and equipped to minister the word of God, not only in caring for a local church but also in confronting the worsening decline of the church.</note>
        <note num="2">Cf. note [link]22[sup]1[/sup] in Rom. 3[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 1:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 15:4[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 10:11[/link]; [link]John 5:39[/link], [link]47[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Psa. 19:7[/link]; [link]119:98[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Cor. 1:21[/link]; [link]Acts 16:31[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>[note]1[/note]All [xref]a[/xref]Scripture is [note]2[/note]God-breathed and profitable for [xref]b[/xref]teaching, for [note]3[/note]conviction, for [note]4[/note]correction, for [note]5[/note]instruction in righteousness,</text>
        <note num="1">Or, Every Scripture God-breathed is also profitable. To confront the death, corruption, and confusion in the church's decline, the eternal life, on which [link]ch. 1[/link] is based ([link]1:1[/link], [link]10[/link]), the divine truth, emphasized in [link]ch. 2[/link] ([link]2:15[/link], [link]18[/link], [link]25[/link]), and the Holy Scripture, highly regarded in [link]ch. 3[/link] ([link]3:14-17[/link]), are all needed. The eternal life not only swallows up death but also renders the life supply; the divine truth replaces the vanity of corruption with the reality of all the divine riches; and the Holy Scripture not only dispels the confusion but also furnishes divine light and revelation. Hence, in this book the apostle stressed these three things.</note>
        <note num="2">This indicates that the Scripture, the word of God, is the breathing out of God. God's speaking is God's breathing out. Hence, His word is spirit ([link]John 6:63[/link]), or breath. Thus, the Scripture is the embodiment of God as the Spirit. The Spirit is therefore the very essence, the substance, of the Scripture, just as phosphorus is the essential substance in matches. We must strike the Spirit of the Scripture with our spirit to catch the divine fire.[br][br]As the embodiment of God the Spirit, the Scripture (God's word) is also the embodiment of Christ. Christ is God's living Word ([link]Rev. 19:13[/link]), and the Scripture is God's written word ([link]Matt. 4:4[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">Reproof, confutation.</note>
        <note num="4">Setting right what is wrong, turning someone to the right way, restoring to an upright state.</note>
        <note num="5">Discipline or chastisement according to righteousness; to discipline or chastise by the element and condition of righteousness.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 1:20-21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 15:4[/link]; [link]Eph. 6:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>That the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]man of God may be [note]2[/note]complete, fully [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]equipped for every good work.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]11[sup]1[/sup] in 1 Tim. 6[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Complete and perfect in qualifications.</note>
        <note num="3">Or, fitted out, furnished, made ready.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 6:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 13:21[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 2:21[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>I solemnly [xref]a[/xref]charge [i]you[/i] before God and Christ Jesus, who is to [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]judge the living and the dead, and by [note]2[/note]His [xref]c[/xref]appearing and His [xref]d[/xref]kingdom:</text>
        <note num="1">God has given all judgment to Christ because He is a man ([link]John 5:22[/link], [link]27[/link]; [link]Acts 10:42[/link]; [link]17:31[/link]; [link]Rom. 2:16[/link]). As the righteous Judge ([link]v. 8[/link]), Christ will judge the living on His throne of glory at His second appearing ([link]Matt. 25:31-46[/link]), and He will judge the dead on the great white throne after the millennium ([link]Rev. 20:11-15[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">This word proves that, in his life and work, Paul took the Lord's appearing and His kingdom as the incentive and goal. The Lord's appearing will be for judgment, to reward each one of us ([link]Matt. 16:27[/link]; [link]Rev. 22:12[/link]), and His kingdom will be for His reigning with His overcomers ([link]Rev. 20:4[/link], [link]6[/link]). The apostle not only took these two matters as the incentive and goal for himself but also by these two matters charged Timothy, who was under his leading, to faithfully fulfill his ministry of the word.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 1:18[/link]; [link]6:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 10:42[/link]; [link]17:31[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Tim. 4:8[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 6:14[/link]; [link]Titus 2:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Tim. 4:18[/link]; [link]Matt. 13:41[/link]; [link]Luke 1:33[/link]; [link]Eph. 5:5[/link]; [link]Col. 1:13[/link]; [link]Heb. 1:8[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 1:11[/link]; [link]Rev. 1:9[/link]; [link]11:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Proclaim the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]word; [note]2[/note]be ready [note]3[/note]in season [i]and[/i] out of season; [xref]b[/xref]convict, [note]4[/note]rebuke, [xref]c[/xref]exhort with [note]5[/note]all [xref]d[/xref]long-suffering and [xref]e[/xref]teaching.</text>
        <note num="1">Composed of what Timothy learned of both Paul and the Old Testament ([link]3:14-15[/link]). This proves that [link]vv. 1-2[/link] are a continuation of [link]3:14-17[/link]. In caring for a local church, especially in a time of the church's decline, the proclaiming of the word is vital.</note>
        <note num="2">Be urgent, stand by.</note>
        <note num="3">Opportunely or inopportunely, whether the opportunity is convenient or inconvenient, whether you are welcome or unwelcome.</note>
        <note num="4">Implying to condemn severely.</note>
        <note num="5">[i]All[/i] also modifies teaching &amp;#8212; teaching in many aspects and directions. The carrying out of such teaching requires long-suffering.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 4:31[/link]; [link]6:7[/link]; [link]12:24[/link]; [link]19:20[/link]; [link]Col. 4:3[/link]; [link]Rev. 1:2[/link], [link]9[/link]; [link]6:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 5:20[/link]; [link]Titus 1:13[/link]; [link]2:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Tim. 4:13[/link]; [link]6:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Tim. 3:10[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 5:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]2 Tim. 2:24[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 3:2[/link]; [link]5:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>For the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]time will come when they will not tolerate the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]healthy teaching; but according to their own lusts they will heap up to themselves teachers, having [note]3[/note]itching ears,</text>
        <note num="1">When the decline of the church worsens.</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]10[sup]1[/sup] in 1 Tim. 1[/link].</note>
        <note num="3">Ears that seek pleasant speaking for their own pleasure.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 3:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 1:10[/link]; [link]Titus 1:9[/link]; [link]2:1[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 1:13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And they will [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]turn away their ear from the [note]2[/note]truth and will be turned aside to [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]myths.</text>
        <note num="1">The itching and turned-away ear is the main factor in the worsening decline in the churches.</note>
        <note num="2">See notes [link]4[sup]2[/sup] in 1 Tim. 2[/link] and [link]15[sup]5[/sup] in 1 Tim. 3[/link].</note>
        <note num="3">See note [link]4[sup]1[/sup] in 1 Tim. 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Titus 1:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 1:4[/link]; [link]4:7[/link]; [link]Titus 1:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>But you, be [xref]a[/xref]sober in all things, [xref]b[/xref]suffer evil, do the work of an [xref]c[/xref]evangelist, [note]1[/note]fully accomplish your [note]2[/note][xref]d[/xref]ministry.</text>
        <note num="1">Fill up the full measure of your ministry.</note>
        <note num="2">The ministry of the word, which is to minister Christ in all His riches ([link]Eph. 3:8[/link]) to both sinners and believers for the building up of the Body of Christ ([link]Eph. 4:11-12[/link]). Such a ministry is desperately needed to counter the trend of decline, as prophesied in [link]vv. 3-4[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 1:7[/link]; [link]Titus 2:12[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:13[/link]; [link]4:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Tim. 1:8[/link]; [link]2:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Acts 21:8[/link]; [link]Eph. 4:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Tim. 4:11[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 1:12[/link]; [link]Col. 4:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>For I am already being [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]poured out, and the time of my [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]departure is at hand.</text>
        <note num="1">As a drink offering (see note [link]17[sup]1[/sup] in Phil. 2[/link]). To be poured out is to shed one's blood. [i]Already being poured out[/i] indicates that the process had begun.</note>
        <note num="2">From the world to be with the Lord ([link]Phil. 1:23[/link]), through martyrdom. Paul was imprisoned in Rome twice. The first imprisonment was from about A.D. 62-64 and was due to the Jews' accusation ([link]Acts 28:17-20[/link]). During that time Paul wrote the Epistles to the Colossians, Ephesians, and Philippians, and the Epistle to Philemon. After his release from the first imprisonment (a release that he expected in [link]Phil. 1:25[/link]; [link]2:24[/link]; and [link]Philem. 22[/link]), he must have visited Ephesus and Macedonia ([link]1 Tim. 1:3[/link]), where he probably wrote the first Epistle to Timothy. Then he visited Crete ([link]Titus 1:5[/link]); Nicopolis ([link]Titus 3:12[/link]), where he wrote the Epistle to Titus; Troas; and Miletus ([link]vv. 13[/link], [link]20[/link]), where he probably wrote the Epistle to the Hebrews. During his second imprisonment, which occurred in about A.D. 67 and was due to Caesar Nero's sudden persecution, he wrote the second Epistle to Timothy while expecting his imminent martyrdom for his Master.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Phil. 2:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Phil. 1:23[/link]; cf. [link]2 Pet. 1:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>I have [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]fought the good fight; I have [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]finished the course; I have kept the [xref]c[/xref]faith.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., struggled the good struggle. A proper Christian life has three aspects: fighting the good fight against Satan and his kingdom of darkness for the interests of God's kingdom ([link]1 Tim. 6:12[/link]); running the course for the carrying out of God's economy according to His eternal purpose ([link]Heb. 12:1[/link]); and keeping the faith for participation in the divine riches in God's economy ([link]1 Tim. 3:9[/link]). In this Paul set up an adequate pattern for us.</note>
        <note num="2">Paul began to run the heavenly race after the Lord took possession of him, and he continually ran ([link]1 Cor. 9:24-26[/link]; [link]Phil. 3:12-14[/link]) that he might finish it ([link]Acts 20:24[/link]). Now at the end he triumphantly proclaimed, "I have finished the course." For this he will receive from the Lord a reward &amp;#8212; the crown of righteousness.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 1:18[/link]; [link]6:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Cor. 9:26[/link]; [link]Heb. 12:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Tim. 1:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Henceforth there is [note]1[/note]laid up for me the [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]crown of [xref]b[/xref]righteousness, with which the Lord, the [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]righteous Judge, will [xref]d[/xref]recompense me in [note]4[/note][xref]e[/xref]that day, and not only me but also all those who have [xref]f[/xref]loved His [note]5[/note][xref]g[/xref]appearing.</text>
        <note num="1">Reserved.</note>
        <note num="2">The crown, a symbol of glory, is given as a prize, in addition to the Lord's salvation, to the triumphant runner of the race ([link]1 Cor. 9:25[/link]). In contrast to salvation, which is of grace and by faith ([link]Eph. 2:5[/link], [link]8-9[/link]), this prize is not of grace nor by faith, but is of righteousness through works ([link]Matt. 16:27[/link]; [link]Rev. 22:12[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 5:10[/link]). The believers will be recompensed with such a reward, not according to the Lord's grace but according to His righteousness. Hence, it is the crown of righteousness. The Recompenser is the Lord as the righteous Judge. Paul was assured that such a prize was reserved for him and that he would be recompensed with it at the day of the Lord's second appearing.</note>
        <note num="3">Not the merciful God or the gracious Redeemer.</note>
        <note num="4">See note [link]12[sup]5[/sup] in ch. 1[/link].</note>
        <note num="5">The Lord's appearing, His coming back, is a warning, an encouragement, and an incentive to us. We should love it and look forward to it with earnest expectation and joy. By that appearing the apostle charged Timothy to fulfill his ministry ([link]vv. 1-2[/link], [link]5[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 2:5[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 9:25[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 5:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Cor. 5:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Acts 17:31[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Matt. 16:27[/link]; [link]Rev. 22:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]2 Tim. 1:12[/link], [link]18[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 3:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]Titus 2:13[/link]; [link]Rev. 22:20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="g">[link]2 Tim. 4:1[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Be diligent to [xref]a[/xref]come to me quickly;</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Titus 3:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>For [xref]a[/xref]Demas has [xref]b[/xref]abandoned me, having [note]1[/note][xref]c[/xref]loved the [xref]d[/xref]present age, and has gone to [xref]e[/xref]Thessalonica; Crescens to [xref]f[/xref]Galatia; [xref]g[/xref]Titus to [note]2[/note]Dalmatia.</text>
        <note num="1">In contrast to [i]loved His appearing[/i] in [link]v. 8[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">A region in southeast Europe adjacent to Macedonia.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 4:14[/link]; [link]Philem. 24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Tim. 1:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 John 2:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Tim. 6:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Acts 17:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]Acts 16:6[/link]; [link]18:23[/link]; [link]Gal. 1:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="g">[link]Titus 1:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Luke alone is with me. Take [xref]b[/xref]Mark and bring [i]him[/i] with you, for he is useful to me for the [xref]c[/xref]ministry.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 4:14[/link]; [link]Philem. 24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 12:12[/link], [link]25[/link]; [link]15:37[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 5:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Tim. 1:12[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 4:1[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>But [xref]a[/xref]Tychicus I have sent to [xref]b[/xref]Ephesus.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 20:4[/link]; [link]Eph. 6:21[/link]; [link]Titus 3:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 18:19[/link]; [link]19:1[/link]; [link]Rev. 1:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>The [note]1[/note]cloak which I left in [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]Troas with Carpus, bring when you come, and the [note]3[/note]scrolls, especially the parchments.</text>
        <note num="1">Probably a cloak or case for traveling.</note>
        <note num="2">A seaport in northwest Asia Minor, where Paul received the Macedonian call ([link]Acts 16:8-11[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">Rolls made of papyrus.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 16:8[/link]; [link]20:5-6[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 2:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Alexander the coppersmith did many evil things to me; the Lord will [xref]b[/xref]recompense him according to his works.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 1:20[/link]; cf. [link]Acts 19:33[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 2:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>You also guard against him, for he greatly opposed our words.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>At my first defense no one was with me to support me, but all [xref]a[/xref]abandoned me. May it not be counted against them.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 1:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>But the Lord [xref]a[/xref]stood with me and [xref]b[/xref]empowered me that through me the [xref]c[/xref]proclamation [i]of the gospel[/i] might be fully accomplished and all the [xref]d[/xref]Gentiles might hear; and I was [xref]e[/xref]delivered out of the [note]1[/note][xref]f[/xref]lion's mouth.</text>
        <note num="1">A figure of speech for any evil matter ([link]v. 18[/link]) or evil person ([link]1 Cor. 15:32[/link] and note 2).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 23:11[/link]; cf. [link]Acts 27:23[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 1:12[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 2:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Titus 1:3[/link]; [link]Rom. 15:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Acts 9:15[/link]; [link]Eph. 3:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]2 Tim. 3:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]Psa. 22:21[/link]; [link]1 Sam. 17:37[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>The Lord will [xref]a[/xref]deliver me from every evil work and will save me into [xref]b[/xref]His [note]1[/note]heavenly kingdom, to whom be the [xref]c[/xref]glory forever and ever. Amen.</text>
        <note num="1">This is "the kingdom of their Father" ([link]Matt. 13:43[/link]), "the kingdom of My Father" ([link]Matt. 26:29[/link]), "the kingdom of Christ and of God" ([link]Eph. 5:5[/link]), and "the eternal kingdom of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ" ([link]2 Pet. 1:11[/link]), which will be a reward to the overcoming saints. It equals the crown of righteousness in [link]v. 8[/link] and is an incentive to the believers to run the heavenly race. (See notes [link]3[sup]4[/sup] in Matt. 5[/link] and [link]28[sup]1[/sup] in Heb. 12[/link].) The apostle Paul's word here and in [link]v. 8[/link] proves that this reward was an incentive to him.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Matt. 6:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Tim. 4:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rom. 11:36[/link]; [link]16:27[/link]; [link]Heb. 13:21[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Greet Prisca and [xref]a[/xref]Aquila and the house of [xref]b[/xref]Onesiphorus.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 18:2[/link], [link]26[/link]; [link]Rom. 16:3[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 16:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Tim. 1:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Erastus remained in [xref]b[/xref]Corinth, and [xref]c[/xref]Trophimus I left at [note]1[/note][xref]d[/xref]Miletus [note]2[/note]sick.</text>
        <note num="1">A city in Asia Minor near Ephesus ([link]Acts 20:15[/link], [link]17[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Why did the apostle leave in sickness one who was so intimate to him, without exercising healing prayer for him? Why did he not exercise his healing gift ([link]Acts 19:11-12[/link]) to cure Timothy of his stomach sickness rather than instruct him to take the natural way for healing ([link]1 Tim. 5:23[/link])? The answer to both questions is that he and his co-workers were under the discipline of the inner life in that time of suffering rather than under the power of the outward gift. The former is a matter of grace in life; the latter is a matter of gift in power &amp;#8212; miraculous power. In the decline of the church and in one's suffering for the church, the gift of power is not needed as much as the grace in life.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 19:22[/link]; [link]Rom. 16:23[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 18:1[/link]; [link]19:1[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 1:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Acts 20:4[/link]; [link]21:29[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Acts 20:15[/link], [link]17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Be diligent to come before [xref]a[/xref]winter. Eubulus greets you, as well as Pudens and Linus and Claudia and all the brothers.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Titus 3:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>The Lord be with your [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]spirit. [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]Grace be with you.</text>
        <note num="1">This book, which gives instructions on how to confront the degradation of the church, strongly stresses our spirit. In the beginning it emphasizes that a strong, loving, and sound spirit was given to us, a spirit by which we can fan the gift of God into flame and suffer evil with the gospel according to the power of God and the Lord's life-imparting grace ([link]1:6-10[/link]). In the conclusion it blesses us by emphasizing the Lord's being with our spirit that we may enjoy Him as grace in order to stand against the downward current of the church's decline and carry out God's economy through His indwelling Spirit ([link]1:14[/link]) and equipping word ([link]3:16-17[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">In the grievous days of the worsening of the church's degradation, what is needed is the eternal grace of God, which was given to us in eternity ([link]1:9[/link]) and is to be appropriated by us in this age. This grace, which is in the indestructible life, is nothing less than Christ, the Son of God, who is the very embodiment of the divine life, dwelling and living in our spirit. We need to exercise our spirit to enjoy the riches of this Christ ([link]Eph. 3:8[/link]) as the sufficient grace ([link]2 Cor. 12:9[/link]). Thus we may live Him as our godliness ([link]1 Tim. 4:7-8[/link]) for the building up of the church as His testimony, bearing all the divine realities (truths) according to God's economy.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gal. 6:18[/link]; [link]Phil. 4:23[/link]; [link]Philem. 25[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 1:14[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 1:9[/link]; [link]2:1[/link]; [link]Titus 2:11[/link]; [link]3:7[/link]; [link]Col. 4:18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    </chapters>
</book>
