<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book name="3 John" description="THE THIRD EPISTLE OF JOHN" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="..\bible.xsd">
    <info title="Author">John the elder ([link]v. 1[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Time of Writing">After the second Epistle was written; see introductions to 1 and 2 John.</info>
    <info title="Place of Writing">The same as the second Epistle; see introduction to 2 John.</info>
    <subject>Encouragement to the Fellow Workers in the Truth</subject>
    <outlines>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="1" ref="vv. 1-4">Introduction</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="v. 1">Loving in Truthfulness</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="v. 2">Prospering in All Things and in Health</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="vv. 3-4">Walking in the Truth</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="2" ref="vv. 5-8">Hospitality to the Traveling Workers</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="vv. 5-6">Given Faithfully, in Love, and in a Manner Worthy of God</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="vv. 7-8">By the Fellow Workers in the Truth</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="3" ref="vv. 9-12">Imitation Not of the Evil but of the Good</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="vv. 9-11">The Self-exalting and Domineering Diotrephes &amp;#8212; An Evil Pattern</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="v. 12">The Well-reported Demetrius &amp;#8212; A Good Example</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="4" ref="vv. 13-14">Conclusion</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="vv. 13-14a">The Hope for Closer Fellowship</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="v. 14b">Mutual Greetings</outline>
    </outlines>
    <chapters>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>The [note]1[/note]elder to [note]2[/note]Gaius the [xref]a[/xref]beloved, whom I [xref]b[/xref]love in [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]truthfulness.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]1[sup]1[/sup] in 2 John[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Not the Gaius of Macedonia in [link]Acts 19:29[/link], nor the Gaius of Derbe in [link]Acts 20:4[/link], nor the Gaius of Corinth in [link]1 Cor. 1:14[/link] and [link]Rom. 16:23[/link], but another named Gaius (the name was very common at that time). According to the contents of this Epistle, he must have been an outstanding brother in the church.</note>
        <note num="3">See note [link]1[sup]3[/sup] in 2 John[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]3 John 2[/link], [link]5[/link], [link]11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 John 1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 John 3:18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Beloved, concerning [note]1[/note]all things I [note]2[/note]wish that you may [note]3[/note]prosper and be in [note]4[/note]health, even as your [note]5[/note]soul [note]3[/note]prospers.</text>
        <note num="1">According to the context of the verse, this refers to external and material things.</note>
        <note num="2">Probably in the sense of prayer.</note>
        <note num="3">The Greek word means [i]to go on well,[/i] as in a journey ([link]Rom. 1:10[/link]). I.e., to succeed in reaching a desired end; thus, to prosper.</note>
        <note num="4">Bodily health, as in [link]Luke 5:31[/link]; [link]7:10[/link]; and [link]15:27[/link].</note>
        <note num="5">Man is of three parts: spirit, soul, and body ([link]1 Thes. 5:23[/link] and note 5). The soul is the organ that mediates between the body and the spirit; it possesses self-consciousness, that man may have his personality. It is contained in the body and is the vessel to contain the spirit. As to the believer, God as the Spirit dwells in his regenerated spirit ([link]Rom. 8:9[/link], [link]16[/link]) and spreads from his spirit to saturate his soul that it may be transformed to express Him ([link]Rom. 12:2[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 3:18[/link]). This is the prosperity of the believer's soul. When our soul is occupied and directed by the Spirit of God through our spirit so that it directs and uses our body for God's purposes, it prospers. The apostle wished that the recipient, who was a beloved brother, outstanding in such a prosperity of his soul, might prosper in all things and in bodily health, just as his soul prospered in the divine life.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>For I [note]1[/note]rejoiced greatly at the brothers' coming and [xref]a[/xref]testifying to [note]2[/note]your [i]steadfastness in the[/i] truth, even as you [note]3[/note]walk in [note]4[/note]truth.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]4[sup]1[/sup] in 2 John[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., your truth. This is the truth concerning Christ, especially His deity (see note [link]1[sup]5[/sup] in 2 John[/link]). By the revelation of this truth the recipient's way of life was determined, and the recipient held to this truth as his fundamental belief. It is the objective truth that had become subjective in the recipient's daily walk.</note>
        <note num="3">The recipient not only held to the truth but also walked and lived in the truth. The truth concerning the person of Christ should be not only our belief but also our living, a living that testifies to our belief.</note>
        <note num="4">See note 4[sup]2[/sup] in [link]v. 4[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]3 John 6[/link], [link]12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>I have no greater joy than these things, that I hear that my [xref]a[/xref]children are walking in the [xref]b[/xref]truth.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 4:14-15[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 2:11[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 1:2[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 1:2[/link]; [link]Titus 1:4[/link]; [link]Philem. 10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. [link]Prov. 23:23[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Beloved, you do [xref]b[/xref]faithfully in [note]1[/note]whatever you have wrought for the brothers, and this [i]for[/i] [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]strangers,</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to the providing of hospitality (as taught by Paul in [link]Rom. 12:13[/link] and [link]Heb. 13:2[/link]), the receiving of the brothers ([link]vv. 7-8[/link]) who traveled for the gospel and the ministry of the word.</note>
        <note num="2">Most of the recipients of the hospitality were strangers, unacquainted with Gaius.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]3 John 1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Cor. 4:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">cf. [link]Matt. 25:35[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Who [xref]a[/xref]testified to your [note]1[/note]love before the [note]2[/note]church; whom you [note]3[/note]will do well to [xref]b[/xref]send forward in a manner [note]4[/note][xref]c[/xref]worthy of God;</text>
        <note num="1">In the past.</note>
        <note num="2">The church where the apostle was.</note>
        <note num="3">In the future. On one hand, the apostle praised Gaius for what he had done in receiving the traveling brothers in the past; on the other hand, he encouraged him to send them forward in the future.</note>
        <note num="4">The sending forward should be in a manner that matches God, who is generous, indicating that the sending forward must be with generosity.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]3 John 3[/link], [link]12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Cor. 16:6[/link], [link]11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Col. 1:10[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 2:12[/link]; cf. [link]Eph. 4:1[/link]; [link]2 Thes. 1:5[/link], [link]11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>For on behalf of the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Name they went out, taking nothing from the [note]2[/note]Gentiles.</text>
        <note num="1">The exalted and glorious name of the wonderful Christ ([link]Phil. 2:9[/link] and note 3; [link]Acts 5:41[/link]; [link]James 2:7[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">The pagans, who have nothing to do with God's move on this earth to carry out His economy. If anyone who works for God's New Testament economy receives help for God's work, especially financial support, from the unbelievers, this is a shame and even an insult to God. In the apostle's time, the brothers who worked for God took nothing from the pagans.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]John 15:21[/link]; [link]Acts 4:10[/link]; [link]9:28[/link]; [link]16:18[/link]; [link]19:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>We therefore ought to [note]1[/note]support such ones that we may become [xref]a[/xref]fellow workers in the [note]2[/note]truth.</text>
        <note num="1">The Greek word is made up of two words: [i]under[/i] and [i]to take;[/i] thus, to take up (from underneath), that is, to undertake, to sustain, to support. We, the believers, including the apostle, ought to support and undertake for the needs of the brothers who work for God in His divine truth and who take nothing from the Gentiles.</note>
        <note num="2">Denoting the revealed divine reality as the contents of the New Testament, according to the apostles' teaching concerning the Divine Trinity, especially the person of the Lord Jesus, for God's economy. All the apostles and faithful brothers worked for this.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Phil. 2:25[/link]; [link]4:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>I wrote something to the [note]1[/note]church; but [note]2[/note]Diotrephes, who loves [note]3[/note]to be [xref]a[/xref]first among them, does not [note]4[/note]receive us.</text>
        <note num="1">Of which Gaius was a member.</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word is made up of [i]of Zeus[/i] (Zeus was the chief of the gods in the Greek pantheon) and [i]to nourish;[/i] hence, Zeus-nourished. This indicates that Diotrephes, a professing Christian, never dropped his pagan name, contrary to the practice of the early believers, who took a Christian name at their baptism. According to history, he advocated the Gnostic heresy, which blasphemed the person of Christ. It is no wonder that he mingled with the believers as one who loved to be first among them.</note>
        <note num="3">This is against the words of the Lord in [link]Matt. 20:25-27[/link] and [link]23:8-11[/link], which keep all His believers on the same level, that of brothers. In [link]2 John 9[/link] the Cerinthian Gnostics took the lead to advance in doctrine beyond the teaching concerning Christ. Here in [link]3 John 9[/link] is one who was under the influence of Gnostic heretical doctrine and loved to be first in the church. The former was a matter of intellectual arrogance; the latter, of self-exaltation in one's actions. These two evils are sharp weapons used by God's enemy, Satan, to execute his evil plot against God's economy. One damages the believers' faith in the divine reality; the other frustrates the believers' work in God's move.</note>
        <note num="4">I.e., receive hospitably.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Matt. 23:6[/link]; [link]Mark 12:38-39[/link]; [link]Luke 11:43[/link]; [link]20:46[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>For this reason, if I come, I will bring to remembrance his works which he does, [note]1[/note]babbling against us with [note]2[/note]evil words; and not being satisfied with these, neither does he himself receive the brothers, and those intending to [i]do so[/i] he forbids and [xref]a[/xref]casts out of the church.</text>
        <note num="1">The Greek word is derived from a word meaning [i]to boil over, to overflow with words, to talk idly;[/i] hence, to babble, to speak folly or nonsense.</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word means [i]pernicious,[/i] as in [link]1 John 5:19[/link] (see note 4 there).</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]John 9:22[/link], [link]34[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Beloved, do not [xref]a[/xref]imitate the [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]evil, but the good. He who [note]2[/note]does [xref]c[/xref]good is [note]3[/note]of God; he who [note]4[/note]does evil has [note]5[/note][xref]d[/xref]not seen God.</text>
        <note num="1">The Greek word means [i]worthless, wicked, depraved.[/i]</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word means [i]to be a well-doer[/i] (as a favor or a duty), [i]practicing good;[/i] hence, to do good.</note>
        <note num="3">Lit., out of (see note [link]19[sup]1[/sup] in 1 John 5[/link]). God is the source of good. A well-doer, a doer of good, is one who is out of God and who belongs to God (cf. [link]1 John 3:8[/link]).</note>
        <note num="4">The Greek word means [i]to[/i] be an evildoer, practicing evil; hence, to do evil.</note>
        <note num="5">An evildoer not only is not out of God but has not even seen God.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 4:16[/link]; [link]11:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Pet. 3:11[/link]; [link]Psa. 34:14[/link]; [link]37:27[/link]; [link]Isa. 1:16-17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]John 5:29[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 John 3:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>To [note]1[/note]Demetrius [xref]a[/xref]testimony has been borne by [note]2[/note]all and by the [note]3[/note]truth itself; and [note]4[/note]we also testify, and you know that our testimony is [note]5[/note][xref]b[/xref]true.</text>
        <note num="1">Demetrius, who might have been one of the brothers who traveled in working for the Lord ([link]vv. 5-8[/link]), perhaps was the one who bore this Epistle to Gaius. Hence, it was necessary that he receive a favorable and strong commendation from the writer.</note>
        <note num="2">This indicates that Demetrius must have been a brother working among the churches, and thus was well known.</note>
        <note num="3">The revealed truth of God as the reality of the essence of the Christian faith (see note [link]6[sup]6[/sup] in 1 John 1[/link]). This truth is the divine rule for the walk of all believers, and by it the believers' walk is determined. Thus, it gives good testimony to him who walks in it, as it did to Demetrius.</note>
        <note num="4">The apostle John and his associates.</note>
        <note num="5">The Greek word (an adjective akin to [i]truth (reality)[/i] &amp;#8212; cf. note [link]20[sup]5[/sup] in 1 John 5[/link]) means [i]genuine, real;[/i] hence, true.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]3 John 3[/link], [link]6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]John 19:35[/link]; [link]21:24[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>I had [xref]a[/xref]many things to write to you, but I do not want to write to you with ink and pen;</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 John 12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>But I [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]hope to see you shortly, and we will speak [note]2[/note]face to face.[separator]Peace to you. The [xref]b[/xref]friends greet you. Greet the friends by [xref]c[/xref]name.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]12[sup]1[/sup] in 2 John[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., mouth to mouth.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 John 12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]John 11:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">cf. [link]John 10:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    </chapters>
</book>
