<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book name="Colossians" description="THE EPISTLE OF PAUL TO THE COLOSSIANS" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="..\bible.xsd">
    <info title="Author">Paul the apostle with Timothy the brother ([link]1:1[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Time of Writing">Approximately A.D. 64, when the Epistle to Philemon was written ([link]4:9[/link]; [link]Philem. 10-12[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Place of Writing">Rome, where Paul was imprisoned ([link]4:3[/link], [link]10[/link], [link]18[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Recipients">The saints in Colossae ([link]1:2[/link]).</info>
    <subject>Christ &amp;#8212; The All-inclusive One, Having the First Place in All Things as the Mystery and Embodiment of God, as the Head and Constituent of the Church, as the Allotted Portion, Life, Constituent, and Hope of the Saints, and as the Body of All Positive Things</subject>
    <outlines>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="1" ref="1:1-8">Introduction</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="vv. 1-2">The Apostle's Greeting</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="vv. 3-8">The Apostle's Thanksgiving</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="2" ref="1:9-3:11">The Preeminent and All-inclusive One, the Centrality and Universality of God</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="1:9-14">The Portion of the Saints</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="1:15-23">The Image of God and the Firstborn Both in Creation and in Resurrection</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="1:24-29">The Mystery of God's Economy</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="4" ref="2:1-7">The Mystery of God</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="5" ref="2:8-23">The Body of All the Shadows</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="6" ref="3:1-4">The Life of the Saints</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="7" ref="3:5-11">The Constituents of the New Man</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="3" ref="3:12-4:6">A Living in Union with Christ</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="3:12-15">The Arbitrating Peace of Christ</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="3:16-17">The Indwelling Word of Christ</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="3:18-4:1">The Expression of Christ in Ethical Relationships</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="4" ref="4:2-6">Praying with Perseverance and Walking in Wisdom</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="4" ref="4:7-18">Conclusion</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="vv. 7-17">The Apostle's Fellowship</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="v. 18">The Apostle's Greeting</outline>
    </outlines>
    <chapters>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus through the [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]will of God, and [xref]b[/xref]Timothy the brother,</text>
        <note num="1">The background of this book is that culture had been mixed into the church life in Colossae. Originally, Christ was the unique element in the church life, yet at that time a disturbance was created because Christ was being replaced by culture. The constituent of the church should be Christ and Christ alone, yet the church had been invaded by certain elements of culture &amp;#8212; especially religion, in the form of asceticism related to Judaic ordinances and observances ([link]2:16[/link], [link]20-21[/link]), and philosophy, in the form of mysticism related to Gnosticism and the worship of angels ([link]2:8[/link], [link]18[/link]). Hence, the central concept of this book is that nothing should be allowed to replace Christ.[br][br]This book concentrates on Christ as the Head of the Body. It reveals the profoundness, all-inclusiveness, and unlimitedness of Christ to a fuller extent than any other book in the Bible.</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]1[sup]2[/sup] in Eph. 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 1:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Cor. 1:1[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 3:2[/link]; [link]Heb. 13:23[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>To the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]saints in Colossae and faithful brothers in Christ: [xref]b[/xref]Grace to you and peace from God our [xref]c[/xref]Father.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., the holy ones, those separated and sanctified unto God. They were living in Colossae, but they were separated from the world.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 1:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]John 1:17[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Eph. 1:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>We give thanks to God, the [note]1[/note]Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, praying always concerning you,</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]3[sup]2[/sup] in Eph. 1[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Because we have heard of your [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]faith in Christ Jesus and the [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]love which you have unto all the saints</text>
        <note num="1">To have faith is to substantiate and receive what is in Christ, to love is to experience and enjoy what we have received of Christ, and to hope ([link]v. 5[/link]) is to expect and wait for the glorification in Christ.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 2:5[/link], [link]7[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 1:3[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 13:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Col. 1:8[/link][br/]See note 4[sup]1[/sup].</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Because of the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]hope [note]2[/note]laid up for you in the heavens, of which you heard before in the [xref]b[/xref]word of the [note]3[/note]truth of the gospel,</text>
        <note num="1">Hope, faith, and love, mentioned in [link]vv. 4[/link] and [link]5[/link], are the three things that the apostle stressed in [link]1 Cor. 13:13[/link]. The emphasis there was on love because of the Corinthians' situation; the emphasis here is on hope, which, strictly speaking, is Christ Himself ([link]v. 27[/link]), that Christ may be revealed as everything to us.</note>
        <note num="2">It is by living and experiencing Christ that we lay up hope in the heavens. The more we live and experience Christ, the more we lay up hope in the heavens. Hence, hope is being laid up now in our daily life.</note>
        <note num="3">The truth of the gospel is the reality, the real facts, not the doctrine, of the gospel. "The word" may be considered the doctrine of the gospel, but "the truth" must refer to reality. Christ, in His all-inclusive person and His multifaceted redemptive work, is the reality of the gospel.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 1:23[/link], [link]27[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:18[/link]; [link]4:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Eph. 1:13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Which has come to you, even as it is also in all the world, bearing fruit and growing, as also in you, since the day you heard and knew the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]grace of God in [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]truth;</text>
        <note num="1">The grace of God is what God is to us and what God gives to us in Christ ([link]John 1:17[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 15:10[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">[i]Truth[/i] here means reality (see point 8 of note [link]6[sup]6[/sup] in 1 John 1[/link]). To know the grace of God in truth is to know it experientially in its reality, not just mentally in vain words or doctrines.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 4:33[/link]; [link]11:23[/link]; [link]Rom. 5:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 1:25[/link]; [link]John 16:7[/link]; [link]Mark 5:33[/link]; [link]12:32[/link]; [link]Luke 4:25[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Even as you learned from [xref]a[/xref]Epaphras, our beloved fellow slave, who is a faithful [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]minister of Christ on your behalf,</text>
        <note num="1">A minister of Christ is not only a servant of Christ, one who serves Christ, but a serving one who serves others with Christ by ministering Christ to them.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 4:12[/link]; [link]Philem. 23[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Col. 4:7[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Who also has made known to us your [xref]a[/xref]love in the Spirit.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 15:30[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:22[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Therefore we also, since the day we heard of [i]it,[/i] do not cease [xref]a[/xref]praying and asking on your behalf that you may be filled with the full knowledge of [note]1[/note]His [xref]b[/xref]will in all [note]2[/note]spiritual [xref]c[/xref]wisdom and understanding,</text>
        <note num="1">Here God's will is His will regarding His eternal purpose, regarding His economy concerning Christ ([link]Eph. 1:5[/link], [link]9[/link], [link]11[/link]), not His will regarding minor things.</note>
        <note num="2">Spiritual wisdom and understanding are of the Spirit of God in our spirit, in contrast to Gnostic philosophy, which is merely in the darkened human mind. Wisdom is in our spirit and is for us to perceive God's eternal will; spiritual understanding is in our mind, renewed by the Spirit, and is for us to understand and interpret what we perceive in our spirit.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 1:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Eph. 1:9[/link]; [link]Rom. 12:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Eph. 1:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>To [note]1[/note]walk worthily of the Lord to please [i]Him[/i] [note]2[/note]in all things, [note]3[/note]bearing fruit in every good work and growing by the full [note]4[/note]knowledge of God,</text>
        <note num="1">Walking worthily of the Lord issues from having the full knowledge of God's will. Such a worthy walk is a walk in which we live Christ.</note>
        <note num="2">I.e., in all ways.</note>
        <note num="3">Here [i]bearing fruit[/i] refers to living Christ, growing Christ, expressing Christ, and propagating Christ in every respect. This is the real essence of every Christian good work.</note>
        <note num="4">Not knowledge in letters in the mind but the living knowledge of God in spirit, by means of which we grow in life.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Being [xref]a[/xref]empowered with all [note]1[/note]power, according to the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]might of His glory, unto all endurance and long-suffering with joy,</text>
        <note num="1">This power is not only the power of Christ's resurrection ([link]Phil. 3:10[/link]) but Christ Himself as a dynamo that empowers us in all things ([link]Phil. 4:13[/link]) unto all endurance and long-suffering with joy that we may have a living in which we experience and live Christ.</note>
        <note num="2">The might that expresses God's glory, glorifying God in His might.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 6:10[/link]; [link]Phil. 4:13[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 2:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Eph. 1:19[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Giving thanks to the Father, who has [note]1[/note]qualified you for a share of the [note]2[/note]allotted [xref]a[/xref]portion of the saints in the [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]light;</text>
        <note num="1">God the Father has qualified us by the redemption of God the Son and through the sanctification of God the Spirit for a share of the all-inclusive Christ, the very embodiment of the processed Triune God, as the allotted portion of the saints.</note>
        <note num="2">This refers to the lot of the inheritance, as illustrated by the allotment of the good land of Canaan given to the children of Israel for their inheritance ([link]Josh. 14:1[/link]). The New Testament believers' inheritance, their allotted portion, is not a physical land; it is the all-inclusive Christ. He is the allotted portion of the saints as their divine inheritance for their enjoyment.</note>
        <note num="3">Light here is in contrast to darkness in the next verse. When we were under Satan's authority, we were in darkness. But now we are in the kingdom of the Son of God's love, enjoying Him in light.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Acts 20:32[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 26:18[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 2:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Who [note]1[/note]delivered us out of the authority of [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]darkness and transferred [i]us[/i] into the [xref]b[/xref]kingdom of the [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]Son of His love,</text>
        <note num="1">For Christ to be the Head of the Body, and for us, His believers, to be the members of His Body, God needed to deliver us out of the authority of darkness, the kingdom of Satan ([link]Matt. 12:26b[/link]), and transfer us into the kingdom of the Son of His love. This is to qualify us to partake of the all-inclusive Christ as our allotted portion.</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., the darkness.</note>
        <note num="3">The Son is the expression of the Father as the source of life ([link]John 1:4[/link], [link]18[/link]; [link]1 John 1:2[/link]). The beloved Son as the object of the Father's love becomes to us the embodiment of life in the divine love.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 26:18[/link]; [link]Eph. 6:12[/link]; [link]Luke 22:53[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 2:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Eph. 5:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Matt. 3:17[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>In whom we have [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]redemption, the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]forgiveness of sins;</text>
        <note num="1">Deliverance, mentioned in the preceding verse, deals with Satan's authority over us by destroying his evil power, whereas redemption, mentioned in this verse, deals with our sins by fulfilling God's righteous requirement.</note>
        <note num="2">The forgiveness of sins is the redemption that we have in Christ. Christ's death accomplished redemption unto the forgiveness of our sins.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 1:7[/link]; [link]Rom. 3:24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Luke 24:47[/link]; [link]Acts 2:38[/link]; [link]10:43[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Who is the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]image of the [xref]b[/xref]invisible God, the [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]Firstborn of all creation,</text>
        <note num="1">God is invisible. But the Son of His love, who is the effulgence of His glory and the impress of His substance ([link]Heb. 1:3[/link]), is His image, expressing what He is. The image here is not a physical form but an expression of God's being in all His attributes and virtues (see note [link]6[sup]2[/sup] in Phil. 2[/link]). This interpretation is confirmed by [link]3:10[/link] and [link]2 Cor. 3:18[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Christ as God is the Creator. However, as man, sharing the created blood and flesh ([link]Heb. 2:14a[/link]), He is part of the creation. [i]Firstborn of all creation[/i] refers to Christ's preeminence in all creation, because from this verse through [link]v. 18[/link] the apostle stresses the first place that Christ has in all things.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 3:10[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 4:4[/link]; [link]Gen. 1:26[/link]; [link]Heb. 1:3[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 3:18[/link]; [link]Rom. 8:29[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 1:17[/link]; [link]Heb. 11:27[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">cf. [link]Rev. 3:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Because [note]1[/note]in Him all things were created, in the heavens and on the earth, the visible and the invisible, whether [note]2[/note]thrones or [note]3[/note][xref]a[/xref]lordships or rulers or authorities; all things have been created [note]4[/note][xref]b[/xref]through Him and [note]5[/note]unto Him.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]In Him[/i] here means in the power of Christ's person. All things were created in the power of what Christ is. All creation bears the characteristics of Christ's intrinsic power.</note>
        <note num="2">[i]Thrones[/i] refers to those who are in authority on the throne.</note>
        <note num="3">See note [link]21[sup]1[/sup] in Eph. 1[/link].</note>
        <note num="4">[i]Through Him[/i] indicates that Christ is the active instrument through which the creation of all things was accomplished in sequence.</note>
        <note num="5">Or, for Him. This indicates that Christ is the end of all creation. All things were created unto Him for His possession. [i]In, through,[/i] and [i]unto[/i] indicate that creation is subjectively related to Christ. The creation was created in Him, through Him, and unto Him.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 1:21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]John 1:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And He is [note]1[/note]before all things, and all things [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]cohere in Him;</text>
        <note num="1">This indicates Christ's eternal preexistence.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, subsist together in Him. To cohere in Christ is to exist together by Christ as the holding center, just as the spokes of a wheel are held together by the hub at their center.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Heb. 1:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And He is the [xref]a[/xref]Head of the [xref]b[/xref]Body, the church; He is the [xref]c[/xref]beginning, the [note]1[/note][xref]d[/xref]Firstborn from the dead, that He Himself might have the first place in all things;</text>
        <note num="1">[link]Verses 15-17[/link] unveil Christ as the first in creation, as the One who has preeminence among all creatures. [link]Verse 18[/link] shows that Christ is the first in resurrection as the Head of the Body. As such, He has the first place in the church, God's new creation ([link]2 Cor. 5:17[/link]; [link]Gal. 6:15[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 1:22-23[/link]; [link]4:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Cor. 12:12[/link]; [link]Rom. 12:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rev. 21:6[/link]; [link]22:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Cor. 15:20[/link], [link]23[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>For in Him [note]1[/note]all the [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]fullness was pleased to dwell</text>
        <note num="1">[i]All the fullness[/i] refers to the fullness in both the old creation and the new creation.</note>
        <note num="2">The word [i]fullness[/i] has no modifier, indicating that this fullness is the unique fullness. It denotes not the riches of what God is but the expression of those riches. The full expression of the rich being of God, in both creation and the church, dwells in Christ. All creation and the whole church are filled with Christ as the expression of God's riches. Such a fullness is pleased with this. This is pleasant to Christ.[br][br]The fullness in this verse refers to the image of God in [link]v. 15[/link], who is Christ, a living person. Such a fullness is pleased to dwell in the expression of God and to reconcile all things to the expression of God.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 2:9[/link]; [link]John 1:16[/link]; [link]Eph. 3:19[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And [note]1[/note]through Him to [xref]a[/xref]reconcile [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]all things to [note]3[/note]Himself, [note]4[/note][xref]c[/xref]having made peace through the [xref]d[/xref]blood of His cross &amp;#8212; [note]1[/note]through Him, whether the [xref]e[/xref]things on the earth or the things in the [note]5[/note]heavens.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Through Him[/i] means through Christ as the active instrument through which the reconciliation was accomplished.</note>
        <note num="2">Not "all people" but "all things," referring not only to human beings but also to all creatures, which were created in Christ and now subsist, cohere, in Him ([link]vv. 16-17[/link]) and are reconciled to God through Him.</note>
        <note num="3">[i]Himself[/i] here refers to the fullness in [link]v. 19[/link].</note>
        <note num="4">To reconcile all things to Himself is to make peace with Himself for all things. This was accomplished through the blood of the cross of Christ.</note>
        <note num="5">Not only things on the earth but also things in the heavens needed to be reconciled to God. This indicates that things in the heavens also are wrong with God because of the rebellion of Satan, the archangel, and the angels who followed him. His rebellion has contaminated the heavens.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Cor. 5:18[/link]; [link]Eph. 2:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 2:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Eph. 2:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Eph. 2:13[/link]; [link]1:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Eph. 1:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And you, though once [xref]a[/xref]alienated and [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]enemies in your [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]mind because of your evil works,</text>
        <note num="1">Because we were sinners, we needed redemption. Because we were also enemies of God, we needed reconciliation.</note>
        <note num="2">Our enmity toward God was mainly in our corrupted mind.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 2:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 5:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Eph. 4:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>[note]1[/note]He now has reconciled in the body of His flesh through death, to present you [xref]a[/xref]holy and without blemish and without reproach before [note]1[/note]Him;</text>
        <note num="1">Both [i]He[/i] and [i]Him[/i] refer to the fullness in [link]v. 19[/link]. It is the fullness that dwells in Christ ([link]v. 19[/link]), it is the fullness that reconciles us to Himself ([link]v. 20[/link]), and it is to the fullness that we will be presented. This fullness is God Himself expressed in Christ.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 1:4[/link]; [link]5:27[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>If indeed you continue in the [note]1[/note]faith, [xref]a[/xref]grounded and steadfast and not being moved away from the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]hope of the gospel, which you heard, which was proclaimed in [xref]c[/xref]all creation under heaven, of which I Paul became a [xref]d[/xref]minister.</text>
        <note num="1">Not our act of believing but the object of our belief.</note>
        <note num="2">Christ in us the hope of glory ([link]v. 27[/link]), from whom we should not be moved away.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 3:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Col. 1:5[/link], [link]27[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:18[/link]; [link]4:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Mark 16:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Col. 1:25[/link]; [link]Eph. 3:7[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 3:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>I now [xref]a[/xref]rejoice in my sufferings on your behalf and [note]1[/note]fill up on my part that which is lacking of the [xref]b[/xref]afflictions of Christ in my flesh for His [xref]c[/xref]Body, which is the church;</text>
        <note num="1">The afflictions of Christ are of two categories: those for accomplishing redemption, which were completed by Christ Himself, and those for producing and building the church, which need to be filled up by the apostles and the believers.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Phil. 2:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Cor. 1:5[/link]; [link]Phil. 3:10[/link]; [link]Rev. 1:9[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 2:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Eph. 4:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Of [note]1[/note]which I became a [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]minister according to the [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]stewardship of God, which was given to me for you, to [note]4[/note]complete the [xref]c[/xref]word of God,</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to [i]the church[/i] in the preceding verse, indicating that Paul became a minister not of a certain teaching, preaching, or mission work but of the church, the Body of Christ, for its building up.</note>
        <note num="2">In Greek, the same word as that for [i]deacon,[/i] meaning [i]one who serves.[/i]</note>
        <note num="3">See note [link]2[sup]2[/sup] in Eph. 3[/link].</note>
        <note num="4">The word of God is the divine revelation, which had not been completed before the New Testament was written. In the New Testament the apostles, especially the apostle Paul, completed the word of God in regard to the mystery of God, which is Christ, and the mystery of Christ, which is the church, to give us a full revelation of God's economy.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 1:23[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Eph. 3:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Col. 3:16[/link]; [link]4:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>The [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]mystery which has been hidden [note]2[/note]from the ages and from the generations but now has been manifested to His saints;</text>
        <note num="1">According to Greek grammar, [i]the mystery[/i] in this verse is in apposition to [i]the word of God[/i] in [link]v. 25[/link], showing that the mystery is the word of God. This mystery concerns Christ and the church ([link]Eph. 5:32[/link]), the Head and the Body. The unveiling of this mystery through the apostle Paul is the completing of the word of God as the divine revelation.</note>
        <note num="2">[i]From the ages[/i] means from eternity, and [i]from the generations[/i] means from the times. The mystery concerning Christ and the church was hidden from eternity and from all the times until the New Testament age, when it was manifested to the saints, including all of us, the believers in Christ.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 3:3-5[/link], [link]9[/link]; [link]Rom. 16:25-26[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>To whom God willed to make known what are the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]riches of the glory of this [xref]b[/xref]mystery among the Gentiles, [note]2[/note]which is [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]Christ [note]4[/note]in you, the [xref]d[/xref]hope of [note]5[/note][xref]e[/xref]glory,</text>
        <note num="1">The riches of the glory of this mystery among the Gentiles are the riches of all that Christ is to the Gentile believers ([link]Eph. 3:8[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">[i]Which[/i] refers to [i]this mystery.[/i] This mystery, full of glory among the Gentiles, is Christ in us. Christ as life in us is mysterious as well as glorious.</note>
        <note num="3">Christ, who dwells in our spirit to be our life and person, is our hope of glory. When He comes, we will be glorified in Him. This indicates that the indwelling Christ will saturate our entire being that our physical body may be transfigured and conformed to the body of His glory ([link]Phil. 3:21[/link]).</note>
        <note num="4">In this book a number of important phrases point to our experience of Christ: [i]Christ in you[/i] ([link]v. 27[/link]), [i]full-grown in Christ[/i] ([link]v. 28[/link]), [i]walk in Him[/i] ([link]2:6[/link]), [i]according to Christ[/i] ([link]2:8[/link]), [i]made alive together with Him[/i] ([link]2:13[/link]), [i]died with Christ[/i] ([link]2:20[/link]), [i]holding the Head[/i] ([link]2:19[/link]), [i]out from whom[/i] ([link]2:19[/link]), and [i]grows with the growth of God[/i] ([link]2:19[/link]). These expressions give us a complete picture of the proper experience of Christ.</note>
        <note num="5">Christ is the mystery that is full of glory now. This glory will be manifested to its fullest extent when Christ returns to glorify His saints ([link]Rom. 8:30[/link]). Hence, it is a hope, the hope of glory. Christ Himself is also this hope of glory.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 9:23[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:18[/link]; [link]3:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Col. 2:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rom. 8:10[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 13:5[/link]; [link]Gal. 2:20[/link]; [link]4:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Tim. 1:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Col. 3:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>Whom we announce, admonishing every man and teaching every man in all wisdom that we may present every man [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]full-grown [note]2[/note]in Christ;</text>
        <note num="1">Or, perfect, complete, mature. [i]Perfect[/i] denotes full in quality, whereas [i]complete[/i] denotes full in quantity. The apostle's ministry, whether in announcing Christ or in admonishing and teaching men in all wisdom, was altogether to minister Christ to men that they might become perfect and complete by maturing with Christ as the element of the divine life unto full growth.</note>
        <note num="2">The preceding verse says that Christ is in us; this verse, that we are in Christ. First, we are put into Christ; then Christ is in us. The more we get into Christ, the more He comes into us, and the more He comes into us, the more we get into Him. It is by this cycle that we grow in life.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 4:13[/link]; [link]Heb. 6:1[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>For which also I labor, [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]struggling according to His [xref]b[/xref]operation which operates in me in [note]2[/note]power.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, contending (as in wrestling). So also in [link]4:12[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">See notes [link book="Eph." chapter="3"]7[sup]3[/sup][/link] and [link]20[sup]3[/sup] in Eph. 3[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 2:1[/link]; [link]4:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Eph. 1:19[/link]; [link]3:7[/link], [link]20[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>For I want you to know how great a [xref]a[/xref]struggle I have for you and [i]for[/i] those in [xref]b[/xref]Laodicea, even all who have not seen my face in the flesh,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 1:29[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Col. 4:13[/link], [link]15[/link], [link]16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>That their hearts may be [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]comforted, they being knit together in [note]2[/note]love and unto all the [note]3[/note]riches of the [note]4[/note][xref]b[/xref]full assurance of understanding, unto the full knowledge of the [note]5[/note][xref]c[/xref]mystery of God, Christ,</text>
        <note num="1">To comfort people's hearts is to cherish people and lovingly warm them up, that they may be knit together unto the full assurance of understanding of the mystery of God.</note>
        <note num="2">The divine love that we have enjoyed and by which we love God's beloved. This love is the factor and element that knits the saints together.</note>
        <note num="3">The riches of the full assurance of understanding equal the full knowledge of the mystery of God, which is Christ.</note>
        <note num="4">To be knit together in love involves the emotion, whereas to have the riches of the full assurance of understanding involves the mind. When our hearts have been comforted, we being knit together in love, and our minds function properly, we will have the full knowledge of Christ as the mystery of God.</note>
        <note num="5">The book of Ephesians concerns the mystery of Christ, which is the church, the Body ([link]Eph. 3:4[/link]). This book concerns the mystery of God, which is Christ, the Head.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 4:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Col. 4:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Col. 1:26[/link], [link]27[/link]; [link]Eph. 3:3[/link], [link]9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>In whom all the treasures of [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]wisdom and knowledge are hidden.</text>
        <note num="1">According to history, the influence of Gnostic teaching, which included Greek philosophy, invaded the Gentile churches in Paul's time. Hence, the apostle told the Colossians that all the treasures of genuine wisdom and knowledge are hidden in Christ. This is the spiritual wisdom and knowledge of the divine economy concerning Christ and the church. Wisdom is related to our spirit, and knowledge is related to our mind ([link]Eph. 1:8[/link], [link]17[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 1:24[/link], [link]30[/link]; [link]2:6-7[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>This I say that no one may [note]1[/note]delude you with [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]persuasive speech.</text>
        <note num="1">In order for believers to be deluded, or carried off as spoil, something close to the truth, such as philosophy, must be used to deceive them. If we have a clear vision of Christ as the center of God's economy, no one will be able to delude us ([link]v. 8[/link]). If we take Christ as life ([link]3:4[/link]), hold Him as the Head of the Body ([link]v. 19[/link]), know Him as the mystery of God ([link]v. 2[/link]), experience Him as the hope of glory ([link]1:27[/link]), and walk in Him as the all-inclusive Spirit ([link]2:6[/link]), we will not be deceived by anything or anyone.</note>
        <note num="2">We should beware of persuasive speech and of eloquence. A speaker may be very persuasive and very eloquent, but the reality of Christ may not be in his persuasive and eloquent speech.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 16:18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>For even though I am absent in the flesh, yet in the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]spirit I am with you, rejoicing and seeing your order and the solid basis of your faith [note]2[/note]in Christ.</text>
        <note num="1">The human spirit indwelt by the Holy Spirit.</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., into.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 5:3-4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>As therefore you have [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]received the Christ, Jesus the Lord, [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]walk in Him,</text>
        <note num="1">Christ is the allotted portion of the saints ([link]1:12[/link]) for their enjoyment. To believe into Him is to receive Him. As the all-inclusive Spirit ([link]2 Cor. 3:17[/link]), He enters into us and dwells in our spirit ([link]2 Tim. 4:22[/link]) to be everything to us.</note>
        <note num="2">As we have received Christ, we should walk in Him. Here to walk is to live, to act, to behave, and to have our being. We should walk, live, and act in Christ that we may enjoy His riches, just as the children of Israel lived in the good land, enjoying all its rich produce. The good land today is Christ as the all-inclusive Spirit ([link]Gal. 3:14[/link]), who dwells in our spirit ([link]2 Tim. 4:22[/link]; [link]Rom. 8:16[/link]) to be our enjoyment. To walk according to this Spirit ([link]Rom. 8:4[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:16[/link]) is the central and crucial point in the New Testament.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]John 1:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 8:4[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Having been [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]rooted and being [xref]b[/xref]built up in Him, and being established [note]2[/note]in the faith even as you were taught, abounding in thanksgiving.</text>
        <note num="1">Like plants, we are living organisms. As such, we have been rooted in Christ, our soil, our earth, that we may absorb all His riches as nourishment. These riches become the element and substance with which we grow and are built up. To be rooted is for the growth in life. This rooting has been completed already. To be built up is for the building of the Body of Christ. This is still going on. Both these matters are in Christ.</note>
        <note num="2">[i]In the faith[/i] here means in our faith, the subjective faith by which we believe.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 3:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Eph. 2:22[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Beware that no one carries you off as spoil through his [note]1[/note]philosophy and [xref]a[/xref]empty deceit, according to the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]tradition of men, according to the [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]elements of the world, and not according to [note]4[/note][xref]d[/xref]Christ;</text>
        <note num="1">This refers to Gnostic teaching, a mixture of Jewish, oriental, and Greek philosophies, which is an empty deceit.</note>
        <note num="2">Tradition is related to culture and has its source in culture. The source of the Gnostic teaching at Colossae was the tradition of men; it was based not on the revealed writings of God but on the traditional practices of men.</note>
        <note num="3">The same expression, [i]elements of the world,[/i] is used in [link]Gal. 4:3[/link] (see note there). Here it refers to the rudimentary teachings of both Jews and Gentiles, consisting of ritualistic observances regarding the eating of meats, drinking, washings, asceticism, and other matters.</note>
        <note num="4">Christ is the governing principle of all genuine wisdom and knowledge, the reality of all genuine teaching, and the only measure of all concepts acceptable to God. This book focuses on Christ as our everything.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 6:20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Matt. 15:2[/link]; [link]Gal. 1:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Col. 2:20[/link]; [link]Gal. 4:3[/link], [link]9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Col. 1:27[/link]; [link]2:2[/link], [link]6[/link], [link]17[/link]; [link]3:4[/link], [link]11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>For in Him dwells all the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]fullness of the [note]2[/note]Godhead [note]3[/note]bodily,</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Fullness[/i] refers not to the riches of God but to the expression of the riches of God. What dwells in Christ is not only the riches of the Godhead but the expression of the riches of what God is. See note [link]19[sup]3[/sup] in Eph. 3[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">This refers to deity, which is different from the divine characteristics manifested by the created things ([link]Rom. 1:20[/link]). This strongly indicates the deity of Christ. The fullness of the Godhead is versus the tradition of men and the elements of the world. The world's tradition and elements simply cannot be compared with the fullness of the Godhead.</note>
        <note num="3">This points to the physical body that Christ put on in His humanity, indicating that all the fullness of the Godhead dwells in Christ as One who has a human body. Before Christ's incarnation, the fullness of the Godhead dwelt in Him as the eternal Word, but not bodily. From the time that Christ became incarnate, clothed with a human body, the fullness of the Godhead began to dwell in Him in a bodily way; and in His glorified body ([link]Phil. 3:21[/link]) now and forever it dwells.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 1:19[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And you have been made [note]1[/note]full in Him, who is the [xref]a[/xref]Head of all [note]2[/note]rule and authority.</text>
        <note num="1">The Greek word implies completion, perfection. Because all the fullness dwells in Him, after we have been put into Christ ([link]1 Cor. 1:30[/link]), we are made full, filled up, with all the divine riches. Hence, we need no other source. Because Christ is our perfection and completion, we do not need other rules and authorities as objects of adoration, for He is the Head of all these. This is versus angel worship ([link]v. 18[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">The rule and authority here are the fallen angels occupying positions of power in the air in subordination to Satan. See note [link]15[sup]2[/sup][/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 1:21-22[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>In Him also you were [xref]a[/xref]circumcised with a [note]1[/note]circumcision [note]2[/note]not [xref]b[/xref]made with hands, in the [note]3[/note]putting off of the body of the flesh, in the circumcision of Christ,</text>
        <note num="1">This is spiritual circumcision, the circumcision of Christ, referring to the proper baptism, which puts off the body of the flesh by the effectual virtue of the death of Christ. This is contrary to asceticism ([link]vv. 20-22[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">The circumcision that is the putting off of the body of the flesh was not made with hands; it was accomplished by the death of Christ, and it is applied, executed, and carried out by the powerful Spirit.</note>
        <note num="3">[i]Putting off[/i] here means to strip off something, as one would strip off clothes.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 2:28-29[/link]; [link]Phil. 3:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Eph. 2:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>[note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Buried together with Him in baptism, in which also you were [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]raised together with [i]Him[/i] through the [note]3[/note]faith of the operation of God, who [xref]c[/xref]raised Him from the dead.</text>
        <note num="1">To be buried in baptism is to put off, to strip off, the body of the flesh.</note>
        <note num="2">In baptism there is the aspect of burial, which is the termination of our flesh, and the aspect of raising, which is the germination of our spirit. In the aspect of raising, we are made alive in Christ with the divine life.</note>
        <note num="3">Faith is not of ourselves; it is the gift of God ([link]2 Pet. 1:1[/link]). The more we turn to God and contact Him, the more faith we have. The Lord is the Author and Perfecter of our faith ([link]Heb. 12:2[/link]). The more we abide in Him, the more we are infused with Him as our faith. It is through this living faith produced by the operation of the living God that we experience the resurrection life, signified by the raising aspect of baptism.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 6:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Col. 3:1[/link]; [link]Eph. 2:6[/link]; [link]Rom. 6:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rom. 8:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And you, though [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]dead in your offenses and in the uncircumcision of your flesh, He [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]made alive together with Him, having forgiven us all our offenses;</text>
        <note num="1">Dead in spirit because of sin.</note>
        <note num="2">In Christ's resurrection, God enlivened us together by His divine life. This was accomplished in Christ's resurrection ([link]1 Pet. 1:3[/link]) and is experienced through our faith.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 2:1[/link], [link]5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Eph. 2:5[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>[note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Wiping out the [note]2[/note]handwriting in [note]3[/note]ordinances, which was against us, which was contrary to us; and He has taken it out of the way, [note]4[/note]nailing it to the cross.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, blotting out, obliterating, erasing, annulling (a decree of law).</note>
        <note num="2">A legal document, a bond. Here it refers to the written law.</note>
        <note num="3">Referring to the ordinances of the ceremonial law with its rituals, which are the forms or ways of living and worship. So also in [link]vv. 20[/link] and [link]21[/link].</note>
        <note num="4">This is to abolish the law of the commandments in ordinances ([link]Eph. 2:15[/link]). It kills the heresy of keeping the Judaic rituals.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 2:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Stripping off the [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]rulers and the authorities, [note]3[/note]He made a [note]4[/note]display [i]of them[/i] openly, triumphing over them in [note]5[/note]it.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, putting off, as in [link]3:9[/link]. [link]Verses 13-15[/link] unveil the economy of God's salvation: (1) to make us alive with Christ, (2) to abolish the ordinances of the ceremonial law, and (3) to strip off the evil angelic powers.[br][br]God was busy while Christ's crucifixion was going on: He nailed the law on the cross and stripped off the rulers and authorities, that the way and the atmosphere might be cleared for us to enter into the participation in Christ.</note>
        <note num="2">These are the angelic rulers and authorities. Because at Colossae there was the heretical teaching of angel worship, the passage here must refer to the evil angels. The law was ordained through angels and was even considered to be ordinances of angels ([link]Gal. 3:19[/link]; [link]Acts 7:53[/link]). Based on this, the heresy at Colossae taught people to worship angels ([link]v. 18[/link]) as mediators between God and man. The apostle dealt with this heresy by unveiling the fact that the law, consisting of ordinances, had been nailed to the cross ([link]v. 14[/link]), and that the leading evil angels had been stripped off from God. This left Christ as the sole Mediator, who is the Head of all rule and authority ([link]v. 10[/link]). This killed the heresy of angel worship.</note>
        <note num="3">Here and throughout [link]vv. 13[/link] and [link]14[/link], [i]He[/i] refers to God ([link]v. 12[/link]).</note>
        <note num="4">Or, show, exhibit in the sense of an open shame. God openly shamed the evil angelic rulers and authorities on the cross and triumphed over them in it.</note>
        <note num="5">Or, in Him; referring to Christ. [i]It[/i] refers to the cross.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 2:2[/link]; [link]6:12[/link]; [link]Heb. 2:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Let no one therefore judge you [note]1[/note]in [xref]a[/xref]eating and in drinking or in respect of a [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]feast or of a [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]new moon or of the [note]4[/note][xref]d[/xref]Sabbath,</text>
        <note num="1">Or, in food and in drink. Food and drink signify satisfaction and strengthening.</note>
        <note num="2">Referring to the annual Jewish festivals, which signify joy and enjoyment.</note>
        <note num="3">Signifying a new beginning with light in the darkness.</note>
        <note num="4">Signifying completion and rest. Feasts are yearly, new moons monthly, Sabbaths weekly, and eating and drinking daily. Daily we eat and drink Christ, weekly we have completion and rest in Him, monthly we experience a new beginning in Him, and throughout the year He is our joy and enjoyment. Therefore, daily, weekly, monthly, and yearly Christ is to us the reality of every positive thing, implying the universal extensiveness of the all-inclusive Christ.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Lev. 11:2[/link]; [link]Rom. 14:2-3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Lev. 23:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Num. 28:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Lev. 23:3[/link]; [link]Mark 2:27[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Which are a [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]shadow of the things to come, but the [note]2[/note]body is of [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]Christ.</text>
        <note num="1">All the aforementioned items of the ceremonial law are a shadow of the spiritual things in Christ, which are the things to come. But the body belongs to Christ and is Christ.</note>
        <note num="2">As with a man's physical body, the body here is the substance. And like the shadow of a man's body, the rituals in the law are a shadow of the real things in the gospel.</note>
        <note num="3">Christ is the reality of the gospel. All the good things in the gospel belong to Him and are Him. This book unveils such an all-inclusive Christ as the focus of God's economy.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 8:5[/link]; [link]10:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Col. 1:27[/link]; [link]2:2[/link], [link]8[/link]; [link]3:4[/link], [link]11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Let no one [note]1[/note]defraud you by judging you unworthy of your [xref]a[/xref]prize, in [xref]b[/xref]self-chosen [note]2[/note]lowliness and the worship of the angels, [note]3[/note]dwelling on the things which he has [note]4[/note]seen, vainly [xref]c[/xref]puffed up by [note]5[/note]his mind set on the flesh,</text>
        <note num="1">The heretical teachers judged the saints unworthy to worship God directly and maintained that they had to approach Him through the mediation of angels. This was to defraud the saints of their prize, depriving them of the enjoyment of Christ. In Christ, our sole Mediator, we can worship God directly.</note>
        <note num="2">The heretical teachers of angel worship taught the saints to show lowliness in realizing that they were not worthy to worship God directly. They defrauded the saints of their prize in Christ in the element and sphere of such self-chosen lowliness and angel worship.</note>
        <note num="3">Or, looking into, investigating (secret things).</note>
        <note num="4">The heretical teachers lived in the realm of sight, in contrast to the faith mentioned in [link]v. 12[/link]. They liked to have curious visions. Such insistence on visual experience resulted in fleshly pride, the vain puffing up by the mind set on the flesh.</note>
        <note num="5">Lit., the mind of his flesh.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Phil. 3:14[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 9:24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Col. 2:23[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Cor. 8:1[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And [note]1[/note]not [xref]a[/xref]holding the Head, [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]out from whom all the [note]3[/note]Body, being richly supplied and knit together by means of the [note]4[/note]joints and [note]5[/note]sinews, [note]6[/note]grows with the [note]7[/note]growth of God.</text>
        <note num="1">The heresy of angel worship distracted the saints from holding Christ as the Head. God's economy is to head up all things in Christ ([link]Eph. 1:10[/link]) through His Body, the church, making Christ the center of all things. The subtle one's device is to carry the saints away and thus cause the Body of Christ to collapse.</note>
        <note num="2">The phrase [i]out from whom[/i] indicates that the Body of Christ grows out from the Head, for all the supply comes from the Head.</note>
        <note num="3">The heresy caused the saints to be severed from the Head, and thus it damaged the Body. The apostle's revelation uplifted Christ and caused the Body to be safeguarded and built up.</note>
        <note num="4">Joints are for the supply of the Body.</note>
        <note num="5">Sinews are for the knitting together of the members of the Body.</note>
        <note num="6">Growing is a matter of life, which is God Himself. As the Body of Christ, the church should not be deprived of Christ, who is the embodiment of God as the source of life. By holding Christ, the church grows with the growth of God, with the increase of God as life.</note>
        <note num="7">The growth of the Body of Christ has nothing to do with doctrinal knowledge of the Bible, the way of worship, or any such matter. Rather, the growth of the Body depends on the growth of God, the increase of God's element, in the Body.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 4:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Eph. 4:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>[note]1[/note]If you [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]died with Christ from the [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]elements of the world, why, as living in the world, do you subject yourselves to [xref]c[/xref]ordinances:</text>
        <note num="1">Or, since.</note>
        <note num="2">In baptism ([link]Rom. 6:3[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">The elements of the world are the elementary principles of outward, material things, the childish teachings of externalism, such as asceticism. This is altogether different from God's way, the way of the cross. See note [link]8[sup]3[/sup][/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 6:2-4[/link], [link]6-8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Col. 2:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Col. 2:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Do not handle, nor taste, nor touch,</text>
        <note num="1">These are ordinances, rules, and regulations concerning material things and deal with, respectively, things that move, things that are edible, and things that are tangible. Handling, tasting, and touching include virtually every kind of action, and the ordinances concerning them are related to the practice of asceticism.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>([i]Regarding[/i] things which are all to [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]perish when [note]2[/note]used) according to the [xref]b[/xref]commandments and teachings of men?</text>
        <note num="1">Or, become corrupted. All material things are destined to decompose and perish through corruption when used ([link]1 Cor. 6:13[/link]; [link]Matt. 15:17[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Or, consumed.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 6:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Matt. 15:9[/link]; [link]Titus 1:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Such things indeed have a [note]2[/note]reputation of wisdom in self-imposed [xref]a[/xref]worship and lowliness and [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]severe treatment of the body, [i]but[/i] are [note]4[/note]not of any value against the [xref]c[/xref]indulgence of the flesh.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Such things[/i] refers to the commandments and teachings of men ([link]v. 22[/link]) and ordinances ([link]v. 20[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word denotes a word or a saying; hence, expression, show of reason, and, therefore, a reputation.</note>
        <note num="3">This is asceticism.</note>
        <note num="4">The ordinances, rules, and regulations of the elementary teachings of externalism and asceticism are of no value in restraining the indulgence of the flesh.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 2:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 4:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rom. 13:14[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[note]1[/note]If therefore you were [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]raised together with Christ, seek the things which are [note]3[/note]above, where Christ is, sitting at the [xref]b[/xref]right hand of God.</text>
        <note num="1">[link]Verses 1-4[/link] imply that with Christ we have one position, one life, one living, one destiny, and one glory.</note>
        <note num="2">This is the raising aspect of baptism, which is altogether contrary to asceticism. We were raised together with Christ. We are now where Christ is, sitting in the heavens. Hence, in contrast to the ascetics, we should not practice the things on the earth. We should seek the things that are in the heavens, such as knowing Christ as everything to us, so that we take Him as life and thereby walk in Him.</note>
        <note num="3">I.e., in the heavens; in contrast to [i]on the earth[/i] in [link]v. 2[/link]. The heavens are linked to Christ and joined to the church. The things above include the ascended Christ and all things pertaining to Him. Therefore, to seek the things above is to seek to live Christ in and with the church.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 2:12[/link]; [link]Eph. 2:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 8:34[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:20[/link]; [link]Heb. 10:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Set your [xref]a[/xref]mind on the things which are above, not on the [note]1[/note]things which are on the earth.</text>
        <note num="1">The things on the earth include culture, religion, philosophy, and improvement in behavior, as spoken of in the preceding two chapters.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 8:5-6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>For you [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]died, and your [note]2[/note]life is [note]3[/note]hidden with Christ in God.</text>
        <note num="1">We died with Christ and so were set free from the things on the earth, especially things related to asceticism. We were baptized into His death ([link]Rom. 6:3[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Because our life (not our natural life, but our spiritual life, which is Christ) is hidden with Christ in God, who is in the heavens, we should no longer be concerned for things on the earth. God in the heavens should be the sphere of our living. With Christ we should live in God.</note>
        <note num="3">That our life is hidden with Christ in God means that it is hidden with Christ in the heavens.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 2:20[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>When [note]1[/note]Christ our [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]life is [xref]b[/xref]manifested, then you also will be manifested with Him in [xref]c[/xref]glory.</text>
        <note num="1">That Christ is our life is a strong indication that we are to take Him as life and live by Him, that we are to live Him in our daily life in order to experience the universally extensive Christ revealed in this book, so that all He is and has attained and obtained will not remain objective but will become our subjective experience.</note>
        <note num="2">In God, Christ is our life. This life is now hidden but will be manifested. Then we will be manifested with this life in glory.[br][br]In [link]2:20-3:4[/link] the unique way and the unique person are revealed to us. The unique way is the cross, the center of God's government, and the unique person is Christ, the preeminent, all-inclusive One, the center of the universe. By the cross, not by asceticism, we were saved from the negative things. By Christ, not by philosophy, we live the life hidden in God.[br][br]Christ, who is our life, is the allotted portion of the saints ([link]1:12[/link]), the image of the invisible God ([link]1:15[/link]), the Firstborn of all creation ([link]1:15[/link]), the Firstborn from the dead ([link]1:18[/link]), the One in whom God's fullness dwells ([link]1:19[/link]; [link]2:9[/link]), the mystery of God's economy ([link]1:26[/link]), the mystery of God ([link]2:2[/link]), the reality of all positive things ([link]2:16-17[/link]), and the constituent of the new man ([link]vv. 10-11[/link]). By taking such an all-inclusive Christ as life and thus living Him, we experience and enjoy all His riches.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]John 11:25[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 John 3:2[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:7[/link]; [link]Heb. 9:28[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rom. 8:17[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 15:43[/link]; [link]Phil. 3:21[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>[note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Put to death therefore your [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]members which are on the earth: fornication, uncleanness, passion, evil desire, and [xref]c[/xref]greediness, which is idolatry;</text>
        <note num="1">This is based on the fact that we have been crucified with Christ ([link]Gal. 2:20a[/link]) and baptized into His death ([link]Rom. 6:3[/link]). We execute Christ's death upon our sinful members by crucifying them, by faith, through the power of the Spirit ([link]Rom. 8:13[/link]). This corresponds with [link]Gal. 5:24[/link]. Christ accomplished the all-inclusive crucifixion. Now we apply it to our lustful flesh. This is absolutely different from asceticism.</note>
        <note num="2">In our sinful members is the law of sin, making us captives of sin and causing our corrupted body to become the body of death ([link]Rom. 7:23-24[/link]). Hence, our members, which are sinful, are identified with sinful things, such as fornication, uncleanness, passion, evil desire, and greediness.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 8:13[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 6:13[/link]; [link]7:5[/link], [link]23[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Eph. 4:19[/link]; [link]5:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Because of which things the [xref]a[/xref]wrath of God is coming upon the [xref]b[/xref]sons of disobedience;</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 1:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Eph. 5:6[/link]; [link]2:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>In which you also once walked, when you lived in these things.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>But now, you also, put away all [i]these[/i] things: wrath, anger, malice, blasphemy, [xref]a[/xref]foul abusive language out of your mouth.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 4:29[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Do not [xref]a[/xref]lie to one another, since you have [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]put off the [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]old man with his practices</text>
        <note num="1">Putting off the old man is like putting off an old garment. First, we put to death the physical lusts, then we put away the psychological evils, and last, we put off the entire old man with his practices. This is not by our own energy but by the power of the all-inclusive Spirit.</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]22[sup]4[/sup] in Eph. 4[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 4:25[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Eph. 4:22[/link]; [link]Col. 2:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rom. 6:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And have [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]put on the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]new man, which is being [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]renewed unto full knowledge according to the [note]4[/note][xref]d[/xref]image of Him [note]5[/note]who [xref]e[/xref]created him,</text>
        <note num="1">Putting on the new man is like putting on a new garment.</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word here means new in relation to time, whereas the word in [link]Eph. 4:24[/link] means new in nature, quality, or form. Concerning the new man, see note [link]24[sup]2[/sup], par. 1, in Eph. 4[/link]. Since Christ is the constituent of the new man, we, who are the new man, are one with Christ. This is the most basic and crucial point in this book.</note>
        <note num="3">Because the new man was created with us, who belong to the old creation ([link]Eph. 2:15[/link]), as his constituents, he needs to be renewed. This renewing takes place mainly in our mind, as indicated by the phrase [i]unto full knowledge.[/i] The new man was created in our spirit and is being renewed in our mind unto full knowledge according to the image of Christ.</note>
        <note num="4">Referring to the image of Christ as the very expression of God ([link]1:15[/link]; [link]Heb. 1:3a[/link]).</note>
        <note num="5">Referring to Christ the Creator, who created the new man in Himself ([link]Eph. 2:15[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 4:24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Eph. 2:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rom. 12:2[/link]; [link]Titus 3:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Col. 1:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Eph. 2:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Where there [note]2[/note]cannot be [note]3[/note]Greek and [xref]a[/xref]Jew, [note]4[/note][xref]b[/xref]circumcision and uncircumcision, [note]5[/note][xref]c[/xref]barbarian, [note]6[/note]Scythian, [note]7[/note]slave, [note]8[/note]free man, but [note]9[/note][xref]d[/xref]Christ is [note]10[/note]all and in [note]10[/note]all.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Where,[/i] referring to the new man in [link]v. 10[/link], means in the new man.</note>
        <note num="2">Not only is there no natural person in the new man, but there is no possibility and no room for any natural person to exist.</note>
        <note num="3">The Greeks favored philosophical wisdom; the Jews, miraculous signs ([link]1 Cor. 1:22[/link]).</note>
        <note num="4">[i]Circumcision[/i] here refers to those who observed the Jewish religious rituals; [i]uncircumcision,[/i] to those who did not care for the Jewish religion.</note>
        <note num="5">A barbarian is an uncultured person.</note>
        <note num="6">Scythians were considered the most barbarous.</note>
        <note num="7">One who has been sold into slavery.</note>
        <note num="8">One who has been freed from slavery.</note>
        <note num="9">In the new man there is room only for Christ. He is all the members of the new man and in all the members. He is everything in the new man. Actually, He is the new man, His Body ([link]1 Cor. 12:12[/link]). In the new man He is the centrality and universality. He is the constituent of the new man, and He is all in all in the new man.</note>
        <note num="10">[i]All[/i] refers to all the members who constitute the new man.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gal. 3:28[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 12:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Cor. 7:19[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:6[/link]; [link]6:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rom. 1:14[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 14:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Col. 2:2[/link], [link]17[/link]; [link]3:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Put on therefore, as God's [xref]a[/xref]chosen ones, [note]2[/note]holy and beloved, [xref]b[/xref]inward parts of compassion, kindness, lowliness, meekness, long-suffering;</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Put on[/i] here is in the sense of putting on a garment.</note>
        <note num="2">To be holy means to be not common or worldly but separated unto God. See note [link]2[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 1:4[/link]; [link]Titus 1:1[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 2:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Luke 1:78[/link]; [link]Phil. 1:8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Bearing one another and [xref]a[/xref]forgiving [note]1[/note]one another, if anyone should have a complaint against anyone; even as the [note]2[/note]Lord forgave you, so also [i]should[/i] you [i]forgive.[/i]</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., yourselves.</note>
        <note num="2">The forgiving Lord is our life and lives within us; forgiving is a virtue of His life. When we take Him as our life and person and live by Him, our forgiving of others will be spontaneous &amp;#8212; it will become a virtue of our Christian life.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Mark 11:25[/link]; [link]Eph. 4:32[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And over all these things [i]put on[/i] [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]love, which is the uniting bond of [note]2[/note]perfectness.</text>
        <note num="1">God is love ([link]1 John 4:16[/link]). Love is the very essence of God's being, the very substance of the divine life. Hence, to put on love is to clothe ourselves with the element of God's life. Such a love is the uniting bond in the combination of perfectness, completeness, and mature virtues. We need to put on not only the new man ([link]v. 10[/link]) but also the virtues of the new man ([link]v. 12[/link]), and to put on love over all the virtues ([link]v. 14[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Or, completeness.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 2:2[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 13:4[/link], [link]13[/link]; [link]Eph. 4:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And let the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]peace of Christ [note]2[/note]arbitrate in your hearts, to [note]3[/note]which [note]4[/note]also you were called in [xref]b[/xref]one Body; and be [note]5[/note][xref]c[/xref]thankful.</text>
        <note num="1">The peace of Christ is Christ Himself. By this peace Christ has made the two peoples, the Jews and the Gentiles, one new man, and this peace has become a part of the gospel ([link]Eph. 2:14-18[/link]). We should let this peace arbitrate in our hearts for the Body life.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, umpire, preside, be enthroned as a ruler and decider of everything. The arbitrating peace of Christ in our hearts dissolves the complaint mentioned in [link]v. 13[/link].</note>
        <note num="3">[i]Which[/i] refers to the peace of Christ. We were called to this peace in the one Body of Christ. For the proper Body life we need the peace of Christ to arbitrate, to adjust, and to decide all things in our heart in our relationship with the members of His Body.</note>
        <note num="4">That we were called to the peace of Christ should also be a motive for our letting this peace arbitrate in our hearts.</note>
        <note num="5">We not only should let the peace of Christ arbitrate in our hearts, but we also should be thankful to the Lord. In the Body life our heart should always be in a peaceful condition toward the members and should be thankful to the Lord.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]John 14:27[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Eph. 4:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Col. 2:7[/link]; [link]3:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Let the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]word of Christ [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]dwell in you [note]3[/note]richly [note]4[/note]in all wisdom, [note]5[/note]teaching and admonishing [note]6[/note]one another with [note]7[/note][xref]c[/xref]psalms [i]and[/i] hymns [i]and[/i] [xref]d[/xref]spiritual songs, [note]5[/note]singing with [note]8[/note]grace in your hearts to God.</text>
        <note num="1">The word spoken by Christ. In His New Testament economy God speaks in the Son, and the Son speaks not only by Himself in the Gospels but also through His members, the apostles and prophets, in Acts, in the Epistles, and in Revelation. All these speakings can be considered His word.[br][br]In this passage the infilling of spiritual life that overflows in praising and singing is related to the word, whereas in the parallel passage, [link]Eph. 5:18-20[/link], the infilling of spiritual life is related to the Spirit. This indicates that the word is the Spirit ([link]John 6:63b[/link]). A normal Christian life should be one that is filled with the word, that the Spirit may bubble over with praise and lauding melodies from within the believers.[br][br]This book is focused on Christ as our Head and life. The way for Him to exercise His Headship and minister His riches to us is through His word. Hence, the emphasis is on the word of Christ. Ephesians is concerned with the church as the Body of Christ. The way for us to live a normal church life is to be filled in our spirit unto all the fullness of God. Hence, the Spirit is emphasized. In Ephesians both the Holy Spirit and our spirit are emphasized again and again; the word is even considered to be the Spirit ([link]Eph. 6:17[/link]). However, in this book each of the two spirits is mentioned only once ([link]1:8[/link]; [link]2:5[/link]). In Ephesians the word is for washing away our natural life ([link]Eph. 5:26[/link]) and fighting against the enemy ([link]Eph. 6:17[/link]), whereas in this book the word is for revealing Christ ([link]1:25-27[/link]) in His preeminence, centrality, and universality.</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., to be in a house, to indwell, to inhabit. The word of the Lord must have adequate room within us that it may operate and minister the riches of Christ into our inner being.</note>
        <note num="3">The riches of Christ ([link]Eph. 3:8[/link]) are in His word. Such a rich word must inhabit us richly.</note>
        <note num="4">The phrase [i]in all wisdom[/i] may also be placed so as to modify [i]teaching and admonishing.[/i]</note>
        <note num="5">[i]Teaching and admonishing[/i] and [i]singing[/i] modify the verb [i]dwell.[/i] This indicates that the way to let the Lord's word dwell in us richly is by teaching, admonishing, and singing.</note>
        <note num="6">Lit., yourselves.</note>
        <note num="7">We should teach and admonish not only with words but also with psalms, hymns, and spiritual songs.</note>
        <note num="8">See notes [link book="John" chapter="1"]14[sup]6[/sup][/link] and [link]17[sup]1[/sup] in John 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 10:17[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 1:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]John 15:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Eph. 5:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">cf. [link]1 Cor. 14:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And whatever you do in word or in deed, [i]do[/i] all things in the [note]1[/note]name of the Lord Jesus, giving [xref]a[/xref]thanks to God the Father through Him.</text>
        <note num="1">The name denotes the person. The Lord's person is the Spirit ([link]2 Cor. 3:17a[/link]). To do things in the name of the Lord is to act in the Spirit. This is to live Christ.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 5:20[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>[note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Wives, be subject to your husbands, as is fitting in the Lord.</text>
        <note num="1">The section from this verse through [link]4:1[/link] is a sister passage to [link]Eph. 5:22-6:9[/link], regarding the believers' ethical relationships. In Ephesians the emphasis is on the need of having spirit-filled ethical relationships for the expression of the Body of Christ in the normal church life. In Colossians the emphasis is on our holding Christ as our Head and taking Him as our life by having His rich word dwell in us, that the highest ethical relationships, issuing not from our natural life but from Christ as our life, may be realized for His expression.[br][br]For each point in this passage, see the appropriate note in Ephesians.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]3:18-4:1[/link]; [link]Eph. 5:22-6:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Husbands, love your wives and do not be bitter against them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Children, obey your parents in all things, for this is well pleasing in the Lord.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Fathers, do not vex your children, that they may not be disheartened.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Slaves, obey in all things those who are your masters according to the flesh, not with eye-service as men-pleasers, but in singleness of heart fearing the Lord.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Whatever you do, work from the soul as to the Lord and not to men,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>Knowing that from the Lord you will receive the [note]1[/note]inheritance as [xref]a[/xref]recompense. You [note]2[/note]serve the Lord Christ.</text>
        <note num="1">This point is not made as clear in [link]Eph. 6:8[/link] as it is here. The inheritance here is what the believers will inherit ([link]Rom. 8:17[/link]; [link]Acts 26:18[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:4[/link]). [i]The inheritance as recompense[/i] indicates that the Lord uses the inheritance that He will give to His believers as an incentive for them to be faithful in their service to Him. The unfaithful ones will surely miss this recompense ([link]Matt. 24:45-51[/link]; [link]25:20-29[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., serve as a slave.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Matt. 5:12[/link]; [link]16:27[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 3:8[/link], [link]14[/link]; [link]Rev. 22:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>For he who does unrighteously will [xref]a[/xref]receive what he unrighteously did, and there is no [xref]b[/xref]respect of persons.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Cor. 5:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 10:34[/link]; [link]Rom. 2:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Masters, grant to your slaves that which is just and equal, knowing that you also have a Master in heaven.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>[note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Persevere in [note]2[/note]prayer, [note]3[/note]watching in it with thanksgiving,</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., continue persistently, steadfastly, and earnestly.</note>
        <note num="2">Prayer preserves the grace that we received in [link]chs. 1-3[/link].</note>
        <note num="3">In prayer we need to be watchful and alert, not negligent. Such watchfulness should be accompanied by thanksgiving. A lack of thanksgiving is an indication of prayerlessness. The prayer life is kept by watching with thanksgiving.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 6:18[/link]; [link]Acts 1:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Praying at the same time for [xref]a[/xref]us also, that God would open to us a [note]1[/note]door for the word, to speak the [xref]b[/xref]mystery of Christ (because of which also I am [xref]c[/xref]bound),</text>
        <note num="1">This implies that we need to keep ourselves open to the word of God.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 6:19-20[/link]; [link]2 Thes. 3:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Col. 1:26-27[/link]; [link]2:2[/link]; [link]Eph. 3:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Col. 4:18[/link]; [link]Phil. 1:7[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>That I may make it manifest as I ought to speak.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Walk in [xref]a[/xref]wisdom toward those who are [xref]b[/xref]without, [note]1[/note][xref]c[/xref]redeeming the time.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]16[sup]1[/sup] in Eph. 5[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 5:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Thes. 4:12[/link]; [link]Mark 4:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Eph. 5:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Let your speech be always with [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]grace, seasoned with [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]salt, that you may know how you ought to [xref]c[/xref]answer each one.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]29[sup]3[/sup] in Eph. 4[/link]. Every word proceeding out of our mouth must be with Christ and must be the uttering of Christ, who is grace.</note>
        <note num="2">Salt makes food agreeable and pleasant to the taste. Speech seasoned with salt keeps us at peace with one another ([link]Mark 9:50[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 4:29[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Mark 9:50[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Pet. 3:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>[note]1[/note]All the things concerning me, [xref]a[/xref]Tychicus, the beloved brother and faithful [xref]b[/xref]minister and fellow slave in the Lord, will make known to you,</text>
        <note num="1">In [link]vv. 7-17[/link] the apostle's fellowship shows us that the new man as practiced at the apostle's time was an issue of the apostle's work, which encouraged the believers to seek after Christ, the very constituent of the new man, as their enjoyment. By means of the traffic among the churches, we experience in a practical way the living of the new man. Such a living has Christ as its reality.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 20:4[/link]; [link]Eph. 6:21[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 4:12[/link]; [link]Titus 3:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Col. 1:7[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Whom I have sent to you for this very thing, that you might know the things concerning us and that he might [xref]a[/xref]comfort your hearts;</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 2:2[/link]; [link]Eph. 6:22[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>With [xref]a[/xref]Onesimus, the faithful and beloved [xref]b[/xref]brother, who is one of you. They will make known to you all the things here.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Philem. 10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Philem. 16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Aristarchus, my fellow prisoner, greets you, as well as [xref]b[/xref]Mark, the cousin of [xref]c[/xref]Barnabas, (concerning whom you received commandments, If he comes to you, receive him),</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 19:29[/link]; [link]20:4[/link]; [link]27:2[/link]; [link]Philem. 24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 12:12[/link], [link]25[/link]; [link]15:37[/link], [link]39[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 4:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Acts 4:36[/link]; [link]9:27[/link]; [link]11:22[/link], [link]24-26[/link]; [link]13:1[/link], [link]7[/link]; [link]15:36-39[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And Jesus, who is called [xref]a[/xref]Justus; these alone of the [xref]b[/xref]circumcision are [i]my[/i] fellow workers for the [xref]c[/xref]kingdom of God, ones who have become a [xref]d[/xref]consolation to me.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Acts 1:23[/link]; [link]18:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 11:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]John 3:3[/link], [link]5[/link]; [link]Acts 1:3[/link]; [link]28:31[/link]; [link]Rom. 14:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Philem. 7[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Epaphras, who is one of you, a slave of Christ Jesus, greets you, always [xref]b[/xref]struggling on your behalf in his prayers that you may [note]1[/note]stand [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]mature and [xref]d[/xref]fully assured in all the [note]3[/note][xref]e[/xref]will of God.</text>
        <note num="1">In the Greek, [i]stand[/i] here is in the passive voice. Hence, it implies being placed, being presented, and corresponds with [i]present[/i] in [link]1:28[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Or, complete.</note>
        <note num="3">See note [link]9[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 1:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Col. 1:29[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Col. 1:28[/link]; [link]Phil. 3:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Col. 2:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Col. 1:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>For I testify of him that he labors much for you and for those in [xref]a[/xref]Laodicea and for those in Hierapolis.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 2:1[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Luke, the beloved physician, greets you, as well as [xref]b[/xref]Demas.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Luke 1:3[/link]; [link]Acts 1:1[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 4:11[/link]; [link]Philem. 24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Tim. 4:10[/link]; [link]Philem. 24[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Greet the brothers in [xref]a[/xref]Laodicea, as well as Nymphas and the [note]1[/note]church, which is in [note]2[/note]his [xref]b[/xref]house.</text>
        <note num="1">The church in the house of Nymphas was the local church in Laodicea, which met in Nymphas's house. Such meetings in the saints' homes afford every attending believer the opportunity to function, and they also strengthen the mutual fellowship among the saints.</note>
        <note num="2">Some MSS read, her; others, their.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 2:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 16:5[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 16:19[/link]; [link]Philem. 2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And when this letter is [xref]a[/xref]read among you, cause that it be read in the church of the [xref]b[/xref]Laodiceans also, and that you also read the one from Laodicea.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Thes. 5:27[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rev. 3:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And say to [xref]a[/xref]Archippus, Take heed to the [xref]b[/xref]ministry which you have received in the Lord, that you fulfill it.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Philem. 2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Tim. 4:5[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>The greeting in [xref]a[/xref]my own hand &amp;#8212; Paul. [xref]b[/xref]Remember my [xref]c[/xref]bonds. [xref]d[/xref]Grace be with you.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 16:21[/link]; [link]2 Thes. 3:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 13:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Col. 4:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Tim. 6:21[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 4:22[/link]; [link]Titus 3:15[/link]; [link]Philem. 25[/link]; [link]Heb. 13:25[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    </chapters>
</book>
