<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="yes"?>
<book name="Ecclesiastes">
    <info title="Author">Solomon ([link]1:1[/link], [link]12[/link]; [link]12:9[/link]; cf. [link]1 Kings 4:32[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Time of Writing">About 977 B.C., after Solomon's fall ([link]1 Kings 11:1-8[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Place of Writing">Jerusalem ([link]1:1[/link], [link]12[/link]).</info>
    <subject>The Teachings of Solomon, Showing That the Human Life in the Corrupted World Is a Vanity, a Chasing after the Wind</subject>
    <outlines>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="1" ref="1:1-11">The opening word</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="2" ref="1:12-6:12">The writer's experiments</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="1:12-18">In wisdom and knowledge</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="2:1-11">In pleasure</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="2:12-26">In being a wise man or a fool</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="4" ref="3:1-15">In fate under God's sovereignty</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="5" ref="3:16-4:16">In ranks and classes in human society</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="6" ref="5:1-7">In contacting God</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="7" ref="5:8-6:12">In sundry illustrations</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="3" ref="7:1-12:12">The writer's searching and testing</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="7:1-11:8; 12:9-12">Words of wisdom</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="11:9-12:1">Advice to young men</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="12:2-8">The sad portrait of man's old age</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="4" ref="12:13-14">The concluding word</outline>
    </outlines>
    <chapters>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>The words of the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Preacher, the [xref]b[/xref]son of David, the king in Jerusalem.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., the Assembly speaker, or, Collector (of sayings); Heb. [i]Qohelet[/i]. The word was translated [i]Ecclesiastes[/i] (meaning [i]Assembly member[/i]) in the Septuagint; hence, the English name of the book.</note>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 1:12; 7:27</xref>
        <xref num="b">Matt. 1:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>[note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Vanity of vanities, says the Preacher; / Vanity of vanities; [note]2[/note]all is [xref]b[/xref]vanity.</text>
        <note num="1">The word can also be translated [i]vapor, breath[/i]. So throughout the book. The contents of Ecclesiastes are a description by Solomon, after his falling away from God ([link]1 Kings 11:1-8[/link]) and returning back to God, of the human life of fallen mankind under the sun, a life in the corrupted world ([link]Eph. 2:12[/link]). According to this book human history, from its beginning to the present, is vanity. Through all the positive and negative experiences of the human life under the sun, Solomon was deeply impressed and occupied with the vanity of vanities of the human life under the sun in its falling away from God. Man was created by God with the highest and most noble purpose, that is, to express God in His image with His divine life and nature ([link]Gen. 1:26[/link] and note 3). But God's enemy, Satan the devil, came in to inject himself as sin into the man God created for His purpose ([link]Gen. 3:1-6[/link]). Through this fall, man and all the created things that had been committed by God to man's dominion were brought into the slavery of corruption and made subject to vanity ([link]Rom. 8:20-21[/link]). Thus, the human life in the corrupted world also became vanity, a chasing after wind ([link]v. 14[/link]). The writer fully realized this and stressed this to the uttermost in his description. Yet he was not fully disappointed in this; rather, he instructed men that there is a way to escape this vanity, i.e., to come back to God and take God as man's everything, man's redemption, life, wealth, enjoyment, pleasure, and satisfaction ([link]12:13[/link]), that man may still be used by God to fulfill His original purpose in creating man, for the accomplishing of God's eternal economy.</note>
        <note num="2">The book of Proverbs stresses the wisdom that man receives of God through his contacting of God, wisdom that teaches man how to behave in his human life. Ecclesiastes stresses the vanity of vanities of all things under the sun, as realized by man through the wisdom received from God. No matter how good, excellent, marvelous, and wonderful a thing may be, as long as it is of the old creation, it is part of the vanity of vanities under the sun. Only the new creation, which is in the heavens and not "under the sun," is not vanity but is reality. The next book, Song of Songs, stresses that Christ is the song of songs, the satisfaction of satisfactions to human life, which is versus the vanity of vanities of all things under the sun.</note>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 39:5-6; Eccl. 12:8</xref>
        <xref num="b">Rom. 8:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]What advantage does a man have in all his work / Which he does [xref]b[/xref]under the sun?</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 2:22; 3:9</xref>
        <xref num="b">Eccl. 1:9, 14; 2:11, 17-20, 22; 5:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>A generation goes and a generation comes, / But the earth [xref]a[/xref]stands forever.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 104:5; 119:90; cf. 1 Cor. 7:31</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Also, the sun [xref]a[/xref]rises, and the sun sets / And hurries to its place where it rises.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 19:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Going to the south, then turning to the north, / Turning about continually, the wind goes on; / And [i]following[/i] its circuits, the wind returns.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>All the rivers run to the sea, / Yet the sea is not full; / To the place where the rivers run, / There they run again.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>All things are wearisome; / No one is able to tell [i]it;[/i] / The [xref]a[/xref]eye is not satisfied with seeing, / Nor is the ear filled with hearing.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 27:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]What has been is what will be, / And what has been done is what will be done, / And there is nothing new [xref]b[/xref]under the sun.</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 3:15</xref>
        <xref num="b">Eccl. 1:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Is there anything of which one can say, See, this is new? / Already it has been, in the ages that were before us.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>There is [xref]a[/xref]no remembrance of those who were before; / And also those who will come to be afterward, for them there will be no / remembrance / With those who come to be after [i]them.[/i]</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 2:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>I, the [xref]a[/xref]Preacher, have been king over Israel in Jerusalem.</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 1:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And I set my heart to seek and to search out by wisdom [note]1[/note]all that is done [xref]a[/xref]under the heavens. It is grievous [xref]b[/xref]travail that God has given to the children of men to travail in.</text>
        <note num="1">Solomon set his heart to seek and to search out all that is done under the heavens, and he observed that all the works of man under the sun are done in cycle, going on and on, remaining the same generation after generation, like the phenomena in nature ([link]vv. 3-7[/link]). All things are wearisome, nothing is satisfying, there is nothing new, and nothing is remembered ([link]vv. 8-11[/link]). In his conclusion after all his experiments in the human life, all is vanity and a chasing after wind ([link]vv. 2[/link], [link]14[/link]). Such a conclusion of the wise king by his wisdom may be considered a history of the vain life of a fallen man. His conclusion in this book is like a dirge to a man whose end is in misery.[br/][br/]All the unveilings that issued out of the writer's experiments and searching and testing should not be considered the divine revelation from God concerning His divine purpose for human life, though they are included in the Scriptures under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit. They are the conclusion of the writer's research in his experiments in the realm of the human life of fallen man under the sun. In the divine intention all the concluding words may be considered proverbs, words of wisdom, that direct fallen and aim-missing men to return to God ([link]12:1a[/link], [link]13-14[/link]) and receive Him, according to His New Testament economy, in His Son as their Redeemer and life, that they may be regenerated to be the God-men for the accomplishing of God's eternal economy. Cf. note [link]1[sup]1[/sup], par. 2, in Psa. 1[/link] and note [link]1[sup]1[/sup], par. 2, in Prov. 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 2:3</xref>
        <xref num="b">Gen. 3:18-19; Eccl. 3:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>I have seen all the works that are done under the sun, and indeed, all is vanity and a [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]chasing after wind.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., shepherding. Alternatively, the phrase could be translated, a feeding on wind (cf. [link]Hosea 12:1[/link]). So throughout the book.</note>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 1:17; 2:11, 17, 26; 4:4, 6, 16; 6:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>What is [xref]a[/xref]crooked cannot be made straight, and what is lacking cannot be counted.</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 7:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>I spoke to my own heart, saying, Now I have magnified and increased [i]my[/i] wisdom more than all who have been over Jerusalem [xref]a[/xref]before me; and my heart has observed in abundance wisdom and knowledge.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 3:12-13; Eccl. 2:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And I set my heart to know wisdom and to know madness and folly; I perceived that this also is a chasing after wind.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>For in much wisdom is much vexation, and he who increases knowledge increases sorrow.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>I said in my heart, Come now, I will test out pleasure; so [note]1[/note]taste enjoyment. But indeed, this also is vanity.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., look on goodness. So throughout the book.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>I said of laughter, Madness! and of pleasure, What does it accomplish?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>I searched with my heart how to cheer my flesh with wine while my heart guided me with wisdom, and how to take hold of folly, until I could see what good there is for the children of men to do [xref]a[/xref]under the heavens the few days of their lives.</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 1:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>I enlarged my works: I [xref]a[/xref]built houses for myself; I planted vineyards for myself;</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 9:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>I made gardens and parks for myself, and planted in them trees of every kind of fruit.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>I made water ponds for myself from which to water a forest of growing trees.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>I bought male and female servants, and had servants born in my house; also I had great possessions of herds and flocks, more than all that had been before me in Jerusalem.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>I gathered also [xref]a[/xref]silver and gold for myself and the treasures of kings and provinces; I got for myself male singers and female singers and the delights of the children of men, [note]1[/note]concubine after concubine.</text>
        <note num="1">The meaning of the Hebrew is uncertain.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 9:28; 10:10, 27; 2 Chron. 1:15; 9:27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And I became great and increased more than all who had been [xref]a[/xref]before me in Jerusalem; also my wisdom remained with me.</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 1:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And whatever my eyes desired I did not keep from them; I did not keep my heart from any pleasure, for my heart found pleasure in all my labor, and this was my portion from all my labor.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Then I turned to all the works that my hands had done and the labor by which I had labored in doing [i]them,[/i] and indeed, all was vanity and a [xref]a[/xref]chasing after wind; and there was no advantage under the sun.</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 1:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And I turned to consider wisdom and madness and folly, for what will the man do who comes after the king? [i]Only[/i] that which has been done already.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And I saw that wisdom excels folly as light excels darkness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>The wise man's eyes are in his head, and the fool walks in darkness; yet I also perceived that [xref]a[/xref]one fate happens to them all.</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 2:16; 9:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And I said in my heart, As it happens to the fool, so also will it happen to me. Why then have I been so wise? And I said in my heart, This also is vanity.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>For of the wise man, even as of the fool, there is no remembrance forever, seeing that in the days to come all will be forgotten. And how the wise man dies just like the fool!</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>So I hated life, for the work that is done under the sun was grievous to me, because everything is vanity and a [xref]a[/xref]chasing after wind.</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 1:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And I hated all my labor for which I had labored under the sun, because I will [xref]a[/xref]leave it to the man who comes after me.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 49:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And who knows whether he will be a wise man or a fool? Yet he will be master over all my labor for which I have labored and in which I exercised wisdom under the sun. This also is vanity.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Therefore I turned and gave my heart up to despair of all the labor for which I had labored [xref]a[/xref]under the sun;</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 1:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>For there is a man whose labor has been with wisdom and with knowledge and with skill, and to a man who has not labored on it he gives it as his portion. This also is vanity and a great evil.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>For what will a man have with all his labor and with the striving of his heart by which he labors under the sun?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>For all his days are sorrow, and his travail is vexation; even at night his heart does not rest. This also is vanity.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>There is nothing better for man than to [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]eat and to drink and to make his soul taste enjoyment in his labor. This also I saw, that it is from the hand of God.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]12[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 3[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 3:13; 5:18; Luke 12:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>For who can eat or who can enjoy [note]1[/note]without Him?</text>
        <note num="1">Following the Septuagint and some Hebrew MSS; other MSS read, more than I.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>For to the man who is good in His sight He gives wisdom and knowledge and joy, but to the sinner He gives the travail of gathering and heaping up that it may be given to him who is good in God's sight. This also is vanity and a [xref]a[/xref]chasing after wind.</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 1:14</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>For everything there is a season, / And a [xref]a[/xref]time for every purpose under heaven:</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 8:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>A time to be [xref]a[/xref]born, and a time to [xref]b[/xref]die; / A time to plant, and a time to pluck up what is planted;</text>
        <xref num="a">Gal. 1:15; 4:4</xref>
        <xref num="b">Heb. 9:27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>A time to kill, and a time to heal; / A time to tear down, and a time to build up;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>A time to weep, and a time to laugh; / A time to mourn, and a time to dance;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>A time to cast away stones, and a time to gather stones together; / A time to embrace, and a time to [xref]a[/xref]refrain from embracing;</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Cor. 7:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>A time to seek, and a time to lose; / A time to keep, and a time to throw away;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>A time to tear, and a time to sew; / A time to [xref]a[/xref]be silent, and a time to [xref]b[/xref]speak;</text>
        <xref num="a">Amos 5:13; 1 Cor. 14:30</xref>
        <xref num="b">Luke 19:40; Acts 4:20; 18:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>A time to [xref]a[/xref]love, and a time to [xref]b[/xref]hate; / A time for war, and a time for peace.</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 26:7</xref>
        <xref num="b">Luke 14:26; John 12:25</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>What profit does the worker have in all that he labors?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>I have seen the [xref]a[/xref]travail that God has given the children of men to travail in.</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 1:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>He has made everything beautiful in its own time; also He has put [note]1[/note]eternity in their heart, yet so that man does not [xref]a[/xref]find out what God has done from the beginning to the end.</text>
        <note num="1">"A divinely implanted sense of purpose working through the ages, which nothing under the sun, but only God, can satisfy" (The Amplified Bible). God created man in His image and formed in him a spirit that man may receive and contain Him ([link]Gen. 1:26[/link] and note 3; [link]2:7[/link] and note 5). In addition, God put eternity, an aspiration for something eternal, in man's heart so that man will seek God, the eternal One. Hence, temporal things can never satisfy man; only the eternal God, who is Christ, can satisfy the deep sense of purpose in man's heart (cf. [link]2 Cor. 4:18[/link]). See note [link]4[sup]1[/sup] in S.S. 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 8:17; Rom. 11:33</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>I know that there is nothing better for them than to [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]rejoice and do good in their lifetime;</text>
        <note num="1">In all his experiments in human life Solomon encouraged the fallen men under the sun, in accordance with God's economy, to rejoice and do good in their lifetime and to enjoy what God has given to them, eating, drinking, and tasting enjoyment in all their labor ([link]2:24[/link]; [link]3:12-13[/link]; [link]5:18-20[/link]; [link]8:15[/link]; [link]9:7-10[/link]). God created man for Himself, but man was seduced by Satan to give God up, and thus man became fallen. Nevertheless, God still blesses man so that he may have a good living and enjoy various material things (cf. [link]Matt. 5:45b[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 6:17[/link]). By so doing God maintains the existence of the human race from generation to generation, thus affording Himself the opportunity to accomplish His redemption for fallen man, to carry out His eternal purpose in His choosing and predestinating men for the Body of Christ, and to maintain the fallen man of His old creation to be the provision for Him to bring in His new creation in Christ out of the old creation ([link]2 Cor. 5:17[/link]; [link]Gal. 6:15[/link]). This is proved by the apostle Paul's preaching in [link]Acts 14:15-17[/link] and [link]17:24-31[/link].[br/][br/]To live a life that we may testify Christ and minister Christ to others to glorify God, we need the material things and physical matters. But we should not be attracted, captured, and usurped by them. If we are usurped by them, we will suffer their vanity. We are living in the world and passing through the "vanity fair," but we should not linger in it for its vainglory ([link]1 John 2:15-17[/link]). Today all things of the old creation are under the slavery of corruption ([link]Rom. 8:20-21[/link]). If we do not escape "the corruption which is in the world by lust" ([link]2 Pet. 1:4[/link]), we will share in its vanity.</note>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 3:22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Moreover, that every man should [xref]a[/xref]eat and drink and taste enjoyment in all his labor; it is the gift of God.</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 2:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>I know that whatever God does, it will be forever; nothing can be added to it, nor can anything be taken from it. God has [i]so[/i] done, that [i]all[/i] would fear Him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]That which is has already been, and that which will be has already been; and God seeks what has [note]1[/note]passed.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., been driven (i.e., into the past). God, in His sovereignty over all, has appointed all things that are in the present and that will be in the future and seeks to reemploy the things that took place in the past. Whatever God does will be forever; nothing can be added to it, nor can anything be taken from it, that all would fear Him that they may have His wisdom to realize the real meaning of human life ([link]vv. 14-15[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 1:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Moreover I saw under the sun [i]that[/i] in the place of judgment, wickedness is there; and in the place of righteousness, wickedness is there.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>I said in my heart, God will [xref]a[/xref]judge the righteous and the wicked; for there is a time there for every purpose and every work.</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 25:32, 46; John 5:29; Rom. 2:5-6, 16; 1 Cor. 4:5; 2 Cor. 5:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>I said in my heart, [i]This is so[/i] for the sake of the children of men, that God may prove them and that they may see for themselves that they are but beasts.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>For what happens to the children of men happens also to beasts; even the same thing happens to them [i]both:[/i] As the one dies, so dies the other; and they all have one [note]1[/note]breath; and man has no advantage over the beast; for all is vanity.</text>
        <note num="1">Heb. [i]ruach,[/i] different from [i]neshamah,[/i] the word translated [i]breath[/i] in [link]Gen. 2:7[/link] (see note 5 there).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>All go to one place: all are of [xref]a[/xref]dust, and all return to dust.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 3:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Who knows the [note]1[/note]breath of the children of men, that it goes upward; or the [note]1[/note]breath of the beasts, that it goes downward to the earth?</text>
        <note num="1">Heb. [i]ruach.[/i] See note [link]5[sup]1[/sup] in Ezek. 37[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Therefore I saw that there is nothing better than that [i]a man[/i] should [xref]a[/xref]rejoice in his works, for that is his portion. For who will bring him to see what will be after him?</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 3:12</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Then again I saw all the acts of oppression that are done under the sun; and indeed, the tears of the oppressed, and they had no comforter; and on the side of the oppressors was power, and they had no comforter.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And I praised the dead, who have already died, more than the living, who are still alive.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And better than both is he who has not yet been, who has not seen the evil work that is done under the sun.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Then I saw all labor and all skill in work, that it is man's jealousy for his neighbor. This also is vanity and a [xref]a[/xref]chasing after wind.</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 1:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>The fool folds his hands together and consumes his own flesh.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Better is a handful with quietness than two hands full with labor and a chasing after wind.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 17:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Then again I saw vanity under the sun.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>There is one [i]alone[/i] and without a second; also he has no son or brother. Yet there is no end to all his labor; moreover his [xref]a[/xref]eye is not satisfied with riches. For whom then, [i]he says,[/i] do I labor and deprive myself of good? This also is vanity and grievous travail.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 27:20; 1 John 2:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Two are better than one, because they have a good reward for their labor;</text>
        <xref num="a">Mark 6:7; cf. Gen. 2:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>For if they fall, the one will lift up his companion. But woe to the one who falls and does not have another to lift him up!</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Again, if two lie together, they keep warm. But how can one be warm [i]alone?[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And while a man may prevail against the one, the two will withstand him; and a threefold cord is not quickly broken.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Better is a poor but wise youth than an old and foolish king who no longer knows how to be admonished.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>For [i]one[/i] can come forth from prison to reign, even though he was born poor in his kingdom.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>I saw all the living that went about under the sun with the youth, the successor, who stood up in place of [note]1[/note]him.</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to the old king.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>There was no end to all the people, to all before whom he stood, [i]yet[/i] even those who come after will not rejoice in him. Surely this also is vanity and a [xref]a[/xref]chasing after wind.</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 1:14</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="5">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Guard your [xref]a[/xref]steps when you go to the house of God, and draw near to listen rather than to offer the [xref]b[/xref]sacrifice of fools; for they do not know that they are doing evil.</text>
        <note num="1">Solomon's word here regarding contacting God is not with the view of encouragement but with the view of caution. This is different from the view of the apostle Paul in his encouraging the believers to approach God to receive mercy and find grace for timely help ([link]Heb. 4:16[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 1:12</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 15:22; Psa. 50:8; Prov. 15:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Do not be [xref]a[/xref]rash with your mouth, and let not your heart hastily utter anything before God; for God is in heaven and you are on the earth; therefore let your words be few.</text>
        <xref num="a">James 1:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>For a dream comes through a multitude of travail, and a fool's voice through a multitude of words.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>When you make a [xref]a[/xref]vow to God, do not delay in paying it; for [i]He takes[/i] no pleasure in fools. [xref]b[/xref]Pay what you vow.</text>
        <xref num="a">Num. 30:2; Deut. 23:21-22</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 50:14; Matt. 5:33</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>It is better that you do not vow than that you vow and not pay.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Do not let your mouth cause your flesh to sin, and do not say before the messenger that it was a mistake. Why should God be angry at your voice and destroy the works of your hands?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>For in the multitude of dreams and [i]in[/i] many words are also vanities. Rather, fear God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>If you see the oppression of the poor and the wresting of justice and righteousness in a province, do not be astonished at the matter; for one higher official watches over another high official, and there are higher officials over them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And a king who cultivates the field is always an advantage for a land.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>He who loves silver will not be satisfied with silver, nor he who loves abundance [i]with[/i] income. This is also vanity.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>When goods increase, those who eat them increase; so what advantage do their owners have except to see [i]them[/i] with their [xref]a[/xref]eyes?</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 27:20; Eccl. 4:8; 1 John 2:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Sweet is the sleep of the laborer, whether he eats little or much; but the fullness of the rich will not let him sleep.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>There is a grievous evil that I have seen under the sun: riches kept by their owner to his own hurt,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And those riches were lost in a bad venture; and having begotten a son, he had nothing in his hand.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>As he came forth from his mother's [xref]a[/xref]womb, he will return naked as he came; and he will take nothing of his labor that he may carry in his hand.</text>
        <xref num="a">Job 1:21; Psa. 49:17; 1 Tim. 6:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And this also is a grievous evil: in all points, as he came, so will he go; so what is the advantage to him who has labored for the wind?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Throughout all his days he also eats in darkness and has much vexation and sickness and resentment.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Here is what I have seen [i]to be[/i] good [i]and[/i] what is pleasant: to [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]eat and to drink and to taste enjoyment in all his labor by which he labors under the sun during the few days of his life, which God has [xref]b[/xref]given him; for this is his portion.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]12[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 3[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 2:24</xref>
        <xref num="b">Eccl. 3:13; 6:2; 1 Tim. 6:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Moreover, [i]for[/i] every man to whom God has given riches and wealth, and has empowered him to eat of them and to take his portion and to rejoice in his labor &amp;#8212; this is the gift of God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>For he will not [note]1[/note]brood much over the days of his life, because God keeps him occupied with the gladness of his heart.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, remember.</note>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="6">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>There is an evil that I have seen under the sun, and it is heavy upon man:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>A man to whom God gives riches, wealth, and honor, so that nothing is lacking to his soul of all that he desires, and yet God [xref]a[/xref]does not empower him to eat of it, but a stranger eats it. This is vanity and an evil plague.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 28:33; Luke 12:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>If a man begets a hundred children and lives many years, so that the days of his years are many, but his soul is not filled with good and even does not get a proper burial, I say that the [xref]a[/xref]stillborn is better off than he;</text>
        <xref num="a">Job 3:16; Psa. 58:8; Eccl. 4:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>For it comes in vanity and goes off in darkness, and in darkness its name is covered;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Moreover it has not seen the sun and does not know [i]anything;[/i] this one has rest rather than that one.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Indeed, even if he lives a thousand years twice and does not taste enjoyment, do not all go to one place?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>All a man's labor is for his mouth, and yet his appetite is not filled.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>For what advantage does the wise man have over the fool? What [i]advantage[/i] does the poor man have in knowing how to walk before the living?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Better is seeing with the eyes than wandering with the soul. This also is vanity and a chasing after wind.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]That which is has already been [note]1[/note]determined, and it is known what man is and that he cannot contend with him who is stronger than he.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., called by its name.</note>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 1:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>For there are many things, which will increase vanity. What is the advantage to man?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>For who knows what is good for a man in life during the few days of his vain life, which he will spend as a shadow? [xref]a[/xref]For who can tell a man what will be after him under the sun?</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 3:22; 8:7</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="7">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>A [xref]a[/xref]good name is better than precious ointment, / And the day of death, than the day of one's birth.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 22:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>It is better to go to the house of mourning / Than to go to the house of feasting, / Because that is the end of every man, / And the living takes it to heart.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Sorrow is better than laughter, / For by the sadness of face the heart is made good.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>The heart of the wise is in the house of mourning, / But the heart of fools is in the house of mirth.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>It is better [i]for one[/i] to hear the rebuke of a wise man / Than for one to hear the song of fools.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>For as the crackling of thorns under a pot, / So is the laughter of fools. / This also is [note]1[/note]vanity.</text>
        <note num="1">In his searching and testing all things of the human life under the sun, Solomon observed that all things are vanity of vanities, regardless of the kind of persons involved &amp;#8212; wise or foolish, diligent or lazy, rich or poor, old or young, high or low, righteous or wicked, good or sinful, clean or unclean &amp;#8212; and regardless of how they were born, how they worked, how they died, and what their end was ([link]7:6[/link], [link]15[/link]; [link]8:10[/link], [link]14[/link]; [link]9:9[/link]; [link]11:8[/link], [link]10[/link]; [link]12:8[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Surely oppression makes a wise man mad, / And a bribe destroys the heart.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Better is the end of a thing than its beginning; / Better is patience of spirit than haughtiness of spirit.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Do not be quick in your spirit to become [xref]a[/xref]angry, / For anger rests in the bosom of fools.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 14:17; 16:32; James 1:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Do not say, How is it that the former days were better than these? / For it is not from wisdom that you ask this.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Wisdom is as good as an inheritance, / And an advantage to those who see the sun.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>For wisdom is a defense, as money is a defense; / But the advantage of knowledge is that wisdom preserves the life of those / who have it.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Consider the work of God, / For who can straighten what He has made [xref]a[/xref]crooked?</text>
        <xref num="a">Job 12:14; Eccl. 1:15; Isa. 14:27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>In the day of prosperity be joyful, / And in the day of adversity consider. / God has made the one as well as the other, / So that man may not find out anything about what is after him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>I have seen everything in my days of vanity: There is a righteous man who perishes in his righteousness, and there is a wicked man who prolongs [i]his life[/i] in his wickedness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Do not be overly righteous, and do not be overly wise; why should you destroy yourself?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Do not be overly wicked, and do not be a fool; why should you die when it is [xref]a[/xref]not your time?</text>
        <xref num="a">Job 15:32; Psa. 55:23; Prov. 10:27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>It is better for you to take hold of the one without letting go of the other, for he who fears God will come out [i]of it[/i] with them all.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Wisdom strengthens the wise man more than ten rulers who are in a city.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Surely there is not a righteous man on the earth who does good and does not [xref]a[/xref]sin.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 8:46; 2 Chron. 6:36; Prov. 20:9; Rom. 3:23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Also, do not give heed to all words spoken, lest you hear your servant cursing you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>For your heart knows that many times you yourself have cursed others also.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>All this I have tested by wisdom; I said, I will be wise; but it was far from me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>That which is, is far off, and deep, very deep; who can find it out?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>I turned and my heart [i]was set[/i] to know and to search and seek out wisdom and the sum [i]of things,[/i] and to know that wickedness is folly and that foolishness is madness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>And I found more bitter than death the woman whose heart is traps and snares, whose hands are fetters. One who is well-pleasing to God escapes from her, but the sinner is taken by her.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>See, this is what I have found, says the Preacher, [i]adding[/i] one thing to another to find the sum,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>Which my soul is still seeking but has not found. One man among a thousand I have found, but a woman among all these I have not found.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>See, this alone have I found, that God made [xref]a[/xref]man upright, but they have sought out many schemes.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 1:27</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="8">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Who is like the wise man? And who knows the interpretation of a matter? A man's wisdom makes his face shine, and the sternness of his face is changed.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>[i]I say,[/i] Keep the commandment of the king, and [i]that,[/i] because of the oath before God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Do not hurry to leave him; do not [note]1[/note]join in an evil matter, for he will do whatever he pleases.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., stand.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>For the king's word is powerful, and who will say to him, What are you doing?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>He who keeps the commandment will know nothing evil, and a wise man's heart will know the proper time and manner.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>For there is a proper [xref]a[/xref]time and manner for every purpose, although the misery of man is heavy upon him;</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 3:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]For he does not know what will be, for who can tell him how it will be?</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 10:14; 6:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>There is no man who has power over his [note]1[/note]breath to retain his breath, and no one has power over the day of death; and there is no discharge in the battle, nor will wickedness deliver its own master.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, spirit (twice).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>All this I have seen, and I applied my heart to every work that is done under the sun when a man overpowers [i]another[/i] man to his hurt.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And then I saw the wicked buried, who [i]before[/i] had gone in and come forth from the holy place and were forgotten in the city where they had thus acted. This also is vanity.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Because the sentence against an evil deed is not [xref]a[/xref]executed speedily, therefore the heart of the children of men is fully set within them to do evil.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Pet. 3:9; cf. Psa. 10:6; 50:21</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Although a sinner does evil a hundred times and prolongs his [i]life,[/i] yet I also know that it will be well with the God-fearing who are in fear before Him;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>But it will not be well with the wicked man, nor will he prolong his days like a shadow, because he is not in fear before God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>There is a vanity that is done on the earth, that there are righteous men to whom [i]things[/i] [xref]a[/xref]happen according to the deeds of the wicked and there are wicked men to whom [i]things[/i] happen according to the deeds of the righteous. I say that this also is vanity.</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 7:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>So I praised pleasure, because there is nothing better for man under the sun than to [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]eat and to drink and to rejoice; for that will stay with him in his labor during the days of his life which God has given him under the sun.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]12[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 3[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 2:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>When I set my heart to know wisdom and to see the travail that is done on the earth (even though [note]1[/note]man's eyes do not see sleep day or night),</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., his.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Then I saw every work of God, that man cannot find out the work that is done under the sun, because however man labors to seek [i]it[/i] out, he will not find [i]it[/i] out; and even if the wise man says that he will come to know [i]it,[/i] he is not able to find [i]it[/i] out.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="9">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>For all this I laid on my heart, so that I might explain all this, that the righteous and the wise and their works are in the hand of God; man knows neither love nor hate; all is before them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>All things are alike to all: One thing happens to the righteous man and to the wicked man, to the good and to the clean and to the unclean, to him who sacrifices and to him who does not sacrifice; as the good man is, so is the sinner; he who swears is like him who fears an oath.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>This is an evil among all that is done under the sun, that one thing happens to all; moreover the heart of the children of men is full of evil, and madness is in their heart while they live; and [xref]a[/xref]after that, [i]they go[/i] to the dead.</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 12:7; 1 Cor. 15:22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>For there is hope for whoever is joined to all the living &amp;#8212; surely a living dog is better than a dead lion &amp;#8212;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>For the living know that they will [xref]a[/xref]die; but the dead know nothing, and they have no more reward, for the [xref]b[/xref]memory of them is forgotten.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Heb. 9:27</xref>
        <xref num="b">Eccl. 2:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Their love, their hate, and their envy have already perished, nor do they have some portion yet in all that is done under the sun forever.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Go; [note]1[/note]eat your bread with joy, and drink your wine with a merry heart; for God has already accepted your works.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]12[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 3[/link]. Man should enjoy God's provision for his living and the marriage life for man's existence and multiplication ([link]vv. 7-10[/link]) to replenish the earth ([link]Gen. 1:28[/link]) that it may be possible for God to save some men in order to produce the church &amp;#8212; the Body of Christ &amp;#8212; which will issue in the New Jerusalem as God's eternal enlargement and expression according to God's eternal economy.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Let your garments always be [xref]a[/xref]white, and do not let [xref]b[/xref]oil be lacking on your head.</text>
        <xref num="a">Rev. 3:4</xref>
        <xref num="b">Matt. 6:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Enjoy life with the wife whom you have loved all the days of your life of vanity which He has given you under the sun, all the days of your vanity; for this is your portion in life and in your labor by which you have labored under the sun.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 5:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Whatever your hand finds to do, do with [i]all[/i] your might; for there is no work or thought or knowledge or wisdom in Sheol, where you are going.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Again I saw under the sun that the race is not to the swift, nor is the battle to the mighty, nor is even the bread to the wise, nor are riches to those who have understanding, nor is favor to those who have knowledge; but time and chance happen to them all.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>For also man does not know his time: Like fish that are caught in a deadly net and like birds that are caught in a snare, so the children of men are [xref]a[/xref]ensnared in an evil time when it falls suddenly on them.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 24:17; Luke 21:34; 1 Tim. 3:7; 6:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>This also I have seen as wisdom under the sun, and it seemed great to me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>There was a small [xref]a[/xref]city with a few men in it; and a great king came against it and surrounded it and built great siegeworks against it.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 2 Sam. 20:15-22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And in it there was found a poor wise man, and he delivered the city by his wisdom; yet no one remembered that poor man.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>So I said, Wisdom is better than strength; but the wisdom of the poor man is despised, and his words are not heard.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>The words of the wise man [i]spoken[/i] quietly are heeded more than the shouting of a ruler among fools.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Wisdom is better than weapons of war, but one sinner destroys much good.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="10">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Dead flies cause the perfumer's ointment to stink, to ferment; [i]so[/i] a little folly outweighs wisdom and honor.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>A wise man's heart [i]inclines[/i] to his right, but a fool's heart [i]inclines[/i] to his left.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And also, when the fool walks on the way, his sense fails [i]him,[/i] and he tells everyone that he is a fool.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>If the ruler's spirit rises up against you, do not leave your place; for composure allays great offenses.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>There is an evil that I have seen under the sun, like an error that proceeds from the ruler:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Folly is set in many high places, and rich men sit in a low place.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>I have seen servants on horses and princes walking on the earth like servants.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>He who digs a pit will fall into it, and he who breaks through a wall will be bitten by a serpent;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Whoever quarries stones will be hurt by them, and whoever splits logs will be endangered by them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>If the iron is blunt, and one does not whet the edge, then he must apply more strength; but wisdom has the advantage of giving success.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>If the serpent bites before it is charmed, then there is no advantage in a charmer.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>The words of a wise man's mouth are gracious, but the lips of a fool swallow him up.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>The beginning of the words of his mouth is folly, and the end of his talk is wicked madness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Yet the fool multiplies words. [xref]a[/xref]No man knows what will be; and what will be after him, who can tell him?</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 8:7; 6:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>The labor of fools wears them out, because they do not know [i]even[/i] how to get to town.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Woe to you, O land whose king is a [xref]a[/xref]young boy and whose princes feast in the morning!</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 3:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Happy are you, O land whose king is the son of nobles and whose princes feast at the [i]proper[/i] time, for strength and not for drunkenness!</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Through slothfulness the rafters sag, and through idleness of hands the house leaks.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>[note]1[/note]They make a feast for laughter, and wine makes life merry, and money is the answer to everything.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., the princes of [link]v. 16[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Do not curse the king even in your thought, and do not curse a rich man in your bedroom; for a bird of [xref]a[/xref]heaven will carry the sound, or [i]something[/i] with wings will tell the matter.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Luke 12:2-3</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="11">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Cast your bread upon the surface of the waters, for you will find it in many days.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Give a portion to seven, and even to eight, for you do not know what calamity will happen on the earth.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 112:9; Luke 6:30</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>If the clouds are full, they pour forth rain on the earth; and whether a tree falls toward the south or toward the north, in the place where it falls, there will it be.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>He who watches the wind will [xref]a[/xref]not sow, and he who looks at the clouds will not reap.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 20:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Just as you do not know what the path of the [xref]a[/xref]wind is [i]or[/i] how the bones [i]are[/i] [xref]b[/xref][i]formed[/i] in the mother's womb, so you do not know the work of God, who makes everything.</text>
        <xref num="a">John 3:8</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 139:14-15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>In the morning sow your seed, and in the evening do not hold back your hands; for you do not know which will prosper, this one or that, or whether both alike will be good.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>The light is sweet, and it is pleasant for the eyes to see the sun.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Indeed if a man should live many years, let him rejoice in all of them; but let him remember the days of [xref]a[/xref]darkness, for they will be many. All that comes is vanity.</text>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 12:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Rejoice, [note]1[/note]young man, in your childhood, and let your heart be merry in the days of your youth; and walk in the ways of your heart and in the sight of your eyes. But know that for all these things God will bring you to [xref]a[/xref]judgment.</text>
        <note num="1">In his advice to young men, the writer says that they should endeavor to enjoy the human life in their youth in the light of God's judgment ([link]12:14[/link] and note) in order to remove vexation from their heart and put away evil from their flesh ([link]vv. 9-10[/link]). He also advises them to remember their Creator while they are young and not hesitate in doing this until old age comes ([link]12:1[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 12:14; Rom. 2:5-11; Heb. 9:27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>So remove vexation from your heart, and put away evil from your flesh; for childhood and the dawn of life are vanity.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="12">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Remember also your [xref]a[/xref]Creator in the days of your [xref]b[/xref]youth, before the [note]1[/note]evil days come and the years draw near when you will say, I have no pleasure in them;</text>
        <note num="1">The days when a person is old and near death, when he has no more pleasure in living.</note>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 1:1; Isa. 40:28; 43:15; Rom. 1:25; 1 Pet. 4:19</xref>
        <xref num="b">Prov. 22:6; Lam. 3:27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Before the sun and the light and the moon and the stars are [note]1[/note]darkened, and the clouds return after the rain;</text>
        <note num="1">In man's old age, the bright environment, with the three lights created by God and the artificial lights made by man, becomes gloomy, and the pleasant atmosphere of the clear sky is cloudy. The hands (the keepers of the house &amp;#8212; man's body &amp;#8212; cf. [link]2 Cor. 5:1-8[/link]) tremble ([link]v. 3a[/link]); the loins (the men of strength) are bent ([link]v. 3b[/link]); the teeth (the women who grind) become few ([link]v. 3c[/link]); the eyes (those who look out of the windows) become dim ([link]v. 3d[/link]); and the ears become dull to sound ([link]v. 4a[/link]). One awakens early in the morning ([link]v. 4b[/link]); the vocal cords (the daughters of song) become low ([link]v. 4c[/link]); and one is afraid of what is high ([link]v. 5a[/link]) and is terrified while walking ([link]v. 5b[/link]). The hair becomes white (the almond tree blossoms &amp;#8212; [link]v. 5c[/link]), and one is unable to bear any burden, even a burden as small as a grasshopper ([link]v. 5d[/link]). No medicine can keep the old man away from death, and mourners attend his funeral ([link]v. 5e[/link]). The corpse &amp;#8212; the spinal cord (the silver cord), the head (the golden bowl), the lungs (the pitcher), and the heart (the wheel) &amp;#8212; decays ([link]v. 6[/link]). The body made of dust returns to the earth, and the breath returns to God who gave it ([link]v. 7[/link]; [link]Gen. 2:7[/link]). This indicates that the entire human being with his human life apart from God is nothing but vanity of vanity ([link]v. 8[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>In the day when the keepers of the house tremble and the men of strength bow themselves and the women who grind cease because they are few, and those who look out of the windows see dimly;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And [i]when[/i] the doors are shut on the street; when the sound of the grinding is low, and one arises at the sound of a bird, and all the daughters of [xref]a[/xref]song are brought low;</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 19:35</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>[i]When[/i] also [i]men[/i] are afraid of what is high, and terrors are on the way; and the almond tree blossoms, and the grasshopper is a burden, and the caperberry is ineffective (for man will go to his everlasting home while mourners go around in the street);</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Before the silver cord is undone, and the golden bowl is broken, and the pitcher is shattered at the fountain, and the wheel is broken at the cistern,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And the [xref]a[/xref]dust returns to the earth as it was, and the [xref]b[/xref]breath returns to God who [xref]c[/xref]gave it.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 3:19; Job 34:15; Psa. 90:3</xref>
        <xref num="b">Eccl. 3:21</xref>
        <xref num="c">Gen. 2:7; Acts 17:25</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Vanity of vanity, says the Preacher; all is vanity.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 62:9; Eccl. 1:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And in addition to being wise, the Preacher also taught the people knowledge; and he pondered and studied and arranged many [xref]a[/xref]proverbs.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 4:32</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>The Preacher sought to find pleasing words, and he wrote words of truth rightly.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>The words of the wise are like goads, and like well-driven nails are the collections [i]of them;[/i] they are given by one [xref]a[/xref]Shepherd.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 23:1; John 10:14; Heb. 13:20; 1 Pet. 5:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And of what is beyond these, my son, beware: Of the making of many books there is no end, and much study is a weariness of the flesh.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>The end of the matter, when all has been heard, [i]is this:[/i] [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Fear God and keep His commandments, for this is the whole of man.</text>
        <note num="1">The writer's concluding word leads men to fear God that God may eventually show them His New Testament economy concerning the producing of His church, the Body of Christ, which consummates in the New Jerusalem as God's eternal enlargement and expression.</note>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 6:2; 10:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>For God will bring every deed to [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]judgment, with every secret thing, whether good or evil.</text>
        <note num="1">God will judge men living in the present age in relation to their deeds, even every secret thing, according to whether it is good or evil, and He will judge the unbelieving dead at His great white throne in relation to their eternal destiny ([link]Rev. 20:11-15[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Eccl. 11:9; Matt. 12:36; Acts 17:30-31; Rom. 2:16; 14:10, 12; 1 Cor. 4:5; 2 Cor. 5:10</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    </chapters>
</book>
