<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="yes"?>
<book name="Ezra">
    <info title="Author">Ezra, a descendant of Aaron ([link]7:1-5[/link]), and a priest and a scribe skilled in the law of Moses ([link]7:6[/link], [link]11-12[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Time of Writing">After 457 B.C.</info>
    <info title="Place of Writing">Jerusalem.</info>
    <info title="Time Period Covered">This book covers a period of about eighty-two years, from 539 B.C. to 457 B.C., from the first year of Cyrus the king of Persia ([link]1:1[/link]) to the first day of the first month following the seventh year of Artaxerxes the king of Persia ([link]10:17[/link]; [link]7:7[/link]).</info>
    <subject>The Return of the Children of Israel from Their Captivity and the Rebuilding of the House of God as the Initiation of God's Recovery among His Elect for His Testimony on the Earth according to His Economy</subject>
    <outlines>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="1" ref="1:1-6:22">The return of the captivity under the kingly leadership of Zerubbabel</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="1:1-4">The decree of Cyrus the king of Persia</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="1:5-6">The response of the heads of the fathers' houses of Judah and Benjamin, the priests, and the Levites</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="1:7-11">The cooperation of King Cyrus</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="4" ref="2:1-67">The number of the returned captives</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="5" ref="2:68-70">The willing offering for the house of Jehovah</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="6" ref="3:1-6a">The rebuilding of the altar of God</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="7" ref="3:6b-13">The rebuilding of the house of God</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="8" ref="4:1-24">The frustration</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="9" ref="5:1-2">The rebuilding work continuing through the encouragement and help of the prophecies of Haggai and Zechariah</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="10" ref="5:3-6:12">The confirmation of the decree of Darius the king of Persia</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="11" ref="6:13-15">The completion of the rebuilding of the house of God</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="12" ref="6:16-18">The dedication of the rebuilt house of God</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="13" ref="6:19-22">The keeping of the Passover by the children of the captivity</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="2" ref="7:1-10:44">The return of the captivity under the priestly leadership of Ezra</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="7:1-8:36">The return of the captivity under Ezra</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="1" ref="7:1-10">The beginning of the return through the request of Ezra to the king</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="2" ref="7:11-28">The decree of Artaxerxes the king of Persia to Ezra</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="3" ref="8:1-20">The genealogical enrollment of those who returned from captivity</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="4" ref="8:21-23">Ezra's proclamation of a fast before they left Babylon</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="5" ref="8:24-30">Ezra's provision for the offerings for the house of God</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="6" ref="8:31-34">The journey and arrival of the returned captivity</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="7" ref="8:35">The offerings to God by the returned captivity</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="8" ref="8:36">The returned captivity's delivery of the king's decrees to the king's satraps and to the governors beyond the River</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="9:1-10:44">The purification of the returned captives from the defilement of foreign wives</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="1" ref="9:1-2">Initiated by the officials of the returned captives</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="2" ref="9:3-15">Ezra's reaction</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="3" ref="10:1-5">The congregation's reaction</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="4" ref="10:6-44">The final decision</outline>
    </outlines>
    <chapters>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Now in the first year of Cyrus the king of Persia, so that the [xref]b[/xref]word of Jehovah by the mouth of Jeremiah might be accomplished, Jehovah [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]stirred up the spirit of [note]3[/note]Cyrus the king of Persia; and he made a proclamation throughout all his kingdom and [i]put it[/i] also in writing, saying,</text>
        <note num="1">Ezra, Nehemiah, and Esther, the last three books of the history of God's chosen people in the Old Testament, are related to God's chosen people in their captivity ([link]2 Chron. 36:17-21[/link]). Ezra concerns the return of God's people from their captivity (cf. [link]Daniel[/link], [link]Haggai[/link], [link]Zechariah[/link], and [link]Malachi[/link]) to Jerusalem to rebuild the temple, and Nehemiah concerns the repair, the rebuilding, of the city. Esther presents to us a pattern of how the omnipresent and omnipotent God becomes the hiding God who secretly preserves and cares for His chosen people in their captivity.[br/][br/]The book of Ezra provides a record of the two returns of the children of Israel from their captivity, which fulfilled God's promise, spoken through Jeremiah, that the captivity would last only seventy years ([link]Jer. 25:11-12[/link]; [link]29:10[/link]; [link]2 Chron. 36:21-22[/link]; [link]Dan. 9:2[/link]). The first return was under the kingly leadership of Zerubbabel ([link]chs. 1-6[/link]), a descendant of the royal family of David who was appointed to be the governor of Judah by Cyrus ([link]5:14[/link]; cf. note [link]8[sup]1[/sup][/link]). The second return was under the priestly leadership of Ezra ([link]chs. 7-10[/link]).[br/][br/]The return of Israel to Jerusalem from their captivity was crucial in four points: (1) it recovered the purpose of God's calling Israel to make them His testimony according to His law (see note [link]1[sup]1[/sup] in Exo. 20[/link]); (2) it recovered the oneness of Israel on the unique ground of Jerusalem ([link]Deut. 12:5[/link], [link]11-14[/link]); (3) it recovered Israel's enjoyment of the good land promised by God; and (4) it allowed God to fulfill His intention of having His house built and His kingdom established on the Satan-usurped earth in order to carry out His eternal economy through Israel's participation in and enjoyment of the good land. All the foregoing crucial points typify today's recovery of the church life, which is a recovery of the church out of captivity in the great Babylon ([link]Rev. 17:1-6[/link]) back to the unique ground of God's choice, the ground of oneness.</note>
        <note num="2">At the expiration of the seventy years of the captivity in Babylon, the omnipotent, sovereign God moved in a hidden way to stir up King Cyrus openly to release the Israelite captives to go back to their own land to build up God's temple ([link]vv. 1-4[/link]). The stirring up of the spirit of Cyrus and the spirits of the leaders of the tribes of Judah, Benjamin, and Levi ([link]v. 5[/link]) was a work of the hiding God (see note [link]1[sup]1[/sup], par. 1, in Esth. 1[/link]) for His move to rebuild His house in Jerusalem.</note>
        <note num="3">Because Cyrus not only issued the decree ordering the captives of Israel to go back to Jerusalem and rebuild the house of God there ([link]vv. 2-4[/link]) but also cooperated in this matter ([link]vv. 7-11[/link]), he is called God's shepherd, one who would fulfill God's desire ([link]Isa. 44:28[/link]), and God's anointed, one who would serve God's purpose ([link]Isa. 45:1-4[/link], [link]13[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">vv. 1-3: 2 Chron. 36:22-23</xref>
        <xref num="b">Jer. 25:12-13; 29:10</xref>
        <xref num="c">Ezra 1:5; Hag. 1:14; cf. 1 Chron. 5:26</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Thus says [xref]a[/xref]Cyrus the king of Persia, All the kingdoms of the earth has Jehovah the [xref]b[/xref]God of heaven given to me; and He has charged me to build Him a [note]1[/note]house in Jerusalem, which is in Judah.</text>
        <note num="1">The particular intention of the recovery of Israel from their captivity was to rebuild the temple as God's house on the earth among His elect and to re-establish the kingdom of God on the earth for the accomplishing of God's eternal economy. Likewise, the particular intention of the Lord's recovery of the church in this age is to have all the saints come together in their localities to be built up together as the house of God in many cities ([link]Eph. 2:22[/link] and notes; [link]Rev. 1:11[/link] and note). Through such a house God will have His kingdom for the carrying out of His economy.</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 44:28; 45:1, 13</xref>
        <xref num="b">2 Chron. 20:6; Ezra 6:9-10; Jonah 1:9; Rev. 11:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Whoever there is among you of all His people, may his God be with him; and let him go up to Jerusalem, which is in Judah, and let him build the house of Jehovah the God of Israel &amp;#8212; He is God &amp;#8212; who is in Jerusalem.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And everyone who is left, in whatever place he sojourns, let the men of his place support him with silver and with gold and with goods and with cattle, besides the freewill offering for the house of God, which is in Jerusalem.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Then the heads of the fathers' [i]houses[/i] of Judah and Benjamin and the priests and the Levites rose up, even everyone whose spirit God had [xref]a[/xref]stirred up to go up to build the house of Jehovah, which is in Jerusalem.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 1:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And all those around them strengthened their hands with vessels of silver, with gold, with goods, and with cattle and with precious things, besides all that was offered willingly.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Also King Cyrus brought out the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]vessels of the house of Jehovah, which Nebuchadnezzar had brought out from Jerusalem and had put in the house of his gods;</text>
        <note num="1">The gold and silver vessels of the house of God typify the experiences of the various aspects of Christ in His redemption (silver) and in His divine nature (gold). These experiences are the means to serve Christ as food to God's people. The return of the vessels from Babylon to Jerusalem typifies the return of Christ's riches to the unique ground of the genuine oneness of the church to enrich the recovery of the church. See note [link]24[sup]2[/sup] in Isa. 22[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 5:14; 6:5; 2 Kings 24:13; 2 Chron. 36:7; Dan. 5:2-3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And Cyrus the king of Persia had them brought out by the hand of Mithredath the treasurer and had them enumerated to [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Sheshbazzar the prince of Judah.</text>
        <note num="1">Perhaps the Babylonian name of Zerubbabel; also mentioned in [link]5:14[/link], [link]16[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 5:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And this was [xref]a[/xref]their number: thirty gold dishes, one thousand silver dishes, twenty-nine knives,</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Ezra 8:25-30</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Thirty gold bowls, four hundred ten silver bowls of a different kind, [i]and[/i] one thousand other vessels.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>There were five thousand four hundred vessels of gold and silver in all. Sheshbazzar brought up all [i]of them[/i] with those of the captivity who were brought up from Babylon to Jerusalem.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Now these were the children of the province who went up out of the captivity of those who had been carried away, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had [xref]b[/xref]carried away to Babylon, and who returned to Jerusalem and Judah, each man to his city.</text>
        <xref num="a">vv. 1-70: Neh. 7:6-73</xref>
        <xref num="b">2 Kings 24:14-16; 25:11; 2 Chron. 36:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>These came with Zerubbabel, Jeshua, Nehemiah, Seraiah, Reelaiah, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispar, Bigvai, Rehum, Baanah. The number of the men of the people of Israel:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>The children of Parosh, two thousand one hundred seventy-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>The children of Shephatiah, three hundred seventy-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>The children of Arah, seven hundred seventy-five.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>The children of Pahath-moab, of the children of Jeshua [i]and[/i] Joab, two thousand eight hundred twelve.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>The children of Elam, one thousand two hundred fifty-four.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>The children of Zattu, nine hundred forty-five.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>The children of Zaccai, seven hundred sixty.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>The children of Bani, six hundred forty-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>The children of Bebai, six hundred twenty-three.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>The children of Azgad, one thousand two hundred twenty-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>The children of Adonikam, six hundred sixty-six.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>The children of Bigvai, two thousand fifty-six.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>The children of Adin, four hundred fifty-four.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>The children of Ater, of Hezekiah, ninety-eight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>The children of Bezai, three hundred twenty-three.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>The children of Jorah, one hundred twelve.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>The children of Hashum, two hundred twenty-three.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>The children of Gibbar, ninety-five.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>The children of Bethlehem, one hundred twenty-three.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>The men of Netophah, fifty-six.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>The men of Anathoth, one hundred twenty-eight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>The children of Azmaveth, forty-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>The children of Kiriath-arim, Chephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred forty-three.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>The children of Ramah and Geba, six hundred twenty-one.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>The men of Michmas, one hundred twenty-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>The men of Bethel and Ai, two hundred twenty-three.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>The children of Nebo, fifty-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>The children of Magbish, one hundred fifty-six.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>The children of the other Elam, one thousand two hundred fifty-four.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>The children of Harim, three hundred twenty.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>The children of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred twenty-five.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>The children of Jericho, three hundred forty-five.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>The children of Senaah, three thousand six hundred thirty.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
        <text>The priests: the children of Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred seventy-three.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
        <text>The children of Immer, one thousand fifty-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
        <text>The children of Pashhur, one thousand two hundred forty-seven.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
        <text>The children of Harim, one thousand seventeen.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
        <text>The Levites: the children of Jeshua and Kadmiel, of the children of Hodaviah, seventy-four.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
        <text>The singers: the children of [xref]a[/xref]Asaph, one hundred twenty-eight.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Chron. 6:39</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
        <text>The children of the [xref]a[/xref]gatekeepers: the children of Shallum, the children of Ater, the children of Talmon, the children of Akkub, the children of Hatita, the children of Shobai, in all one hundred thirty-nine.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Chron. 9:17-18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
        <text>The [xref]a[/xref]temple servants: the children of Ziha, the children of Hasupha, the children of Tabbaoth,</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Chron. 9:2; Neh. 11:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
        <text>The children of Keros, the children of Siaha, the children of Padon,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
        <text>The children of Lebanah, the children of Hagabah, the children of Akkub.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
        <text>The children of Hagab, the children of Shamlai, the children of Hanan,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="47">
        <text>The children of Giddel, the children of Gahar, the children of Reaiah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="48">
        <text>The children of Rezin, the children of Nekoda, the children of Gazzam,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="49">
        <text>The children of Uzza, the children of Paseah, the children of Besai,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="50">
        <text>The children of Asnah, the children of Meunim, the children of Nephisim,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="51">
        <text>The children of Bakbuk, the children of Hakupha, the children of Harhur,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="52">
        <text>The children of Bazluth, the children of Mehida, the children of Harsha,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="53">
        <text>The children of Barkos, the children of Sisera, the children of Temah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="54">
        <text>The children of Neziah, the children of Hatipha.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="55">
        <text>The children of Solomon's servants: the children of Sotai, the children of Hassophereth, the children of Peruda,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="56">
        <text>The children of Jaalah, the children of Darkon, the children of Giddel,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="57">
        <text>The children of Shephatiah, the children of Hattil, the children of Pochereth-hazzebaim, the children of Ami.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="58">
        <text>All the temple servants and the children of Solomon's servants were three hundred ninety-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="59">
        <text>And these were those who went up from Tel-melah, Tel-harsha, Cherub, Addon, [i]and[/i] Immer; but they could not give evidence of their fathers' houses nor their descendants, whether they were of Israel:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="60">
        <text>The children of Delaiah, the children of Tobiah, the children of Nekoda, six hundred fifty-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="61">
        <text>And of the children of the priests: the children of Hobaiah, the children of Hakkoz, the children of Barzillai, who took a wife from among the daughters of [xref]a[/xref]Barzillai the Gileadite and was called by their name.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 17:27; 19:31</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="62">
        <text>These sought their registry among those who were enrolled by genealogy, but they were not found; therefore they were considered defiled [i]and were excluded[/i] from the priesthood.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="63">
        <text>And the governor told them that they should not eat of the most holy things until a priest stood up with [xref]a[/xref]Urim and Thummim.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 28:30</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="64">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]The whole assembly together was forty-two thousand three hundred sixty,</text>
        <xref num="a">vv. 64-67: Neh. 7:66-69</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="65">
        <text>Besides their male servants and their female servants, of whom there were seven thousand three hundred thirty-seven; and they had two hundred male singers and female singers.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="66">
        <text>Their horses were seven hundred thirty-six; their mules, two hundred forty-five;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="67">
        <text>Their camels, four hundred thirty-five; [i]their[/i] donkeys, six thousand seven hundred twenty.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="68">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]And some of the heads of fathers' [i]houses,[/i] when they came to the house of Jehovah, which is in Jerusalem, offered willingly for the house of God to restore it on its foundation.</text>
        <xref num="a">vv. 68-69: Neh. 7:70-72</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="69">
        <text>They gave to the treasury of the work, according to their ability, sixty-one thousand darics of gold and five thousand minas of silver and one hundred priestly garments.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="70">
        <text>So the priests and the Levites and some of the people and the singers and the gatekeepers and the temple servants and all Israel dwelt in their cities.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And when the seventh month came, and the children of Israel were in the cities, the people gathered together as [xref]a[/xref]one man to Jerusalem.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 8:1; Judg. 20:1; Acts 2:46; 4:32</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Then [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Jeshua the son of Jozadak rose up, [i]along[/i] with his brothers the priests and [xref]b[/xref]Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel and his brothers, and they built the altar of the God of Israel to offer [xref]c[/xref]burnt offerings upon it, as it is written in the law of Moses the [xref]d[/xref]man of God.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., Joshua the high priest (cf. [link]Hag. 1:1[/link] and [link]Zech. 3:1[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 12:1, 7; cf. Hag. 1:1, 12, 14; 2:2, 4; Zech. 3:1, 3, 6, 8-9</xref>
        <xref num="b">Ezra 5:2; 1 Chron. 3:19; Matt. 1:12; Luke 3:27</xref>
        <xref num="c">Deut. 12:5-6</xref>
        <xref num="d">Deut. 33:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And they set up the altar upon its bases, for fear was upon them because of the peoples of the lands; and they offered burnt offerings on it to Jehovah, burnt offerings of the [xref]a[/xref]morning and evening.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 29:39; Num. 28:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And they held the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Feast of Tabernacles, as it is written, and [i]offered[/i] the [xref]b[/xref]daily burnt offerings by number according to the ordinance as the duty of every day required;</text>
        <note num="1">The keeping of the Feast of Tabernacles and the offering of the daily burnt offerings and the offerings of the new moons and of all the appointed feasts of Jehovah ([link]vv. 4-6a[/link]) indicate that Israel recovered the worship of God, which had been lost for at least seventy years.</note>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 23:34; Neh. 8:14-17; Zech. 14:16</xref>
        <xref num="b">Num. 29:12-38</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And afterward [i]they offered[/i] the continual burnt offering and [i]the offerings[/i] of the [xref]a[/xref]new moons and of all the [xref]b[/xref]appointed feasts of Jehovah that were sanctified and of everyone who offered willingly a freewill offering to Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">Num. 28:11-15</xref>
        <xref num="b">Num. 29:39</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>From the first day of the seventh month they began to offer up burnt offerings to Jehovah;[separator]however the [xref]a[/xref]foundation of the temple of Jehovah had not yet been laid.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 3:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>They also gave money to the stone hewers and to the carpenters, and [xref]a[/xref]food and drink and oil to the Sidonians and to the Tyrians, to bring [xref]b[/xref]cedar trees from Lebanon to the sea at Joppa according to the authorization granted them by [xref]c[/xref]Cyrus the king of Persia.</text>
        <xref num="a">Acts 12:20</xref>
        <xref num="b">2 Sam. 5:11; 1 Kings 5:6</xref>
        <xref num="c">Ezra 1:2-3; 6:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Now in the second year after they came to the house of God at Jerusalem, in the second month, [xref]a[/xref]Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel and Jeshua the son of Jozadak and the rest of their brothers, the priests and the Levites, and all those who came out of captivity to Jerusalem began by appointing the Levites, from [xref]b[/xref]twenty years old and upward, to have oversight over the work of the house of Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 2:2; 4:3</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Chron. 23:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Then Jeshua stood [i]with[/i] his sons and his brothers, as [xref]a[/xref]one man, [i]with[/i] Kadmiel and his sons, the sons of Judah, [i]and with[/i] the sons of Henadad [i]and[/i] their sons and their brothers the Levites, to have oversight over the workmen in the house of God.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 3:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And when the builders laid the foundation of the temple of Jehovah, they set the priests in their apparel with trumpets and the Levites, the [xref]a[/xref]sons of Asaph, with cymbals, to praise Jehovah according to the directions of David the king of Israel.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Chron. 16:4-6; 25:1-2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And they sang to one another in praising and giving thanks to Jehovah, [i]saying,[/i] For He is good, for His lovingkindness is forever upon Israel. And all the people shouted with a great shout when they praised Jehovah, because the [xref]a[/xref]foundation of the house of Jehovah was laid.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Chron. 3:3; cf. 2 Chron. 7:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>But many of the priests and Levites and heads of fathers' [i]houses,[/i] the old men who had seen the first [xref]a[/xref]house, wept with a loud voice when the foundation of this house was laid before their eyes; and many shouted aloud for joy,</text>
        <xref num="a">Hag. 2:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>So that the people could not discern the sound of the shout of joy from the sound of the weeping of the people; for the people shouted with a loud shout, and the sound was heard far away.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Now when the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]adversaries of Judah and Benjamin heard that the children of the captivity were building a temple to Jehovah the God of Israel,</text>
        <note num="1">These were people brought from Babylon and Assyria by the king of Assyria to inhabit Samaria ([link]2 Kings 17:24[/link] and note; [link]John 4:9[/link] and note). Imitating Israel in seeking God and sacrificing to God, they pretended to help the rebuilding of the house of Jehovah, but they were rejected by Zerubbabel, Joshua, and the rest of the heads of the fathers' houses ([link]vv. 1-3[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. Neh. 4:1-11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>They drew near to Zerubbabel and to the heads of fathers' [i]houses[/i] and said to them, Let us build with you; for we seek your God as you do, and we have been sacrificing to Him since the days of Esarhaddon the king of [xref]a[/xref]Assyria, who brought us up here.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 17:23-24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>But Zerubbabel and Jeshua and the rest of the heads of fathers' [i]houses[/i] of Israel said to them, You have [xref]a[/xref]nothing to do with us in building a house to our God; but we ourselves together will build to Jehovah the God of Israel, as King Cyrus the king of Persia has commanded us.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Neh. 2:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Then the people of the land [xref]a[/xref]weakened the hands of the people of Judah and troubled them in building.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 6:9; Jer. 38:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And they hired counselors against them to frustrate their purpose all the days of Cyrus the king of Persia, even until the reign of Darius the king of Persia.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And in the reign of [xref]a[/xref]Ahasuerus, in the beginning of his reign, they wrote an accusation against the inhabitants of Judah and Jerusalem.</text>
        <xref num="a">Esth. 1:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And in the days of [xref]a[/xref]Artaxerxes, Bishlam, Mithredath, Tabeel, and the rest of his companions wrote to Artaxerxes the king of Persia; and the script of the letter was written in [xref]b[/xref]Aramaic and translated [i]into[/i] Aramaic.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 7:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">2 Kings 18:26; Dan. 2:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Rehum the chancellor and Shimshai the scribe wrote a letter against Jerusalem to Artaxerxes the king as follows</text>
        <note num="1">From here through [link]6:18[/link] the text is in Aramaic, not in Hebrew.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>(Then Rehum the chancellor, and Shimshai the scribe, and the rest of their companions, the judges, and the officials, the Tarpelites, the Persians, the men of Erech, the Babylonians, the men of Susa, that is the Elamites,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And the rest of the nations, whom the great and noble Osnappar carried into exile and settled in the city of [xref]a[/xref]Samaria and in the rest [i]of the province[/i] beyond the River, [i]wrote.[/i] And now</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 10:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>This is the copy of the letter that they sent to him): To Artaxerxes the king, [i]from[/i] your servants the men beyond the River. And now</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Let it be known to the king that the Jews who came up from you have come to us to Jerusalem; they are [xref]a[/xref]rebuilding the rebellious and evil city and are finishing the walls and have repaired the foundations.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Neh. 2:17; 6:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Now let it be known to the king that if this city is rebuilt and the walls are finished, they will not pay tribute, taxes, or tolls; and in the end it will cause damage to the kings.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Now because [note]1[/note]we eat the salt of the palace, and it is not fitting for us to see the king's dishonor, we therefore have sent [i]this letter[/i] to inform the king,</text>
        <note num="1">A figurative expression meaning to be supported by the king.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>So that a search may be made in the book of the records of your fathers, and you may find in the book of the records and know that this city is a rebellious city and one that causes damage to kings and provinces and that they have stirred up sedition within it in times past; for which reason this city was laid waste.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>We inform the king that if this city is rebuilt and its walls are finished, then you will have no portion beyond the River.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>[i]Then[/i] the king sent an answer to Rehum the chancellor and Shimshai the scribe and the rest of their companions who dwelt in Samaria and in the rest [i]of the province[/i] beyond the River: Greetings. And now</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>The letter which you sent to us has been read before me in translation.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And a decree has been issued by me, and a search has been made; and it was found that this city in times past has risen against kings, and that rebellion and sedition have been made in it,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And that there have been mighty kings over Jerusalem, who have [xref]a[/xref]ruled over all [i]the lands[/i] beyond the River; and tribute, taxes and tolls were paid to them.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 4:21; 2 Chron. 9:26</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Now make a decree to stop these men, so that this city is not rebuilt until a decree is made by me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And take care not to be negligent in this. Why should damage grow to the detriment of the kings?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Then when the copy of King Artaxerxes's letter was read before Rehum and Shimshai the scribe and their companions, they went in haste to Jerusalem to the Jews and stopped them by force and power.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>So the work of the house of God, which is in Jerusalem, ceased; and it was stopped until the second year of the reign of Darius the king of Persia.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="5">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Now the [note]1[/note]prophets, [xref]a[/xref]Haggai the prophet and [xref]b[/xref]Zechariah the son of Iddo, prophesied to the Jews who were in Judah and Jerusalem in the name of the God of Israel who was over them.</text>
        <note num="1">The rebuilding work continued through the encouragement and help of the prophesying of the prophets Haggai and Zechariah ([link]vv. 1-2[/link]). In God's theocratic administration among the people of Israel, there were three offices: the priests, the kings, and the prophets. The responsibility of the high priest was to bring the matters concerning God's people into God's presence and wait on God for His instant speaking through the Urim and the Thummim ([link]Exo. 28:30[/link] and notes). The high priest then passed on God's decision and instructions to the king, who was responsible in God's administration to carry them out. Whenever the priests and the kings became weak and inadequate, God raised up the prophets to speak for Him in order to strengthen and assist the priesthood and the kingship ([link]1 Sam. 3:11-21[/link]; [link]2 Sam. 12:1-25[/link]). See note [link]21[sup]1[/sup] in Num. 27[/link] and note [link]18[sup]1[/sup] in Deut. 16[/link].[br/][br/]For the building of God's dwelling place on earth, the ministries of both the priesthood and the kingship are needed. The tabernacle was raised up through Aaron, the high priest, and Moses, representing the divine authority; the temple was built under the high priest and Solomon the king; the rebuilding of the temple was accomplished through the priesthood of Joshua and the authority of Zerubbabel, the governor of Judah ([link]Hag. 1:1[/link]). In the building of the recovered temple both Joshua and Zerubbabel became somewhat weak and discouraged. Therefore, God used the prophets Haggai and Zechariah to speak for Him and to strengthen and encourage Joshua and Zerubbabel (see the books of Haggai and Zechariah).[br/][br/]In God's economy the priesthood and the kingship will remain forever ([link]Rev. 22:3[/link], [link]5[/link]), whereas in the age of the millennium and in eternity the prophethood will not be needed ([link]Dan. 9:24[/link] and note 4).</note>
        <xref num="a">Hag. 1:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">Zech. 1:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Then [xref]a[/xref]Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel and Jeshua the son of Jozadak rose up and began to [xref]b[/xref]build the house of God, which is in Jerusalem; and the prophets of God were with them, helping them.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Chron. 3:19; Ezra 3:2; Matt. 1:12; Luke 3:27</xref>
        <xref num="b">Hag. 1:12-14; cf. Ezra 6:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>At the same time Tattenai the governor beyond the River and Shethar-bozenai and their companions came to them and spoke to them in this way, Who gave you a decree to build this house and to finish this wall?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Then we told them accordingly what the names of the men were who were constructing this building.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>But the [xref]a[/xref]eye of their God was upon the elders of the Jews, and they did not stop them, until a report went to Darius; and then [i]an answer[/i] was returned by letter concerning it.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 33:18; 34:15; 1 Pet. 3:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>[i]This is[/i] the copy of the letter that Tattenai the governor beyond the River and Shethar-bozenai and his companions the officials, who were beyond the River, sent to Darius the king;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>They sent a report to him in which was written as follows, To Darius the king, all peace.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Let it be known to the king that we went to the province of Judah, to the house of the great God, which is being built with large stones, and timber is being laid in the walls; and this work is being conducted with diligence and prospers in their hands.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Then we asked those elders, speaking to them in this way, Who gave you a decree to build this house and to finish this wall?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>We also asked them their names in order to inform you, so that we might write down the names of the men who were at their head.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And they returned us an answer in this way, saying, We are the servants of the [xref]a[/xref]God of heaven and earth and are rebuilding the [xref]b[/xref]house that was built many years ago, which a great king of Israel built and finished.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Ezra 6:9, 10; Psa. 136:26; Dan. 2:19, 44; Rev. 11:13</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Kings 6:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>But because our fathers had provoked the God of heaven to anger, He gave them into the hand of [xref]a[/xref]Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon, the Chaldean, who destroyed this house and carried the people away to Babylon.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 24:1-2; 25:8-11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>But in the first year of [xref]a[/xref]Cyrus the king of Babylon, King Cyrus made a decree to build this house of God.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 1:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And also the gold and silver [xref]a[/xref]vessels of the house of God, which Nebuchadnezzar took out of the temple that was in Jerusalem and brought into the temple of Babylon, these King Cyrus took out of the temple of Babylon, and they were given to one whose name was [xref]b[/xref]Sheshbazzar, whom he had made governor;</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 1:7-8; 6:5</xref>
        <xref num="b">Ezra 1:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And he said to him, Take these vessels, go [i]and[/i] put them in the temple in Jerusalem, and let the [xref]a[/xref]house of God be rebuilt in its place.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 3:8-10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Then the same Sheshbazzar came [i]and[/i] laid the foundations of the house of God, which is in Jerusalem; and since that time even until now it has been under construction and has not [i]yet[/i] been finished.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Now therefore if it seems good to the king, let a search be made in the king's treasure house, which is there in Babylon, [i]to see[/i] whether it is the case that a decree was made by King Cyrus for the building of this house of God in Jerusalem; and let the king send his pleasure to us concerning this.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="6">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Then Darius the king made a decree, and search was made in the house of the archives, where the treasures were stored in Babylon.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And a scroll was found at Achmetha, in the palace that is in the province of Media, and on it this was written as a record:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>In the first year of King Cyrus, King [xref]a[/xref]Cyrus made a decree [i]concerning[/i] the house of God at Jerusalem: Let the house be built, the place where they offer sacrifices; and let its foundations be raised, its height being sixty cubits, and its width sixty cubits,</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 1:1-4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>With three layers of large stones, and one layer of timber; and let the expenses be given out of the king's house.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And also let the gold and silver [xref]a[/xref]vessels of the house of God, which Nebuchadnezzar took out of the temple which is in Jerusalem and brought to Babylon, be returned and brought again to the temple which is in Jerusalem, to its place; and you shall put [i]them[/i] in the house of God.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 1:7-8; 5:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Now [i]therefore,[/i] Tattenai the governor beyond the River, Shethar-bozenai, and your companions the officials, in [i]the province[/i] beyond the River, keep far away from there.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Leave the work of this house of God alone; let the governor of the Jews and the elders of the Jews build this house of God on its site.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Moreover I make a decree concerning what you are to do for these elders of the Jews for the building of this house of God: From the property of the king, even the tribute [i]of the province[/i] beyond the River, expenses are to be given in full to these men that [i]the work[/i] not cease.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And whatever is needed, young bulls and rams and lambs, for burnt offerings to the God of heaven; [i]also[/i] wheat, salt, wine, and oil, according to the word of the priests who are in Jerusalem, let it be given to them day by day without fail,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>That they may offer incense to the God of heaven and [xref]a[/xref]pray for the life of the king and his sons.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Jer. 29:7; 1 Tim. 2:1-2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Also I have made a decree that whoever alters this word, timber shall be pulled out from his house, and he shall be lifted up and impaled on it, and his house shall be made a dunghill on account of this.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And may the God who has caused His [xref]a[/xref]name to dwell there overthrow any king or people who put forth their hand to alter [i]this or[/i] to destroy this house of God, which is in Jerusalem. I, Darius, have made a decree; let it be carried out with all diligence.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 20:24; Deut. 12:5; 1 Kings 9:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Then Tattenai the governor beyond the River, Shethar-bozenai, and their companions, carried out [i]everything[/i] with all diligence according to what Darius the king had sent [i]order to do.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And the elders of the Jews built, and they prospered through the [xref]a[/xref]prophesying of Haggai the prophet and Zechariah the son of Iddo. And they [xref]b[/xref]finished building according to the command of the God of Israel and according to the decree of [xref]c[/xref]Cyrus and [xref]d[/xref]Darius and [xref]e[/xref]Artaxerxes the king of Persia.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 5:1-2</xref>
        <xref num="b">Zech. 4:9</xref>
        <xref num="c">Ezra 1:1-2; 5:13; 6:3</xref>
        <xref num="d">Ezra 4:24; 6:12</xref>
        <xref num="e">Ezra 7:1; Neh. 2:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And this house was finished on the third day of the month Adar, which was in the sixth year of the reign of Darius the king.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And the children of Israel, the priests, and the Levites, and the rest of the children of the captivity, celebrated the [xref]a[/xref]dedication of this house of God with joy.</text>
        <xref num="a">Num. 7:10; Deut. 20:5; 1 Kings 8:63; 2 Chron. 7:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And they offered for the dedication of this house of God one hundred bulls, two hundred rams, four hundred lambs, and for a sin offering for all Israel, twelve male goats according to the number of the tribes of Israel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And they set the priests in their courses and the Levites in their [xref]a[/xref]divisions for the service of God, which is in Jerusalem, as it is written in the [xref]b[/xref]book of Moses.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Chron. 23:6; 24:1; 2 Chron. 8:14; 35:4</xref>
        <xref num="b">Num. 3:6; 8:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And the children of the captivity held the Passover on the [xref]a[/xref]fourteenth [i]day[/i] of the first month.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 12:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>For the priests and the Levites had purified themselves together; all of them were pure. Then they slaughtered the [xref]a[/xref]passover for all the children of the captivity and for their brothers the priests and for themselves.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Chron. 30:15; 35:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And the children of Israel who returned from the captivity and all who had separated themselves from the defilement of the nations of the land to [i]join[/i] them, to seek Jehovah the God of Israel, ate [i]the passover[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And held the [xref]a[/xref]Feast of Unleavened Bread seven days with joy; for Jehovah had made them joyful and had turned the [xref]b[/xref]heart of the [note]1[/note]king of Assyria to them, to strengthen their hands in the work of the house of God, the God of Israel.</text>
        <note num="1">The king of Assyria here was Darius king of Persia because Assyria was at that time a part of Persia.</note>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 12:15-20; 13:6-7; 2 Chron. 30:21; 35:17</xref>
        <xref num="b">Ezra 7:27; Prov. 21:1</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="7">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Now after these things, in the reign of Artaxerxes the king of Persia, [note]1[/note]Ezra the son of [xref]a[/xref]Seraiah, the son of Azariah, the son of Hilkiah,</text>
        <note num="1">The first return of Israel from their captivity (see note [link]1[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 1[/link]) needed the kingly leadership of Zerubbabel, a royal descendant who knew how to govern and who took the lead in building up the altar and the temple. After this, the need shifted from the royal family to the priesthood, to Ezra, a descendant of the high priest Aaron ([link]vv. 1-5[/link]). Ezra was not only a priest but also a scribe, a person who was skilled in the law of God ([link]v. 6[/link]). As such a one, Ezra had the capacity to meet the need.[br/][br/]After the rebuilding of the temple under the leadership of Zerubbabel, the people were still unruly, for they had become Babylonian in their constitution. Therefore, there was the need for an Ezra, one who was both a priest who served God and also a scribe, a scholar, who was skilled in the Word of God, skilled in the law of Moses. Ezra bore the totality of the heavenly and divine constitution and culture. He brought the people back to the Word of God that they might be re-educated and reconstituted with the heavenly truths in the divine Word. See note [link]1[sup]1[/sup] in Neh. 8[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">vv. 1b-5: 1 Chron. 6:4-14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>The son of Shallum, the son of Zadok, the son of Ahitub,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>The son of Amariah, the son of Azariah, the son of Meraioth,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>The son of Zerahiah, the son of Uzzi, the son of Bukki,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>The son of Abishua, the son of Phinehas, the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron the chief priest;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>This Ezra went up from Babylon, and he was a [xref]a[/xref]scribe skilled in the law of Moses, which Jehovah the God of Israel had given; and the king granted him all his [note]1[/note]request according to the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]hand of Jehovah his God upon him.</text>
        <note num="1">The first return from Babylon to Jerusalem was initiated by God ([link]1:1[/link], [link]5[/link]). The second return was initiated by Ezra, who went to the king and appealed to him to grant his request. Ezra realized that the first return was not perfect, not complete. He realized that there was the need for someone who was skilled in the law of God and who knew God's heart, God's desire, and God's economy, to help the people to know God not merely in a general way but according to what God had spoken. Ezra had such a capacity, so he volunteered to go to the king and to request a decree from the king permitting the Jews to return to the land of their fathers.</note>
        <note num="2">This book does not speak of the Spirit of God, but the hand of God is mentioned a number of times (see reference 6[sup]b[/sup]). When God's Spirit works inwardly, that is the Spirit. When God's Spirit works outwardly, that is God's hand.</note>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 7:11-12; Neh. 8:1, 4, 13; 12:26, 36; Matt. 2:4; 23:2; Mark 12:35; cf. Matt. 13:52</xref>
        <xref num="b">Ezra 7:9, 28; 8:18, 22, 31; Neh. 2:8, 18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Some of the [xref]a[/xref]children of Israel and some of the [xref]b[/xref]priests, and the Levites and the singers and the gatekeepers and the [xref]c[/xref]temple servants also went up to Jerusalem in the seventh year of [xref]d[/xref]Artaxerxes the king.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Ezra 8:1-14</xref>
        <xref num="b">Ezra 8:15-19</xref>
        <xref num="c">Ezra 2:43; 8:17, 20</xref>
        <xref num="d">Ezra 4:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And he came to Jerusalem in the fifth month, which was in the seventh year of the king;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>For on the first [i]day[/i] of the first month he began to go up from Babylon, and on the first [i]day[/i] of the fifth month he came to Jerusalem according to the good [xref]a[/xref]hand of his God upon him.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 7:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>For Ezra had set his heart to seek the law of Jehovah and to do it and to teach [i]His[/i] [note]1[/note]statutes and ordinances in Israel.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]6[sup]4[/sup] in Luke 1[/link]. Ezra set his heart not only to seek and do the main part of the law of Jehovah but also to teach His statutes, the details, and His ordinances, the verdicts and judgments.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Now this is the copy of the letter that King Artaxerxes gave to Ezra the priest, the scribe, a scribe of the words of the commandments of Jehovah and of His statutes for Israel:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Artaxerxes, the king of kings, to Ezra the priest, the scribe of the law of the God of heaven, perfect [i]peace.[/i] And now</text>
        <note num="1">From here through [link]7:26[/link] the text is in Aramaic, not in Hebrew.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>I make a decree that any of the people of Israel and their priests and the Levites in my kingdom who offer themselves willingly to go to Jerusalem may go with you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Inasmuch as you have been sent by the king and his [xref]a[/xref]seven counselors to inquire concerning Judah and Jerusalem according to the law of your God, which is in your hand,</text>
        <xref num="a">Esth. 1:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And to carry the silver and gold, which the king and his counselors have offered willingly to the God of Israel, whose dwelling is in Jerusalem,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>As well as all the silver and gold that you shall find in the whole province of Babylon, with the freewill offering of the people and the priests, who offered willingly for the house of their God, which is in Jerusalem;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>With this money therefore you shall with all diligence buy bulls, rams, lambs, with their meal offerings and their drink offerings; and you shall offer them on the altar of the house of your God, which is in Jerusalem.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And whatever seems good to you and to your brothers to do with the rest of the silver and the gold, you may do according to the will of your God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And the vessels that are given to you for the service of the house of your God, deliver in full before the God of Jerusalem.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And the rest of the needs for the house of your God, which you have occasion to provide, you may provide [i]for it[/i] out of the king's treasure house.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And I, even I, Artaxerxes the king, make a decree to all the treasurers who are in [i]the province[/i] beyond the River, that whatever Ezra the priest, the scribe of the law of the God of heaven, requires of you, it shall be done with all diligence,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Up to one hundred talents of silver and up to one hundred cors of wheat and up to one hundred baths of wine and up to one hundred baths of oil and salt without prescribing how much.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Whatever is commanded by the God of heaven, let it be done exactly for the house of the God of heaven. For why should wrath come upon the kingdom of the king and his sons?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>We also inform you that it shall not be lawful to impose tribute, taxes, or tolls upon any of the priests and Levites, the singers, gatekeepers, temple servants, or servants of this house of God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>And you, Ezra, according to the [xref]a[/xref]wisdom of your God that is in your hand, appoint magistrates and judges, who may judge all the people who are in [i]the province[/i] beyond the River, all those who know the laws of your God; and teach anyone who does not know [i]them.[/i]</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Kings 3:28</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>And everyone who will not observe the law of your God and the law of the king, let judgment be executed upon him with all diligence, whether to death or to banishment or to confiscation of goods or to imprisonment.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>Blessed be Jehovah, the God of our fathers, who has put such a thing as this into the king's [xref]a[/xref]heart, to beautify the house of Jehovah, which is in Jerusalem,</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 6:22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>And has extended lovingkindness to me before the king and his counselors, and before all the mighty officers of the king. And I was strengthened according to the [xref]a[/xref]hand of Jehovah my God upon me, and I gathered together out of Israel leading men to go up with me.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 7:6</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="8">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Now these are the heads of their fathers' [i]houses[/i] and the genealogical enrollment of those who went up with me from Babylon in the reign of Artaxerxes the king:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Of the sons of Phinehas, Gershom. Of the sons of Ithamar, Daniel. Of the sons of David, Hattush.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Of the sons of Shecaniah, of the sons of Parosh, Zechariah; and with him one hundred fifty males were enrolled by genealogy.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Of the sons of Pahath-moab, Eliehoenai the son of Zerahiah; and with him two hundred males.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Of the sons of Shecaniah, the son of Jahaziel; and with him three hundred males.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And of the sons of Adin, Ebed the son of Jonathan; and with him fifty males.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And of the sons of Elam, Jeshaiah the son of Athaliah; and with him seventy males.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And of the sons of Shephatiah, Zebadiah the son of Michael; and with him eighty males.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Of the sons of Joab, Obadiah the son of Jehiel; and with him two hundred eighteen males.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And of the sons of Shelomith, the son of Josiphiah; and with him one hundred sixty males.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And of the sons of Bebai, Zechariah the son of Bebai; and with him twenty-eight males.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And of the sons of Azgad, Johanan the son of Hakkatan; and with him one hundred ten males.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And of the sons of Adonikam, the last ones; and these are their names: Eliphelet, Jeuel, and Shemaiah; and with them sixty males.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And of the sons of Bigvai, Uthai and Zabbud; and with them seventy males.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And I gathered them together to the river that runs to Ahava, and we camped there three days. When I observed the people and the priests, I found none of the sons of Levi there.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Then I sent for Eliezer, for Ariel, for Shemaiah, and for Elnathan, and for Jarib, and for Elnathan, and for Nathan, and for Zechariah, and for Meshullam, leading men; also for Joiarib, and for Elnathan, who were teachers.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And I sent them to Iddo the leading man at the place Casiphia; and I told them what to say to Iddo [i]and[/i] his brothers the temple servants at the place Casiphia, [i]namely,[/i] to bring ministers to us for the house of our God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And according to the good [xref]a[/xref]hand of our God upon us they brought us a man of discretion, of the sons of Mahli, the son of Levi, the son of Israel; namely, Sherebiah, with his sons and his brothers, eighteen men;</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 7:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And Hashabiah, and with him Jeshaiah of the sons of Merari, his brothers and their sons, twenty;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And of the [xref]a[/xref]temple servants, whom David and the leaders had given for the service of the Levites, two hundred twenty temple servants &amp;#8212; all of them were mentioned by name.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 2:43; 7:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Then I proclaimed a [xref]a[/xref]fast there, at the river Ahava, that we might humble ourselves before our God to seek from Him a straight way for ourselves and for our little ones and for all our possessions.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Chron. 20:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>For I was ashamed to ask for troops and horsemen from the king to help us against the enemy in the way because we had spoken to the king, saying, The [xref]a[/xref]hand of our God is for good upon all those who seek Him, but His power and His wrath is against all those who forsake Him.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 7:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>So we fasted and sought our God for this, and He was entreated by us.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>Then I set apart twelve of the leading men of the priests, even Sherebiah, Hashabiah, and ten of their brothers with them,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>And weighed out to them the silver and the gold and the vessels, the [note]1[/note]heave offering for the house of our God, which the king and his counselors and his princes, and all Israel there present had offered.</text>
        <note num="1">See notes [link book="Exo." chapter="25"]2[sup]1[/sup][/link] and [link]3[sup]1[/sup] in Exo. 25[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>I weighed out into their hand six hundred fifty talents of silver and one hundred silver vessels of [i]one hundred[/i] talents, one hundred talents of gold</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>And twenty bowls of gold of one thousand darics, and two vessels of fine polished bronze as precious as gold.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>And I said to them, You are [xref]a[/xref]holy to Jehovah, and the vessels are holy; and the silver and the gold are a freewill offering to Jehovah, the God of your fathers.</text>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 21:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>Watch and keep [i]them[/i] until you weigh [i]them[/i] before the leaders of the priests and the Levites and the leaders of the fathers' [i]houses[/i] of Israel at Jerusalem in the chambers of the house of Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>So the priests and the Levites received the weight of the silver and the gold and the vessels, to bring [i]them[/i] to Jerusalem to the house of our God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>Then we set out from the river Ahava on the twelfth [i]day[/i] of the first month to go to Jerusalem; and the [xref]a[/xref]hand of our God was upon us, and He delivered us from the hand of the enemy and from people set in ambush on the way.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 7:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>And we came to [xref]a[/xref]Jerusalem and remained there three days.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 2:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>And on the fourth day the silver and the gold and the vessels were weighed out in the house of our God into the hand of Meremoth the son of Uriah the priest, and with him was Eleazar the son of Phinehas; and with them were the Levites, Jozabad the son of Jeshua, and Noadiah the son of Binnui.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>Everything was numbered and weighed, and all its weight was recorded at that time.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>The children of those who had been carried away, who [xref]a[/xref]came out of captivity, offered burnt offerings to the God of Israel, twelve bulls for all Israel, ninety-six rams, seventy-seven lambs, twelve male goats for a sin offering, all as a burnt offering to Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Ezra 2:1-2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
        <text>And they delivered the king's decrees to the king's satraps and to the governors beyond the River, and these supported the people and the house of God.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="9">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Now when these things had been completed, the officials approached me, saying, The people of Israel and the priests and the Levites have [xref]a[/xref]not separated themselves from the peoples of the lands, [i]doing[/i] according to their abominations, even [i]those[/i] of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Perizzites, the Jebusites, the Ammonites, the Moabites, the Egyptians, and the Amorites.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Ezra 6:21; Neh. 9:2; 10:28; Exo. 33:16; Num. 23:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>For they have taken some of their [note]1[/note]daughters for themselves and for their sons, so that the [xref]a[/xref]holy seed have [xref]b[/xref]mingled themselves with the peoples of the lands; indeed, the hand of the leaders and rulers has been foremost in this unfaithfulness.</text>
        <note num="1">God had charged the children of Israel not to intermarry with the peoples of the land when they entered into the good land ([link]v. 12[/link]; [link]Deut. 7:1-6[/link]). At Ezra's time not only the common people but even the priests and the Levites had foreign wives ([link]v. 1[/link]). Ezra confessed that because of their taking foreign wives Israel despised and neglected their right to enjoy the good land and, as a result, were given by God into captivity ([link]vv. 7[/link], [link]10-15[/link]). Cf. notes [link]1[sup]1[/sup] in 1 Kings 3[/link] and [link book="2 Cor." chapter="6"]14[sup]2[/sup][/link] and [link]14[sup]3[/sup] in 2 Cor. 6[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Mal. 2:11; cf. Deut. 7:6; 1 Cor. 7:14</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 106:35; cf. Deut. 7:3; Josh. 23:12; 2 Cor. 6:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And when I heard about this matter, I tore my garment and my robe, and pulled out hair from my head and my beard, and sat down appalled.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Then everyone who trembled at the words of the God of Israel on account of the unfaithfulness of those of the captivity was gathered to me, and I sat appalled until the evening meal offering.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And at [i]the time of[/i] the evening meal offering I rose up from my affliction, even with my garment and my robe torn, and I fell on my knees and [xref]a[/xref]spread out my hands to Jehovah my God.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 8:22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And I said, O my God, I am ashamed and [xref]a[/xref]embarrassed to lift up my face to You, my God; for our [xref]b[/xref]iniquities have multiplied over [i]our[/i] head, and our guilt has increased up to the heavens.</text>
        <xref num="a">Job 10:15; Luke 18:13</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 38:4; 40:12; cf. Psa. 106:6; Dan. 9:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Since the days of our fathers up to this day we have been exceedingly guilty; and because of our iniquities we, our kings [i]and[/i] our priests, have been delivered up into the hand of the kings of the lands, to the sword, to captivity, and to plunder, and to shamefacedness, as it is this day.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And now for a brief moment favor has been [i]shown[/i] by Jehovah our God to leave us a [xref]a[/xref]remnant to escape and to give us a [xref]b[/xref]peg in His holy place, that our God may enlighten our eyes and give us a little reviving in our bondage.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 9:14-15; cf. 2 Kings 19:30-31</xref>
        <xref num="b">Isa. 22:23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>For we are slaves, yet our God has not forsaken us in our bondage but has extended lovingkindness to us in the sight of the kings of Persia, to give us a reviving, to raise up the [xref]a[/xref]house of our God and to repair its ruins, and to give us a wall in Judah and in Jerusalem.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 6:14-15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And now, O our God, what shall we say after this? For we have forsaken Your commandments,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Which You commanded by Your servants the prophets, saying, The land which you are entering to possess is a land unclean with the uncleanness of the peoples of the lands, with their abominations, with which they have filled it from one end to another, and with their defilement.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Now therefore do not give your daughters to their sons, neither [xref]a[/xref]take their daughters for your sons, nor seek their peace or their prosperity forever; that you may be strong and eat the good of the land and leave [i]it[/i] for an inheritance to your children forever.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 7:3; cf. Ezra 9:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And after all that has come upon us for our evil deeds and for our great guilt, seeing that You our God have punished [i]us[/i] less than our iniquities [i]deserve[/i] and have given us those who have escaped as this,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Shall we again break your commandments and intermarry with the peoples that do these abominations? Will You not be angry with us until You have consumed us, so that there should be no remnant nor any who escape?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>O Jehovah the God of Israel, You are righteous; for we have been left a [xref]a[/xref]remnant of those who have escaped, as it is this day. Here we are before You in our guilt, although none can stand before You because of this.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 9:8</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="10">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Now while Ezra [xref]a[/xref]prayed and made confession, weeping and throwing himself down before the [xref]b[/xref]house of God, a very large gathering of men and women and children was gathered together to him out of Israel; for the people wept very bitterly.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 1:4, 6; Dan. 9:20</xref>
        <xref num="b">2 Chron. 20:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And Shecaniah the son of Jehiel, one of the sons of Elam, answered and said to Ezra, We have acted unfaithfully against our God and have married foreign women from the peoples of the land, yet now there is hope for Israel concerning this.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Now therefore let us make a [xref]a[/xref]covenant with our God to put away all the wives and those born of them according to the counsel of my lord and of those who tremble at the commandment of our God, and let it be done according to the law.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Chron. 34:31</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Arise, for the matter is your responsibility, but we are with you; be strong, and do [i]it.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Then Ezra arose and made the leaders of the priests, the Levites, and all Israel swear that they would do according to this word; so they swore.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Then Ezra rose up from before the house of God and went into the chamber of Jehohanan the son of Eliashib; and [i]when[/i] he came there, he [xref]a[/xref]ate no bread and drank no water, for he was mourning because of the unfaithfulness of those of the captivity.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 9:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And they made proclamation throughout Judah and Jerusalem to all the children of the captivity, that they should gather themselves together to Jerusalem;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And that whoever did not come within three days, according to the counsel of the leaders and the elders, all his possessions should be forfeited, and he himself should be separated from the congregation of the captivity.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Then all the men of Judah and Benjamin gathered themselves together to Jerusalem within the three days. It was the ninth month, on the twentieth [i]day[/i] of the month, and all the people sat in the open square [i]in front of[/i] the house of God, trembling because of this matter and because of the heavy rain.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And Ezra the priest stood up and said to them, You have acted unfaithfully and have married foreign women to increase the guilt of Israel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Now therefore make confession to Jehovah the God of your fathers, and do His will, and separate yourselves from the peoples of the land and from the foreign women.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Then all the congregation answered and said with a loud voice, It is so; we must do as you have said.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>But the people are many, and it is a time of heavy rain, and we are not able to stand outside; neither is this a task for one day or two, for we have transgressed greatly in this matter.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Let our leaders represent the whole congregation, and let all those who are in our cities who have married foreign women come at appointed times and with them the elders of every city and their judges, until the fierce anger of our God is turned away from us on account of this matter.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Only Jonathan the son of Asahel and Jahzeiah the son of Tikvah stood up against this, and Meshullam and Shabbethai the Levite supported them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And the children of the captivity did so. And Ezra the priest [i]and[/i] certain heads of fathers' [i]houses[/i] were set apart according to their fathers' houses, all of them by name; and they sat down on the first day of the tenth month to examine the matter.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And they finished with all the men who had married foreign women by the first day of the first month.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And among the sons of the priests who had married foreign women there were found of the sons of Jeshua the son of Jozadak and his brothers: Maaseiah and Eliezer and Jarib and Gedaliah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And they [xref]a[/xref]pledged that they would put away their wives; and being guilty, [i]they offered[/i] a [xref]b[/xref]ram of the flock for their guilt.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 2 Kings 10:15; Gal. 2:9</xref>
        <xref num="b">Lev. 6:6-7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And of the sons of Immer: Hanani and Zebadiah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And of the sons of Harim: Maaseiah, and Elijah, and Shemaiah, and Jehiel, and Uzziah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And of the sons of Pashhur: Elioenai, Maaseiah, Ishmael, Nethanel, Jozabad, and Elasah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>And of the Levites: Jozabad, and Shimei, and Kelaiah (that is, Kelita), Pethahiah, Judah, and Eliezer.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And of the singers: Eliashib. And of the gatekeepers: Shallum, and Telem, and Uri.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>And of Israel: of the sons of Parosh: Ramiah, and Izziah, and Malchijah, and Mijamin, and Eleazar, and Malchijah, and Benaiah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>And of the sons of Elam: Mattaniah, Zechariah, and Jehiel, and Abdi, and Jeremoth, and Elijah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>And of the sons of Zattu: Elioenai, Eliashib, Mattaniah, and Jeremoth, and Zabad, and Aziza.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>And of the sons of Bebai: Jehohanan, Hananiah, Zabbai, Athlai.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>And of the sons of Bani: Meshullam, Malluch, and Adaiah, Jashub, and Sheal, Jeremoth.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>And of the sons of Pahath-moab: Adna, and Chelal, Benaiah, Maaseiah, Mattaniah, Bezalel, and Binnui, and Manasseh.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>And [i]of[/i] the sons of Harim: Eliezer, Isshijah, Malchijah, Shemaiah, Shimeon,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>Benjamin, Malluch, Shemariah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>Of the sons of Hashum: Mattenai, Mattattah, Zabad, Eliphelet, Jeremai, Manasseh, Shimei.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>Of the sons of Bani: Maadai, Amram, and Uel,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>Benaiah, Bedeiah, Cheluhi,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
        <text>Vaniah, Meremoth, Eliashib,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
        <text>Mattaniah, Mattenai, and Jaasu,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
        <text>And Bani, and Binnui, Shimei,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
        <text>And Shelemiah, and Nathan, and Adaiah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
        <text>Machnadebai, Shashai, Sharai,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
        <text>Azarel, and Shelemiah, Shemariah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
        <text>Shallum, Amariah, Joseph.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
        <text>Of the sons of Nebo: Jeiel, Mattithiah, Zabad, Zebina, Jaddai, and Joel, Benaiah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
        <text>All these had taken foreign wives; and some of them had wives [i]by whom[/i] they had children.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    </chapters>
</book>
