<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="yes"?>
<book name="Habakkuk">
    <info title="Author">Habakkuk ([link]1:1[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Time of His Ministry">About 626 B.C., close to the time of the Babylonian invasion and the first exile to Babylon (605 B.C.).</info>
    <info title="Place of His Ministry">The southern kingdom of Judah.</info>
    <info title="Object of His Ministry">The southern kingdom of Judah.</info>
    <subject>The Righteous Judgment of God First on Israel by the Chaldeans and Then on the Chaldeans by the Nations</subject>
    <outlines>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="1" ref="1:1">The introductory word</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="2" ref="1:2-11">The first dialogue between the prophet and Jehovah</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="vv. 2-4">The prophet's inquiring of Jehovah</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="vv. 5-11">Jehovah's answer to the prophet</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="3" ref="1:12-2:20">The second dialogue between the prophet and Jehovah</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="1:12-2:1">The prophet's inquiring of Jehovah</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="2:2-20">Jehovah's answer to the prophet</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="" ref="vv. 5-20">(Five woes to the Chaldeans)</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="4" ref="3:1-19">The prophet's song to Jehovah in prayer, lauding, and trusting in Him</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="vv. 1-2">In prayer</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="vv. 3-15">In lauding</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="vv. 16-19">In trusting in Jehovah</outline>
    </outlines>
    <chapters>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>The burden which [note]1[/note]Habakkuk the prophet saw.</text>
        <note num="1">Meaning [i]embracing,[/i] or [i]clinging to[/i]. The meaning of the prophet's name indicates that in order for sinners to receive God's eternal salvation ([link]2:4[/link]), which is actually God Himself ([link]Isa. 12:2[/link]; [link]Luke 2:30[/link]), God became a man on the earth that He might embrace sinners and sinners might cling to Him (cf. [link]Luke 19:1-10[/link]). See note [link]4[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 2[/link] and note [link]4[sup]1[/sup] in Hosea 11[/link].[br/]The central thought of Habakkuk is that the righteous God will judge both the evil Israel and the violent Chaldeans, and only the righteous one will live by his faith ([link]2:4b[/link]), so that all the earth may know the glory of Jehovah ([link]2:14[/link]) and be silent before Jehovah, who is in His holy temple ([link]2:20[/link]), and so that His seeker may sing to Him in prayer, in lauding, and in trusting in Him ([link]ch. 3[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>How long, O Jehovah, shall I cry / And You do [xref]a[/xref]not hear? / I cry out to You, Violence! / And You do not save.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 22:1-2; Lam. 3:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Why do You cause me to see iniquity / And look upon wrong? / Indeed destruction and violence are before me; / And there is strife, and contention arises.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Therefore the law is ineffective, / And justice never goes forth; / For the wicked encompasses the righteous, / Therefore justice goes forth perverted.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Look among the nations, and see, / And be [xref]a[/xref]amazed, utterly amazed. / For I am doing a work in your days / [i]Which[/i] you would not believe if it were told [i]you.[/i]</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 29:14; Acts 13:41</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>For I am about to raise up the [xref]a[/xref]Chaldeans, / That bitter and hasty nation / That marches through the breadth of the earth / To possess habitations that are not [note]1[/note]theirs.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., his; the masculine singular is used through the end of the chapter.</note>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 24:2; 2 Chron. 36:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>They are terrible and dreadful; / Their judgment and their authority issue from themselves.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And their horses are swifter than leopards / And more agile than the wolves of evening. / And their horsemen prance about; / Indeed their horsemen come from [xref]a[/xref]afar; / They fly like an [xref]b[/xref]eagle that hastens to devour.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 28:49-50; Jer. 5:15</xref>
        <xref num="b">Jer. 4:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>All of them come to do violence; / The set of their faces is forward, / And they gather captives like sand.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Indeed they scoff at kings, / And potentates are a derision to them; / They deride every fortress, / For they heap up dirt and take it.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Then they will sweep through [i]like[/i] the wind and pass over / And thus become guilty; this &amp;#8212; their strength &amp;#8212; is their god.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Are You not from [xref]a[/xref]everlasting, O Jehovah, / My God, my Holy One? We will not die. / O Jehovah, You have appointed [note]1[/note]them for [xref]b[/xref]judgment; / And You, O Rock, have established [note]1[/note]them for correction.</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to the Chaldeans.</note>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 90:2; 93:2</xref>
        <xref num="b">2 Kings 19:25; Psa. 17:13; Isa. 10:5-7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>You who are of purer eyes than to behold evil / And who cannot look upon wrong, / Why do You [xref]a[/xref]look upon them who deal treacherously / [i]And[/i] keep silent when the wicked man swallows up him who is [note]1[/note]more / righteous than he?</text>
        <note num="1">According to Habakkuk, the people of Israel were more righteous than the Babylonians, yet they were suffering the violence of the Babylonians. Habakkuk's word here indicates that he was angry with God.</note>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 12:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And You make man like the fish of the sea, / Like the creeping things, who have no one to rule for them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>They take all of them up with a [xref]a[/xref]hook; / They drag them off in their net / And gather them into their seine; / So they rejoice and exult.</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 16:16; Amos 4:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Therefore they offer [xref]a[/xref]sacrifices to their net / And burn incense to their seine, / For by them their portion is fat / And their food is plenteous.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Deut. 8:17; Isa. 10:13; 37:24-25</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Will they then empty their net / And continually slay the nations without sparing?</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>I will stand at my [xref]a[/xref]watch / And station myself on the fortress, / And I will watch to see what He will [xref]b[/xref]speak to me / And what I will reply concerning my complaint.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 21:8</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 85:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Then Jehovah answered and said,[br/][xref]a[/xref]Write the [note]1[/note]vision, and render it plainly upon tablets, / [note]2[/note]That even he who runs by may read it.</text>
        <note num="1">Concerning God's judgment on the Chaldeans.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, That he who reads it may run.</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 8:1; 30:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>For the vision is yet for the [xref]a[/xref]appointed time, / And it hastens toward the end and will not lie. / Though it tarries, wait for it; / For it will surely [xref]b[/xref]come; it will not delay.</text>
        <xref num="a">Dan. 10:14; 11:27, 35</xref>
        <xref num="b">Heb. 10:37; 2 Pet. 3:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>See, he who is puffed up, his soul is not upright within him, / [note]1[/note]But [xref]a[/xref]the righteous one will [note]2[/note]live by his faith.</text>
        <note num="1">This word, quoted three times in the New Testament by the apostle Paul ([link]Rom. 1:17[/link]; [link]Gal. 3:11[/link]; [link]Heb. 10:38[/link]), unveils God's eternal salvation given to sinners. According to the background of this book, both Israel (God's elect) and the Chaldeans (the nations) were under God's judgment. Under God's judgment all sinners, whether Jews or Gentiles, are destined to die ([link]Rom. 6:23[/link]). The unique way for sinners to escape God's judgment and obtain God's eternal salvation is to believe in God's embodiment, Christ, that they may become righteous and be justified in order to have life and live ([link]John 3:16-18[/link]). God's eternal salvation is to save our entire being &amp;#8212; spirit, soul, and body &amp;#8212; for eternity ([link]1 Thes. 5:23[/link]). The way for us to receive such a salvation is to believe in Christ so that we may be justified by God and thus be qualified to have the eternal, divine life, and live by that life ([link]Rom. 3:24[/link]; [link]5:1-2[/link], [link]10[/link], [link]17[/link]; [link]Eph. 2:8[/link]). This is the New Testament gospel in an Old Testament prophetic book.[br/]Christ is the factor that links the books of Micah, Jonah, and Habakkuk. According to [link]Micah 5:2[/link], Christ as the eternal One, whose origin is in eternity, has gone forth by being born as a man in Bethlehem (see note [link]2[sup]1[/sup] in Micah 5[/link]). Then, the type in [link]Jonah 1:17[/link] reveals the continuation of Christ's going forth in His death and resurrection (see note [link]17[sup]1[/sup] in Jonah 1[/link]). In the book of Jonah, Jehovah's salvation was brought to Nineveh, an evil city of the Gentiles, through the preaching of the prophet. Today, God's salvation, which was prepared, completed, and consummated by Christ's going forth, has come to us through the preaching of the gospel. The way to receive and apply this salvation is by faith, as mentioned in this verse.</note>
        <note num="2">Here, to live means to have life and live. See note [link]17[sup]3[/sup] in Rom. 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Rom. 1:17; Gal. 3:11; Heb. 10:38</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Furthermore [i]his[/i] wine is treacherous: / A boasting man, he does not abide at home, / He who enlarges his appetite like [note]1[/note]Sheol, / And is like death and cannot be satisfied, / But gathers to himself all the nations / And collects for himself all the peoples.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]23[sup]1[/sup] in Matt. 11[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Will not all of these take up a parable against him, / Indeed a mocking song [i]and[/i] a riddle against him, and say, / Woe to him who increases what is not his (For how long?) / And who loads himself with the burden of pledges?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Will not those who bite you rise up suddenly, / And those who shake you awake, / And you will become booty to them?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Because you have [xref]a[/xref]plundered many nations; / All the remnant of the peoples will [note]1[/note]plunder you, / Because of the bloodshed of men and the violence [i]done[/i] to the land, / To the city, and to all the inhabitants in it.</text>
        <note num="1">This plundering of Babylon by the nations, as God's recompense on Babylon, took place a little more than eighty-five years after Habakkuk's prophecy (see [link]Dan. 5[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 33:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Woe to him who by violence takes evil gain for his house, / So as to place his nest on high / That he may be delivered from the hand of evil!</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>You have devised shame against your own house / By cutting off many peoples, / And have sinned against your own soul.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>For the [xref]a[/xref]stone will cry out from the wall, / And the rafter will answer from the timber.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Luke 19:40</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Woe to him who builds a city by bloodshed / And establishes a town by iniquity!</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 22:13; Ezek. 24:9; Micah 3:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Indeed is it not of Jehovah of hosts / That the peoples toil for the [xref]a[/xref]fire / And the nations weary themselves for vanity?</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 51:58</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>For the [xref]a[/xref]earth will be [note]1[/note]filled / With the knowledge of the glory of Jehovah / As water covers the sea.</text>
        <note num="1">While the peoples were toiling for vanity ([link]v. 13[/link]), something particular, something mysterious was happening on earth: the earth would be filled with the knowledge of the glory of Jehovah as water covers the sea.</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 11:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Woe to him who makes his neighbor drink, / Adding in [note]1[/note]his poison, / And also making [i]him[/i] drunk / In order to look at their nakedness!</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., your.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>You are sated with shame, not glory. / You also, drink and be shown to be uncircumcised! / The [xref]a[/xref]cup of Jehovah's right hand will come around to you, / And disgrace will be upon your glory.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 75:8; Jer. 25:26-29; 51:57</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>For the violence [i]done[/i] to Lebanon will cover you, / As well as the destruction of the beasts which frightened them, / Because of the bloodshed of men and the violence [i]done[/i] to the land, / To the city, and to all the inhabitants in it.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>What profit is the graven [xref]a[/xref]idol that its maker should engrave it, / [i]Or[/i] the molten idol, even the teacher of lies, / That he who forms its form depends on it / To make dumb idols?</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 44:9-10; 46:6-7; Acts 17:29; 1 Cor. 12:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Woe to him who says to wood, Awake! / [i]And,[/i] Arise! to silent stone. / Will it teach [i]him?[/i] / Behold, it is set in gold and silver, / And there is no breath at all within it.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>But Jehovah is in His holy [xref]a[/xref]temple: / Be [xref]b[/xref]silent before Him, all the earth!</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 11:4</xref>
        <xref num="b">Zeph. 1:7; Zech. 2:13; Rev. 8:1; cf. Psa. 46:10; Zech. 1:11</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>A prayer of Habakkuk the prophet in [note]1[/note]shigionoth.</text>
        <note num="1">The meaning of the term is obscure, but the term apparently denotes a musical form or tempo (cf. [link]Psa. 7[/link], title).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>O Jehovah, I have heard the report concerning You [i]and[/i] am afraid. / O Jehovah, [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]revive Your work / In the midst of the years; / In the midst of the years make [i]it[/i] known; / In wrath remember compassion.</text>
        <note num="1">In his prayer for revival, Habakkuk represents all God's elect throughout the generations. Among God's elect there has always been an aspiration to be revived. Moreover, since the fall of man there has been in all creation an aspiration for revival ([link]Rom. 8:19-23[/link]). Adam's fall brought corruption, slavery, and death into the whole creation ([link]Rom. 5:12[/link]); everything is decaying and is under the slavery of corruption. All the things that are under this slavery aspire to be revived.[br/]The universal need for revival, for restoration, can be met only by Christ and in Christ. Only Christ, who was resurrected on the third day ([link]1 Cor. 15:4[/link]), is the renewing power. For the whole universe and for all mankind, Christ is the reality of the third day ([link]John 11:25[/link]). The reality of the third day is the person of the resurrected Christ with the reality of revival. Christ, therefore, is the element of the revival for which all creation aspires. The corruption and desolation can be swallowed up only by Christ's resurrection. The way to experience revival is to contact Christ by repenting and confessing our sins, failures, and darkness, thereby entering into Him as the resurrection. Cf. [link]Hosea 6:2[/link] and note.</note>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 80:18; 85:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>God comes from Teman, / Even the [xref]a[/xref]Holy One from Mount Paran. [note]1[/note]Selah / His splendor covers the heavens, / And the earth is filled with His praise.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]2[sup]1[/sup] in Psa. 3[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 33:2; Judg. 5:4; Psa. 68:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And [i]His[/i] brightness is like the light: / Rays [i]come forth[/i] from His hand, / And the hiding of His power is there.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Before Him goes pestilence, / And the [xref]a[/xref]fire bolt comes forth at His feet.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 18:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>He stands and [note]1[/note]measures the earth; / He looks and startles the nations; / And the ancient mountains are [xref]a[/xref]shattered into dust, / And the everlasting hills sink down; / His goings are eternal.</text>
        <note num="1">Or (as the Septuagint translates), shakes.</note>
        <xref num="a">Nahum 1:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>I see the tents of [note]1[/note]Cushan / Under affliction; / The tent curtains of the land of Midian tremble.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., Ethiopia.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Is it against the rivers, O Jehovah, / Against the rivers that Your anger is kindled? / Is Your overflowing wrath against the sea / That You [xref]a[/xref]ride upon Your horses, / Upon Your chariots of salvation?</text>
        <xref num="a">Hab. 3:15; Deut. 33:26-27; Psa. 68:4; Rev. 6:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Your bow is bared utterly; / The rods [i]of discipline[/i] are sworn according to [i]Your[/i] word. Selah / You cleave the earth with rivers.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>The mountains see you; they [xref]a[/xref]writhe; / The tempest of water passes by; / The deep utters its voice, / It lifts its hands high.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 19:16, 18; Judg. 5:4-5; Psa. 68:8; 77:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>The sun [i]and[/i] the moon stand [xref]a[/xref]still in their high abode / At the light of Your arrows going forth, / At the brightness of Your glittering spear.</text>
        <xref num="a">Josh. 10:12-13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>In wrath You march through the earth, / In anger You [xref]a[/xref]thresh the nations.</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 51:33; Amos 1:3; Micah 4:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>You go forth for the [xref]a[/xref]salvation of Your people, / For the salvation of Your anointed one, / You strike the head from the house of the wicked one, / Laying bare the foundation, even to the neck. Selah</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 68:19-22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>You pierce, with his own staves, / The heads of his warriors. / They come out like a whirlwind to scatter me; / Their exultation is as if to devour the poor in secret.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>You tread the sea with Your horses, / The heap of mighty waters.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>I heard and my body trembled; / My lips quivered at the sound. / Rottenness entered my bones, / And I tremble in my place, / Because I must wait quietly for the day of distress, / When [note]1[/note]he who attacks comes up against the people.</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to the Chaldeans.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>For the fig tree will not sprout, / And there will be no yield on the vines; / The labor on the olive tree will fail, / And the fields will make no food; / The flock will be cut off from the fold, / And there will be no herd in the stalls.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Yet I will [xref]a[/xref]exult in Jehovah; / I will rejoice in the God of my salvation.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 41:16; 61:10; Luke 1:47</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Jehovah the Lord is my [xref]a[/xref]strength; / And He makes my feet like [xref]b[/xref]hinds' [i]feet[/i] / And will cause me to walk on my [xref]c[/xref]high places. / For the choir director, with [note]1[/note]my stringed instruments.</text>
        <note num="1">Perhaps indicating that Habakkuk was also qualified to participate in the musical temple worship. He might have been a priest or a Levite.</note>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 27:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">2 Sam. 22:34; Psa. 18:33; cf. Gen. 49:21</xref>
        <xref num="c">Deut. 32:13; 33:29</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    </chapters>
</book>
