<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="yes"?>
<book name="Haggai">
    <info title="Author">Haggai ([link]1:1[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Time of His Ministry">About 520 B.C., the second year of Darius Hystaspes ([link]1:1[/link]; [link]Ezra 4-6[/link]; different from both the Darius in [link]Dan. 9:1[/link]; [link]11:1[/link] and the one in [link]Neh. 12:22[/link]), at the time of Zechariah ([link]Ezra 5:1[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Place of His Ministry">Jerusalem.</info>
    <info title="Object of His Ministry">The captives who returned to Jerusalem ([link]1:1[/link]).</info>
    <subject>Jehovah's Dealing with the Returned Captives for the Building of His House</subject>
    <outlines>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="1" ref="1:1">The introductory word</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="2" ref="1:2-15">Jehovah's rebuke and charge concerning the delay of the building of His house</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="vv. 2-6">Jehovah's rebuke</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="vv. 7-8">Jehovah's charge</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="vv. 9-11">Jehovah's further rebuke</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="4" ref="vv. 12-15">The people's response</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="3" ref="2:1-23">The prophecy concerning the house of Jehovah in the millennium and the promise concerning the Messiah in the coming kingdom</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="vv. 1-9">The prophecy concerning the house of Jehovah in the millennium</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="vv. 10-19">The people's uncleanness and Jehovah's dealing with them and then blessing them</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="vv. 20-23">The promise concerning the Messiah (typified by Zerubbabel) in the coming kingdom</outline>
    </outlines>
    <chapters>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>In the [xref]a[/xref]second year of [note]1[/note]Darius the king, in the sixth month, on the first day of the month, the word of Jehovah came through [note]2[/note]Haggai the prophet unto [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, the governor of Judah, and unto [xref]c[/xref]Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, saying,</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., Darius Hystaspes, who ruled the Medo-Persian empire from 521-486 B.C. See [link]Ezra 4:5[/link], [link]24[/link]; [link]5:3-6:12[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Meaning [i]My feast,[/i] or [i]the feast of Jah; Jah[/i] being a shortened form of [i]Jehovah[/i]. The name indicates that Haggai the prophet, who had been born in captivity in Babylon, expected earnestly to return from the captivity that the feasts of Jehovah might be restored.[br/][br/]The central thought of Haggai's prophecy is that the building of the house of Jehovah is related to the welfare of God's people today and to the coming of the millennial kingdom with its Messiah in the age of restoration ([link]Matt. 19:28[/link]; [link]Acts 3:20-21[/link]). In the Old Testament the house of God, or the temple, was first a type of Christ as the house of God individually ([link]John 2:19-21[/link]) and then a type of the church, the Body, the enlarged Christ, as God's house corporately ([link]1 Tim. 3:15[/link]). Thus, Haggai's prophecy refers to us, the New Testament believers, since we are the reality of the type.</note>
        <note num="3">During the years when the rebuilding of the temple was interrupted through the opposition of the adversaries ([link]Ezra 4[/link]), the children of Israel began to build houses for themselves and gradually forgot the building of the temple ([link]vv. 2-4[/link]). Haggai's speaking to Zerubbabel the governor, representing the kingship, and Joshua the high priest, representing the priesthood, was to strengthen and encourage them and the people for the rebuilding of the temple as God's house ([link]Ezra 5:1[/link] and note). </note>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 4:24; Zech. 1:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Chron. 3:17, 19; Ezra 3:2; 5:2; Matt. 1:12</xref>
        <xref num="c">Zech. 3:1; 6:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Thus says Jehovah of hosts, saying, This people says, The time has not come, the time for the house of Jehovah to be built.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Then the word of Jehovah came through [xref]a[/xref]Haggai the prophet, saying,</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 5:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Is it time for you yourselves to dwell in your paneled-up houses, while this [xref]a[/xref]house lies waste?</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 7:2; Psa. 132:3-5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Now therefore thus says Jehovah of hosts, [note]1[/note]Consider your ways.</text>
        <note num="1">The self-serving and God-neglecting returned captives were taking care of their houses but not Jehovah's house; hence, He came in to ask them concerning His house.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>You [xref]a[/xref]have sown much, but you bring in [note]1[/note]little; you eat, but there is no satisfaction; you drink, but there is no being filled with drink; you dress yourselves, but there is no warmth in doing so; and he who earns wages, earns wages [i]to put them[/i] into a bag with holes.</text>
        <note num="1">This indicates that if we do not have the heart to take care of God's house for His satisfaction, no matter how much we eat or drink or how well we dress, there will be no satisfaction. If we neglect the church, we will have no real enjoyment or satisfaction.</note>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 28:38; Hosea 4:10; Micah 6:14-15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Thus says Jehovah of hosts, Consider your ways.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Go up to the mountain and [note]1[/note]bring wood and build the house, and I will take pleasure in it and will be glorified, says Jehovah.</text>
        <note num="1">Today our gospel preaching is our gathering of material for the building of God's house.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>You looked for much, and yet [i]it amounted[/i] to little; and when you brought it home, I blew on it. Why? declares Jehovah of hosts. Because of My house that lies waste while you each [note]1[/note]run to your own house.</text>
        <note num="1">The word run indicates that the people were busy caring for their own houses. It is impossible for us to be neutral. We must be absolute, either taking care of our houses first or taking care of the Lord's house first (cf. [link]Matt. 6:33[/link]; [link]Luke 9:57-62[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Therefore over you the heavens withhold their [xref]a[/xref]dew, and the earth withholds its yield.</text>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 26:19; Deut. 28:23; 1 Kings 8:35</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Indeed I called for a [xref]a[/xref]drought upon the land and upon the mountains and upon the grain and upon the new wine and upon the fresh oil and upon that which the ground brings forth and upon man and upon beast and upon all the toil of the hands.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 17:1; 2 Kings 8:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And [xref]a[/xref]Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel and Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and all the remnant of the people listened to the voice of Jehovah their God and to the words of Haggai the prophet, as Jehovah their God had sent him; and the people were in fear before Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 5:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Then Haggai, Jehovah's messenger, spoke in Jehovah's message to the people, saying, I am with you, declares Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And Jehovah [xref]a[/xref]stirred up the [note]1[/note]spirit of Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, the governor of Judah, and the [note]1[/note]spirit of Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and the [note]1[/note]spirit of all the remnant of the people; and they came and did [note]2[/note]work in the [xref]b[/xref]house of Jehovah of hosts their God,</text>
        <note num="1">For the recovery of the building of God's house, God's elect were stirred up by the Lord in their spirit in the order of God's authority, beginning with Zerubbabel the governor (cf. [link]Ezra 1:5[/link]). In the Minor Prophets both the divine Spirit and the stirred-up human spirit of God's elect are mentioned. In the New Testament the divine Spirit has been consummated and poured out ([link]Acts 2:17-21[/link]; [link]Joel 2:28-32[/link]), and our human spirit responds to such a Spirit by being stirred up (cf. [link]Acts 17:16[/link]; [link]Rom. 8:16[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 2:13[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">In our response to the Lord's charge, we all should be occupied by the Lord Jesus in the work of preaching the gospel, feeding the new believers, and taking care of others for the building up of the Lord's house, the church as the Body of Christ ([link]John 21:15-17[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">2 Chron. 36:22; Ezra 1:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">Ezra 5:2, 8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>On the twenty-fourth day of the month, in the sixth month, in the second year of Darius the king.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>In the seventh month, on the twenty-first day of the month, the word of Jehovah came through Haggai the prophet, saying,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Speak now to Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, the governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and to the remnant of the people, saying,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Who is left among you who saw this [xref]a[/xref]house in its former glory? And how do you see it now? Is it not as [xref]b[/xref]nothing in your eyes?</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 3:12</xref>
        <xref num="b">Zech. 4:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Yet now [xref]a[/xref]be strong, O Zerubbabel, declares Jehovah; and be strong, O Joshua, son of Jehozadak, the high priest; and be strong, all you people of the land, declares Jehovah, and work; for I am with you, declares Jehovah of hosts.</text>
        <xref num="a">Zech. 8:9; Eph. 6:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>[i]Both[/i] the word which I covenanted with you when you came forth from Egypt and My [xref]a[/xref]Spirit endure among you; do not fear.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 9:20; Isa. 63:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>For thus says Jehovah of hosts, [note]1[/note]Yet once more &amp;#8212; it is but a little while &amp;#8212; I will [xref]a[/xref]shake the heavens and the earth and the sea and the dry land;</text>
        <note num="1">The prophecy in [link]vv. 6-9[/link] concerns the house of Jehovah in the millennium. It was an encouragement to the building of Jehovah's house at Zerubbabel's time.</note>
        <xref num="a">Joel 3:16; Hag. 2:21; Heb. 12:26; Rev. 6:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And I will shake all the nations, and the [note]1[/note]Desire of all the nations will [xref]a[/xref]come; and I will [xref]b[/xref]fill this house with glory, says Jehovah of hosts.</text>
        <note num="1">This refers to Christ, who is the Desire of all the nations ([link]Mal. 3:1b[/link]). Even though the nations do not know Christ, they still desire Christ. All people desire to have peace and a good life with virtues such as light, love, patience, humility, meekness, endurance, joy, and righteousness. Since Christ is the reality of all these things, for the nations to desire these things means that, unconsciously, they desire Christ.[br/][br/]The coming of Christ as the Desire of all the nations depends on the return of God's people from their captivity in Babylon and the recovery of the building of God's house. Christ came the first time, in His incarnation, through the return of a remnant of Israel to Jerusalem from their captivity in Babylon for the rebuilding of the temple. He will come the second time through the return of a remnant of His New Testament elect from their captivity in the religious Babylon ([link]Rev. 17[/link]) to the proper ground of the church for the recovery of the building of the church, God's spiritual house ([link]1 Tim. 3:15[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 2:5[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 49:10; Mal. 3:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">Acts 2:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>The silver is [xref]a[/xref]Mine, and the gold is Mine, declares Jehovah of hosts.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Psa. 50:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>The latter glory of this house will be [xref]a[/xref]greater than the former, says Jehovah of hosts; and in this place I will give peace, declares Jehovah of hosts.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Matt. 12:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>In the twenty-fourth day of the ninth month, in the second year of Darius, the word of Jehovah came to Haggai the prophet, saying,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Thus says Jehovah of hosts, Ask now the priests for instruction, saying,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>If one carries holy flesh in the skirt of his garment, and with his skirt he touches bread or boiled food or wine or oil or any [i]other[/i] food, will it become holy? And the priests answered and said, No.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Then Haggai said, If one who is unclean because of a [xref]a[/xref]corpse touches any of these, will it be unclean? And the priests answered and said, It will be unclean.</text>
        <xref num="a">Num. 19:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Then Haggai answered and said, So is this people and so is this nation before Me, declares Jehovah, and so is all the work of their hands. Thus what they offer there is [note]1[/note]unclean.</text>
        <note num="1">The uncleanness here was not related to their physical offerings but to their moral and spiritual situation, which involved their relationship with God. Once the uncleanness was removed, they would be blessed by God.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And now, consider from this day and previously, before a stone was set upon a stone in the temple of Jehovah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Before [i]these days[/i] were, someone would come to a grain heap for twenty measures, and there would be [i]only[/i] ten; someone would come to a vat to draw fifty troughfuls, and there would be [i]only[/i] twenty.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>I struck you with [xref]a[/xref]blight and with mildew and with hail on all the work of your hands; but on your part, [i]none turned[/i] to Me, declares Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 28:22; 1 Kings 8:37; Amos 4:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Consider from this day and previously, from the twenty-fourth day of the ninth month, from the [xref]a[/xref]day when the foundation of the temple of Jehovah was laid; consider.</text>
        <xref num="a">Zech. 8:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Is there yet seed in the barn? Indeed even the vine and the fig tree and the pomegranate and the olive tree have not borne [i]fruit;[/i] from this day I will bless [i]you.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And the word of Jehovah came a second time to Haggai on the twenty-fourth day of the month, saying,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Speak to [note]1[/note]Zerubbabel the governor of Judah, saying, I will [xref]a[/xref]shake the heavens and the earth.</text>
        <note num="1">[link]Verses 20-23[/link] are the promise concerning the Messiah (typified by Zerubbabel) in the coming kingdom. Jehovah's making Zerubbabel as a signet ring ([link]v. 23[/link]) indicates that Jehovah regarded him as His representative and that He loved him and trusted him. In this matter Zerubbabel is a type of Christ. He represents God ([link]Matt. 28:18[/link]), and He is the One whom God loves and trusts ([link]Matt. 3:17[/link]; [link]17:5[/link]; [link]John 3:35[/link]; [link]17:2[/link]). As such a person, He is qualified to take care of the building of God's house, the church ([link]Matt. 16:18[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Hag. 2:6-7; Heb. 12:26</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And I will overthrow the throne of the [xref]a[/xref]kingdoms and will destroy the strength of the kingdoms of the nations; and I will overthrow the chariots and their riders, and the horses and their riders will go down, each by the sword of his brother.</text>
        <xref num="a">Dan. 2:44</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>In that day, declares Jehovah of hosts, I will take you, O Zerubbabel, son of Shealtiel, My servant, declares Jehovah, and make you as a [xref]a[/xref]signet; for I have [xref]b[/xref]chosen you, declares Jehovah of hosts.</text>
        <xref num="a">S.S. 8:6; Jer. 22:24</xref>
        <xref num="b">Isa. 42:1; 43:10</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    </chapters>
</book>
