<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book name="Hebrews" description="THE EPISTLE TO THE HEBREWS" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="..\bible.xsd">
    <info title="Author">Apparently the apostle Paul, who alone was qualified to write the deep, high, and rich content of this book. The mention of Timothy and the tone of the fellowship also point to Paul as the author (see also [link]1:1[sup]1[/sup][/link]).</info>
    <info title="Time of Writing">Perhaps A.D. 67, after Paul's release from his first Roman imprisonment, while he was in Miletus ([link]2 Tim. 4:20[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Place of Writing">Perhaps Miletus (see verse in the previous item). The mention of "those from Italy" in [link]13:24[/link] indicates that the book was not written in Rome.</info>
    <info title="Recipients">The Hebrew believers, as indicated by the book's content.</info>
    <subject>Christ Being Superior to Judaism and Everything Related to It, and the New Covenant Which He Consummated Being Better than the Old Covenant</subject>
    <outlines>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="1" ref="1:1-3">Introduction &amp;#8212; God Speaking in the Son</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="2" ref="1:4-10:39">The Superiority of Christ</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="1:4-2:18">Superior to the Angels</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="1" ref="1:4-14">As the Son of God &amp;#8212; As God</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="" ref="2:1-4">(The First Warning &amp;#8212; Give Heed to What Is Spoken concerning the Son)</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="2" ref="2:5-18">As the Son of Man &amp;#8212; As Man</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="3:1-6">Superior to Moses &amp;#8212; As an Apostle Worthy of More Glory and Honor</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="" ref="3:7-4:13">(The Second Warning &amp;#8212; Do Not Come Short of the Promised Rest)</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="4:14-7:28">Superior to Aaron</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="1" ref="4:14-5:10">A High Priest according to the Order of Melchizedek</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="" ref="5:11-6:20">(The Third Warning &amp;#8212; Be Brought On to Maturity)</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="2" ref="7:1-28">A High Priest, Perpetual, Great, Living, and Able to Save to the Uttermost</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="4" ref="8:1-10:18">Christ's New Covenant Superior to the Old</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="1" ref="8:1-13">A Better Covenant of Better Promises with a More Excellent Ministry</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="2" ref="9:1-10:18">Better Sacrifices and Better Blood with the Greater and More Perfect Tabernacle</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="" ref="10:19-39">(The Fourth Warning &amp;#8212; Come Forward to the Holy of Holies and Do Not Shrink Back to Judaism)</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="3" ref="11:1-40">The Unique Way of Faith</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="v. 1">The Definition of Faith</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="vv. 2-40">The Witnesses of Faith</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="" ref="12:1-29">(The Fifth Warning &amp;#8212; Run the Race and Do Not Fall Away from Grace)</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="4" ref="13:1-19">Virtues for the Church Life</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="vv. 1-7">Six Practical Items</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="vv. 8-15">Experiences of Christ</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="vv. 16-19">Another Four Items Needed</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="5" ref="13:20-25">Conclusion</outline>
    </outlines>
    <chapters>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[note]1[/note]God, having [xref]a[/xref]spoken of old in [note]2[/note]many portions and in many ways to the fathers in the prophets,</text>
        <note num="1">God has spoken! Praise Him! Without His speaking, God is mysterious. But He has revealed Himself in His speaking. He is no longer mysterious. Now He is the revealed God.[br][br]The emphasis of this book is that God, not man, has spoken. Therefore, it does not identify its writer, nor in any of its quotations from the Old Testament does it mention the speaker's name. According to the concept of this book, the entire Scripture is the speaking of God. Hence, in referring to the Old Testament, this book always says that it is the Holy Spirit's speaking ([link]3:7[/link]; [link]9:8[/link]; [link]10:15-17[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">In the Old Testament, God spoke to the people not once for all and in only one way but in many portions and in many ways: in one portion to the Patriarchs in one way, in another portion through Moses in another way; in one portion through David in one way, in other portions through a number of prophets in several different ways.[br][br]It is most fitting and meaningful that this book, a book of God's speaking, is entitled [i]The Epistle to the Hebrews.[/i] The first Hebrew was Abraham ([link]Gen. 14:13[/link]), the father of all those who contact God by faith ([link]Rom. 4:11-12[/link]). Therefore, God is called "the God of the Hebrews" ([link]Exo. 9:1[/link], [link]13[/link]). The root of the word [i]Hebrew[/i] means [i]to pass over.[/i] It can mean specifically to pass over a river, that is, to pass over from this side of the river to the other side, to pass over from one side to another. Therefore, a Hebrew is a river crosser. Abraham was such a one. From Chaldea, the land of idolatry, which was on the other side of the great river Euphrates, he crossed over to Canaan, the land of the worship of God, which was on this side of the Euphrates ([link]Josh. 24:2-3[/link]). The intention of God's speaking in this book was that the Jews who believed in the Lord but still lingered in Judaism would leave the law and cross over to grace ([link]4:16[/link]; [link]7:18-19[/link]; [link]12:28[/link]; [link]13:9[/link]), that they would leave the old covenant and cross over to the new covenant ([link]8:6-7[/link], [link]13[/link]), and that they would leave the ritualistic service of the Old Testament and cross over to the spiritual reality of the New Testament ([link]8:5[/link]; [link]9:9-14[/link]); that is, that they would leave Judaism and cross over to the church ([link]13:13[/link]; [link]10:25[/link]), that they would leave the earthly things and cross over to the heavenly things ([link]12:18-24[/link]), that they would leave the outer court, where the altar is, and cross over to the Holiest of all, where God is ([link]13:9-10[/link]; [link]10:19-20[/link]), that they would leave the soul and cross over to the spirit ([link]4:12[/link]), and that they would leave the beginning of truth and life and cross over to the maturity of life in the truth ([link]5:11-6:1[/link]). Not only the Jews who believed in the Lord but all who contact God by faith should be such river crossers. This is the purpose of God's speaking in this book.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 3:21[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Has at the [note]1[/note]last of these days spoken to us in the [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]Son, [note]3[/note]whom He appointed [note]4[/note][xref]b[/xref]Heir of all things, [xref]c[/xref]through whom also He made the [note]5[/note][xref]d[/xref]universe;</text>
        <note num="1">A Hebrew expression indicating the end of the dispensation of the law, when Messiah was to be introduced. See [link]Isa. 2:2[/link]; [link]Micah 4:1[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">In the Old Testament, God spoke in the prophets, in men borne by His Spirit ([link]2 Pet. 1:21[/link]). In the New Testament, He speaks in the Son, in the person of the Son. The Son is God Himself ([link]v. 8[/link]), God expressed. God the Father is hidden; God the Son is expressed. No one has ever seen God; the Son, as the Word of God ([link]John 1:1[/link]; [link]Rev. 19:13[/link]) and the speaking of God, has declared Him with a full expression, explanation, and definition of Him ([link]John 1:18[/link]).[br][br]The Son is the center, the focus, of this book. In the Godhead He is the effulgence of God's glory and the impress of God's substance. In creation He is (1) the means through which the universe was made ([link]v. 2[/link]); (2) the power that upholds and bears all things ([link]v. 3[/link]); and (3) the Heir appointed to inherit all things. In redemption He accomplished the purification of man's sins and is now sitting on the right hand of God in the heavens ([link]v. 3[/link]).[br][br]This book reveals to us the contrast between the Old Testament and the New Testament. The Old Testament was of the law in letters and forms, of man, earthly, temporary, and by sight and issued in a religion called Judaism. The New Testament is of life, spiritual, heavenly, permanent, and by faith and is focused in a person who is the Son of God.</note>
        <note num="3">This short recommendation of the Son in [link]vv. 2-3[/link] unfolds to us both the person and work of the Son. In His person He is the effulgence of God's glory and the impress of God's substance. In His work He created the universe and upholds and bears all things, and made purification of our sins.</note>
        <note num="4">I.e., the legal Heir, inheriting all things in God's economy. Since He is not only the Son of God but also the Heir of God, all that God the Father is and has is His possession ([link]John 16:15[/link]). In the past the Son was the Creator ([link]vv. 2[/link], [link]10[/link]; [link]John 1:3[/link]; [link]Col. 1:16[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 8:6[/link]); in the present He is the Upholder of all things and the One who bears all things ([link]v. 3[/link]); in the future He will be the Heir, inheriting all things (cf. [link]Rom. 11:36[/link]).</note>
        <note num="5">Lit., ages. [i]The ages[/i] is a Jewish expression that means [i]the universe. Ages[/i] here does not refer to the matter of time but to creation (the universe) unfolded in time through successive ages.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Matt. 17:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Psa. 2:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]John 1:3[/link]; [link]Col. 1:16[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 8:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 11:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Who, being the [note]1[/note]effulgence of His glory and the [xref]a[/xref]impress of His substance and [xref]b[/xref]upholding and bearing all things by the [note]2[/note]word of His power, having made [note]3[/note]purification of sins, [note]4[/note][xref]c[/xref]sat down on the right hand of the [note]5[/note][xref]d[/xref]Majesty on [note]6[/note]high;</text>
        <note num="1">The effulgence of God's glory is like the shining or the brightness of the light of the sun. The Son is the shining, the brightness, of the Father's glory. This refers to God's glory. The impress of God's substance is like the impress of a seal. The Son is the expression of what God the Father is. This refers to God's substance.</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word denotes the instant word. The Son upholds and bears all things not by His work but by His instant word, the word of His power. In creation all things came into being through Him as the Word ([link]John 1:1-3[/link]). The universe has been framed by the word of God ([link]11:3[/link]): "He spoke, and it was; He commanded, and it stood" ([link]Psa. 33:9[/link]). In salvation we are saved through His word ([link]John 5:24[/link]; [link]Rom. 10:8[/link], [link]17[/link]). It is through His word that His authority with power is exercised ([link]Matt. 8:8-9[/link]). It is by His word that His healing power is realized ([link]John 4:50-51[/link]). Here, this book says that God speaks in the Son and the Son upholds and bears all things by His word. It is altogether a matter of speaking. When the Lord speaks, everything is in order.</note>
        <note num="3">In the Old Testament type the expiation was able only to cover sins ([link]Psa. 32:1[/link]); it was unable to take away sins. So the expiating priests stood daily, offering the same sacrifices ([link]10:11[/link]), and could never sit down. But the Son took away sin ([link]John 1:29[/link]) and accomplished the purification of sins once for all. So He sat down forever ([link]10:10[/link], [link]12[/link]).</note>
        <note num="4">This book, having the concept that all positive things are heavenly, points us to the very Christ who is in the heavens. In the Gospels is the Christ who lived on the earth and died on the cross for the accomplishing of redemption. In the Acts is the resurrected and ascended Christ propagated and ministered to men. In Romans is the Christ who is our righteousness for justification and our life for sanctification, transformation, conformation, glorification, and building up. In Galatians is the Christ who enables us to live a life that is versus the law, religion, tradition, and forms. In Philippians is the Christ who is lived out of His members. In Ephesians and Colossians is the Christ who is the life, the content, and the Head of the Body, the church. In 1 and 2 Corinthians is the Christ who is everything in the practical church life. In 1 and 2 Thessalonians is the Christ who is our holiness for His coming back. In 1 and 2 Timothy and Titus is the Christ who is God's economy, enabling us to know how to conduct ourselves in the house of God. In the Epistles of Peter is the Christ who enables us to take God's governmental dealings administered through sufferings. In the Epistles of John is the Christ who is the life and fellowship of the children of God in God's family. In Revelation is the Christ who is walking among the churches in this age, ruling over the world in the kingdom in the coming age, and expressing God in full glory in the new heaven and new earth for eternity. In this book is the present Christ, who is now in the heavens as our Minister ([link]8:2[/link]) and our High Priest ([link]4:14-15[/link]; [link]7:26[/link]), ministering to us the heavenly life, grace, authority, and power and sustaining us to live a heavenly life on earth. He is the Christ now, the Christ today, and the Christ on the throne in the heavens, who is our daily salvation and moment-by-moment supply.</note>
        <note num="5">Or, Greatness; denoting God as the greatest One with His dignity.</note>
        <note num="6">The high place, the third heaven, the highest place in the universe.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Cor. 4:4[/link]; [link]Col. 1:15[/link]; cf. [link]John 1:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Col. 1:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Eph. 1:20[/link]; [link]Heb. 1:13[/link]; [link]8:1[/link]; [link]10:12[/link]; [link]12:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 8:1[/link]; [link]Jude 25[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Having become as much better than the angels as to have inherited a [note]1[/note]more distinguished name than they.</text>
        <note num="1">This more distinguished name is "the Son," a name that is fully defined in the succeeding verses.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>For to which of the angels has He ever said, [xref]a[/xref]"You are My Son; [note]1[/note]this day have I begotten You"? And again, [xref]b[/xref]"I will be a Father to Him, and He will be a Son to Me"?</text>
        <note num="1">[i]This day[/i] refers to the day of resurrection ([link]Acts 13:33[/link]). This chapter gives us an account of Christ from eternity past to eternity future. He was the very God in eternity past ([link]v. 8[/link]); He was the Creator of the earth and the heavens ([link]vv. 10[/link], [link]2[/link]); He is the Upholder of all things and the One who bears all things ([link]v. 3[/link]); He is the Heir of all things ([link]v. 2[/link]); He was incarnated to accomplish redemption by being crucified ([link]v. 3[/link]); He was begotten as the Son of God in resurrection for the imparting of life to the many sons of God ([link]v. 5[/link]); He is the firstborn Son of God who will come again ([link]v. 6[/link]); He will be the King on the throne with the scepter in the kingdom ([link]vv. 8-9[/link]); and He will remain forever and ever in eternity future ([link]vv. 11-12[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 2:7[/link]; [link]Heb. 5:5[/link]; [link]Acts 13:33[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Sam. 7:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And when He brings again the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Firstborn into the inhabited earth, He says, [xref]b[/xref]"And let all the angels of God worship Him."</text>
        <note num="1">This verse refers to the Son's second coming. In His first coming He was God's only begotten Son ([link]John 1:14[/link]). Through the process of resurrection the only begotten Son became the Firstborn among many brothers ([link]Rom. 8:29[/link]). Thus, in His second coming He will be the Firstborn.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 8:29[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Psa. 97:7[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And of the angels He says, [xref]a[/xref]"Who makes His angels [note]1[/note]winds and His ministers a flame of fire";</text>
        <note num="1">In Greek, the same word as for [i]spirits.[/i] Here it denotes [i]winds,[/i] to match [i]flame[/i] of fire. The angels are like winds and a flame of fire. They are simply creatures, while the Son is the Creator. As creatures, the angels are much inferior to the Son, and as the Creator, the Son is much superior to the angels.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 104:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>But of the Son, [xref]a[/xref]"Your [xref]b[/xref]throne, [note]1[/note]O God, is forever and ever, and the scepter of uprightness is the scepter of Your [xref]c[/xref]kingdom.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]O God[/i] here and [i]Your God[/i] in [link]v. 9[/link] refer to the Son. Since the Son is God Himself, He is God; therefore, here it says, "O God." Since the Son is also man, God is His God; therefore, in [link]v. 9[/link] it says, "Your God."[br][br]The intention of this book is to show the Hebrew believers that God's salvation is superior to Judaism. In Judaism the boast was in God, angels, Moses, Aaron the high priest, and the Old Testament with its services. Initially, the writer points out that in God's salvation the first superior thing is not only God but God expressed, i.e., God the Son ([link]vv. 2-3[/link], [link]5[/link], [link]8-12[/link]). Then he goes on to unfold that Christ is superior to angels ([link]1:4-2:18[/link]), to Moses ([link]3:1-6[/link]), and to Aaron ([link]4:14-7:28[/link]) and that the new covenant of life made by Him is superior to the old covenant of letters ([link]8:1-10:18[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 45:6-7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Sam. 7:13[/link]; [link]Luke 1:32[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Sam. 7:12[/link]; [link]Dan. 7:14[/link]; [link]Luke 1:33[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>You have loved righteousness and hated lawlessness; therefore God, [note]1[/note]Your God, has [xref]a[/xref]anointed You with the oil of exultant joy above Your [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]partners";</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]8[sup]1[/sup][/link].</note>
        <note num="2">In God's economy Christ is the One appointed by God to accomplish God's plan, and we are Christ's partners in the divine interest. He was anointed by God, and we share with Him this anointing for the fulfillment of God's purpose. See note [link]14[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 3[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Isa. 61:1[/link]; [link]Luke 4:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 3:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And, [xref]a[/xref]"You in the beginning, [note]1[/note]Lord, laid the foundation of the earth, and the heavens are the works of Your hands;</text>
        <note num="1">Since the Son is God ([link]v. 8[/link]), He is the eternal Lord, who remains perpetually ([link]v. 11[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 102:25-27[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>They will perish, but You remain perpetually; and they all will become [xref]a[/xref]old like a [xref]b[/xref]garment,</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Rev. 21:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Isa. 51:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And like a mantle You will roll them up; like a garment they will also be changed; but You are the [xref]a[/xref]same, and Your years will not fail."</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 13:8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>But to which of the angels has He ever said, [xref]a[/xref]"Sit at My right hand [note]1[/note]until I set Your enemies as a [xref]b[/xref]footstool for Your feet"?</text>
        <note num="1">This book stresses the fact that Christ has accomplished everything for God and us, leaving nothing for us to do. His sitting at the right hand of God signifies that His work has been accomplished and that He is resting there, waiting for only one thing &amp;#8212; for God to set His enemies as a footstool for His feet. He is sitting there in the heavens waiting for a footstool that He may have complete rest.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 110:1[/link]; [link]Matt. 22:44[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 10:13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Are they not all [xref]a[/xref]ministering spirits, sent forth for service for the sake of [note]1[/note]those who are to inherit salvation?</text>
        <note num="1">The Son is the appointed Heir of all things ([link]v. 2[/link]). We, His believers, are His partners ([link]v. 9[/link]). Thus, we are His joint heirs ([link]Rom. 8:17[/link]), not only inheriting salvation but also inheriting all things with Him ([link]1 Cor. 3:21-22[/link]). Hence, we with Him are joint owners of the universe, while the angels are merely our servants, inferior not only to Him but also to us.[br][br]The Son was appointed to be the Heir. We are saved to be His joint heirs, sharing in His inheritance. The "so great a salvation" mentioned in [link]2:3[/link] is able to save us to such an extent that it brings us into partnership with Him in His appointment. Thus we share in whatever He inherits.[br][br]As the partners of the Son, we are the house of God, the real Bethel, the gate of heaven, where the Son is the heavenly ladder, joining earth to heaven and bringing heaven to earth. On this ladder the angels of God are ascending and descending ([link]Gen. 28:12[/link], [link]16-19[/link]; [link]John 1:51[/link]) as the ministering spirits to serve us, those who inherit so great a salvation. What is spoken of in this book is like the gate of heaven. Here we enjoy Christ as the heavenly One who joins us to heaven and brings heaven to us that we may be a heavenly people, living a heavenly life on earth and inheriting all the heavenly things. How could the Hebrew believers withdraw from this and return to their old religion and boast in the angels? The angels are simply our ministering servants.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 34:7[/link]; [link]Matt. 18:10[/link]; [link]Acts 10:3[/link]; [link]12:7-11[/link], [link]15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Therefore we ought to give heed more abundantly to the things which have been heard lest perhaps we [note]2[/note]drift away.</text>
        <note num="1">Along with every major point in this book there is a warning. There are five such warnings in the book. Along with the first major point, that Christ is superior to angels, unfolded in [link]1:4-2:18[/link], there is the first warning in [link]vv. 1-4[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Or, drift by them, drift past them.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>For if the word spoken through [xref]a[/xref]angels proved firm and every transgression and disobedience received a just recompense,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 7:53[/link]; [link]Gal. 3:19[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>How shall we [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]escape if we have neglected so great a [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]salvation, which, having had its beginning in being spoken by the Lord, has been confirmed to us by those who heard,</text>
        <note num="1">In principle, to escape here is to escape some recompense, as mentioned in [link]v. 2[/link]. If we neglect so great a salvation, it is right and just that we receive a certain recompense.</note>
        <note num="2">Salvation here refers back to what is mentioned in [link]1:14[/link]. It is God's full salvation, from the forgiveness of sins to the sharing of the coming kingdom with glory. It refers not only to what Christ has done and will do for us but also to Himself, the One who is able to save us to the uttermost ([link]7:25[/link]). As the Son of God &amp;#8212; as God &amp;#8212; and as the Son of Man &amp;#8212; as man &amp;#8212; He is our salvation. His wonderful person plus His splendid work constitute so great a salvation, a salvation that none of us should neglect. Our negligence will cause us to miss this great salvation's (1) most precious part &amp;#8212; the enjoying of Christ as our saving life and rest in this age; and (2) most glorious part &amp;#8212; the inheriting of Christ's kingdom with glory in the coming age. These two points are fully developed and dealt with in the succeeding chapters of this book.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 12:25[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 1:14[/link]; [link]2:10[/link]; [link]5:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>God bearing [xref]a[/xref]witness with [i]them[/i] both by signs and wonders and by various works of power and by [note]1[/note]distributions of the Holy Spirit according to His will?</text>
        <note num="1">Distributions of the Holy Spirit, which include the Holy Spirit Himself, are the things that the Holy Spirit distributes to those who receive salvation by believing.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Mark 16:20[/link]; [link]Acts 14:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>For [i]it was[/i] not to angels [i]that[/i] He subjected the coming [note]1[/note]inhabited earth, concerning which we speak.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., the earth that will become the Lord's kingdom in the next age ([link]Psa. 2:8[/link]; [link]Dan. 2:35[/link]; [link]Rev. 11:15[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>But one has solemnly testified somewhere, saying, [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]"What is man, that You bring him to mind? Or the son of man, that You care for him?</text>
        <note num="1">The first man, Adam, created by God in [link]Gen. 1[/link], failed to accomplish God's purpose for man. Psalm 8 then alludes, through prophecy, to another man, a man who would replace the first man and would fulfill God's purpose. This chapter tells us that this other man, the second man, who is Jesus, has come and has accomplished so much for the fulfilling of God's desire in man as revealed in [link]Gen. 1:26[/link], [link]28[/link] and alluded to in [link]Psa. 8:4-8[/link]. Hence, in whatever the first man, Adam, failed, the second man, Christ, succeeded, by replacing the first man.[br][br]This chapter is the fulfillment of the prophecies in [link]Psa. 8[/link] and [link book="Psa."]22[/link] concerning the major steps taken by Christ, as a man, to fulfill God's purpose. In incarnation He partook of human nature ([link]v. 14[/link]). In crucifixion He suffered death for everything ([link]v. 9[/link]) and destroyed the devil ([link]v. 14[/link]). In resurrection He brought forth many sons of God, His brothers, to form the church ([link]vv. 10-12[/link]). In exaltation He was crowned with glory and honor. All these steps are the qualifications that qualify Him to be our High Priest ([link]v. 17[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 8:4-8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>You have made Him [note]1[/note]a little inferior to the angels; You have crowned Him with glory and honor and have set Him [xref]a[/xref]over the works of Your hands;</text>
        <note num="1">Or, for a little while inferior. So also in [link]v. 9[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 1:26[/link], [link]28[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>You have [xref]a[/xref]subjected all things under His feet." For in subjecting all things to Him, He left nothing unsubject to Him. But now we do not yet see all things subjected to Him,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 15:27[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:22[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>But we see Jesus, who was made a little [note]1[/note]inferior to the angels because of the suffering of [xref]a[/xref]death, [xref]b[/xref]crowned with [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]glory and honor, so that by the grace of God He might taste death on behalf of [note]3[/note][xref]d[/xref]everything.</text>
        <note num="1">In eternity Christ was the Creator, unlimited and omnipresent, but when He became a man in time, He was limited so that one day He could go to the cross to deal with the universal problem &amp;#8212; death. In order to suffer death and thus destroy and nullify death, Christ had to become a man and lose His freedom temporarily, for thirty-three and a half years. In that sense, He was inferior to the angels during that period. However, three days after His death He resurrected out of that inferiority and is now much superior to all the angels.</note>
        <note num="2">Glory is the splendor related to Jesus' person; honor is the preciousness related to Jesus' worth, value, and dignity, which is related to His position ([link]2 Pet. 1:17[/link]; cf. [link]1 Pet. 2:17[/link]; [link]Rom. 13:7[/link]). In [link]1 Pet. 2:7[/link] the Greek word for [i]preciousness[/i] is the same as that for [i]honor[/i] here.</note>
        <note num="3">Or, everyone. The Lord Jesus' redemption was accomplished not only for people but for everything created by God. Thus, God can reconcile all things to Himself through Christ ([link]Col. 1:20[/link]). This is clearly typified by the redemption accomplished through Noah's ark, in which not only eight persons but all living things created by God were saved ([link]Gen. 7:13-23[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Phil. 2:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rev. 19:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 1:17[/link]; [link]Rev. 5:12[/link], [link]13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Col. 1:20[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>For it was fitting for [note]1[/note]Him, [xref]a[/xref]for whom are all things and through whom are all things, in leading [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]many sons into [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]glory, to make the [note]4[/note][xref]d[/xref]Author of their [xref]e[/xref]salvation [note]5[/note][xref]f[/xref]perfect through sufferings.</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to God, who created all things.</note>
        <note num="2">The many sons here are the many brothers in [link]Rom. 8:29[/link] and the many grains in [link]John 12:24[/link].</note>
        <note num="3">The last step of God's great salvation is to bring His many sons into glory. [link]Romans 8[/link] tells us that God's work of grace upon us began with His foreknowing, passed through His predestination, calling, and justification, and will end with His glorification ([link]Rom. 8:29-30[/link]). Also, [link]Rom. 8[/link] tells us that the whole creation eagerly awaits the revelation (glorification) of the sons of God, in hope that the creation itself will enter into the freedom of the glory of the children of God ([link]Rom. 8:19-21[/link]). This will be accomplished by the Lord's coming back ([link]Phil. 3:21[/link]), at which time we will be manifested with Him in glory ([link]Col. 3:4[/link]); this is our hope ([link]Col. 1:27[/link]). This glorification of the sons of God, as the goal of God's salvation, will last through the millennial kingdom and will be manifested in full in the New Jerusalem for eternity ([link]Rev. 21:11[/link], [link]23[/link]).</note>
        <note num="4">Or, Captain, Originator, Inaugurator, Leader, Pioneer. The salvation mentioned in this verse and referred to in [link]v. 3[/link] and [link]1:14[/link] saves us from our fallen state into glory. Jesus, as the Pioneer, the Forerunner ([link]6:20[/link]), took the lead to enter into glory, and we, His followers, are taking the same way to be brought into the same glory, which was ordained by God for us ([link]1 Cor. 2:7[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 2:12[/link]). He cut the way, and we are now taking the way. Hence, He is not only the Savior who saved us from our fallen state but also the Author who, as the Pioneer, entered into glory that we may be brought into the same estate.</note>
        <note num="5">To make Jesus perfect was to make Him perfect in terms of qualification. It does not imply that there was any imperfection of virtue or attribute in Jesus, but only that the completing of His experience of human sufferings was needed to make Him fit to become the Author, the Leader, of His followers' salvation.[br][br]As the self-existing and ever-existing God, the Lord Jesus is complete from eternity to eternity. But He needed to be perfected through the processes of incarnation, the partaking of human nature, human living, crucifixion, resurrection, and ascension, that He might be qualified to be God's Christ and our Savior.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 11:36[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 8:29[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rom. 8:21[/link], [link]30[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 2:7[/link]; [link]Col. 3:4[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 2:12[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 5:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 12:2[/link]; [link]Acts 3:15[/link]; [link]5:31[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Heb. 1:14[/link]; [link]2:3[/link]; [link]5:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]Heb. 5:9[/link]; [link]7:19[/link], [link]28[/link]; [link]9:9[/link]; [link]10:1[/link], [link]14[/link]; [link]11:40[/link]; [link]12:23[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>For both [note]1[/note]He who [xref]a[/xref]sanctifies and those who are being [xref]b[/xref]sanctified are all [note]2[/note]of One, for which cause He is not ashamed to call them [xref]c[/xref]brothers,</text>
        <note num="1">He who sanctifies is Christ as the firstborn Son of God, and those who are being sanctified are the believers of Christ as the many sons of God. Both the firstborn Son and the many sons of God are born of the same Father God in resurrection ([link]Acts 13:33[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:3[/link]) and have the same divine life and nature. Hence, He is not ashamed to call them brothers.</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., out of. The Sanctifier and the sanctified are all out of one source, one Father.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 13:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 10:10[/link], [link]14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]John 20:17[/link]; [link]Rom. 8:29[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Saying, [xref]a[/xref]"I will [note]1[/note]declare Your name to My brothers; in the midst of the [note]2[/note]church [note]3[/note]I will sing hymns of praise to You."</text>
        <note num="1">The firstborn Son declared the Father's name to His brothers after He resurrected from the dead, when He met with the Father's many sons ([link]John 20:17[/link], [link]19-23[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">The church is mentioned only twice in this book, here and in [link]12:23[/link]. Here it is referred to as a corporate composition of the many brothers of the firstborn Son of God.</note>
        <note num="3">This is the firstborn Son's praising of the Father within the Father's many sons in the church meetings. When we, the many sons of God, meet as the church and praise the Father, the firstborn Son praises the Father in our praising. It is not that He praises the Father apart from us and alone; rather, He praises within us and with us through our praising. In our singing He sings hymns of praise to the Father. If then we do not sing, how can He sing? The more we sing to the Father, the more we enjoy His presence, His moving, His anointing, and His life-imparting within us. Thus we will grow in Him and be brought into His glorification above all.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 22:22[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And again, [xref]a[/xref]"I will trust in Him." And again, [xref]b[/xref]"Behold, I and the children whom God has given to Me."</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 18:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Isa. 8:18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Since therefore the children have shared in [xref]a[/xref]blood and flesh, He also Himself in like manner [xref]b[/xref]partook of the same, that through [xref]c[/xref]death He might [note]1[/note][xref]d[/xref]destroy him who has the might of [xref]e[/xref]death, that is, the [xref]f[/xref]devil,</text>
        <note num="1">Or, bring to nought, make of none effect, do away with, abolish, annul, discard. After the devil, the serpent, seduced man into the fall, God promised that the seed of woman would come to bruise the head of the serpent ([link]Gen. 3:15[/link]). In the fullness of the time the Son of God came to become flesh ([link]John 1:14[/link]; [link]Rom. 8:3[/link]) by being born of a virgin ([link]Gal. 4:4[/link]), that He might destroy the devil in man's flesh through His death in the flesh on the cross. (See notes [link]14[sup]1[/sup] in John 3[/link], [link]31[sup]1[/sup] in John 12[/link], and [link]3[sup]3[/sup] in Rom. 8[/link].) This was to abolish Satan, to bring him to nought. Hallelujah, Satan has been abolished and done away with!</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Matt. 16:17[/link]; [link]Eph. 6:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]John 1:14[/link]; [link]Rom. 8:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]John 12:31[/link], [link]33[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Gen. 3:15[/link]; [link]1 John 3:8[/link]; cf. [link]John 3:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Rom. 5:14[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 15:55-56[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 1:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]Rev. 12:9[/link]; [link]20:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And might [note]1[/note]release those who because of the fear of death through all their life were held in slavery.</text>
        <note num="1">Since the Lord destroyed the devil, who has the might of death, we who were held in slavery through the fear of death have been released by Him. Death reigned over us ([link]Rom. 5:14[/link]), and we were under its slavery, continually fearing death. Since the Lord destroyed the devil and nullified death ([link]2 Tim. 1:10[/link]), we now have no more fear of death and are released from its slavery.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>For assuredly [i]it is[/i] not to angels [i]that[/i] He [note]1[/note]gives help, but He [note]1[/note]gives help to the seed of Abraham.</text>
        <note num="1">Jesus has rendered us &amp;#8212; human beings, not the angels &amp;#8212; help to succor us, to release us from the slavery of death under the devil's might, which is in our nature. He did this by partaking of our nature, in which the devil dwells, and then annulling it on the cross through His all-inclusive death.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Hence He should have been [note]1[/note]made [xref]a[/xref]like His brothers in all things that He might become a merciful and faithful [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]High Priest in the [note]3[/note]things [xref]c[/xref]pertaining to God, to make [note]4[/note][xref]d[/xref]propitiation for the sins of the people.</text>
        <note num="1">The Son of God was made like us, His brothers, in that He partook of blood and flesh ([link]v. 14[/link]). This was done for two purposes, one negative and the other positive. The negative purpose was to destroy for us the devil, who is in the flesh. The positive purpose is to be our merciful and faithful High Priest who has the human nature, that He may sympathize with us in all things.</note>
        <note num="2">As the High Priest, Christ ministers God Himself and the riches of the divine life to us. As the God-man, He is more than fully qualified to be our High Priest. Here, [i]merciful[/i] corresponds with His being a man; [i]faithful[/i] corresponds with His being God.</note>
        <note num="3">Lit., things toward God.</note>
        <note num="4">Jesus made propitiation for our sins, thereby satisfying the demand of God's righteousness and appeasing the relationship between God and us, that God may be peacefully gracious to us. See note [link]25[sup]2[/sup] in Rom. 3[/link]. Cf. [link]Luke 18:13[/link] and note 1.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Phil. 2:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 3:1[/link]; [link]4:14[/link]; [link]5:5[/link], [link]10[/link]; [link]6:20[/link]; [link]7:26[/link], [link]28[/link]; [link]8:1[/link], [link]3[/link]; [link]10:21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 5:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Rom. 3:25[/link]; [link]1 John 2:2[/link]; [link]4:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>For being [xref]a[/xref]tempted in that which He Himself has suffered, He is able to help those who are being tempted.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 4:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Therefore, [note]1[/note]holy brothers, [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]partakers of a [note]3[/note]heavenly [xref]b[/xref]calling, consider the [note]4[/note][xref]c[/xref]Apostle and [xref]d[/xref]High Priest of our confession, Jesus,</text>
        <note num="1">To be holy is to be separated to God for a definite purpose. (See note [link]2[sup]3[/sup] in Rom. 1[/link].) Here, by calling the receivers of the book "holy brothers," the writer intended to remind them that they should not remain common in Judaism but should be separated to God for His purpose.</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]14[sup]1[/sup][/link].</note>
        <note num="3">The concept of this book is focused on the heavenly nature of the positive things. First, it points out to us that Christ today is sitting in the heavens ([link]1:3[/link]). He entered into the heavens ([link]9:24[/link]). He passed through the heavens ([link]4:14[/link]) and became higher than the heavens ([link]7:26[/link]). Then this book unfolds to us the heavenly calling ([link]v. 1[/link]), the heavenly gift ([link]6:4[/link]), the heavenly things ([link]8:5[/link]), the heavenly country ([link]11:16[/link]), and the heavenly Jerusalem ([link]12:22[/link]). Also, it tells us that we are enrolled in the heavens ([link]12:23[/link]) and that God warns us today from the heavens ([link]12:25[/link]). All the things in the Old Testament that were held by Judaism were of an earthly nature. In this book the writer's intention was to show the Hebrew Christians the contrast between the heavenly nature of the New Testament and the earthly nature of the Old Testament that they might forsake the earthly things and attach themselves to the heavenly.</note>
        <note num="4">The Apostle is the One who was sent to us from God and with God ([link]John 6:46[/link]; [link]8:16[/link], [link]29[/link]). The High Priest is the One who went back to God from us and with us ([link]Eph. 2:6[/link]). As the Apostle, Christ came to us with God to share God with us that we may partake of His divine life, nature, and fullness. As the High Priest, Christ went to God with us to present us to God that we and all our case may be fully cared for by Him. As the Apostle, He is typified by Moses, who came from God to serve the house of God ([link]vv. 2-6[/link]), and as the High Priest, He is typified by Aaron, who went to God with the house of Israel and their cases ([link]4:14-7:28[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 6:4[/link]; [link]12:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Cor. 1:9[/link]; [link]Phil. 3:14[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:18[/link]; [link]4:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Acts 3:26[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 2:17[/link]; [link]4:14[/link]; [link]7:26[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Who was faithful to Him who constituted Him, as also [xref]a[/xref]Moses was in all His [xref]b[/xref]house.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Num. 12:7[/link]; [link]Heb. 3:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Lev. 22:18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>For He has been counted worthy of more [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]glory than Moses, by as much as He who [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]built the house has more [note]1[/note]honor than [note]3[/note]the house.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]9[sup]2[/sup] in ch. 2[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Moses had the human nature, which is fit for God's building, but he did not have the divine nature, which is suitable for being the builder. In contrast, Christ in His humanity is the good material for God's building (the foundation stone &amp;#8212; [link]Isa. 28:16[/link]; the cornerstone &amp;#8212; [link]Matt. 21:42[/link]; [link]Acts 4:11[/link]; the topstone &amp;#8212; [link]Zech. 4:7[/link]; and the living stone that produces us as living stones &amp;#8212; [link]1 Pet. 2:4-5[/link]). Moreover, in His divinity He is the Builder.</note>
        <note num="3">Lit., it.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 2:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Zech. 6:12-13[/link]; [link]Matt. 16:18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>For every house is built by someone, but He who built all things is God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And [xref]a[/xref]Moses was faithful in all His house as a [note]1[/note]servant, for a [note]2[/note]testimony of the things to be spoken later;</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Servant[/i] here is a designation that implies dignity and freedom.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, prefigure; a type of the real, typical, and genuine Apostle sent from God.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 3:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>But Christ [i]was faithful[/i] as a Son over His house, whose [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]house we are if indeed we hold fast the boldness and the boast of [xref]b[/xref]hope [xref]c[/xref]firm to the end.</text>
        <note num="1">In Old Testament times the house of God was the house of Israel ([link]Lev. 22:18[/link]; [link]Num. 12:7[/link]), symbolized by the tabernacle or the temple, which was in Israel's midst ([link]Exo. 25:8[/link]; [link]Ezek. 37:26-27[/link]). Today, the house of God is actually the church ([link]1 Tim. 3:15[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 4:17[/link]). The children of Israel, as people of God, are a type of us, the New Testament believers ([link]1 Cor. 9:24-10:11[/link]). Their entire history is a prefigure of the church.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 3:15[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 4:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 6:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 3:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Therefore, even as the Holy [xref]a[/xref]Spirit says, [xref]b[/xref]"Today if you hear His voice,</text>
        <note num="1">This word connects the house of God in [link]v. 6[/link] with the Sabbath rest in [link]4:9[/link], indicating that these two are the same. The house of God is our church life today, our Sabbath rest.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rev. 2:7[/link], [link]11[/link], [link]17[/link], [link]29[/link]; [link]3:6[/link], [link]13[/link], [link]22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]vv. 7-11[/link]; [link]Psa. 95:7-11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Do not harden your hearts as in the provocation, in the day of trial in the wilderness,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Where your fathers [xref]a[/xref]tried [i]Me[/i] by testing [i]Me[/i] and saw My works for forty years.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 17:2[/link], [link]7[/link]; [link]Deut. 6:16[/link]; [link]Psa. 78:18[/link], [link]41[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Therefore I was [xref]a[/xref]displeased with this [xref]b[/xref]generation, and I said, They always [note]1[/note]go astray in their heart, and they have not known My [note]2[/note]ways;</text>
        <note num="1">Or, err, are deceived.</note>
        <note num="2">God's ways are different from His acts. His acts are His activities; His ways are the principles by which He acts. The children of Israel knew only His acts, but Moses knew His ways ([link]Psa. 103:7[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 3:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. [link]Acts 2:40[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>As I swore in My wrath, [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]They shall not enter into My rest!"</text>
        <note num="1">The Hebrew is idiomatic and conveys a strong negative. So also in [link]4:3[/link], [link]5[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 4:3[/link], [link]5[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Beware, brothers, lest perhaps there be in any one of you an evil heart of unbelief in [note]1[/note]falling away from the [xref]a[/xref]living God.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, turning away, deserting, departing, standing aloof.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 9:14[/link]; [link]10:31[/link]; [link]12:22[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 3:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>But [xref]a[/xref]exhort one another each day, as long as it is called "today," lest any one of you be hardened by the [xref]b[/xref]deceitfulness of sin &amp;#8212;</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 10:25[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 7:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>For we have become [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]partners of Christ, if indeed we hold fast the beginning of the assurance [xref]b[/xref]firm to the end &amp;#8212;</text>
        <note num="1">In Greek, the same word as that for [i]partakers[/i] in [link]3:1[/link]; [link]6:4[/link]; and [link]12:8[/link]. In those three places the meaning is that we share in the heavenly calling, the Holy Spirit, and the discipline; thus, the word is rendered [i]partakers.[/i] Here and in [link]1:9[/link] the meaning is that we share with Christ; hence, the word is rendered [i]partners.[/i] We are partakers of heavenly, holy, and spiritual things, sharing in the heavenly calling, the Holy Spirit, and the spiritual discipline. We are partners of Christ, sharing with Him the spiritual anointing ([link]1:9[/link]), as the members share the Spirit with the Head, and sharing with Him the heavenly rest, as Caleb shared with Joshua the rest of the good land ([link]Num. 14:30[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 1:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 3:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>While it is said, [xref]a[/xref]"Today if you hear His voice, do not harden your hearts as in the provocation."</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 95:7[/link], [link]8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>For who [xref]a[/xref]provoked [i]Him[/i] when they heard? Indeed was it [xref]b[/xref]not all who came out of Egypt by [note]1[/note]Moses?</text>
        <note num="1">Moses brought the children of Israel out of Egypt, but he did not bring them into the good land of Canaan. It was his successor, Joshua, who did this ([link]4:8[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Deut. 9:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Num. 26:64[/link], [link]65[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 10:5[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And with whom was He [xref]a[/xref]displeased for forty years? Was it not with those who sinned, whose carcasses [xref]b[/xref]fell in the wilderness?</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 3:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Num. 14:29[/link], [link]32[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 10:8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And to whom did He swear that they should [xref]a[/xref]not enter into His rest, except to the [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]disobedient?</text>
        <note num="1">Or, unpersuadable, obstinate, unbelieving.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Num. 14:30[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 4:6[/link], [link]11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And we see that they were not able to enter in because of unbelief.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Let us fear therefore, lest, a promise being left of entering into His [note]1[/note]rest, any one of you may [note]2[/note]seem to have [note]3[/note]come short [i]of it.[/i]</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]9[sup]1[/sup][/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Or, think that he has come too late for it.</note>
        <note num="3">See note [link]11[sup]1[/sup][/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>For indeed we have had the good news announced to us, even as they also; but the word heard did not profit them, [note]1[/note]not being mixed together with faith in those who heard.</text>
        <note num="1">Only the Codex Sinaiticus can be rendered in this way. All other ancient MSS read, they [referring to those who heard the word] not being mixed together by faith with those who heard [referring to Caleb and Joshua].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>For we who have believed enter into the rest, even as He has said, [xref]a[/xref]"As I swore in My wrath, They shall not enter into My rest!" although the works [i]of creation[/i] were completed from the [xref]b[/xref]foundation of the world.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 95:11[/link]; [link]Heb. 3:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Zech. 12:1[/link]; [link]Rev. 13:8[/link]; cf. [link]Eph. 1:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>For He has spoken somewhere concerning the seventh day thus, [xref]a[/xref]"And God rested on the seventh day from all His works."</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 2:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And in this place again, [xref]a[/xref]"They shall not enter into My rest!"</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 95:11[/link]; [link]Heb. 3:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Since therefore it remains that some should enter into it and those who formerly had the good news announced [i]to them[/i] did not enter because of [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]disobedience,</text>
        <note num="1">Or, obstinacy, rebellion, stubbornness, unbelief.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 3:18[/link]; [link]4:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>He again designates a certain day, today, saying in David after so long a time, even as He has said before, [xref]a[/xref]"Today, if you hear His voice, do not harden your hearts."</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 95:7-8[/link]; [link]Heb. 3:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>For if [note]1[/note]Joshua had brought them into rest, He would not have spoken concerning [note]2[/note]another day after these things.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Joshua,[/i] which means [i]Jehovah the Savior[/i] or [i]the salvation of Jehovah[/i] ([link]Num. 13:16[/link]), is a Hebrew name, of which the equivalent in Greek is [i]Jesus.[/i] Hence, Joshua was a type of the Lord Jesus, who brought the people of God into rest.</note>
        <note num="2">This "another day" is "today" ([link]3:7[/link], [link]13[/link], [link]15[/link]; [link]4:7[/link]). This is the promised Sabbath rest that remains for us ([link]v. 9[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>So then there remains a [note]1[/note]Sabbath rest for the people of God.</text>
        <note num="1">This Sabbath rest is Christ as our rest, typified by the good land of Canaan ([link]Deut. 12:9[/link]; [link]Heb. 4:8[/link]). Christ is rest to the saints in three stages: (1) in the church age, as the heavenly Christ, the One who rests from His work and sits on the right hand of God in the heavens, He is the rest to us in our spirit ([link]Matt. 11:28-29[/link]); (2) in the millennial kingdom, after Satan is removed from this earth ([link]Rev. 20:1-3[/link]), Christ with the kingdom will be the rest in a fuller way to the overcoming saints, who will be His co-kings ([link]Rev. 20:4[/link], [link]6[/link]), sharing and enjoying His rest; (3) in the new heaven and new earth, after all the enemies, including death, the last enemy, have been made subject to Him ([link]1 Cor. 15:24-27[/link]), Christ, as the all-conquering One, will be the rest in the fullest way to all God's redeemed for eternity. But the Sabbath rest mentioned here and typified by the rest of the good land of Canaan covers only the first two stages of Christ's being our rest; it does not include the third stage. The rest in the first two stages is a prize to His diligent seekers, who not only are redeemed but also have enjoyed Him in a full way, thus becoming the overcomers; whereas the rest in the third stage is not a prize but the full portion allotted to all the redeemed ones. Therefore, in the first two stages, and especially in the second, Christ as our rest is the Sabbath rest mentioned here, the rest that remains for us to seek after and enter into diligently. It is in the second stage of His being our rest that Christ will take possession of the whole earth as His inheritance ([link]Psa. 2:8[/link]; [link]Heb. 2:5-6[/link]), making it His kingdom for a thousand years ([link]Rev. 11:15[/link]). All His overcoming followers who seek and enjoy Him as their rest in the first stage will participate in His reign in the millennium ([link]Rev. 20:4[/link], [link]6[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 2:12[/link]). Moreover, they will inherit the earth ([link]Matt. 5:5[/link]; [link]Psa. 37:11[/link]), some having authority over ten cities, some over five ([link]Luke 19:17[/link], [link]19[/link]), and will partake of the joy of their Lord ([link]Matt. 25:21[/link], [link]23[/link]). That will be the kingdom rest, which is typified by the rest of entering into the good land of Canaan. The rest of the good land was the goal of all the children of Israel, who had been redeemed and delivered from Egypt; likewise, the rest of the coming kingdom is the goal of the New Testament believers, who have been redeemed and saved from the world. We are now all on the way toward this goal.[br][br]God's full salvation, which He intended for the children of Israel, included redemption through the passover lamb, the exodus from Egypt, feeding on the heavenly manna, having their thirst quenched by the living water from the cleft rock, and partaking of the good land of Canaan. All the children of Israel shared in the passover lamb, the heavenly manna, and the living water, but only Joshua and Caleb, out of those who shared the exodus from Egypt, entered into the good land and partook of it; all the rest fell in the wilderness ([link]Num. 14:30[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 10:1-11[/link]). Though all were redeemed, only the two overcomers, Joshua and Caleb, received the prize of the good land.[br][br]The passover lamb, the heavenly manna, the living water, and the good land of Canaan are all types of different aspects of Christ. According to what is depicted by the experiences of the children of Israel, not all believers who have been redeemed through Christ will partake of Christ as a prize, as their rest, their satisfaction, in both the church age and the coming kingdom; only those who, after being redeemed, seek Christ diligently will partake of Him in such a way. This is why the apostle Paul, though fully redeemed, was still pursuing toward the goal that he might gain Christ as the prize ([link]Phil. 3:10-14[/link]). In [link]Phil. 3[/link] Paul told us that he had been in Judaism but that for Christ's sake he had given it up ([link]Phil. 3:4-9[/link]). Here, in this book, the writer held the same concept, encouraging the Hebrew believers to forsake Judaism and press toward Christ so that they would not miss the prize.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>For he who has entered into His rest has himself also rested from his works, as [xref]a[/xref]God did from His own.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 2:2[/link]; [link]Heb. 4:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Let us therefore be diligent to enter into that rest lest anyone [note]1[/note]fall [note]2[/note]after the same example of [note]3[/note][xref]a[/xref]disobedience.</text>
        <note num="1">Since the rest that is covered in this portion of the word is the all-inclusive Christ, to fall from it is to fall from Christ, to be brought to nought from Christ ([link]Gal. 5:4[/link]). In Galatians the danger was that the Galatian believers would drift into the bondage of law from the freedom of grace ([link]Gal. 5:1-4[/link]). Paul advised them to stand fast in the freedom of grace, that is, not to be brought to nought from Christ. Here, in this book, the danger was that the Hebrew believers would not forsake their old religion, which was according to the law, and press on into the enjoyment of Christ as their rest. If they continued to stagger in their old religion, i.e., in Judaism, they would come short of Christ, who was their rest. The writer of this book earnestly encouraged them, as Christ's partners, to press on with Christ and enter into the rest, that they, as His partakers, might enjoy Christ as their rest.</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., in.</note>
        <note num="3">See note [link]6[sup]1[/sup][/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 3:18[/link]; [link]4:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>For the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]word of God is [xref]b[/xref]living and operative and sharper than any two-edged [xref]c[/xref]sword, and piercing even to the dividing of [note]2[/note][xref]d[/xref]soul and [xref]e[/xref]spirit and of joints and marrow, and able to discern the [note]3[/note]thoughts and intentions of the heart.</text>
        <note num="1">The Greek word denotes the constant word of God. Here it refers to the word in [link]3:7-4:11[/link] that is quoted from the Old Testament (as indicated by the word [i]for[/i] at the beginning of this verse). That word is living, operative, and sharper than a two-edged sword.</note>
        <note num="2">According to the Bible, man is a tripartite being &amp;#8212; spirit, soul, and body ([link]1 Thes. 5:23[/link]). Here, in this verse, are the joints and marrow &amp;#8212; which are parts of the body &amp;#8212; and the soul and spirit.[br][br]The foregoing verses describe the children of Israel as falling away from entering into the rest of the good land. With them there were three places: (1) Egypt, from which they were delivered; (2) the wilderness, in which they wandered; and (3) Canaan, into which they entered. Their history in these three places signifies the three stages of their participation in God's full salvation. This is a type of us, the New Testament believers, in our participation in the full salvation of God. In the first stage we receive Christ and are redeemed and delivered from the world. In the second stage we become wanderers in following the Lord; our wandering always takes place in our soul. In the third stage we partake of and enjoy Christ in a full way; this is experienced in our spirit. When we pursue the pleasures of material and sinful things, we are in the world, typified by Egypt. When we wander in our soul, we are in the wilderness. When we enjoy Christ in our spirit, we are in Canaan. When the Israelites were wandering in the wilderness, they were always murmuring, reasoning, and chiding. This surely took place in their soul, not in their spirit. But Caleb and Joshua believed in the word of God, obeyed the Lord, and pressed toward the goal. This surely took place not in their soul but in their spirit. At that time the receivers of this book, the Hebrew believers, were wondering what they should do with their old Hebrew religion. This wondering in their mind was a wandering in their soul, not an experience of Christ in their spirit. So the writer of this book said that the word of God, i.e., what was quoted from the Old Testament, could pierce into their wondering like a sharp two-edged sword and divide their soul from their spirit. As the marrow is concealed deep in the joints, so the spirit is deep in the soul. The dividing of the marrow from the joints requires mainly the breaking of the joints. In the same principle, the dividing of the spirit from the soul requires the breaking of the soul. The Hebrew believers' soul, with its wondering mind, its doubting concerning God's way of salvation, and its considering of its own interests, had to be broken by the living, operative, and piercing word of God that their spirit might be divided from their soul.[br][br]Our soul is our very self ([link]Matt. 16:25[/link]; cf. [link]Luke 9:25[/link]). In following the Lord we must deny our soul, our very self ([link]Matt. 16:24[/link]; [link]Luke 9:23[/link]). Our spirit is the deepest part of our being, a spiritual organ with which we contact God ([link]John 4:24[/link]; [link]Rom. 1:9[/link]). It is in our spirit that we are regenerated ([link]John 3:6[/link]). It is in our spirit that the Holy Spirit dwells and works ([link]Rom. 8:16[/link]). It is in our spirit that we enjoy Christ and His grace ([link]2 Tim. 4:22[/link]; [link]Gal. 6:18[/link]). Hence, the writer of this book advised the Hebrew believers not to stagger in the wandering of their soul, which soul they had to deny, but to press on into their spirit to partake of and enjoy the heavenly Christ that they might participate in the kingdom rest of His reign in the millennium. If they staggered in the wandering of their soul, they would miss God's goal and suffer the loss of the full enjoyment of Christ and the kingdom rest.</note>
        <note num="3">Our spirit is the organ with which we contact God ([link]John 4:24[/link]), while our heart is the organ with which we love God ([link]Mark 12:30[/link]). Our spirit contacts, receives, contains, and experiences God. However, this requires that our heart love God first. Our soul is of three parts &amp;#8212; mind, will, and emotion; and our spirit too is of three parts &amp;#8212; conscience, fellowship, and intuition. Our heart is not separate from our soul and spirit but is a composition of all the parts of our soul, plus the conscience, a part of our spirit. Hence, in our heart is the mind, with the thoughts, and the will, with the intentions. The thoughts affect the intentions, and the intentions carry out the thoughts. The living word of God is able to discern the thoughts in our mind and the intentions in our will. What was quoted from the word of God by the writer in the foregoing verses was able to expose what and where the thoughts and intentions of the Hebrew believers were while they were staggering in the process of their salvation.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Pet. 1:23[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 7:38[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Eph. 6:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Thes. 5:23[/link]; [link]Luke 1:46-47[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Zech. 12:1[/link]; [link]Job 32:8[/link]; [link]Prov. 20:27[/link]; [link]John 3:6[/link]; [link]4:24[/link]; [link]Rom. 8:16[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 5:4[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 4:22[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 3:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And there is no creature that is not manifest before Him, but all things are naked and laid bare to the eyes of Him to whom we are [i]to give[/i] our account.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Having therefore a [note]1[/note]great [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]High Priest who has [note]3[/note]passed through the [xref]b[/xref]heavens, Jesus, the [xref]c[/xref]Son of God, let us hold fast the [note]4[/note][xref]d[/xref]confession.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., excellent, wonderful, glorious, and most honorable. Christ is great in His person ([link]1:5[/link], [link]8[/link]; [link]2:6[/link]), work ([link]1:3[/link]; [link]2:17[/link], [link]9[/link], [link]14-15[/link], [link]10[/link]; [link]3:5-6[/link]; [link]4:8-9[/link]; [link]Acts 2:24[/link], [link]27[/link]), and attainment ([link]6:20[/link]; [link]9:24[/link]; [link]2:9[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">The Lord Jesus first was sent from God to us through incarnation ([link]2:14[/link]) to be our Apostle ([link]3:1[/link]), our Author, our Leader ([link]2:10[/link]), the One superior to Moses ([link]3:3[/link]), and our real Joshua ([link]4:8[/link]) to bring us, His partners ([link]1:9[/link]; [link]3:14[/link]), into glory and rest ([link]2:10[/link]; [link]4:11[/link]). He then went back from us to God through resurrection and ascension ([link]5:5-6[/link]) to be our High Priest to bear us in the presence of God and to care for all our needs ([link]2:17-18[/link]; [link]4:15[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">Having had the principalities and powers stripped off ([link]Col. 2:15[/link]), having risen from Hades ([link]Acts 2:24[/link], [link]27[/link]), and having passed through the heavens, our High Priest is now sitting on the throne at the right hand of God.</note>
        <note num="4">Referring to the faith.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 2:17[/link]; [link]7:26[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Eph. 4:10[/link]; [link]Heb. 8:1[/link]; [link]9:24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 7:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 3:1[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>For we do not have a High Priest who cannot be touched with the feeling of our weaknesses, but One who has been [xref]a[/xref]tempted in all respects like [i]us, yet[/i] [xref]b[/xref]without sin.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 2:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 7:26[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 5:21[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Let us therefore [xref]a[/xref]come forward with boldness to the [note]1[/note]throne of grace that we may receive [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]mercy and find [xref]c[/xref]grace for timely help.</text>
        <note num="1">Undoubtedly, the throne mentioned here is the throne of God, which is in heaven ([link]Rev. 4:2[/link]). The throne of God is the throne of authority toward all the universe ([link]Dan. 7:9[/link]; [link]Rev. 5:1[/link]). But toward us, the believers, it becomes the throne of grace, signified by the expiation cover (the mercy seat) within the Holy of Holies ([link]Exo. 25:17[/link], [link]21[/link]). This throne is the throne of both God and the Lamb ([link]Rev. 22:1[/link]). How can we come to the throne of God and the Lamb, Christ, in heaven while we still live on earth? The secret is our spirit, referred to in [link]v. 12[/link]. The very Christ who is sitting on the throne in heaven ([link]Rom. 8:34[/link]) is also now in us ([link]Rom. 8:10[/link]), that is, in our spirit ([link]2 Tim. 4:22[/link]), where the habitation of God is ([link]Eph. 2:22[/link]). At Bethel, the house of God, the habitation of God, which is the gate of heaven, Christ is the ladder that joins earth to heaven and brings heaven to earth ([link]Gen. 28:12-17[/link]; [link]John 1:51[/link]). Since today our spirit is the place of God's habitation, it is now the gate of heaven, where Christ is the ladder that joins us, the people on earth, to heaven, and brings heaven to us. Hence, whenever we turn to our spirit, we enter through the gate of heaven and touch the throne of grace in heaven through Christ as the heavenly ladder.</note>
        <note num="2">Both God's mercy and God's grace are the expression of His love. When we are in a pitiful condition, first God's mercy reaches us and brings us into a situation in which He is able to favor us with His grace. [link]Luke 15:20-24[/link] tells us that when the father saw the prodigal son returning, he had compassion on him. That was mercy, which expressed the father's love. Then the father clothed him with the best robe and fed him with the fattened calf. That was grace, which again manifested the father's love. God's mercy reaches farther and bridges the gap between us and God's grace.[br][br]God's mercy and grace are always available to us. However, we need to receive and find them by exercising our spirit to come to the throne of grace and contact our High Priest, who is touched with the feeling of all our weaknesses. By this word the writer of this book encouraged the wearied Hebrew believers to receive mercy and find grace for timely help, that they might be set upright ([link]12:12[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 10:22[/link]; [link]7:25[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 9:15[/link], [link]18[/link], [link]23[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]John 1:14[/link], [link]16[/link], [link]17[/link]; [link]Rom. 5:2[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 12:9[/link]; [link]13:14[/link]; [link]Gal. 6:18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="5">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>For every high priest, being taken from among men, is [xref]a[/xref]established on behalf of men in the things [xref]b[/xref]pertaining to God that he may [xref]c[/xref]offer both [note]1[/note]gifts and [note]1[/note]sacrifices for sins.</text>
        <note num="1">Gifts are for God's pleasure; sacrifices are for our sins.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 7:28[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 2:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 7:27[/link]; [link]8:3[/link]; [link]10:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>He is [xref]a[/xref]able to exercise [note]1[/note]compassion toward the [xref]b[/xref]ignorant and [xref]c[/xref]erring since he also is encompassed with [xref]d[/xref]weakness;</text>
        <note num="1">The Greek here implies a feeling toward the ignorant and erring that is neither too severe nor too tolerant. To exercise compassion is to be moderate or tender in judging their situation. The thought in this verse is a continuation of the thought in [link]4:15[/link]. Though not encompassed with weakness like the high priest taken from among men, Christ as our High Priest was tempted in all respects like us. Hence, being touched with the feeling of our weaknesses, He is able to exercise compassion toward us, the ignorant and erring ones.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 2:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]James 5:19[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 2:25[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 4:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And because of it, he ought, even as [xref]a[/xref]for the people, so also for himself, to offer for sins.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 7:27[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And [xref]a[/xref]no one takes the honor upon himself, but [i]only[/i] as he is called by God, just as [xref]b[/xref]Aaron also was.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Num. 18:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Exo. 28:1[/link]; [link]1 Chron. 23:13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>So also Christ did not [note]1[/note]glorify Himself in becoming a [xref]a[/xref]High Priest, but [i]it was[/i] He who said to Him, [xref]b[/xref]"You are My Son; this day have I [note]2[/note]begotten You";</text>
        <note num="1">In this verse the word [i]glorify[/i] replaces [i]honor[/i] used in the foregoing verse. With the high priest taken from among men, there is only honor, a matter of position. With Christ as the High Priest, there is not only honor but also glory, not only the preciousness of His position but also the splendor of His person. See note [link]9[sup]2[/sup] in ch. 2[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">This refers to Christ's resurrection ([link]Acts 13:33[/link]), which qualifies Him to be our High Priest. For Christ to be our High Priest, He had to partake of our humanity, as mentioned in [link]2:14-18[/link], and enter with this humanity into resurrection. In His humanity He can be touched with the feeling of our weaknesses and be merciful to us ([link]4:15[/link]; [link]2:17[/link]). In resurrection, in His divinity He can do everything for us and be faithful to us ([link]7:24-25[/link]; [link]2:17[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 2:17[/link]; [link]4:15[/link]; [link]5:10[/link]; [link]7:26[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 1:5[/link]; [link]Psa. 2:7[/link]; [link]Acts 13:33[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Even as also in another place He says, [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]"You are a Priest forever according to the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]order of Melchizedek."</text>
        <note num="1">This refers to the ascension and enthronement of Christ ([link]Psa. 110:1-4[/link]), which are in addition to His resurrection and further qualify Him to be our High Priest ([link]7:26[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">The order of Melchizedek is higher than the order of Aaron. The order of Aaron was for the priesthood that was only in humanity, whereas the order of Melchizedek is for the priesthood that is in both humanity and divinity. This is fully delineated in [link]ch. 7[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 110:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 5:10[/link]; [link]6:20[/link]; [link]7:11[/link], [link]17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>This One, in the days of His [xref]a[/xref]flesh, having offered up both [xref]b[/xref]petitions and supplications with strong crying and tears to Him who was able to save Him [note]1[/note]out of death and having been heard because of [i]His[/i] piety,</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Out of death[/i] here does not mean that Christ did not enter into death and suffer death. It means that He resurrected out of death. Before He died, Christ prayed for this, and God answered by raising Him from the dead.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]John 1:14[/link]; [link]Heb. 2:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Matt. 26:39[/link], [link]42[/link], [link]44[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Even though He was a Son, learned [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]obedience from the things which He [xref]b[/xref]suffered.</text>
        <note num="1">God ordained that Christ should die, and Christ obeyed ([link]Phil. 2:8[/link]). He learned this obedience through the suffering of death.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Phil. 2:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Luke 24:26[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And having been [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]perfected, He became to all those who obey Him the [note]2[/note]source of [note]3[/note]eternal [xref]b[/xref]salvation,</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]10[sup]5[/sup] in ch. 2[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word implies the thought of author and cause.</note>
        <note num="3">Not everlasting salvation but eternal salvation, of which all the effects, benefits, and issues are of an eternal nature, transcending the conditions and limitations of time.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 2:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 2:3[/link], [link]10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Being [note]1[/note]addressed by God as a [xref]a[/xref]High Priest according to the [xref]b[/xref]order of Melchizedek;</text>
        <note num="1">This word also conveys the sense of [i]designated, hailed.[/i]</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 5:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 5:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Concerning whom we have much to say that is also difficult to interpret since you have become dull of hearing.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>For when because of the time you ought to be teachers, you have need again for someone to teach you what the [note]1[/note]rudiments of the [xref]a[/xref]beginning of the [note]2[/note]oracles of God are and have become those who have need of [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]milk and not of solid [xref]c[/xref]food.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, primary elements.</note>
        <note num="2">I.e., divine utterances.</note>
        <note num="3">Though this verse mentions [i]teachers[/i] and [i]teach,[/i] it likens the word of God to milk and solid food, which are for nourishment. This corresponds with the Lord's word in [link]Matt. 4:4[/link] and the prophet's word in [link]Jer. 15:16[/link]. Paul and Peter held this same concept concerning the divine word ([link]1 Cor. 3:2[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 2:2[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 6:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Cor. 3:2[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 2:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Matt. 4:4[/link]; [link]Jer. 15:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>For everyone who partakes of [note]1[/note]milk is inexperienced in the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]word of righteousness, for he is an [xref]b[/xref]infant;</text>
        <note num="1">Milk here refers to the rudiments of the beginning of the oracles of God mentioned in [link]v. 12[/link], whereas the word of righteousness refers to solid food. The good word mentioned in [link]6:5[/link] is the word of the beginning of Christ ([link]6:1[/link]). But the word of righteousness is deeper than the rudiments of the beginning of the oracles of God because it embodies the deeper thought of God's justice and righteousness in His dispensational and governmental dealings with His people. This word is more difficult to discriminate than the word of grace ([link]Acts 14:3[/link]; [link]20:32[/link]) and the word of life ([link]Phil. 2:16[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Heb. 6:1[/link], [link]5[/link]; [link]Acts 14:3[/link]; [link]20:32[/link]; [link]Phil. 2:16[/link][br/]See note 13[sup]1[/sup].</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Cor. 3:1[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 2:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>But solid food is for the [xref]a[/xref]full-grown, who because of practice have their [note]1[/note]faculties exercised for discriminating between both [note]2[/note]good and evil.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, senses; implying powers of perception that depend not only on our mental capability but also on our spiritual apprehension.</note>
        <note num="2">[i]Good and evil[/i] here refers to what is superior in contrast to what is inferior, e.g., the superiority of Christ in contrast to the inferiority of the angels, Moses, and Aaron, or the superiority of the new covenant in contrast to the inferiority of the old covenant. According to the context of this verse, the discriminating mentioned here is similar to discriminating between different foods and has nothing to do with the moral nature of things.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 6:1[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 2:6[/link]; [link]Phil. 3:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="6">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Therefore leaving the [note]1[/note]word of the [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]beginning of Christ, let us [note]3[/note]be brought on to [note]4[/note][xref]b[/xref]maturity, not laying again a foundation of [xref]c[/xref]repentance from [xref]d[/xref]dead works and of [xref]e[/xref]faith in God,</text>
        <note num="1">Or, primary word. The word of the beginning of Christ refers to the six items mentioned in this verse and the next verse, items that constitute the foundation of the Christian life: (1) repentance from dead works, (2) faith in God, (3) the teaching of baptisms, (4) the laying on of hands, (5) the resurrection of the dead, and (6) eternal judgment. These six items form three pairs. The first item of each pair refers to our emergence from a negative situation, and the second speaks of our entering into the positive things. Repentance is a turning away from dead works; faith is the entry into God. Baptisms are separations from and terminations of the negative things; the laying on of hands is the identification and fellowship with the divine things. The resurrection of the dead is the emergence from death; eternal judgment is the entry into eternity and the eternal destiny.</note>
        <note num="2">The beginning of Christ includes not only the beginning of the believers' experience of Christ, e.g., the six items enumerated in the latter half of this verse and the next verse, but also the early ministry of Christ, i.e., all His work on earth, recorded in the four Gospels. All saved believers have already experienced, as had the Hebrew believers, the beginning of Christ; henceforth they must pursue unto perfection, unto maturity. The Lord intends to complete this perfecting in His later heavenly ministry, as revealed in this book.</note>
        <note num="3">In the experience of our spiritual life, there is always the Lord's doing, on the one side, and our pursuing in cooperation with Him, on the other side. The Lord wants to bring us on to maturity, but we still need to cooperate with Him by being brought on to perfection, to maturity.[br][br]The Lord wants to bring us on, but we must let Him do it. This is our willing cooperation with His gracious work. In order to be brought on to perfection, to maturity, we need to share with Christ in His attainments ([link]1:9[/link]; [link]3:14[/link]), to be diligent to enter into the remaining Sabbath rest ([link]4:9[/link], [link]11[/link]), to come forward to the throne of grace to receive mercy and find grace ([link]4:16[/link]), and to feed on the solid food to enjoy Christ as our High Priest according to the order of Melchizedek ([link]5:9-10[/link], [link]14[/link]).</note>
        <note num="4">Or, perfection.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 5:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 5:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Mark 1:15[/link]; [link]Acts 5:31[/link]; [link]20:21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 9:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Rom. 1:17[/link]; [link]Eph. 2:8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Of the teaching of [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]baptisms and of the [xref]b[/xref]laying on of hands, of the [xref]c[/xref]resurrection of the dead and of eternal [xref]d[/xref]judgment.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Baptisms,[/i] the same word in Greek as for [i]washings[/i] in [link]9:10[/link] and [i]dipping[/i] in [link]Mark 7:4[/link], refers to the washing of the utensils and vessels used for God's service in the tabernacle or temple ([link]Lev. 6:28[/link]) and also, probably, to the washing of the priests ([link]Exo. 30:18-21[/link]; [link]Lev. 16:4[/link]). This matter is, of course, related to the background of the Hebrew believers. However, it is the same in principle as the New Testament baptism &amp;#8212; both are the washing away and terminating of the negative things.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 9:10[/link]; [link]Lev. 6:27[/link]; [link]Mark 7:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 6:6[/link]; [link]8:17[/link]; [link]9:17[/link]; [link]13:3[/link]; [link]19:6[/link]; [link]28:8[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 4:14[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 1:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Matt. 22:31[/link]; [link]Acts 4:2[/link]; [link]23:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 9:27[/link]; [link]Rom. 2:5[/link]; [link]Rev. 20:12[/link], [link]13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And [note]1[/note]this we will do if God permits.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., we will do what is mentioned in [link]v. 1[/link]: be brought on to perfection, to maturity, not laying again the foundation.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>For it is [note]1[/note]impossible for those who have once been [xref]a[/xref]enlightened and have tasted of the [note]2[/note]heavenly [xref]b[/xref]gift and have become [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]partakers of the Holy [xref]d[/xref]Spirit</text>
        <note num="1">Those who have once been enlightened and have tasted of the heavenly gift and have become partakers of the Holy Spirit and have tasted the good word of God and the powers of the age to come have already laid the foundation, at the time they believed. If they fall away and turn back, there is no need for them to lay the foundation again ([link]v. 1[/link]); there is only the need to go on, to be brought on to perfection, to maturity. There is no need for them to repeat repentance, for it is impossible for them to renew themselves unto repentance. [link]Verse 1[/link] indicates that it is not needed; [link]v. 4[/link] says that it is not possible; and [link]vv. 7-8[/link] show that it is not right.</note>
        <note num="2">The heavenly gift here refers to God's giving of the heavenly things, such as His forgiveness, righteousness, divine life, peace, and joy, at the time we repented and believed in the Lord.</note>
        <note num="3">The Holy Spirit is what God in His gospel promised to give man ([link]Gal. 3:14[/link]). God called us from the heavens to the heavenly things that we might become partakers of His Holy Spirit and share in His Holy Spirit. It is by God's Holy Spirit that we can live a heavenly life on earth and partake of the divine holiness. As partakers of the Holy Spirit, we partake of God as our enjoyment. See note [link]14[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 3[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 10:32[/link]; [link]John 1:9[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 4:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 2:38[/link]; [link]Rom. 6:23[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 3:1[/link]; [link]12:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Cor. 1:22[/link]; [link]5:5[/link]; [link]Gal. 3:2[/link], [link]5[/link], [link]14[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:13[/link]; [link]1 John 3:24[/link]; [link]4:13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And have [xref]a[/xref]tasted the [xref]b[/xref]good [note]1[/note]word of God and the [note]2[/note]powers of the age [xref]c[/xref]to come,</text>
        <note num="1">The Greek word denotes the instant word of God. The good word of God here refers to the word of the beginning of Christ, which was mentioned in [link]v. 1[/link] and which was the milk the Hebrew believers tasted when they believed in the Lord. Now they had to go on to the deeper word, the word of righteousness ([link]5:13[/link]), which is concerned not mainly with God's redemption but with the way of His economy, and which was the solid food by which they could reach perfection, maturity ([link]v. 1[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">[i]Powers[/i] here refers to the divine power, and [i]the age to come[/i] refers to the age of the coming kingdom. The divine power of the coming kingdom restores, renews, and revives the things that have become old ([link]Matt. 19:28[/link]). At the time of their regeneration ([link]Titus 3:5[/link]) the believers all tasted this divine power and were restored, renewed, and revived.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Pet. 2:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 6:1[/link]; cf. [link]5:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 2:5[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And yet have [note]1[/note]fallen away, to renew [i]themselves[/i] again unto repentance, [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]crucifying again for themselves the Son of God and [note]2[/note]putting [i]Him[/i] to open shame.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Fallen away[/i] refers to the fact that the Hebrew Christians deviated from the pure Christian faith by returning to their old, traditional, Judaic religion. In principle, this could be applied to any Christians who fall away from the right track of God's way.</note>
        <note num="2">[i]Crucifying[/i] and [i]putting[/i] modify the predicate [i]renew.[/i] To renew unto repentance means to repeat the repentance that has been made already; this is not needed. To do this is to crucify again the Son of God and put Him to open shame.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Heb. 10:29[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>For the earth, which drinks the [note]1[/note]rain which often comes upon it and [note]2[/note]produces vegetation suitable to those for whose sake also it is cultivated, partakes of blessing from God.</text>
        <note num="1">The rain here refers back to the five categories of good things mentioned in [link]vv. 4-5[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">[i]Produces vegetation[/i] is an illustration of being brought on to perfection, to maturity ([link]v. 1[/link]). The believers, as the earth, are tilled for God's sake that they may bring forth Christ, as the vegetation, to perfection, to maturity. By bringing forth Christ they partake of blessing from God.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>But if it brings forth [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]thorns and thistles, it is [note]2[/note]disapproved and [note]3[/note]near a curse, whose end is to be [note]4[/note][xref]b[/xref]burned.</text>
        <note num="1">Strictly, the thorns and thistles here refer to the traditional things of the Hebrew believers' old religion.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, rejected, disqualified, counted worthless. The same word is used in [link]1 Cor. 9:27[/link]. If a believer would not be brought on to perfection, to maturity, but rather falls back to the old things, he will be disapproved, be counted worthless, by God.</note>
        <note num="3">Once saved, the believers can never be a real curse. However, if they do not go on to grow Christ but rather hold on to things that displease God, they are near the curse of suffering the punishment of God's governmental dealing. (This should be considered with the discipline or chastisement in [link]12:7-8[/link].) Being near a curse is absolutely different from the suffering of eternal perdition, which is the real curse.</note>
        <note num="4">The earth could never be burned, but what it brings forth could be burned. The believers could never be burned, but all they bring forth that is not according to God's economy will be burned. The believers are God's cultivated land. Whatever they grow as wood, grass, and stubble will be burned ([link]1 Cor. 3:9[/link], [link]12[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 3:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Cor. 3:13[/link], [link]15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>But we are persuaded of better things concerning you, beloved, and [note]1[/note]things which belong to [note]2[/note]salvation, though we speak thus.</text>
        <note num="1">To bring forth thorns and thistles ([link]v. 8[/link]) is not a thing that belongs to salvation. To give heed to the things that we have heard ([link]2:1[/link]), to be diligent to enter into the promised rest ([link]4:11[/link]), to come forward to the throne of grace ([link]4:16[/link]), and to be brought on to perfection, to maturity ([link]v. 1[/link]) are things that belong to salvation.</note>
        <note num="2">Salvation here refers to God's full salvation, the "so great a salvation" mentioned in [link]2:3[/link], including the saving mentioned in [link]7:25[/link], the salvation mentioned in [link]Phil. 1:19[/link] and [link]2:12[/link], and the salvation of the soul mentioned in [link]1 Pet. 1:9[/link]. To be so saved is to be saved from being near the curse of suffering the punishment of God's governmental dealing, mentioned in [link]v. 8[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>For God is not unrighteous, so as to forget your [xref]a[/xref]work and the love which you have shown toward His [xref]b[/xref]name in having [note]1[/note][xref]c[/xref]ministered to the saints and in ministering [i]still.[/i]</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to the ministering of material things to the needy saints.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Thes. 1:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Mark 9:41[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 13:16[/link]; [link]Rom. 12:13[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 8:4[/link]; [link]Phil. 4:15[/link], [link]16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>But we desire earnestly that each of you show the same diligence unto the full [xref]a[/xref]assurance of our [xref]b[/xref]hope [xref]c[/xref]until the end,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 3:14[/link]; [link]10:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 3:6[/link]; [link]6:18[/link]; [link]7:19[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 3:6[/link], [link]14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>That you may not be [note]1[/note]sluggish, but [xref]a[/xref]imitators of those who through [xref]b[/xref]faith and long-suffering are [xref]c[/xref]inheriting the promises.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, dull; as in [link]5:11[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 13:7[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 4:16[/link]; [link]11:1[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 1:6[/link]; [link]2:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Thes. 1:4[/link]; [link]Rev. 13:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 11:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>For God, when He made the promise to Abraham, since He could swear by no one greater, [xref]a[/xref]swore by Himself,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 22:16[/link]; [link]Luke 1:73[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Saying, [xref]a[/xref]"Surely blessing, I will bless you; and multiplying, I will multiply you."</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 22:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And thus when [i]Abraham[/i] had patiently [xref]a[/xref]endured, he obtained the [xref]b[/xref]promise.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 4:17-21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Gal. 3:16-18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>For men swear by the greater, and for all disputes among them an oath is final for confirmation.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Therefore God, intending to show more abundantly to the [xref]a[/xref]heirs of the promise the [xref]b[/xref]unchangeableness of His counsel, interposed with an oath,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 11:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Psa. 33:11[/link]; [link]110:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>In order that by [note]1[/note]two unchangeable things, in which it was impossible for God to [xref]a[/xref]lie, we may have strong encouragement, we who have [note]2[/note]fled for [note]3[/note]refuge to lay hold of the [xref]b[/xref]hope set before [i]us,[/i]</text>
        <note num="1">These two things are God's promise and oath ([link]v. 17[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., fled intensively; implying to flee to a safeguard. Cf. [link]Acts 14:6[/link].</note>
        <note num="3">The Lord Jesus entered the heavens, the Holy of Holies within the veil, as mentioned in [link]v. 20[/link], and with Him is the heavenly haven for our refuge, which we can now enter in our spirit ([link]10:19[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Num. 23:19[/link]; [link]Titus 1:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 6:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Which we have as an [note]1[/note]anchor of the soul, both secure and firm and which [note]2[/note]enters within the veil,</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Anchor[/i] signifies that we are on a stormy sea and that without the anchor of hope we may shipwreck ([link]1 Tim. 1:19[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">The heavens, into which the Lord Jesus entered, are today the Holy of Holies within the veil. Our hope, as a secure and firm anchor, has entered there, and we may now enter there in our spirit ([link]10:19-20[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Where the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Forerunner, Jesus, has entered for us, having become forever a High Priest according to the [xref]b[/xref]order of Melchizedek.</text>
        <note num="1">As the Forerunner, the Lord Jesus took the lead to pass through the stormy sea and enter the heavenly haven to be the High Priest for us according to the order of Melchizedek. As such a Forerunner, He is the Author of our salvation ([link]2:10[/link]). As the Forerunner, He cut the way to glory, and as the Author, He entered into glory.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Heb. 2:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 5:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="7">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[note]1[/note]For this [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]Melchizedek, [note]2[/note]king of Salem, priest of the Most High God, who met Abraham returning from the [xref]b[/xref]slaughter of the kings and blessed him,</text>
        <note num="1">According to the work and ministry of Christ, this book has a turn at this verse, a turn from earth to heaven. To the end of [link]ch. 6[/link], what is revealed is mainly Christ's work on earth, typified by the priesthood of Aaron. That section is the word of foundation. From this verse, Christ's ministry in heaven according to the order of Melchizedek is unveiled. This section is the word of perfection, which shows us how the heavenly Christ ministers in the heavenly tabernacle. His purifying of sins is typified by the work of Aaron, while His sitting down on the right hand of the Majesty on high ([link]1:3[/link]) is according to the order of Melchizedek ([link]Psa. 110:1[/link], [link]4[/link]). His work on the cross on earth, typified by the work of Aaron, affords us forgiveness of sins. His ministry on the throne in heaven ministers to us the overcoming of sin. His cross delivered us out of Egypt; His throne brings us into Canaan. The Hebrew believers participated in His work on the cross. Now they had to press on to enter into the enjoyment of His ministry on the throne.</note>
        <note num="2">[i]Melchizedek[/i] means [i]king of[/i] righteousness, and [i]king of Salem[/i] means [i]king of peace[/i] ([link]v. 2[/link]). As the King of righteousness ([link]Isa. 32:1[/link]), Christ made all things right with God and made all things right with one another. Righteousness issues in peace ([link]Isa. 32:17[/link]). As the King of peace ([link]Isa. 9:6[/link]), Christ, through righteousness, brings in peace between God and us, and in such a peace He fulfills the ministry of His priesthood. He is the King who becomes the Priest; thus, His priesthood is kingly, royal ([link]1 Pet. 2:9[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 5:6[/link], [link]10[/link]; [link]6:20[/link]; [link]Gen. 14:18-20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Gen. 14:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>To whom also Abraham apportioned a [xref]a[/xref]tenth part of all; first being interpreted [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]king of righteousness, and then also king of Salem, which is [note]1[/note][xref]c[/xref]king of peace;</text>
        <note num="1">At the beginning of this chapter we have the King, and at the end we have the Son of God ([link]v. 28[/link]), indicating that Christ as our High Priest is both kingly and divine. His kingship maintains a condition that is full of righteousness and peace that He may minister the processed Triune God to us for our enjoyment; His divinity as the Son of God constitutes Him a High Priest who is living and full of life that He may be able to continue His priesthood perpetually.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 14:20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Psa. 72:2[/link]; [link]Isa. 32:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Isa. 9:6[/link]; [link]Eph. 2:14[/link]; [link]Isa. 32:17[/link]; [link]Psa. 72:3[/link]; [link]85:10[/link][br/]See note 2[sup]1[/sup].</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Being [note]1[/note]without father, without mother, without genealogy; having neither [xref]a[/xref]beginning of days nor [xref]b[/xref]end of life, but likened to the Son of God, abides a priest [xref]c[/xref]perpetually.</text>
        <note num="1">For all the important persons in Genesis, except Melchizedek, there is a genealogy. In the divine writing, the Holy Spirit sovereignly gave no account of the beginning of Melchizedek's days or of the end of his life, that he might be a proper type of Christ as the eternal One, as our perpetual High Priest. This corresponds with the presentation of the Son of God in the Gospel of John. Being eternal, the Son of God has no genealogy ([link]John 1:1[/link]). But as the Son of Man, Christ does have a genealogy ([link]Matt. 1:1-17[/link]; [link]Luke 3:23-38[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]John 1:1[/link]; [link]8:58[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 1:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 7:24[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And consider how [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]great this one was, to whom the patriarch Abraham gave a tenth of the choice spoils.</text>
        <note num="1">The fact that Abraham gave a tenth of the spoils testifies to the greatness of Melchizedek, who is a type of Christ. Christ, as a Priest according to the order of Melchizedek, is greater than the priests of the tribe of Levi, who offered tithes to Melchizedek through their father Abraham ([link]v. 9[/link]), since they were in Abraham's loins when he met Melchizedek ([link]v. 10[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 10:21[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And they of the sons of Levi, who received the priestly service, have a commandment to take [xref]a[/xref]tithes from the people according to the law, that is, from their brothers, though they have come forth from the loins of Abraham.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Num. 18:21[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>But he whose genealogy is not counted from them has taken tithes from Abraham and has [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]blessed him who has the promises.</text>
        <note num="1">The fact that Melchizedek blessed Abraham testifies again that he is greater than Abraham ([link]v. 7[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 14:19[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>But without any dispute the [note]1[/note]lesser is blessed by the [note]2[/note]greater.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, inferior.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, superior, better.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And here men, who die, receive tithes; but there, one [xref]a[/xref]of whom it is testified that he [xref]b[/xref]lives.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 110:4[/link]; [link]Heb. 5:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]John 14:19[/link]; [link]Rev. 1:18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And, so to speak, through Abraham, [note]1[/note]Levi also, he who receives tithes, has been made to pay tithes,</text>
        <note num="1">This corresponds with the fact that all the human race sinned in Adam, since all the human race was in the loins of Adam when he sinned ([link]Rom. 5:12[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>For he was still in the loins of his father when Melchizedek met him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>If indeed then perfection were through the Levitical priesthood (for under it the people have received the law), what need was there still that a different [note]1[/note]Priest should arise according to the order of [xref]a[/xref]Melchizedek and that He should not be said [i]to be[/i] according to the order of Aaron?</text>
        <note num="1">This book is focused on the heavenly Christ, and the chief point concerning this Christ is that He is a Priest not according to the order of Aaron but according to the order of Melchizedek. All the other aspects of Christ in the foregoing chapters, such as His being the Son of God, the Son of Man, the Author of salvation, the Apostle, and the real Joshua, are the necessary qualifications for Him to be such a Priest, a Priest who can minister to us whatever we need and save us to the uttermost.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 5:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>For since the [xref]a[/xref]priesthood is [note]1[/note]transferred, of necessity there comes into being a [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]transfer of law also.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., transferred from the order of Aaron to the order of Melchizedek ([link]v. 11[/link]), from the priestly tribe of Levi to the kingly tribe of Judah ([link]v. 14[/link]), and from men to the Son of God ([link]v. 28[/link]), who is both the only begotten Son and the firstborn Son.</note>
        <note num="2">This was a transfer from the law of letters to the law of life, according to which Christ has been appointed a living and perpetual High Priest ([link]v. 16[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Heb. 7:24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 8:7[/link], [link]8[/link], [link]13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>For He of whom these things are said [note]1[/note]belongs to a different tribe, from which [xref]a[/xref]no one has attended to the altar.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., has partaken of.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Num. 16:40[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>For it is evident that our Lord has [note]1[/note]risen out of [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]Judah, concerning which tribe Moses spoke nothing about priests.</text>
        <note num="1">The Greek word carries the sense of [i]sprung up, sprouted.[/i]</note>
        <note num="2">In the Old Testament, Levi was the tribe of the priests, and Judah was the tribe of the kings. The Lord descended from the tribe of Judah, causing a transfer in the priesthood and combining in one tribe the priesthood and the kingship ([link]Zech. 6:13[/link]), as manifested in Melchizedek, who was both high priest and king ([link]v. 1[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Matt. 2:6[/link]; [link]Rev. 5:5[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And it is still more abundantly evident since [i]it is[/i] according to the [xref]a[/xref]likeness of Melchizedek [i]that[/i] a different Priest arises,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 7:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Who has been appointed not according to the law of a [xref]a[/xref]fleshy commandment but according to the [xref]b[/xref]power of an [note]1[/note]indestructible [xref]c[/xref]life.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, indissoluble. Christ was appointed the High Priest not according to the powerless letters of law but according to the powerful element of an indestructible life, which nothing can dissolve. This life is endless, being the eternal, divine, uncreated life, and the resurrection life, which passed through the test of death and Hades ([link]Acts 2:24[/link]; [link]Rev. 1:18[/link]). It is by such a life that Christ ministers today as our High Priest. Hence, He is able to save us to the uttermost ([link]v. 25[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 9:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 1:4[/link]; [link]Phil. 3:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Tim. 1:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>For it is testified, "You are a Priest forever according to the [xref]a[/xref]order of Melchizedek."</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 5:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>For there is, on the one hand, the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]setting aside of the preceding commandment because of its [xref]b[/xref]weakness and unprofitableness</text>
        <note num="1">The commandment, or the regulations, of the law concerning the Levitical priesthood was set aside because it was merely in letters and thus was weak. It was not a matter of life but was a dead commandment in letters; thus, it was unprofitable.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 2:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 8:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>(For the [xref]a[/xref]law [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]perfected nothing), and, on the other hand, the bringing in [note]2[/note]thereupon of a [note]3[/note]better [xref]c[/xref]hope, through which we [xref]d[/xref]draw near to God.</text>
        <note num="1">Because of the weakness of man, the law perfected nothing ([link]Rom. 8:3[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Upon the position occupied by the commandment.</note>
        <note num="3">This better hope is the priesthood in an indestructible life ([link]v. 16[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 8:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:9[/link]; [link]10:1[/link]; [link]Rom. 8:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 6:18[/link]; [link]10:23[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 7:25[/link]; cf. [link]Heb. 4:16[/link]; [link]10:22[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And inasmuch as [i]He was[/i] not [i]made a Priest[/i] without the taking of an oath</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>(For they are appointed priests without the taking of an oath, but He, with the taking of an oath by Him who said to Him, [xref]a[/xref]"The Lord has sworn and will not regret [i]it,[/i] You are a Priest forever"),</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 110:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>By so much Jesus has also become the [note]1[/note]surety of a [xref]a[/xref]better [xref]b[/xref]covenant.</text>
        <note num="1">The Greek word means [i]a[/i] guarantee, [i]bondsman, sponsor,[/i] and is from the root word meaning [i]a hand into which something is placed as a pledge,[/i] implying that the guarantee, the surety, cannot be unbound. Christ is not only the consummator of the new covenant; He is also the surety, the pledge that everything in that covenant will be fulfilled. That Christ has become the surety of a better covenant is based on the fact that He is the living and perpetual High Priest.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 8:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 8:8[/link]; [link]9:15[/link]; [link]12:24[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>And they are appointed priests many in number because death prevents [i]them[/i] from continuing;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>But He, because He [xref]a[/xref]abides forever, has His priesthood unalterable.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 6:9[/link]; [link]Rev. 1:18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Hence also He is [xref]a[/xref]able to save [note]1[/note]to the uttermost those who [xref]b[/xref]come forward to God through Him, since He [xref]c[/xref]lives always to [note]2[/note][xref]d[/xref]intercede for them.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, completely, entirely, perfectly, to the end, and for eternity.</note>
        <note num="2">Christ as our High Priest undertakes our case by interceding for us. He appears before God on our behalf and prays for us that we may be saved and brought fully into God's eternal purpose.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 2:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 4:16[/link]; [link]11:6[/link]; [link]10:22[/link]; [link]7:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 7:8[/link]; [link]Rev. 1:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Rom. 8:34[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>For such a [xref]a[/xref]High Priest was also fitting to us, holy, [xref]b[/xref]guileless, undefiled, separated from sinners and having become [note]1[/note]higher than the [xref]c[/xref]heavens,</text>
        <note num="1">In His ascension Christ passed through the heavens ([link]4:14[/link]), so that now He not only is in heaven ([link]9:24[/link]) but also is higher than the heavens, far above all the heavens ([link]Eph. 4:10[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 2:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 4:15[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 2:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 4:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>Who does not have daily need, as the high priests [i]do,[/i] to [xref]a[/xref]offer up sacrifices first for his [xref]b[/xref]own sins and then for those of the people; for this He did [xref]c[/xref]once for all when He [xref]d[/xref]offered up Himself.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 5:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 5:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 9:12[/link], [link]28[/link]; [link]10:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 9:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>For the law establishes men as high priests who have [xref]a[/xref]weakness, but the word of the oath, which [i]was[/i] after the law, [i]establishes[/i] the [xref]b[/xref]Son, [note]1[/note][xref]c[/xref]perfected forever.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Perfected[/i] means [i]brought to an end by being completed,[/i] implying to be made qualified. The Son of God here must be not just the only begotten Son but also the firstborn Son, who has been perfected forever through His incarnation, human living, death, and resurrection. Now He is completely perfected, equipped, and qualified to be our divine High Priest.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 5:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 5:5-6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 5:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="8">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Now in the things which are being said the chief point [i]is this:[/i] We have such a [xref]a[/xref]High Priest, who sat down on the [xref]b[/xref]right hand of the [xref]c[/xref]throne of the [xref]d[/xref]Majesty in the [note]1[/note]heavens,</text>
        <note num="1">Christ, as the High Priest in the heavens, brings us into heaven, from the earthly outer court into the heavenly Holy of Holies, which is joined to our spirit by Him as the heavenly ladder ([link]Gen. 28:12[/link]; [link]John 1:51[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 2:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 1:13[/link]; [link]Mark 16:19[/link]; [link]Col. 3:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rev. 3:21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 1:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>A [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Minister of the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]holy places, even of the true tabernacle, which the Lord pitched, not man.</text>
        <note num="1">One who ministers as a priest. As a minister of the true (heavenly) tabernacle, Christ ministers heaven (which is not only a place but also a condition of life) into us that we may have the heavenly life and power to live a heavenly life on earth, as He did while He was here.</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word for [i]holy places,[/i] used as a noun, is plural here. It refers to all the holy places in the tabernacle; strictly, it refers to the Holy of Holies, the holiest of all the holy places ([link]9:8[/link], [link]12[/link], [link]25[/link]; [link]10:19[/link]; [link]13:11[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Rom. 15:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:24[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>For every high priest is established for the [xref]a[/xref]offering of both [note]1[/note]gifts and sacrifices; hence it is necessary that this One also have something which He may [xref]b[/xref]offer.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]1[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 5[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 5:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:14[/link]; [link]Eph. 5:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Now then if He were on earth, He would not be a Priest at all, there being those who offer the gifts according to the law,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Who serve the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]example and [xref]b[/xref]shadow of the heavenly things, even as Moses was divinely instructed when he was about to complete the tabernacle; for, [xref]c[/xref]"See," He said, "that you make all things according to the pattern that was shown to you in the mountain."</text>
        <note num="1">Or, copy, representation.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 9:23[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Col. 2:17[/link]; [link]Heb. 10:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Exo. 25:40[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>But now He has obtained a more excellent [note]1[/note]ministry inasmuch as He is also the [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]Mediator of a [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]better [xref]c[/xref]covenant, which has been [note]4[/note]enacted upon [note]5[/note]better [xref]d[/xref]promises.</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to the ministry of a priest; derived from the same Greek word as [i]minister[/i] in [link]v. 2[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">In His heavenly ministry Christ, as the Mediator, is the Executor of the new covenant, the new testament, which He bequeathed to us by His death.</note>
        <note num="3">This better covenant not only was enacted upon better promises of a better law, the inner law of life ([link]vv. 10-12[/link]), but also was consummated with Christ's better sacrifices ([link]9:23[/link]), which accomplished for us an eternal redemption ([link]9:12[/link]), and the better blood of Christ, which purifies our conscience ([link]9:14[/link]). Even more, the High Priest of this better covenant, the eternal Son of the living God, ministers with a more excellent ministry ([link]v. 6[/link]) and in the greater and more perfect tabernacle ([link]9:11[/link]).</note>
        <note num="4">Just as the old covenant was the old law enacted by God, so the new covenant is the new law enacted by God, as mentioned in [link]vv. 10-12[/link].</note>
        <note num="5">The better promises are given in [link]Jer. 31:31-34[/link] and are quoted in [link book="Heb." chapter="8"]vv. 8-12[/link] of this chapter and [link chapter="10"]vv. 16-17[/link] of [link]ch. 10[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 9:15[/link]; [link]12:24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 7:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 8:8[/link]; [link]9:15[/link]; [link]12:24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 8:8-12[/link]; [link]Jer. 31:31-34[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>For if that [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]first [i]covenant[/i] had been faultless, no [note]2[/note]place would have been [xref]b[/xref]sought for a [note]1[/note]second.</text>
        <note num="1">The first covenant is the old covenant, and the second is the new covenant.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, space; metaphorically, occasion, condition.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 8:13[/link]; [link]9:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 7:12[/link], [link]18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>For finding fault with them He says, [xref]a[/xref]"Behold, the days are coming, says the Lord, and I will consummate a [xref]b[/xref]new covenant upon the house of Israel and upon the house of Judah,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]vv. 8-12[/link]; [link]Jer. 31:31-34[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 8:13[/link]; [link]9:15[/link]; [link]12:24[/link]; [link]Luke 22:20[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 11:25[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Not according to the covenant which I made with their fathers in the day when I took them by their hand to lead them out of the land of Egypt, because they did not continue in My covenant, and I disregarded them, says the Lord.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>For [xref]a[/xref]this is the covenant which I will covenant with the house of Israel after those days, says the Lord: I will impart My [note]1[/note]laws into their [note]2[/note]mind, and on their hearts I will [note]3[/note]inscribe them; and [note]4[/note]I will be God to them, and [note]5[/note]they will be a people to Me.</text>
        <note num="1">In [link]Jer. 31:33[/link], the source of this quotation, the word used is [i]law[/i] (singular), whereas in this verse it is [i]laws[/i] (plural). This proves that it is one law that spreads to become a number of laws. This one law is the law of life (see [i]the law of the Spirit of life[/i] &amp;#8212; [link]Rom. 8:2[/link]). Every life has a law. The higher the life, the higher is its law. The divine life that we receive of God is the highest life; therefore, it has the highest law, the law referred to here. By imparting His divine life into us, God puts this highest law into our spirit, whence it spreads into our inward parts, such as our mind, emotion, and will, and becomes several laws.[br][br]The law of life differs from the law of letters. The law of life regulates us from within by and according to its life element, whereas the law of letters regulates us from without by and according to its dead letters. The law of dead letters depends on outward teachings, but the law of life depends on the inward consciousness. Since we all, great or small, have the law of life, we do not need outward teachings that are according to the law of letters ([link]v. 11[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Here, [i]mind[/i] corresponds with [i]inward parts[/i] in [link]Jer. 31:33[/link]. This proves that the mind is one of the inward parts and that it is the interpretation of the term [i]inward parts.[/i] The inward parts consist of not only the mind but also the emotion and the will. These three are components of the heart, mentioned in the succeeding clause.</note>
        <note num="3">First, God imparts His laws into us; then He inscribes them on us. He does the inscribing while we are experiencing the law of life.</note>
        <note num="4">Lit., I will be to them for God.</note>
        <note num="5">Lit., they will be to Me for a people. It is according to the law of life that we are a people to God and that He is God to us. God's relationship with us today is based fully on the law of life, so that today we do not need to walk according to the knowledge of the law of letters but should walk according to the consciousness of the law of life.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 10:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And they shall by no means each [xref]a[/xref]teach his fellow citizen and each his brother, saying, [note]1[/note]Know the Lord; for all will [note]1[/note]know Me from the little one to the great one among them.</text>
        <note num="1">In this verse two Greek words are used for [i]know:[/i] the first is [i]ginosko,[/i] which signifies the outward, objective knowledge; the second is [i]oida,[/i] which refers to the inward, subjective consciousness. In [link]John 8:55[/link] the Lord Jesus told the Pharisees that they did not know ([i]ginosko[/i]) God the Father (even in the outward, objective knowledge), and that He did know ([i]oida[/i]) the Father (in the inward, subjective consciousness). Both words are used in [link]1 John 2:29[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 John 2:27[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>For [xref]a[/xref]I will be [note]1[/note]propitious to their unrighteousnesses, and their sins I shall by no means remember anymore."</text>
        <note num="1">The word is the root of the Greek word for [i]make propitiation[/i] in [link]2:17[/link]. To be propitious is to make propitiation for our sins (see note [link]17[sup]4[/sup] in ch. 2[/link]). In the new covenant four blessings are promised: (1) propitiation for our unrighteousnesses and the forgetting (forgiveness) of our sins ([link]v. 12[/link]); (2) the imparting of the law of life by the imparting of the divine life into us ([link]v. 10a[/link]); (3) the privilege of having God as our God and of being His people &amp;#8212; the divine life's enabling us to participate in the enjoyment of God in fellowship with Him ([link]v. 10b[/link]); and (4) the function of life that enables us to know Him in the inward way of life ([link]v. 11[/link]). According to the covenant that God consummated, these four blessings are His promise. But according to the testament that the Lord bequeathed to us, they are His bequests. See note [link]16[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 9[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 10:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>In saying, A [xref]a[/xref]new [i]covenant,[/i] He has made the [note]1[/note]first old. But that which is becoming old and growing decrepit is near to [xref]b[/xref]disappearing.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., the old covenant. So also in [link]9:1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 8:8[/link]; [link]9:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 7:12[/link], [link]18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="9">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Now then the [xref]a[/xref]first [i]covenant[/i] also had [xref]b[/xref]ordinances of service, and its [note]1[/note][xref]c[/xref]sanctuary was of [xref]d[/xref]this world.</text>
        <note num="1">The same Greek word as for [i]holy places[/i] in [link]8:2[/link]. Here, however, it is singular and, hence, is rendered [i]sanctuary.[/i] The sanctuary is the entire tabernacle ([link]Exo. 25:8-9[/link]), including the first tabernacle, which is called the Holy Place ([link]v. 2[/link]), and the second tabernacle, which is called the Holy of Holies ([link]v. 3[/link]). See note [link]2[sup]2[/sup] in ch. 8[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 8:7[/link], [link]13[/link]; [link]9:15[/link], [link]18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 9:24[/link]; [link]Exo. 25:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 9:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>For a [xref]a[/xref]tabernacle was prepared, the first, in which were the [xref]b[/xref]lampstand and the [xref]c[/xref]table and the [xref]d[/xref]loaves that were set forth, which is called the [xref]e[/xref]Holy Place;</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 9:6[/link]; [link]Exo. 26:35[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Exo. 25:31-39[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Exo. 25:23-29[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Exo. 25:30[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Exo. 26:33[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And after the second [xref]a[/xref]veil, a [xref]b[/xref]tabernacle, which is called the [xref]c[/xref]Holy of Holies,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 26:31-33[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Exo. 40:21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Exo. 26:33-34[/link]; [link]Heb. 9:8[/link], [link]12[/link], [link]25[/link]; [link]10:19[/link]; [link]13:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Having a [xref]a[/xref]golden [note]2[/note]altar and the [xref]b[/xref]Ark of the Covenant covered about everywhere with gold, in which were the golden [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]pot that had the manna and Aaron's [xref]d[/xref]rod that budded and the [xref]e[/xref]tablets of the covenant,</text>
        <note num="1">Regarding the place where the incense altar stood, there is apparently a discrepancy between the Old Testament and the New Testament. [link]Exodus 30:6[/link] says that the incense altar was put before the veil, i.e., outside the veil. This indicates clearly that the incense altar was put in the Holy Place, which is outside the veil, not in the Holy of Holies, which is within the veil. But here it says that the Holy of Holies has the incense altar. Therefore, most Christian teachers and Bible readers have thought that some error or misconstruction must somehow have occurred. But this is not so! The apparent discrepancy has great spiritual significance, as shown by the following points:[br][br](1) The Old Testament record of the incense altar's location implies the closest relationship between the incense altar and the Ark of the Testimony, over which was the expiation cover, where God met with His people ([link]Exo. 30:6[/link]). The record even says that the incense altar was set before the Ark of the Testimony, with no mention being made of the separating veil that stood between them ([link]Exo. 40:5[/link]).[br][br](2) [link]First Kings 6:22[/link] (ASV) says that the incense "altar...belonged to the oracle." The Hebrew word for [i]oracle[/i] includes the meaning [i]the speaking place of God.[/i] The oracle denotes the Holy of Holies, in which was the Ark of the Testimony with the expiation cover, where God spoke to His people. Thus, the Old Testament indicated beforehand that the incense altar belonged to the Holy of Holies. (Though the incense altar was in the Holy Place, its function was for the Ark of the Testimony in the Holy of Holies. On the Day of Expiation, both the incense altar and the expiation cover of the Ark of the Testimony were sprinkled with the same blood for expiation &amp;#8212; [link]Exo. 30:10[/link]; [link]Lev. 16:15-16[/link].) Hence, in [link]Exo. 26:35[/link] only the showbread table and the lampstand are mentioned as being in the Holy Place; the incense altar is not mentioned.[br][br](3) The incense altar is related to prayer ([link]Luke 1:10-11[/link]), and in this book we are shown that to pray is to enter the Holy of Holies ([link]10:19[/link]) and to come to the throne of grace, which is signified by the expiation cover over the Ark of the Testimony in the Holy of Holies. Our prayer often begins with our mind, which is a part of our soul, signified by the Holy Place. But our prayer always ushers us into our spirit, signified by the Holy of Holies.[br][br](4) On account of all the above points, the writer of this book had to consider the incense altar as belonging to the Holy of Holies. [link]Verse 4[/link] does not say that a golden altar was in the Holy of Holies, as the lampstand and the table were in the Holy Place ([link]v. 2[/link]). It says that the Holy of Holies had a golden altar, because the altar belonged to the Holy of Holies. This concept fits the entire emphasis of the book of Hebrews, i.e., that we should press on from the soul (signified by the Holy Place) to the spirit (signified by the Holy of Holies).[br][br]The incense altar belongs to the oracle &amp;#8212; the speaking place of God, i.e., the Holy of Holies. The incense altar typifies Christ in His resurrection as the sweet and fragrant incense, in which God extends to us His well-pleased acceptance. We pray with such a Christ in order to contact God that God may be pleased to speak to us. We speak to God in our prayer with Christ as the sweet incense, and God speaks to us in the sweet savor of this incense. This is the dialogue in the sweet fellowship between us and God through Christ as the sweet incense.</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word here for [i]altar[/i] can be translated [i]censer.[/i] But here it refers to the incense altar, not the censer; according to the record of the Old Testament, there was no incense censer in the Holy Place or in the Holy of Holies.</note>
        <note num="3">The arrangement of the furniture of the tabernacle portrays our experience of Christ. In the outer court were the bronze altar and the bronze laver ([link]Exo. 40:29-32[/link]). This signifies that our experience of Christ begins, in an outward sense, with His redemption, which was accomplished on the cross, and the cleansing of the Holy Spirit, which is based on Christ's redemption. In the Holy Place were the showbread table and the lampstand, with the incense altar located close to the Holy of Holies, in front of the Ark of the Testimony. The showbread table signifies our experience of Christ as our life supply, and the lampstand, our experience of Christ as the shining light. These experiences are rather inward, in the intellect and consciousness of our being. The incense altar signifies our experience of Christ as the sweet incense ascending to God. This experience is deeper and more inward, leading to the deepest and most inward experiences, in the Holy of Holies. In the Holy of Holies was the Ark of the Testimony, in which were the golden pot containing the hidden manna; Aaron's budding rod; and the tablets of the covenant. The hidden manna in the golden pot signifies our experience of Christ as our life supply in the deepest way, an experience much deeper than that signified by the showbread table in the Holy Place. The budding rod signifies our experience of Christ in His resurrection as our acceptance by God for authority in the God-given ministry. This is deeper than the experience of Christ as the incense for our acceptance by God. The tablets of the covenant, which are the tablets of the Ten Commandments, signify our experience of Christ as the enlightening inner law, which regulates us according to God's divine nature. This is deeper than the experience of Christ as the shining lampstand in the Holy Place. All these deepest experiences of Christ take place in our spirit, signified by the Holy of Holies.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 30:1-4[/link], [link]6[/link]; [link]40:5[/link]; [link]1 Kings 6:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Exo. 25:10-22[/link]; [link]26:34[/link]; [link]40:21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Exo. 16:33-34[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Num. 17:3[/link], [link]5[/link], [link]8[/link], [link]10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Deut. 10:4-5[/link]; [link]Exo. 34:1[/link], [link]29[/link]; [link]25:21[/link]; [link]40:20[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And above it [xref]a[/xref]cherubim of glory overshadowing the [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]expiation cover, concerning which it is not now [i]the time[/i] to speak in detail.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., propitiation place. See note [link]25[sup]2[/sup] in Rom. 3[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 25:18-20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Exo. 25:17[/link], [link]21[/link]; [link]Rom. 3:25[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Now these things having been thus prepared, [xref]a[/xref]into the [xref]b[/xref]first tabernacle the priests enter [xref]c[/xref]continually, accomplishing their worship;</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Lev. 4:5-7[/link]; [link]Exo. 27:21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 10:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>But into the [xref]a[/xref]second, only the [xref]b[/xref]high priest [i]enters,[/i] [xref]c[/xref]once a year [i]and[/i] not without [xref]d[/xref]blood, which he offers for [xref]e[/xref]himself and for the [note]1[/note]sins of ignorance of the [xref]f[/xref]people,</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., ignorances. The word refers to those sins that are committed in ignorance of God's law; hence, they are sins of ignorance ([link]Lev. 4:2[/link], [link]13[/link], [link]22[/link], [link]27[/link]; [link]5:17-18[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 9:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Lev. 16:15-17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Exo. 30:10[/link]; [link]Lev. 16:34[/link]; [link]Heb. 10:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Lev. 16:14[/link], [link]15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Lev. 16:6[/link], [link]11[/link]; [link]Heb. 5:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]Lev. 16:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>The [xref]a[/xref]Holy Spirit [i]thus[/i] making this clear, that the [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]way of the [xref]c[/xref][i]Holy of[/i] Holies has not yet been manifested while the [xref]d[/xref]first tabernacle still has [i]its[/i] standing,</text>
        <note num="1">The first tabernacle, the Holy Place, signifies the old covenant, and the second tabernacle, the Holy of Holies, signifies the new covenant. The veil that closed off the Holy of Holies was rent ([link]Matt. 27:51[/link]) by the death of Christ, which crucified the flesh ([link]10:20[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:24[/link]), and now the way of the Holy of Holies has been manifested. Hence, we do not need to remain in the Holy Place, i.e., the old covenant, the soul; we must enter into the Holy of Holies, i.e., the new covenant, the spirit. That is the goal of this book.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 3:7[/link]; [link]10:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 10:20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 9:3[/link], [link]12[/link], [link]25[/link]; [link]10:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 9:2[/link], [link]6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Which is a [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]figure for the present time. According to [i]this tabernacle[/i] both [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]gifts and sacrifices are offered, which are [xref]c[/xref]unable to perfect, according to [xref]d[/xref]conscience, him who worships,</text>
        <note num="1">Or, symbol, type; lit., parable.</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]1[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 5[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Heb. 9:23[/link], [link]24[/link]; [link]8:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 5:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 10:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 10:2[/link], [link]22[/link]; [link]9:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>[i]Consisting[/i] only of [xref]a[/xref]foods and drinks and various [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]washings, being ordinances of the flesh, imposed until the time of [note]2[/note]setting things right.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., baptisms; as in [link]6:2[/link] (see note 1 there).</note>
        <note num="2">Or, reformation, putting in order, setting things straight. The time of setting things right occurred at Christ's first coming, when He fulfilled all the shadows of the Old Testament that a new covenant might replace the old. This is a right arrangement, a right ordering. Hence, it is a reformation. This is different from the restoration in [link]Acts 3:21[/link], which will occur at Christ's second coming.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Col. 2:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 6:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>But Christ, having come as a [xref]a[/xref]High Priest of [note]1[/note]the [xref]b[/xref]good things that have come into being, through the greater and more perfect [xref]c[/xref]tabernacle not [xref]d[/xref]made by hands, that is, not of [xref]e[/xref]this creation,</text>
        <note num="1">Some ancient MSS read, the good things to come.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 2:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 10:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 8:2[/link]; [link]9:24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Mark 14:58[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 5:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Heb. 9:1[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And not through the [xref]a[/xref]blood of goats and calves but through His [xref]b[/xref]own blood, [xref]c[/xref]entered [xref]d[/xref]once for all into the [xref]e[/xref][i]Holy of[/i] Holies, [note]1[/note]obtaining an [xref]f[/xref]eternal [note]2[/note]redemption.</text>
        <note num="1">Christ accomplished redemption on the cross ([link]Col. 1:20[/link]), but it was not until He entered into the heavenly Holy of Holies through the redeeming blood, i.e., when He brought His redeeming blood to offer it before God, that He obtained the redemption that has an eternal effect.</note>
        <note num="2">In the old covenant the blood of goats and calves only made expiation for people's sins ([link]Lev. 16:15-18[/link]); it never accomplished redemption for their sins, because it is impossible for the blood of bulls and goats to take away sins ([link]10:4[/link]). In Hebrew the root of the word for [i]expiation[/i] means [i]to cover.[/i] Thus, to make expiation means to cover sins; it does not mean to take away sins. Since Christ as the Lamb of God took away the sin of the world ([link]John 1:29[/link]) by offering Himself once for all on the cross as the sacrifice for sins ([link]v. 14[/link]; [link]10:12[/link]), His blood, which He sprinkled in the heavenly tabernacle ([link]12:24[/link]), has accomplished an eternal redemption for us, even the redemption of the transgressions under the first (old) covenant ([link]v. 15[/link]), transgressions that were only covered by animal blood. Thus, we have been redeemed with the precious blood of Christ ([link]1 Pet. 1:18-19[/link]). See note 1[sup]1[/sup] in Lev. 16.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Lev. 16:14[/link], [link]15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:14[/link]; [link]12:24[/link]; [link]13:12[/link]; [link]Matt. 26:28[/link]; [link]Rom. 3:25[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:7[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:19[/link]; [link]Rev. 1:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 6:19[/link], [link]20[/link]; [link]9:24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 7:27[/link]; [link]10:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Heb. 9:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]Heb. 5:9[/link]; [link]9:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>For if the [xref]a[/xref]blood of goats and bulls and the [xref]b[/xref]ashes of a heifer [xref]c[/xref]sprinkling those who are [note]1[/note]defiled sanctify to the purity of the flesh,</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., made common.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 9:19[/link]; [link]Lev. 16:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Num. 19:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Num. 19:18[/link], [link]19[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>How much more will the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]blood of Christ, who through the [note]2[/note]eternal Spirit [xref]b[/xref]offered Himself [xref]c[/xref]without blemish to God, purify our [note]3[/note][xref]d[/xref]conscience from [note]4[/note][xref]e[/xref]dead works to [xref]f[/xref]serve the [note]5[/note][xref]g[/xref]living God?</text>
        <note num="1">The blood of Christ was shed for the forgiveness of sins ([link]Matt. 26:28[/link]), and the new covenant was consummated with it ([link]10:29[/link]; [link]Luke 22:20[/link]). It accomplished an eternal redemption for us ([link]v. 12[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:7[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:18-19[/link]) and purchased the church for God ([link]Acts 20:28[/link]). It washes us from our sins ([link]1 John 1:7[/link]), purifies our conscience ([link]v. 14[/link]), sanctifies us ([link]13:12[/link]), and speaks something better for us ([link]12:24[/link]). By this blood we enter the Holy of Holies ([link]10:19[/link]) and overcome Satan the accuser ([link]Rev. 12:10-11[/link]). Therefore, it is precious and better than the blood of goats and bulls ([link]vv. 12-13[/link]). We must value it highly and should not regard it a common thing, like animal blood. If we do, we will suffer God's punishment ([link]10:29-31[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">On the cross Christ offered Himself to God in the human body ([link]10:5[/link], [link]10[/link]), which was under the limitation of time. But He offered Himself through the eternal Spirit, who is of eternity and is not under the limitation of time. Hence, in the eyes of God, Christ as the Lamb of God was slain from the foundation of the world ([link]Rev. 13:8[/link]). His offering of Himself was once for all ([link]7:27[/link]), and the redemption consummated through His death is eternal ([link]v. 12[/link]), having an eternal effect. The span of His redemption fully covers the span of sin. See note [link]26[sup]1[/sup][/link], par. 2.</note>
        <note num="3">The blood of Christ purifies our conscience to serve the living God. To serve the living God requires a blood-purified conscience. To worship in dead religion or to serve any dead thing, anything that is outside God, does not require our conscience to be purified. The conscience is the leading part of our spirit. The living God whom we desire to serve always comes to our spirit ([link]John 4:24[/link]) by touching our conscience. He is righteous, holy, and living. Our defiled conscience needs to be purified that we may serve Him in a living way. To worship God in our mind in a religious way does not require this.</note>
        <note num="4">Since we were dead ([link]Eph. 2:1[/link]; [link]Col. 2:13[/link]), whatever we did, whether bad or good, was dead works before the living God.</note>
        <note num="5">This book does not teach religion; rather, it reveals the living God ([link]3:12[/link]; [link]9:14[/link]; [link]10:31[/link]; [link]12:22[/link]). To touch this living God we need to exercise our spirit ([link]4:12[/link]) and have a blood-purified conscience in our spirit.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 9:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 7:27[/link]; [link]9:28[/link]; [link]10:10[/link], [link]12[/link], [link]14[/link]; [link]Eph. 5:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Pet. 1:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 10:2[/link], [link]22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Heb. 6:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]1 Thes. 1:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="g">[link]Heb. 3:12[/link]; [link]10:31[/link]; [link]Acts 14:15[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 3:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And because of this He is the [xref]a[/xref]Mediator of a [xref]b[/xref]new covenant, so that, death having taken place for redemption of the [note]1[/note]transgressions under the [xref]c[/xref]first covenant, those who have been [xref]d[/xref]called might receive the [note]2[/note]promise of the [note]3[/note]eternal [xref]e[/xref]inheritance.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., transgressions reckoned as sins according to the standard of the provisions of the first covenant.</note>
        <note num="2">The promise of the eternal inheritance is based on Christ's eternal redemption, not on our work, and is different from the promise in [link]10:36[/link], which is conditioned on our endurance and our doing the will of God. (See note [link]36[sup]2[/sup] in ch. 10[/link].) The eternal inheritance in the promise here is through the eternal redemption of Christ, whereas the great reward ([link]10:35[/link]) in the promise in [link]10:36[/link] is given by virtue of our endurance and our doing the will of God.</note>
        <note num="3">See note [link]34[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 10[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 8:6[/link]; [link]12:24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 8:8[/link], [link]13[/link], [link]6[/link]; [link]7:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 9:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 3:1[/link]; [link]Rom. 8:30[/link]; [link]Eph. 4:1[/link], [link]4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Acts 20:32[/link]; [link]26:18[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:14[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>For where there is a [note]1[/note]testament, the death of him who made the testament must of necessity be established.</text>
        <note num="1">In Greek the same word is used for both [i]covenant[/i] and [i]testament.[/i] A covenant is an agreement containing some promises to accomplish certain things for the covenanted people, while a testament is a will containing certain accomplished things that are bequeathed to the inheritor. The new covenant consummated with the blood of Christ is not merely a covenant but a testament in which all the things that were accomplished by the death of Christ have been bequeathed to us. First, God gave the promise that He would make a new covenant ([link]Jer. 31:31-34[/link]). Then Christ shed His blood to enact the covenant ([link]Luke 22:20[/link]). Since accomplished facts are promised in this covenant, it is also a testament. This testament, this will, was confirmed and validated by Christ's death and is being executed and enforced by Christ in His resurrection. The promise of God's covenant is insured by God's faithfulness; God's covenant is guaranteed by God's righteousness; and the testament is enforced by Christ's resurrection power.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>For a [note]1[/note]testament is confirmed [note]2[/note]in the case of the dead, since it never has force when he who made the testament is living.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]16[sup]1[/sup][/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., over the dead.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Hence neither was the [xref]a[/xref]first [i]covenant[/i] [note]1[/note]initiated without [xref]b[/xref]blood;</text>
        <note num="1">The word implies the sense of [i]newly enacted, inaugurated.[/i]</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 9:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Exo. 24:6-8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>For when every commandment according to the law had been spoken by Moses to all the people, he [xref]a[/xref]took the blood of the calves and the goats, with water and [xref]b[/xref]scarlet wool and hyssop, and sprinkled both the scroll [i]of the covenant[/i] itself and all the people,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 24:6-8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Lev. 14:6[/link], [link]49-52[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Saying, "This is the blood of the covenant which God has commanded to you."</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And both the [xref]a[/xref]tabernacle and all the vessels of the service he sprinkled in like manner with the blood.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Lev. 16:14-19[/link], [link]33[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And almost all things are purified by blood according to the law, and [note]1[/note]without shedding of [xref]a[/xref]blood there is no forgiveness.</text>
        <note num="1">Without the shedding of blood there is no forgiveness of sins. Without forgiveness of sins there is no way for the requirement of God's righteousness to be fulfilled that the covenant may be enacted. But Christ's blood was shed for the forgiveness of sins, and the covenant was enacted with His blood ([link]Matt. 26:28[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Lev. 17:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>It was necessary therefore for the [xref]a[/xref]examples of the things in the heavens to be purified by these, but the [note]1[/note]heavenly things themselves, by [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]better sacrifices than these.</text>
        <note num="1">The tabernacle and all things pertaining to it were sprinkled with and purified by the blood of goats and bulls ([link]vv. 21-23[/link]). That was a figure showing that the heavenly things needed to be purified by the blood of better sacrifices, which are the sacrifices of Christ ([link]7:27[/link]; [link]9:14[/link], [link]28[/link]; [link]10:10[/link], [link]12[/link], [link]14[/link]). Heaven and all things in heaven were defiled by the rebellion of Satan and the fallen angels, who followed Satan in his rebellion against God. So all the heavenly things needed to be purified. Christ accomplished this purification with His own blood when He entered into heaven itself ([link]v. 24[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Christ offered Himself as the one sacrifice ([link]v. 14[/link]; [link]10:12[/link]). This one sacrifice, viewed from its various aspects, can be considered many sacrifices. As Christ is the eternal Son of the living God incarnated to be the Son of Man, and as He offered Himself to God through the eternal Spirit, so His sacrifices, which are Himself, are better than the animal sacrifices. Those were shadows that could never remove sins ([link]10:11[/link]), but His sacrifices are real and have put away sin once for all ([link]v. 26[/link]). Thus He obtained an eternal redemption for us ([link]v. 12[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 9:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:26[/link]; [link]10:10[/link], [link]12[/link], [link]14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>For Christ did not [xref]a[/xref]enter into a [note]1[/note]holy place made by hands, a [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]figure of the [xref]c[/xref]true, but into [xref]d[/xref]heaven itself, to appear now before the face of God for us;</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]2[sup]2[/sup] in ch. 8[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Or, copy.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 9:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 8:2[/link]; [link]9:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 4:14[/link]; [link]7:26[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Nor in order that He might offer Himself often, just as the [xref]a[/xref]high priest enters into the [xref]b[/xref][i]Holy of[/i] Holies year by year by the blood of other [i]creatures;[/i]</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 9:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>Since then He would have had to suffer often [xref]a[/xref]since the foundation of the world. But now [xref]b[/xref]once at the [note]1[/note][xref]c[/xref]consummation of the ages He has been [xref]d[/xref]manifested for the [xref]e[/xref]putting away of sin through the [xref]f[/xref]sacrifice of Himself.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, completion of the ages, end of the ages. Here it means the end of the Old Testament age, whereas [i]the consummation of the age[/i] in [link]Matt. 28:20[/link] refers to the close of the church age.[br][br]Christ was foreordained for us before the foundation of the world ([link]1 Pet. 1:20[/link]), and He was slain from the foundation of the world ([link]Rev. 13:8[/link]). Actually, His being slain occurred once for all at the consummation of the ages, when He offered Himself to God, in His first manifestation, for the putting away of sin. See note [link]14[sup]2[/sup][/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rev. 13:8[/link]; cf. [link]1 Pet. 1:20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:12[/link]; [link]7:27[/link]; [link]10:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 1:2[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 John 3:5[/link], [link]8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]John 1:29[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]Heb. 9:23[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>And inasmuch as it is [note]1[/note]reserved for men to [xref]a[/xref]die [note]2[/note]once, and after this [i]comes[/i] [xref]b[/xref]judgment,</text>
        <note num="1">Or, laid up.</note>
        <note num="2">As man has to die once and be judged after dying, so Christ died once to bear man's sins ([link]v. 28[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 2:24[/link]) and on the cross suffered judgment for man ([link]Isa. 53:5[/link], [link]11[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 5:12[/link]; [link]6:23[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 10:42[/link]; [link]Rom. 2:16[/link]; [link]Rev. 20:11-13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>So Christ also, having been offered [xref]a[/xref]once to [xref]b[/xref]bear the sins of many, will [xref]c[/xref]appear a second time to those who [xref]d[/xref]eagerly await Him, [note]1[/note]apart from sin, unto [note]2[/note][xref]e[/xref]salvation.</text>
        <note num="1">Since in His first appearing Christ put away sin ([link]v. 26[/link]; [link]1 John 3:5[/link]), His second appearing will be apart from sin, having nothing to do with sin.</note>
        <note num="2">Salvation here means the redemption of our body and deliverance from the vanity and slavery of corruption of the old creation into the freedom of the glory of the children of God ([link]Rom. 8:18-23[/link]; [link]Phil. 3:20-21[/link]). This is to be glorified ([link]Rom. 8:17[/link], [link]30[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 7:27[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 3:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Isa. 53:11[/link], [link]12[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 2:24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Col. 3:4[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:7[/link]; [link]1 John 2:28[/link]; [link]3:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Cor. 1:7[/link]; [link]Phil. 3:20[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 1:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Rom. 8:23[/link], [link]24[/link]; [link]Phil. 3:20-21[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="10">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>For the law, having a [xref]a[/xref]shadow of the [xref]b[/xref]good things to come, not the image itself of the things, can [xref]c[/xref]never by the same sacrifices year by year, which they offer continually, [xref]d[/xref]perfect those who draw near.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 8:5[/link]; [link]Col. 2:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 9:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">cf. [link]Heb. 10:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Otherwise would they not have [xref]a[/xref]ceased to be offered, because those worshipping, having once been purified, would have no longer had the [xref]b[/xref]consciousness of sins?</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 10:18[/link], [link]26[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>But in those [i]sacrifices[/i] there is a bringing to mind of sins [xref]a[/xref]year by year;</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 30:10[/link]; [link]Lev. 16:34[/link]; [link]Heb. 9:7[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>For it is [xref]a[/xref]impossible for the [xref]b[/xref]blood of bulls and goats to [xref]c[/xref]take away sins.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 10:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">cf. [link]John 1:29[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Therefore, coming into the world, He says, [xref]a[/xref]"Sacrifice and offering You did not desire, but a [xref]b[/xref]body You have prepared for Me.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]vv. 5-7[/link]; [link]Psa. 40:6-8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 10:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>In [xref]a[/xref]burnt offerings and [xref]b[/xref][i]sacrifices[/i] for sin You did not delight.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Lev. 1:3[/link], [link]4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Lev. 4:3[/link], [link]14[/link], [link]29[/link]; [link]Heb. 10:26[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Then I said, Behold, I have come [xref]a[/xref](in the [note]1[/note]roll of the book it is written concerning Me) to do Your [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]will, O God."</text>
        <note num="1">The Old Testament gives us a full record of Christ, either by plain words or by types ([link]Luke 24:27[/link], [link]44[/link], [link]46[/link]; [link]John 5:39[/link], [link]46[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">The will of God here was to take away the first, the animal sacrifices of the old covenant, that the second, the sacrifice of Christ of the new testament, might be established. So in [link]vv. 9-10[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Luke 24:27[/link], [link]44[/link], [link]46[/link]; [link]John 5:39[/link], [link]46[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 10:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Saying above, "Sacrifices and offerings and burnt offerings and [i]sacrifices[/i] for sin You did not desire nor delight in" (which are offered according to the law),</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>He then has said, "Behold, I have come to do Your will." He takes away the [note]1[/note]first that He may establish the [note]1[/note]second,</text>
        <note num="1">[i]The[/i] first here refers to the sacrifices of the first covenant, the old covenant; [i]the[/i] second refers to the sacrifice of the second covenant, the new covenant, which sacrifice is Christ. Christ came into the world that He might, according to the will of God, put away the animal sacrifices of the old covenant and establish Himself as the sacrifice of the new covenant.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>By which [xref]a[/xref]will we have been [xref]b[/xref]sanctified through the [xref]c[/xref]offering of the [xref]d[/xref]body of Jesus Christ [note]1[/note][xref]e[/xref]once for all.</text>
        <note num="1">The main thought in [link]vv. 1-18[/link] is that Christ has removed sins, accomplishing what all the Levitical sacrifices were unable to do. Having put away sin once for all, Christ has now imparted Himself into us as the divine life so that through the working of this divine life we may become the corporate reproduction of Himself.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 10:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 2:11[/link]; [link]10:14[/link], [link]29[/link]; [link]13:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 10:12[/link]; [link]7:27[/link]; [link]9:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 10:5[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 2:24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Heb. 9:28[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And every priest [note]1[/note]stands daily, ministering and offering often the same sacrifices, which can [xref]a[/xref]never [xref]b[/xref]remove sins;</text>
        <note num="1">The priests in the old covenant stood daily and offered the same sacrifices again and again, because what they offered could never remove sins. But Christ put away sin ([link]9:26[/link]) by offering Himself to God as the one sacrifice for sins, whereupon He sat down forever on the right hand of God ([link]v. 12[/link]). His sitting in heaven is a sign and proof that the removing of sins has been accomplished. His sitting there is forever. Hence, He no longer needs to do anything for sin. He did it once for all. His sitting down forever after having offered one sacrifice for sins is in contrast to the priests' standing daily to offer often the same sacrifices.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 10:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. [link]John 1:29[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>But this One, having [xref]a[/xref]offered one [xref]b[/xref]sacrifice for sins, [note]1[/note][xref]c[/xref]sat down [note]2[/note]forever on the right hand of God,</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]11[sup]1[/sup][/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., unto perpetuity. So in [link]v. 14[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 10:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:26[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 1:3[/link], [link]13[/link]; [link]8:1[/link]; [link]12:2[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:20[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Henceforth waiting until His [xref]a[/xref]enemies are made the footstool for His feet.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 110:1[/link]; [link]Matt. 22:44[/link]; [link]Acts 2:35[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>For by [xref]a[/xref]one offering He has [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]perfected forever those who are being [xref]c[/xref]sanctified.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, completed. Christ has already perfected and completed us through His one offering.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 10:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. [link]Heb. 7:19[/link]; [link]9:9[/link]; [link]10:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 10:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And the [xref]a[/xref]Holy Spirit also testifies to us, for after having said,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 3:7[/link]; [link]9:8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]"This is the covenant which I will covenant with them after those days, says the Lord: I will impart My laws upon their hearts, and upon their mind I will inscribe them,"</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Jer. 31:33[/link]; [link]Heb. 8:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>[i]He then says,[/i] "And [xref]a[/xref]their sins and their lawlessnesses I shall by no means remember anymore."</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Jer. 31:34[/link]; [link]Heb. 8:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Now where forgiveness of these is, there is [xref]a[/xref]no longer an offering for sin.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 10:26[/link], [link]2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Having therefore, brothers, [xref]a[/xref]boldness for [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]entering the [xref]c[/xref][i]Holy of[/i] Holies in the [xref]d[/xref]blood of Jesus,</text>
        <note num="1">The Holy of Holies today is in heaven, where the Lord Jesus is ([link]9:12[/link], [link]24[/link]). How, then, can we enter the Holy of Holies while we are still on earth? The secret is our spirit, referred to in [link]4:12[/link]. The very Christ who is in heaven is now also in our spirit ([link]2 Tim. 4:22[/link]). As the heavenly ladder ([link]Gen. 28:12[/link]; [link]John 1:51[/link]), He joins our spirit to heaven and brings heaven into our spirit. Hence, whenever we turn to our spirit, we enter into the Holy of Holies. There we meet with God, who is on the throne of grace. See note [link]16[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 4[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 4:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:25[/link]; cf. [link]Heb. 9:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 9:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 9:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Which [i]entrance[/i] He initiated for us as a [note]1[/note]new and living [xref]a[/xref]way through the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]veil, that is, His [xref]c[/xref]flesh,</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., recently opened.</note>
        <note num="2">This is the second veil ([link]Heb. 9:3[/link]) within the tabernacle, which veil typifies the flesh of Christ. When Christ's flesh was crucified, this veil was rent ([link]Matt. 27:51[/link]), thus opening the way for us, those who were alienated from God, who is signified by the tree of life ([link]Gen. 3:22-24[/link]), to enter into the Holy of Holies to contact Him and take Him as the tree of life for our enjoyment. This implies that because our old man was crucified with Christ, we have an open way to contact and enjoy God in our spirit as our life and life supply.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 9:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Exo. 26:33[/link]; [link]Heb. 9:3[/link]; [link]Matt. 27:51[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]John 1:14[/link]; [link]Rom. 8:3[/link]; [link]Heb. 2:14[/link]; [link]Eph. 2:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And [i]having[/i] a [xref]a[/xref]great [xref]b[/xref]Priest over the [xref]c[/xref]house of God,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 7:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 2:17[/link]; [link]4:14[/link]; [link]7:26[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 3:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Let us [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]come forward to [i]the[/i] [xref]b[/xref][i]Holy of Holies[/i] with a true heart in full [xref]c[/xref]assurance of faith, having our hearts [xref]d[/xref]sprinkled from an evil conscience and having our [note]2[/note]bodies [xref]e[/xref]washed with [note]2[/note]pure water.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Come forward[/i] (to the Holy of Holies) is in contrast to [i]shrink back[/i] (to Judaism) in [link]vv. 38-39[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Both the bodies and the pure water here are figurative, like the spot, the wrinkle, and the water in [link]Eph. 5:26-27[/link]. The body refers to our visible outward being, just as the heart refers to our invisible inward being. The pure water refers to the Lord's living word that cleanses our outward conduct and walk (cf. [link]John 15:3[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 4:16[/link]; [link]7:25[/link]; cf. [link]Heb. 7:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 6:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 9:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">cf. [link]Exo. 29:4[/link]; [link]40:12[/link]; [link]Lev. 8:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Let us [xref]a[/xref]hold fast the [xref]b[/xref]confession of our [xref]c[/xref]hope unwavering, for He who has promised is [xref]d[/xref]faithful;</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 3:6[/link], [link]14[/link]; [link]4:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 3:1[/link]; [link]4:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 3:6[/link]; [link]6:11[/link], [link]18[/link]; [link]7:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Cor. 1:9[/link]; [link]10:13[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 5:24[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 2:13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And let us consider one another so as to incite [i]one another[/i] to love and good works,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Not [note]1[/note]abandoning our own [note]2[/note]assembling together, as the custom with some is, but [xref]a[/xref]exhorting [i]one another;[/i] and so much the more as you see the [xref]b[/xref]day drawing [xref]c[/xref]near.</text>
        <note num="1">For the Hebrew believers, at their time and in their situation, to abandon their own assembling together would have been to abandon the new covenant way of contacting God, to abandon the church and return to their old religion &amp;#8212; Judaism. This would have broken God's administration of grace, thus constituting a serious sin before God ([link]v. 26[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Our assembling together as Christians. In those days the Hebrews who believed in the Lord had come out of Judaism and had formerly gone to the gatherings in Judaism. When they believed in Christ and became Christians, they attended Christian gatherings; this equaled their being separated from Judaism. Therefore, if any of them had gone back to the gatherings in Judaism, that would have been equivalent to their being separated from the proper Christian assemblings, which are according to God's New Testament economy. Hence, Paul exhorted them not to abandon their own assembling together as Christians.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 3:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Cor. 3:13[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 3:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rom. 13:12[/link]; [link]James 5:8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>For when we [note]1[/note]sin willfully after receiving the knowledge of the [note]2[/note]truth, there [note]3[/note][xref]a[/xref]no longer remains a [xref]b[/xref]sacrifice [i]of bulls and goats[/i] for sins,</text>
        <note num="1">To sin willfully here means to abandon one's own assembling together with the church. The Hebrew believers had been instructed to abandon Judaism and remain under the new covenant. If they had still returned to Judaism, they would have abandoned their own assembling with the church. This would have constituted a willful sin in the eyes of God, in that it would have been committed after they had received the knowledge of the truth, after they had come to know that God had abandoned Judaism, which was formed according to the old covenant, and had initiated the new and living way of contacting God according to the new covenant.</note>
        <note num="2">[i]Truth[/i] here refers to the things disclosed in the foregoing chapters and verses; those things afforded the Hebrew believers the full knowledge that God had annulled the old covenant and had established the new.</note>
        <note num="3">If the Hebrew believers had abandoned the church and returned to Judaism, there would have remained no sacrifice for sins in the economy of God, for all the sacrifices of the old covenant had been altogether replaced by the one sacrifice of Christ. Since Christ offered Himself once for all as the sacrifice for our sins ([link]7:27[/link]; [link]10:10[/link], [link]12[/link]), the sacrifice for sins ceased ([link]v. 2[/link]). It was taken away by Christ ([link]v. 9[/link]), who offered Himself to God as the real sacrifice for our sins.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 10:18[/link], [link]2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 10:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>But a certain [xref]a[/xref]fearful expectation of [xref]b[/xref]judgment and [xref]c[/xref]fervor of fire, which is to [xref]d[/xref]consume the adversaries.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 10:31[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 10:30[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Psa. 79:5[/link]; [link]Ezek. 38:19[/link]; [link]Zeph. 1:18[/link]; [link]3:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Isa. 26:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Anyone who has set aside the law of Moses dies without compassion on [i]the testimony of[/i] [xref]b[/xref]two or three witnesses.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Deut. 17:2-7[/link]; [link]Heb. 2:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Num. 35:30[/link]; [link]Deut. 19:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]By [xref]b[/xref]how much do you think he will be thought worthy of [note]1[/note]worse punishment who has [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]trampled underfoot the Son of God and has [note]3[/note]considered [xref]d[/xref]the blood of the covenant by which he was [xref]e[/xref]sanctified a common thing and has [note]4[/note]insulted the [xref]f[/xref]Spirit of grace?</text>
        <note num="1">This is different from suffering the second death, which is to perish in the lake of fire for eternity ([link]Rev. 20:6[/link], [link]14[/link]; [link]21:8[/link]). Although believers cannot be lost, they may suffer some dispensational punishment for their failures. This punishment will be worse than that received by those who broke the law of letters.</note>
        <note num="2">In the new covenant the Son of God replaces all the sacrifices of the old covenant. If the Hebrew believers had returned to Judaism to offer any of the old sacrifices, they would have been, in effect, trampling underfoot the Son of God.</note>
        <note num="3">If the Hebrew believers had returned to Judaism to offer the old sacrifices and thus rely on the blood of slain animals, they would have been, in effect, considering the precious blood of Christ a common thing. This would have been to seriously disregard the unique redemptive work of Christ.</note>
        <note num="4">Under the new covenant, through the redeeming blood of Christ, the Hebrew believers became partakers of the Holy Spirit ([link]6:4[/link]), the Spirit of grace. If they had returned to Judaism, the Spirit of grace, who dwelled in them and worked in them, would have been insulted by their willful sin.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 12:25[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 2:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">cf. [link]Heb. 6:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 13:20[/link]; [link]Matt. 26:28[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Heb. 10:14[/link]; cf. [link]Heb. 9:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]Zech. 12:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>For we know Him who said, [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]"Vengeance is Mine; I will repay"; and again, [xref]b[/xref]"The Lord will [xref]c[/xref]judge His people."</text>
        <note num="1">The Greek word conveys no thought of vindictiveness; rather, it implies a full meting out of justice to all parties.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Deut. 32:35[/link]; [link]Rom. 12:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Deut. 32:36[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 10:27[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>It is a [xref]a[/xref]fearful thing to fall into the hands of the [xref]b[/xref]living God.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 10:27[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 5:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 3:12[/link]; [link]9:14[/link]; [link]12:22[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>But call to mind the former days, in which, having been [xref]a[/xref]enlightened, you endured a great [xref]b[/xref]conflict of [xref]c[/xref]sufferings;</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 6:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Phil. 1:29-30[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rev. 1:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>On one hand, being made a [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]spectacle both in [xref]b[/xref]reproaches and in afflictions, and on the other, having become [xref]c[/xref]partakers with those who are treated the same.</text>
        <note num="1">A show exposed to the public, a gazingstock. The same thing happened to the apostles ([link]1 Cor. 4:9[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 4:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 11:26[/link]; [link]13:13[/link]; [link]Rom. 15:3[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 12:10[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 4:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Thes. 2:14[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 1:8[/link]; [link]Phil. 4:14[/link]; [link]3:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>For you both sympathized with those in [xref]a[/xref]bonds and accepted with [xref]b[/xref]joy the plundering of your possessions, knowing that you yourselves have a [note]1[/note]better [xref]c[/xref]possession and one that abides.</text>
        <note num="1">This better and abiding possession is the eternal inheritance ([link]9:15[/link]) and the incorruptible, undefiled, and unfading inheritance that is kept in the heavens ([link]1 Pet. 1:4[/link]). Under the old covenant the Jewish people inherited earthly things as their possession; but under the new covenant the believers inherit the heavenly riches as their possession. This better and abiding possession was a great incentive to the Hebrew believers to suffer the loss of earthly things.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 13:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Matt. 5:11-12[/link]; [link]Acts 5:41[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 4:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 9:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>Do not cast away therefore your [xref]a[/xref]boldness, which has great [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]reward.</text>
        <note num="1">The reward is something in addition to eternal salvation. Eternal salvation is obtained through faith, having nothing to do with our works ([link]Eph. 2:8-9[/link]), whereas the reward is given for the work that we do after we are saved ([link]1 Cor. 3:8[/link], [link]14[/link]). We may not receive a reward but may suffer loss, even though we are saved, because we are void of the work that the Lord approves ([link]1 Cor. 3:15[/link]). The reward will be given to us at the Lord's coming back, according to our works ([link]Matt. 16:27[/link]; [link]Rev. 22:12[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 4:5[/link]). What we receive will be decided at the judgment seat of Christ ([link]2 Cor. 5:10[/link]) and will be enjoyed in the coming kingdom ([link]Matt. 25:21[/link], [link]23[/link]). The apostle Paul strived to gain the reward ([link]1 Cor. 9:24-27[/link]; [link]Phil. 3:13-14[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 4:7-8[/link]). Even Moses looked away to the reward ([link]11:26[/link]; see note 3 there). Here the Hebrew believers were charged not to miss the reward &amp;#8212; the coming Sabbath rest ([link]4:9[/link]), the enjoyment of Christ and the reigning with Christ in the coming kingdom.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 4:13[/link]; [link]Phil. 1:20[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 3:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Matt. 5:12[/link]; [link]16:27[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 3:8[/link], [link]14[/link]; [link]Heb. 11:26[/link]; [link]Rev. 22:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
        <text>For you have need of [xref]a[/xref]endurance in order that, having done the [note]1[/note]will of God, you may obtain the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]promise.</text>
        <note num="1">The will of God here for the Hebrew believers was that they take the new covenant way ([link]vv. 19-23[/link]) and remain with the church ([link]v. 25[/link]), not shrinking back to Judaism ([link]vv. 38-39[/link]) but suffering persecution from Judaism ([link]vv. 32-34[/link]). For this they would receive the promise of a great reward ([link]v. 35[/link]) at the Lord's coming back ([link]v. 37[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">The promise here is the promise of the Sabbath rest mentioned in [link]4:9[/link], a rest in which we will reign with Christ in the coming kingdom. That will be the great reward mentioned in [link]v. 35[/link], which is the gaining of the soul mentioned in [link]v. 39[/link]. This promise is conditioned on our endurance and our doing the will of God. It differs from the promise in [link]9:15[/link]. See note 2 there.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 12:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 4:1[/link], [link]9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
        <text>"For in yet a very little while the Coming One will [xref]a[/xref]come and will not delay.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Hab. 2:3[/link]; [link]Rev. 22:20[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
        <text>But My [xref]a[/xref]righteous one shall live [xref]b[/xref]by [note]1[/note]faith; and if he shrinks back, My soul does not delight in him."</text>
        <note num="1">After this verse and the next, [link]ch. 11[/link] gives a full definition of faith.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Hab. 2:4[/link]; [link]Rom. 1:17[/link]; [link]Gal. 3:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Cor. 5:7[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
        <text>But we are not of those who [note]1[/note]shrink back to [note]2[/note]ruin but of them who have faith to the [note]3[/note][xref]a[/xref]gaining of the soul.</text>
        <note num="1">For the Hebrew believers to shrink back to Judaism was for them to shrink back to ruin, which is not eternal perdition but punishment meted out by the living God ([link]vv. 29-31[/link]). See next note.</note>
        <note num="2">The ruin here is the punishment mentioned in [link]vv. 27-31[/link], which will come upon those who forsake the new covenant and return to Judaism, thus trampling underfoot the Son of God, regarding Christ's precious blood a common thing, like animal blood, and insulting the Spirit of grace.</note>
        <note num="3">Or, saving, preserving, possessing. Our being is of three parts &amp;#8212; spirit, soul, and body ([link]1 Thes. 5:23[/link]), and our soul is different from our spirit. At the time that we believed in the Lord Jesus and were saved, our spirit was regenerated with the Spirit of God ([link]John 3:6[/link]). But we must wait until the Lord Jesus comes back for our body to be redeemed, saved, and transfigured ([link]Rom. 8:23-25[/link]; [link]Phil. 3:21[/link]). Concerning the saving, or gaining, of our soul, it depends on how we deal with our soul in following the Lord after we are saved and regenerated. If we lose our soul now for the Lord's sake, we will save it ([link]Matt. 16:25[/link]; [link]Luke 9:24[/link]; [link]17:33[/link]; [link]John 12:25[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:9[/link]), and it will be saved, or gained, at the Lord's coming back ([link]v. 37[/link]). This gaining of the soul will be the reward ([link]v. 35[/link]) of the kingdom to the overcoming followers of the Lord ([link]Matt. 16:22-28[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Matt. 16:25[/link]; [link]Luke 9:24[/link]; [link]17:33[/link]; [link]John 12:25[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="11">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Now [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]faith is the [note]2[/note]substantiation of things [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]hoped for, the [note]4[/note]conviction of things [note]5[/note][xref]c[/xref]not seen.</text>
        <note num="1">After presenting in the first ten chapters a thorough comparison of Judaism and God's economy, this book charges the Hebrew believers, who were in danger of shrinking back, to live, to walk, to go on, by faith ([link]10:38-39[/link]), that is, not by appearance ([link]2 Cor. 5:7[/link]). Then, in [link]ch. 11[/link] it goes on to define faith according to the history of faith. Both the eternal inheritance ([link]9:15[/link]) and the great reward ([link]10:35[/link]) promised by God are things hoped for and things not seen. Faith is the substantiation of things hoped for. Hence, it is the assurance, the confidence, the confirmation, the reality, the essence, the supporting ground, of things hoped for, the foundation that supports the things hoped for. Faith is also the conviction of things not seen. It convinces us of what we do not see. Hence, it is the evidence, the proof, of things not seen.</note>
        <note num="2">The same Greek word is used for [i]substance[/i] in [link]1:3[/link], [i]assurance[/i] in [link]3:14[/link], and [i]confidence[/i] (in which one knows that he has a sure foundation) in [link]2 Cor. 11:17[/link]. Moreover, it can be translated [i]confirmation, reality, essence[/i] (which denotes the real nature of things, as opposed to the appearance), [i]foundation,[/i] or [i]supporting ground.[/i] The word means, primarily, [i]substance,[/i] but here it denotes the substantiating of the substance (of the things hoped for); hence, it is translated [i]substantiation.[/i] The word [i]substantiate[/i] is [i]substance[/i] in verb form; to substantiate is to give substance to the reality of the substance not seen. This is the action of faith. Therefore, it says here that faith is the substantiation of things hoped for.</note>
        <note num="3">The unbelievers, being without Christ, have no hope ([link]Eph. 2:12[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 4:13[/link]). But we, the believers in Christ, are a people of hope. The calling that we receive from God brings us hope ([link]Eph. 1:18[/link]; [link]4:4[/link]). We have been regenerated unto a living hope ([link]1 Pet. 1:3[/link]). Our Christ, who is in us, is the hope of glory ([link]Col. 1:27[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 1:1[/link]), which will issue in the redemption, the transfiguration, of our body in glory ([link]Rom. 8:23-25[/link]). This is the hope of salvation ([link]1 Thes. 5:8[/link]), a blessed hope ([link]Titus 2:13[/link]), a good hope ([link]2 Thes. 2:16[/link]), the hope of eternal life ([link]Titus 1:2[/link]; [link]3:7[/link]); it is also the hope of the glory of God ([link]Rom. 5:2[/link]), the hope of the gospel ([link]Col. 1:23[/link]), the hope laid up for us in the heavens ([link]Col. 1:5[/link]). We should keep this hope always ([link]1 John 3:3[/link]) and boast in it ([link]Rom. 5:2[/link]). Our God is the God of hope ([link]Rom. 15:13[/link]), and through the encouragement of the Scriptures we can have hope ([link]Rom. 15:4[/link]) all the time in God ([link]1 Pet. 1:21[/link]) and can rejoice in it ([link]Rom. 12:12[/link]). This book charges us to hold fast the boast of hope firm to the end ([link]3:6[/link]), to show diligence unto the full assurance of our hope until the end ([link]6:11[/link]), and to lay hold of the hope set before us ([link]6:18[/link]). It also tells us that the new covenant brings in a better hope, through which we draw near to God ([link]7:19[/link]). Our life should be a life of hope, which accompanies and abides with faith ([link]1 Pet. 1:21[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 13:13[/link]). We should follow Abraham, who beyond hope believed in hope ([link]Rom. 4:18[/link]).</note>
        <note num="4">The conviction of truth. The Greek word can be translated [i]evidence,[/i] or [i]proof.[/i]</note>
        <note num="5">All things hoped for are things not seen ([link]Rom. 8:24-25[/link]). As people of hope, we should aim our life not at the things that are seen but at the things that are not seen; for the things that are seen are temporary, but the things that are not seen are eternal ([link]2 Cor. 4:18[/link]). Hence, we walk by faith, not by appearance ([link]2 Cor. 5:7[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 10:38[/link], [link]39[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 3:6[/link]; [link]6:11[/link]; [link]7:19[/link]; [link]10:23[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 11:7[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 4:18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>For in this the elders have obtained a good [xref]a[/xref]testimony.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 11:4[/link], [link]5[/link], [link]39[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>[note]1[/note]By faith we understand that the [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]universe has been framed by the [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]word of God, so that what is seen has not come into [xref]c[/xref]being out of things which appear.</text>
        <note num="1">From [link]v. 3[/link] this chapter presents to us a brief history of faith &amp;#8212; from God's creation, through all the generations of God's chosen people, to the New Testament believers ([link]v. 40[/link]) &amp;#8212; to prove that faith is the unique pathway by which God's seekers receive His promise and take His way.</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., ages. See note [link]2[sup]5[/sup] in ch. 1[/link].</note>
        <note num="3">The Greek word denotes the instant word.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 1:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Psa. 33:6[/link], [link]9[/link]; [link]John 1:1[/link], [link]3[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 3:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rom. 4:17[/link]; [link]John 1:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>By faith [xref]a[/xref]Abel offered to God a [note]1[/note]more excellent sacrifice than [xref]b[/xref]Cain, through which he obtained the [xref]c[/xref]testimony that he was righteous, God [xref]d[/xref]testifying to his gifts; and through [note]2[/note]faith, though he has died, he still [xref]e[/xref]speaks.</text>
        <note num="1">This more excellent sacrifice was a type of Christ, who is the real "better sacrifices" ([link]9:23[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., it.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 4:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Gen. 4:3[/link], [link]5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 11:2[/link], [link]5[/link], [link]39[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Gen. 4:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Gen. 4:10[/link]; [link]Heb. 12:24[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>By faith [xref]a[/xref]Enoch was translated so that he should not see death; and he was not found, because God had translated him. For before his translation he obtained the [xref]b[/xref]testimony that he had been well pleasing to God.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 5:21-24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 11:2[/link], [link]4[/link], [link]39[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>But without faith it is impossible to [note]1[/note]be well pleasing [i]to Him,[/i] for he who [xref]a[/xref]comes forward to God must believe that He is and that He is a rewarder of those who [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]diligently seek Him.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, please [i]Him.[/i]</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., seek Him out.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 4:16[/link]; [link]7:25[/link], [link]19[/link]; [link]10:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Psa. 24:6[/link]; [link]27:8[/link]; [link]105:4[/link]; [link]119:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>By faith [xref]a[/xref]Noah, having been divinely instructed concerning things not yet seen [i]and[/i] being moved by pious fear, [xref]b[/xref]prepared an ark for the salvation of his house, through which he condemned the world, and became [xref]c[/xref]heir of the righteousness which is according to faith.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 6:8[/link], [link]9[/link], [link]13-22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Pet. 3:20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 1:14[/link]; [link]6:17[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 3:7[/link]; [link]James 2:5[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>By faith [xref]a[/xref]Abraham, being called, obeyed to [xref]b[/xref]go out unto a place which he was to [xref]c[/xref]receive as an inheritance; and he went out, [note]1[/note]not knowing where he was going.</text>
        <note num="1">This afforded Abraham constant opportunity to exercise his faith to trust in God for His instant leading, taking God's presence as the map for his traveling.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 12:1-5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 7:3-4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Gen. 12:7[/link]; [link]17:8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>By faith he dwelt as a foreigner in the [xref]a[/xref]land of promise as in a foreign [i]land,[/i] making his home in [xref]b[/xref]tents with Isaac and Jacob, the fellow [xref]c[/xref]heirs of the same promise;</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 7:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Gen. 12:8[/link]; [link]13:3[/link], [link]18[/link]; [link]18:1[/link]; [link]24:67[/link]; [link]26:17[/link], [link]25[/link]; [link]25:27[/link]; [link]31:25[/link]; [link]33:19[/link]; [link]35:21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 6:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>For he eagerly waited for the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]city which has the [xref]b[/xref]foundations, whose Architect and Builder is [xref]c[/xref]God.</text>
        <note num="1">This is the city of the living God, the heavenly Jerusalem ([link]12:22[/link]), the Jerusalem above ([link]Gal. 4:26[/link]), the holy city, New Jerusalem ([link]Rev. 21:2[/link]; [link]3:12[/link]), which God has prepared for His people ([link]v. 16[/link]), and the tabernacle of God, in which God will dwell with men for eternity ([link]Rev. 21:3[/link]). As the patriarchs waited for this city, so we also seek it ([link]13:14[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 11:16[/link]; [link]12:22[/link]; [link]13:14[/link]; [link]Rev. 21:2[/link], [link]10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rev. 21:14[/link], [link]19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 11:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>By faith also [xref]a[/xref]Sarah herself received power to conceive seed, even beyond the season of age, since she considered Him [xref]b[/xref]faithful who promised.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 17:19[/link], [link]21[/link]; [link]18:12-14[/link]; [link]21:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 10:23[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 10:13[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 2:13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Therefore also there were born of one, and that of him who had become [xref]a[/xref]dead, [i]as many[/i] as even the [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]stars of heaven in multitude and as the [note]1[/note][xref]c[/xref]sand by the [note]2[/note]seashore innumerable.</text>
        <note num="1">The stars of heaven signify Abraham's heavenly descendants, the descendants who are of faith ([link]Gal. 3:7[/link], [link]29[/link]), whereas the sand by the seashore signifies Abraham's earthly descendants, the descendants in the flesh.</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., the lip of the sea.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 4:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Gen. 15:5[/link]; [link]22:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Gen. 22:17[/link]; [link]32:12[/link]; cf. [link]Gen. 13:16[/link][br/]See note 12[sup]1[/sup].</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>All [xref]a[/xref]these died [note]1[/note]in faith, [xref]b[/xref]not receiving the promises but [xref]c[/xref]seeing them from afar and joyfully greeting [i]them[/i] and confessing that they were [xref]d[/xref]strangers and [note]2[/note]sojourners on the earth.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., according to.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, pilgrims, exiles, expatriates. Abraham was the first Hebrew ([link]Gen. 14:13[/link]), a river crosser. He left Chaldea, the idolatrous land of curse, crossed the flood, the river Perath, or Euphrates ([link]Josh. 24:2-3[/link]), and came to Canaan, the good land of blessing. Yet he did not settle there; rather, he sojourned in the land of promise as a pilgrim, even as an exile, an expatriate, longing after a better country, a heavenly one ([link]v. 16[/link]), seeking a country of his own ([link]v. 14[/link]). This might imply that he was ready to cross another river, from the earthly side to the heavenly side. Isaac and Jacob followed him in the same steps, living on the earth as strangers and sojourners and waiting for the God-built city that has the foundations ([link]v. 10[/link]). The word in [link]vv. 9-16[/link] may imply that the writer of this book intended to impress on the memory of the believing Hebrews the fact that they, as the real Hebrews, should follow their forefathers, considering themselves strangers and sojourners on the earth and looking forward to the heavenly country, which is better than the earthly one.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Matt. 13:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 11:39[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]John 8:56[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Gen. 17:8[/link]; [link]23:4[/link]; [link]47:9[/link]; [link]1 Chron. 29:15[/link]; cf. [link]1 Pet. 2:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>For those who say such things make it manifest that they seek after a [xref]a[/xref]country of their own.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 11:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And if indeed they continued to remember that [i]country[/i] from which they went out, they would have had opportunity to return;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>But as it is, they long after a better [xref]a[/xref][i]country,[/i] that is, a [xref]b[/xref]heavenly one. Therefore God is [xref]c[/xref]not ashamed of them, to be called [xref]d[/xref]their God, for He has prepared a [xref]e[/xref]city for them.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 11:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 12:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 2:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Exo. 3:6[/link], [link]15[/link]; [link]4:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Heb. 11:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>By faith Abraham, being tested, [xref]a[/xref]offered up Isaac; indeed he who gladly received the [xref]b[/xref]promises was offering up his only begotten,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 22:1-10[/link]; [link]James 2:21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Gen. 12:2[/link], [link]7[/link]; [link]13:15-16[/link]; [link]21:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Of whom it was said, [xref]a[/xref]"In Isaac shall your seed be called";</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 21:12[/link]; [link]Rom. 9:7[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Counting that God was [xref]a[/xref]able to [xref]b[/xref]raise [i]men[/i] even from the dead, from which he also received him back in [note]1[/note]figure.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., a parable.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 4:21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 4:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>By faith [xref]a[/xref]Isaac blessed Jacob and Esau, even concerning things to come.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 27:26-29[/link], [link]39-40[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>By faith [xref]a[/xref]Jacob, while he was dying, blessed each of the sons of Joseph and [xref]b[/xref]worshipped [i]God, while[/i] [note]1[/note][i]leaning[/i] on the top of his staff.</text>
        <note num="1">This signifies that Jacob confessed that he was a sojourner, a traveler, on the earth ([link]v. 13[/link]), and that God had shepherded him all his life long ([link]Gen. 48:15[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 48:9[/link], [link]14-16[/link], [link]20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Gen. 47:31[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>By faith [xref]a[/xref]Joseph, nearing his end, made mention of the exodus of the sons of Israel and [xref]b[/xref]gave orders concerning his bones.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 50:24[/link], [link]25[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Exo. 13:19[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>By faith [xref]a[/xref]Moses, when he was born, was hidden for three months by his parents because they saw that the child was [xref]b[/xref]lovely, and they did not fear the [xref]c[/xref]king's decree.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 2:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 7:20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Exo. 1:15[/link], [link]16[/link], [link]22[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>By faith Moses, when he had [xref]a[/xref]grown up, refused to be called the [xref]b[/xref]son of Pharaoh's daughter,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 2:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Exo. 2:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Choosing rather to be [xref]a[/xref]ill-treated with the people of God than to have the [note]1[/note]temporary [note]2[/note]enjoyment of sin,</text>
        <note num="1">Or, for a while, fleeting, passing.</note>
        <note num="2">The enjoyment in Egypt, i.e., the enjoyment in the world, is sinful in the eyes of God. It is the enjoyment of sin, of a sinful life, and is temporary, fleeting, and passing.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 11:37[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>[note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Considering the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]reproach of the Christ greater riches than the [xref]c[/xref]treasures of Egypt; for he [xref]d[/xref]looked away to the [note]3[/note][xref]e[/xref]reward.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, accounting, esteeming.</note>
        <note num="2">Christ, as the Angel of the Lord, was always with the children of Israel in their afflictions ([link]Exo. 3:2[/link], [link]7-9[/link]; [link]14:19[/link]; [link]Num. 20:16[/link]; [link]Isa. 63:9[/link]). Furthermore, the Scripture identifies Him with them ([link]Hosea 11:1[/link]; [link]Matt. 2:15[/link]). Hence, the reproach falling on them was considered His reproach, and the reproaches of those who reproached God fell also on Him ([link]Rom. 15:3[/link]). The New Testament believers, as His followers, bear His reproach ([link]13:13[/link]) and are reproached for His name ([link]1 Pet. 4:14[/link]). Moses, choosing to be ill-treated with the people of God ([link]v. 25[/link]), considered this kind of reproach, the reproach of the Christ of God, greater riches than the treasures of Egypt in Pharaoh's palace; for Moses looked away to the reward.</note>
        <note num="3">Because he was willing to suffer the reproach of the Christ, Moses will receive the reward of the kingdom. He was not allowed to enter into the rest of the good land because of his failure at Meribah ([link]Num. 20:12-13[/link]; [link]Deut. 4:21-22[/link]; [link]32:50-52[/link]), but he will be with Christ in the kingdom ([link]Matt. 16:28-17:3[/link]). In referring to this, surely the writer intended to encourage his readers who were suffering persecution for Christ's sake to follow Moses by considering the reproach of the Christ greater riches than the things they had lost, and by looking away to the reward. See note [link]35[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 10[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Phil. 3:7-8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 13:13[/link]; [link]Rom. 15:3[/link]; [link]Heb. 10:33[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 4:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Exo. 1:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 12:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Heb. 10:35[/link]; [link]Rev. 22:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>By faith he [xref]a[/xref]left Egypt, not fearing the [xref]b[/xref]wrath of the king, for he [note]1[/note]persevered as one [xref]c[/xref]seeing the [xref]d[/xref]unseen One.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, was steadfast.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 12:50-51[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Exo. 10:28[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Exo. 3:2[/link], [link]16[/link]; [link]4:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Col. 1:15[/link]; [link]John 1:18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>By faith he instituted the [xref]a[/xref]Passover and the pouring out of the blood so that the [xref]b[/xref]one destroying the firstborn would not touch them.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 12:21-27[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Exo. 12:23[/link], [link]12[/link], [link]29[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>By faith they [xref]a[/xref]passed through the Red Sea as through dry land, in which the Egyptians, while making the attempt, were swallowed up.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 14:21-30[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>[note]1[/note]By faith the [xref]a[/xref]walls of Jericho fell, having been [xref]b[/xref]encircled for a period of seven days.</text>
        <note num="1">Nothing is mentioned here regarding the forty years during which the children of Israel wandered in the wilderness, since they did nothing by faith there to please God, but rather provoked God by their unbelief during those years ([link]3:16-18[/link]). Even their crossing of the Jordan River is not mentioned here, because that crossing was due to the delay caused by their unbelief. That crossing would not have been needed if they had not had the unbelief that disqualified them from entering the good land at Kadesh-barnea ([link]Deut. 1:19-46[/link]) just a short time after they left Mount Sinai ([link]Deut. 1:2[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Josh. 6:20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Josh. 6:3-4[/link], [link]12-15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>By faith [xref]a[/xref]Rahab the harlot did not perish with those who were disobedient, since she had [xref]b[/xref]received the spies with peace.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Josh. 6:22-25[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Josh. 2:4[/link], [link]6[/link]; [link]James 2:25[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>And what more shall I say? For time will fail me if I tell of [xref]a[/xref]Gideon, [xref]b[/xref]Barak, [xref]c[/xref]Samson, [xref]d[/xref]Jephthah, of [xref]e[/xref]David and [xref]f[/xref]Samuel and the prophets,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Judg. 6-8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Judg. 4-5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Judg. 13-16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Judg. 11-12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]1 Sam. 16[/link]-[link]2 Sam. 24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]1 Sam. 7-16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>Who through faith [xref]a[/xref]overcame kingdoms, [xref]b[/xref]worked righteousness, [xref]c[/xref]obtained promises, [xref]d[/xref]stopped the mouths of lions,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Judg. 4:7[/link], [link]14[/link]; [link]2 Sam. 5:19[/link]; [link]8:2[/link]; [link]10:12-19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Sam. 12:3-5[/link]; [link]2 Sam. 8:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Sam. 7:10-16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Dan. 6:22[/link]; [link]Judg. 14:5-6[/link]; [link]1 Sam. 17:34-37[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Quenched the power of fire, [xref]b[/xref]escaped the edge of the sword, were made strong in weakness, became [xref]c[/xref]mighty in war, routed the armies of foreigners.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Dan. 3:23[/link]; [link]Isa. 43:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Exo. 18:4[/link]; [link]1 Sam. 19:10[/link]; [link]Psa. 144:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Judg. 7:19-21[/link]; [link]1 Sam. 17:51[/link]; [link]2 Sam. 8:1-6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>Women [xref]a[/xref]received their dead by resurrection; and others were tortured [i]to death,[/i] not accepting [note]1[/note]deliverance, in order that they might obtain a [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]better resurrection.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, release. The Greek word means [i]redemption[/i] (offered at a price).</note>
        <note num="2">The better resurrection is not only the first resurrection ([link]Rev. 20:4-6[/link]), the resurrection of life ([link]John 5:28-29[/link]), but also the out-resurrection ([link]Phil. 3:11[/link]), the extra-resurrection, the resurrection in which the Lord's overcomers will receive the reward ([link]v. 26[/link]) of the kingdom. This is what the apostle Paul sought after.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Kings 17:23[/link], [link]24[/link]; [link]2 Kings 4:36[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rev. 20:5[/link]; [link]Phil. 3:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
        <text>And still others underwent the trial of [xref]a[/xref]mockings and scourgings, even, moreover, of bonds and [xref]b[/xref]imprisonment.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Judg. 16:25[/link]; [link]Jer. 20:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Gen. 39:20[/link]; [link]Jer. 37:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
        <text>They were [xref]a[/xref]stoned, they were sawn in two, they were tempted, they died by the [xref]b[/xref]murder of the sword, they wandered about in sheepskins, in goatskins, destitute, afflicted, [xref]c[/xref]ill-treated</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Kings 21:13[/link]; [link]2 Chron. 24:21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Kings 19:10[/link]; [link]Jer. 26:23[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 11:25[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
        <text>(Of [note]1[/note]whom the world was not worthy), wandering over [xref]a[/xref]deserts and [xref]b[/xref]mountains and [i]in[/i] [xref]c[/xref]caves and holes of the earth.</text>
        <note num="1">These faith-people are an extra-people, a people on the highest plane, of whom the corrupted world is not worthy. Only the holy city of God, New Jerusalem, is worthy to have them.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Sam. 23:15[/link]; [link]24:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Sam. 23:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Sam. 22:1[/link]; [link]1 Kings 18:4[/link], [link]13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
        <text>And these all, having obtained a good [xref]a[/xref]testimony through their faith, did [xref]b[/xref]not obtain the promise,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 11:2[/link], [link]4[/link], [link]5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 11:13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
        <text>Because God has [note]1[/note]provided something [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]better for us, so that [note]3[/note]apart from us they would not be made perfect.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, foreseen.</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word means [i]superior,[/i] nobler, greater; hence, better. It is used thirteen times in this book: the better Christ ([link]1:4[/link]), better things ([link]6:9[/link]), a better hope ([link]7:19[/link]), a better covenant (twice &amp;#8212; [link]7:22[/link]; [link]8:6[/link]), better promises ([link]8:6[/link]), better sacrifices ([link]9:23[/link]), a better possession ([link]10:34[/link]), a better country ([link]11:16[/link]), a better resurrection ([link]11:35[/link]), something better ([link]11:40[/link]), and better speaking ([link]12:24[/link]). (The other instance is in [link]7:7[/link], where it is translated [i]greater[/i].) All these better things are the fulfillment and reality of the things that the Old Testament saints had in types, figures, and shadows. What God provided at that time was a picture of the things concerning us, the things that were to come in the new covenant and that are the true and real things, better, stronger, more powerful, nobler, and greater than their types, figures, and shadows. The Old Testament saints, who had only the shadows, need us for their perfection that they may share with us in the real things of the new covenant. Why, then, should we leave the real things of the new covenant and turn to the shadows of the old covenant?</note>
        <note num="3">Both the participation in the kingdom for one thousand years ([link]Rev. 20:4[/link], [link]6[/link]) and the sharing in the New Jerusalem for eternity ([link]Rev. 21:2-3[/link]; [link]22:1-5[/link]) are corporate matters. The kingdom feast will be for the overcomers of both the Old and New Testaments ([link]Matt. 8:11[/link]). The blessed New Jerusalem will be composed of both the Old Testament saints and the New Testament believers ([link]Rev. 21:12-14[/link]). Hence, apart from the New Testament believers, the Old Testament believers cannot obtain what God promised. To obtain and enjoy the good things of God's promise, they need the New Testament believers to perfect them. Now they are waiting for us to go on that they may be made perfect.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 7:19[/link], [link]22[/link]; [link]8:6[/link]; [link]9:23[/link]; [link]11:35[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="12">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Therefore let us also, having so great a [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]cloud of [note]2[/note]witnesses surrounding us, put away every [note]3[/note]encumbrance and the [note]4[/note][xref]b[/xref]sin which so easily entangles [i]us[/i] and [xref]c[/xref]run with [xref]d[/xref]endurance the [note]5[/note]race which is set before us,</text>
        <note num="1">The cloud is for leading people to follow the Lord ([link]Num. 9:15-22[/link]), and the Lord is in the cloud to be with the people ([link]Exo. 13:21-22[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">In Greek [i]witnesses[/i] implies the sense of martyrs.</note>
        <note num="3">Or, weight, burden, impediment. The runners of the race strip off every unnecessary weight, every encumbering burden, that nothing may impede them from winning the race.</note>
        <note num="4">Sin here refers mainly to the thing that entangles us and prevents us from running the race, just as the willful sin mentioned in [link]10:26[/link] would have kept the Hebrew believers away from the new covenant way in God's economy. (See note [link]26[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 10[/link].) Both the encumbering weight and the entangling sin would have frustrated the Hebrew believers and restrained them from running the heavenly race in the new covenant way of following Jesus, who was rejected by Judaism.</note>
        <note num="5">The Christian life is a race. All the saved Christians must run the race to win the prize ([link]1 Cor. 9:24[/link]), not salvation in the common sense ([link]Eph. 2:8[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 3:15[/link]) but a reward in a special sense ([link]10:35[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 3:14[/link]). The apostle Paul ran the race and won the prize ([link]1 Cor. 9:26-27[/link]; [link]Phil. 3:13-14[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 4:7-8[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 13:21[/link], [link]22[/link]; [link]Num. 9:15-22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 10:26[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Cor. 9:24[/link], [link]26[/link]; [link]Phil. 3:14[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 4:7[/link]; [link]Gal. 2:2[/link]; [link]5:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 10:36[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Looking away [xref]a[/xref]unto [note]2[/note]Jesus, the [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]Author and [note]4[/note]Perfecter of our faith, who for the joy set before Him endured the [xref]c[/xref]cross, despising the [xref]d[/xref]shame, and has [note]5[/note][xref]e[/xref]sat down on the right hand of the [xref]f[/xref]throne of God.</text>
        <note num="1">The Greek word translated [i]looking away unto[/i] denotes looking with undivided attention by turning away from every other object. The Hebrew believers had to look away from all the things in their environment, away from their old religion, Judaism, and its persecution, and away from all earthly things, that they might look unto Jesus, who is now seated on the right hand of the throne of God in the heavens.</note>
        <note num="2">The wonderful Jesus, who is enthroned in heaven and crowned with glory and honor ([link]2:9[/link]), is the greatest attraction in the universe. He is like an immense magnet, drawing all His seekers to Him. It is by being attracted by His charming beauty that we look away from all things other than Him. Without such a charming object, how could we look away from so many distracting things on this earth?</note>
        <note num="3">Or, Originator, Inaugurator, Leader, Pioneer, Forerunner. The same Greek word as in [link]2:10[/link]. All the overcoming saints in the Old Testament are only witnesses of faith, whereas Jesus is the Author of faith. He is the Originator, the Inaugurator, the source, and the cause of faith. In our natural man we have no believing ability. We do not have faith by ourselves. The faith by which we are saved is the precious faith that we have received from the Lord ([link]2 Pet. 1:1[/link]). When we look unto Jesus, He as the life-giving Spirit ([link]1 Cor. 15:45[/link]) transfuses us with Himself, with His believing element. Then, spontaneously, a kind of believing arises in our being, and we have the faith to believe in Him. This faith is not of ourselves but of Him who imparts Himself as the believing element into us that He may believe for us. Hence, He Himself is our faith. We live by Him as our faith; i.e., we live by His faith ([link]Gal. 2:20[/link]), not by our own.[br][br]As the Author and the source of faith, Jesus is also the Leader, the Pioneer, and the Forerunner of faith. He cut the way of faith and, as the Forerunner, took the lead to pioneer it. Hence, He can carry us in His footsteps through the pathway of faith. As we look to Him as the Originator of faith in His life and in His path on earth, and as the Perfecter of faith in His glory and on His throne in heaven, He transfuses and even infuses us with the faith that He originated and perfected.</note>
        <note num="4">Or, Finisher, Completer. Jesus is also the Finisher, the Completer, of faith. He will finish what He originated. He will complete what He inaugurated. If we look to Him continually, He will finish and complete the faith that we need for the running of the heavenly race.</note>
        <note num="5">From [link]1:3[/link] this book points us continually to the Christ seated in heaven. In all his other Epistles Paul presents to us mainly the Christ who dwells in our spirit ([link]Rom. 8:10[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 4:22[/link]) as the life-giving Spirit ([link]1 Cor. 15:45[/link]) to be our life and our everything. But in this book he points us particularly to the Christ who has sat down in heaven and who is of so many aspects, that He may care for us in every way. In Paul's other Epistles the indwelling Christ is versus our flesh, self, and natural man. In this book the heavenly Christ is contrasted to the earthly religion and all earthly things. To experience the indwelling Christ, we need to turn to our spirit and contact Him. To enjoy the heavenly Christ, we need to look away from all things on earth unto Him, who has sat down on the right hand of the throne of God. By His death and resurrection He accomplished everything that is needed by both God and man. Now in His ascension He is sitting in the heavens, in the person of the Son of God ([link]1:5[/link]) and the Son of Man ([link]2:6[/link]), in the person of God ([link]1:8[/link]) and man ([link]2:6[/link]), as the appointed Heir of all things ([link]1:2[/link]), the anointed One of God ([link]1:9[/link]), the Author of our salvation ([link]2:10[/link]), the Sanctifier ([link]2:11[/link]), the constant Succor ([link]2:16[/link]), the instant Helper ([link]4:16[/link]), the Apostle from God ([link]3:1[/link]), the High Priest ([link]2:17[/link]; [link]4:14[/link]; [link]7:26[/link]), the Minister of the true tabernacle ([link]8:2[/link]) with a more excellent ministry ([link]8:6[/link]), the surety and the Mediator of a better covenant ([link]7:22[/link]; [link]8:6[/link]; [link]12:24[/link]), the Executor of the new testament ([link]9:16-17[/link]), the Forerunner ([link]6:20[/link]), the Author and Perfecter of faith ([link]v. 2[/link]), and the great Shepherd of the sheep ([link]13:20[/link]). If we look to Him as such a wonderful and all-inclusive One, He will minister heaven, life, and strength to us, transfusing and infusing us with all that He is, that we may be able to run the heavenly race and live the heavenly life on earth. In this way He will carry us through all the lifelong pathway and lead and bring us into glory ([link]2:10[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 13:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 2:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Phil. 2:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Psa. 69:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Heb. 1:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]Heb. 4:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>For [xref]a[/xref]compare Him who has endured such [xref]b[/xref]contradiction by sinners against Himself, so that you may not grow weary, [note]1[/note]fainting in your souls.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., becoming loosened.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 3:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]John 5:16[/link], [link]18[/link]; [link]7:30[/link]; [link]10:31[/link]; [link]11:53[/link]; [link]19:1-3[/link], [link]5[/link], [link]6[/link]; [link]Matt. 27:39-44[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>You have not yet resisted unto blood, struggling against [note]1[/note]sin,</text>
        <note num="1">Sin here must refer to something evil in the sight of God that frustrates the believers and holds them back from the new covenant way, for it needs to be resisted, even unto blood.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And you have completely forgotten the exhortation which reasons with you as with sons, [xref]a[/xref]"My son, do not regard lightly the [note]1[/note]discipline of the Lord, nor faint when reproved by Him;</text>
        <note num="1">Or, chastening. So in [link]vv. 7[/link], [link]8[/link], and 11.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Prov. 3:11[/link], [link]12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>For whom the Lord loves He [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]disciplines, and He [xref]b[/xref]scourges every son whom He receives."</text>
        <note num="1">Or, chastens. So in [link]vv. 7[/link] and [link]10[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rev. 3:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Sam. 7:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>It is for [note]1[/note]discipline [i]that[/i] you endure; God deals with you as with [xref]a[/xref]sons. For what son is there whom the father does not discipline?</text>
        <note num="1">From the viewpoint of God, the persecution from Judaism that the Hebrew believers suffered was a discipline, a chastening.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Deut. 8:5[/link]; [link]Prov. 13:24[/link]; [link]19:18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>But if you are without discipline, of which all [i]sons[/i] have become partakers, then you are illegitimate and not sons.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Furthermore we have had the fathers of our flesh as [note]1[/note]discipliners and we [xref]a[/xref]respected [i]them;[/i] shall we not much more be in subjection to the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]Father of spirits and [xref]c[/xref]live?</text>
        <note num="1">Or, chasteners.</note>
        <note num="2">[i]Father of spirits[/i] is contrasted with [i]fathers of our flesh.[/i] In regeneration we are born of God ([link]John 1:13[/link]) in our spirit ([link]John 3:6[/link]). Hence, God is the Father of (our) spirits.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 20:12[/link]; [link]Eph. 6:2[/link]; cf. [link]Deut. 21:18-21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]John 1:13[/link]; [link]3:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Eph. 6:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>For they disciplined for a few days as it seemed good to them; but He, for what is profitable that we might partake of His [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]holiness.</text>
        <note num="1">Holiness is God's nature. To partake of God's holiness is to partake of His holy nature. It was common, unholy, for the Hebrew believers to remain in Judaism. They needed to be sanctified unto God's new covenant so that they could partake of God's holy nature. For that purpose, persecution was aroused to discipline them that they might be sanctified from the common.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 12:14[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:15[/link], [link]16[/link]; [link]Lev. 11:45[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Now no discipline at the present time seems to be [i]a matter[/i] of joy, but of grief; but afterward it yields the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]peaceable fruit of righteousness to those who have been exercised by it.</text>
        <note num="1">Peace is the fruit of righteousness ([link]Isa. 32:17[/link]). Holiness is the inward nature, whereas righteousness is the outward behavior. God's discipline helps the believers not only to partake of His holiness but also to be right with both God and man, that in such a situation of righteousness they may enjoy peace as a sweet fruit, a peaceable fruit of righteousness.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 12:14[/link]; [link]Isa. 32:17[/link]; [link]James 3:18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Therefore [note]1[/note]set straight the [xref]a[/xref]hands which hang down and the paralyzed knees,</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., set upright.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Isa. 35:3[/link]; [link]Job 4:3[/link], [link]4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And make [xref]a[/xref]straight [note]1[/note]paths for your feet, that what is lame may not be [note]2[/note]put out of joint but rather may be [xref]b[/xref]healed.</text>
        <note num="1">The Christian life is not a matter of theoretical doctrines for the mind to think about. It must consist of practical paths for our feet to walk on. All the sound, healthy doctrines in the Bible are paths that can be walked on. This is especially true with the book of Hebrews. First, this book ministers to us the highest and healthiest doctrines concerning Christ and His new covenant. Then, based on the proper doctrines that it shows us, it charges us to run the race and make straight paths for our feet. The first section of this book ([link]1:1-10:18[/link]) deals with doctrines, and the second ([link]10:19-13:25[/link]) deals with the race and the paths.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, dislocated, wrenched. An alternate meaning, [i]turned aside,[/i] as in [link]1 Tim. 1:6[/link]; [link]5:15[/link]; and [link]2 Tim. 4:4[/link], does not match the antithesis that follows, "but rather may be healed," nor does it fit the context like the first meaning. The implication of the context is that the staggering Hebrew believers should abandon all appearance of the practices of Judaism (i.e., make straight paths) that they, the lame members (limbs) of the Body, might not fall into apostasy (i.e., not be put out of joint) but rather be brought fully into the new covenant way (i.e., be healed).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Isa. 40:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Isa. 6:10[/link]; [link]Matt. 13:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Pursue peace with all men and [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]sanctification, without which no one will see the Lord;</text>
        <note num="1">With God, holiness is His holy nature; with us, holiness is our sanctification, our being separated unto God. (See note [link]2[sup]3[/sup] in Rom. 1[/link].) The implication here is that while we are pursuing peace with all men, we must pay attention to the matter of sanctification before God. Our pursuing of peace with all men must be balanced by our sanctification before God, our being separated unto God, without which no one will see the Lord and have fellowship with Him.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 12:18[/link]; [link]14:19[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 2:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 12:10[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 7:1[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Looking carefully lest anyone [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]fall away from the [xref]b[/xref]grace of God; lest any [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]root of bitterness springing up trouble [i]you,[/i] and through this many be [xref]d[/xref]defiled;</text>
        <note num="1">The grace of God came to us through Christ ([link]John 1:14[/link], [link]17[/link]). Hence, it is also the grace of Christ ([link]2 Cor. 13:14[/link]; [link]12:9[/link]). In our experience this grace is just Christ Himself ([link]Gal. 6:18[/link], cf. [link]2 Tim. 4:22[/link]). When we fall from grace we are brought to nought, separated from Christ ([link]Gal. 5:4[/link]). Regarding this matter, Paul warned the churches of Galatia, which were in the same danger as the Hebrew believers, not to be separated from Christ by being turned aside to the law of the Jewish religion, lest they fall away from the grace of God, which is Christ Himself. We should not fall away from grace but should have grace ([link]v. 28[/link]), be confirmed by grace ([link]13:9[/link]), and stand in grace ([link]Rom. 5:2[/link]). Both Galatians and Hebrews close with the blessing of grace ([link]Gal. 6:18[/link]; [link]Heb. 13:25[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">According to the implication of the context, the root of bitterness must be a Judaizer who would have caused the Hebrew believers to be turned aside from the grace of God to the rituals of Judaism and thus to defile themselves in the sight of God, neglecting the holiness of God.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gal. 5:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]John 1:17[/link]; [link]Rom. 5:2[/link]; [link]6:14[/link]; [link]Heb. 4:16[/link]; [link]12:28[/link]; [link]13:9[/link], [link]25[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Deut. 29:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]2 Cor. 7:1[/link]; [link]Lev. 11:44[/link]; [link]Neh. 13:29[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Lest there be any [xref]a[/xref]fornicator or profane person like [xref]b[/xref]Esau, who for one meal gave up his own [note]1[/note]birthright.</text>
        <note num="1">Esau's birthright as the firstborn son of Isaac was the double portion of land, the priesthood, and the kingship. Because of Esau's profaneness in giving up his birthright, the double portion of land was given to Joseph ([link]1 Chron. 5:1-2[/link]), the priesthood was passed to Levi ([link]Deut. 33:8-10[/link]), and the kingship was assigned to Judah ([link]Gen. 49:10[/link]; [link]1 Chron. 5:2[/link]).[br][br]We Christians, born of God, are the firstfruits of His creatures ([link]James 1:18[/link]) that He has reaped in His creation. In that sense we are the firstborn sons of God. Hence, the church, composed of us, is called the church of the firstborn ([link]v. 23[/link]). As the firstborn sons of God, we have the birthright. This includes the inheritance of the earth ([link]2:5-6[/link]), the priesthood ([link]Rev. 20:6[/link]), and the kingship ([link]Rev. 20:4[/link]), which will be the main blessings in the coming kingdom and which the profane, world-loving-and-seeking Christians will lose at the Lord's coming back. Eventually, this birthright will be a reward given to the overcoming Christians in the millennial kingdom. Any worldly enjoyment, even one meal, could cause us to forfeit this birthright of ours. After such a serious warning, if the Hebrew believers had still preferred to indulge in "one meal" of their old religion, they would have missed the full enjoyment of Christ and would have lost the kingdom rest with all its blessings.[br][br]Esau was not the only one who lost his birthright ([link]Gen. 25:29-34[/link]); Reuben was another who lost the blessing of the birthright ([link]Gen. 49:3-4[/link]; [link]1 Chron. 5:1[/link]). Esau lost it because of his lust in eating. Reuben lost it because of the defilement of his lust. Both cases should be warnings to us. The word [i]lest there be any fornicator[/i] in this verse might have been written with Reuben as the background.[br][br]Actually, what we are privileged to enjoy in Christ is the foretaste of the blessings in the coming kingdom. The proper enjoyment of this foretaste will usher us into the full taste of the kingdom blessings. If we do not enjoy Christ today as our good land, as defined in note [link]9[sup]1[/sup][/link] of [link]ch. 4[/link], how can we enter into His rest in the kingdom and inherit the earth with Him? If we do not exercise our priesthood today to contact Him and prayerfully minister to Him, how can we fulfill our priestly duty in the kingdom? If we do not exercise our spirit with the God-given authority to rule our self, our flesh, our entire being, and the enemy with all his power of darkness today, how can we be Christ's co-kings and rule the nations with Him in His kingdom ([link]Rev. 2:26-27[/link])? Our enjoyment of Christ and the practice of the priesthood and kingship today are the preparation and qualification for our participating in Christ's kingdom tomorrow!</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 13:4[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 5:11[/link]; [link]6:9[/link], [link]10[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:19[/link], [link]21[/link]; [link]Eph. 5:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Gen. 25:29-34[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>For you know that also afterward, when he [xref]a[/xref]desired to inherit the blessing, he was rejected; for he found [note]1[/note]no place for repentance, even though he sought it with tears.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]No place for repentance[/i] does not mean that Esau had no ground to repent; it means that he had no ground, no way, to reverse by repentance the result of what he had done.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 27:30-40[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>For you have not come forward to [i]a[/i] [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref][i]mountain[/i] which could be [xref]b[/xref]touched and which was set on [xref]c[/xref]fire, and to [xref]d[/xref]darkness and [xref]e[/xref]gloom and whirlwind,</text>
        <note num="1">The things mentioned in [link]vv. 18-19[/link] are earthly and physical, signifying the side of the law, where everyone, including Moses, was in fear and trembling ([link]vv. 19-21[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 19:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Exo. 19:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Exo. 19:18[/link]; [link]Deut. 4:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Deut. 5:23[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Exo. 20:21[/link]; [link]Deut. 5:22[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And to the [xref]a[/xref]sound of a trumpet and to the [xref]b[/xref]voice of words, [i]because of[/i] which those who heard [xref]c[/xref]entreated that no further word be spoken to them;</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 19:13[/link], [link]16[/link], [link]19[/link]; [link]20:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Deut. 4:12[/link]; [link]Exo. 19:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Exo. 20:19[/link]; [link]Deut. 18:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>For they could not bear that which was being commanded: [xref]a[/xref]"If even a beast touch the mountain, it shall be stoned."</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 19:12[/link], [link]13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And so fearful was the sight, Moses said, "I am [xref]a[/xref]full of fear and trembling."</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Deut. 9:19[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>But you have come forward to [note]1[/note]Mount [xref]a[/xref]Zion and to the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]city of the [xref]c[/xref]living God, the [xref]d[/xref]heavenly Jerusalem; and to [xref]e[/xref]myriads of angels, to the [note]3[/note]universal gathering;</text>
        <note num="1">The things mentioned in [link]vv. 22-24[/link] are heavenly and spiritual, in contrast to the earthly and physical things listed in [link]vv. 18-19[/link]. These things signify the side of grace, where both the firstborn and the spirits of righteous men are saved by grace. The people under the old covenant came to the side of the law, whereas we Christians, who are under the new covenant, come to the side of grace. Hence, we are not under the law but under grace ([link]Rom. 6:14[/link]). This portion of the word ([link]vv. 18-24[/link]), like [link]Gal. 4:21-31[/link], shows us that we are not under the bondage of the law but under the freedom of grace to be the heirs of the inheritance. This is our birthright! We should not give this up by falling away from grace ([link]v. 15[/link]), but should have grace ([link]v. 28[/link]). The things on the side of grace are heavenly, but not all are in heaven yet. A great number of the firstborn of the church are still on earth, while the spirits of righteous men, who are the Old Testament saints, are in Paradise, where Abraham is ([link]Luke 16:22-23[/link], [link]25-26[/link]) and where the Lord Jesus and the saved robber went after they died on the cross ([link]Luke 23:43[/link]).[br][br]None of the six items listed on the side of the law is pleasant. First, there is a mountain set on fire. Who would approach such a place? Then there are the darkness, the gloom, and the stormy whirlwind. Last, there are the terrifying sound of a trumpet and the solemn, warning voice of words. All these present a fearsome sight. On the side of grace, however, everything is pleasant. The eight items here can be considered four pairs. The elevated Mount Zion and the beautiful heavenly Jerusalem are the first pair, denoting God's habitation and the center of His universal administration. What a lovely place! The celebrating, jubilant angels, so closely related to the heirs of salvation to whom they minister ([link]1:14[/link]), and the blessed firstborn of the church form the second pair in the scene. What a joyful demonstration of an angelic gathering! They celebrate the participation by the human heirs of salvation, the church of the firstborn, in the blessings of the new covenant. God, the Judge of all, and the spirits of righteous men, the Old Testament saints (their bodies, not resurrected, were not worthy to be listed in this portion) are linked as the third pair, showing that God, being righteous, justifies the righteous saints of old because of their faith. The dear Lord Jesus, the Mediator of the new covenant, which is a better covenant, and His precious sprinkled blood, which speaks something better, compose the last pair, indicating that a better covenant was enacted with Jesus' better blood, that Jesus died and bequeathed this new covenant as a new testament to His believers, and that He is now the Mediator, the Executor, of this new testament, bringing about the full realization of all the blessed facts contained within it. What a pleasant scene! What a contrast to the scene on the side of the law, where no God, no Savior, and even no angels are mentioned! It is no wonder that not one saved person is seen there. In the scene of grace there is the justifying God, the Savior, who is the Mediator of His new testament, with His speaking blood, the ministering angels with the assembly (the church) of the saved ones, and the spirits of the justified saints. On the side of the law the scene ends with the terrifying sound of a trumpet and the warning words. On the side of grace the scene ends with a sympathizing Mediator and a vindicating speaking. After seeing such a contrast, who would be so foolish as to leave the side of grace and turn to the side of the law? All eight items on the side of grace are not only heavenly and spiritual but also eternal. Hence, even when heaven is shaken ([link]v. 26[/link]), these eight items that are eternal will still remain ([link]v. 27[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]10[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 11[/link].</note>
        <note num="3">Or, festal gathering. The Greek word means [i]universal gathering, whole[/i] or [i]full assembly,[/i] and is used to denote a group of people gathered to celebrate a public festival, such as the Olympic games. The entire new covenant age is a festival, and the myriads of angels, who are the ministering spirits rendering service to the heirs of salvation ([link]1:14[/link]) under the new covenant, are a universal gathering celebrating the marvelous festival of "so great a salvation" ([link]2:3[/link]), the greatest and most exciting "game" in the universe! The Lord's word in [link]Luke 15:7[/link], [link]10[/link], and [link]1 Pet. 1:12[/link] may indicate this.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 2:6[/link]; [link]Rev. 14:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 11:10[/link], [link]16[/link]; [link]13:14[/link]; [link]Rev. 21:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 3:12[/link]; [link]9:14[/link]; [link]10:31[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Gal. 4:26[/link]; [link]Heb. 11:16[/link]; [link]Rev. 21:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Rev. 5:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>And to the [xref]a[/xref]church of the [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]firstborn, who have been [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]enrolled in the heavens; and to God, the [xref]d[/xref]Judge of all; and to the spirits of righteous men who have been made perfect;</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]16[sup]1[/sup][/link], par. 2.</note>
        <note num="2">Though the firstborn of the church are not yet in heaven, they are enrolled in the heavens.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 2:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]James 1:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Luke 10:20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Gen. 18:25[/link]; [link]Psa. 50:6[/link]; [link]94:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And to Jesus, the [xref]a[/xref]Mediator of a [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]new covenant; and to the [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]blood of [xref]d[/xref]sprinkling, which [note]3[/note]speaks something better than [i]that of[/i] [xref]e[/xref]Abel.</text>
        <note num="1">The Greek word for [i]new[/i] here means [i]fresh, youthful,[/i] with respect to age, while the word for [i]new[/i] in [link]8:8[/link], [link]13[/link], and [link]9:15[/link] means [i]new, fresh,[/i] with respect to quality.</note>
        <note num="2">In this book the blood of Christ is particularly prominent and crucial. It is the blood of the eternal covenant ([link]13:20[/link]), with which the new and better covenant was enacted ([link]10:29[/link]). Through this blood Christ entered once for all into the Holy of Holies and obtained an eternal redemption for us ([link]9:12[/link]). By this blood Christ cleansed the heavens and all things in the heavens ([link]9:22-24[/link]). This blood sanctifies us ([link]13:12[/link]; [link]10:29[/link]), purifies our conscience to serve the living God ([link]9:14[/link]), and speaks something better for us than the blood of Abel ([link]v. 24[/link]). It is in this blood that we have boldness for entering the Holy of Holies ([link]10:19[/link]). We should not regard this blood common, like animal blood; if we do, we will suffer God's punishment ([link]10:29[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">The blood of Christ not only redeems, sanctifies, and purifies; it also speaks. It is the speaking blood, speaking something better than the blood of Abel. Abel's blood speaks to God for accusation and vengeance ([link]Gen. 4:10-15[/link]), whereas Christ's blood speaks to God for forgiveness, justification, reconciliation, and redemption. Moreover, this precious blood speaks to God on our behalf, saying that by the blood (as unveiled in this book) the new covenant, which is eternal, has been enacted, and that in this new covenant God must give Himself and all His blessings to the believers in Christ who receive this covenant out of faith.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 8:6[/link]; [link]9:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 8:8[/link]; [link]9:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 9:12[/link], [link]14[/link]; [link]10:19[/link]; [link]13:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Exo. 24:8[/link]; [link]Lev. 4:6[/link], [link]7[/link], [link]17[/link], [link]18[/link]; [link]16:14[/link], [link]15[/link], [link]18[/link], [link]19[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Gen. 4:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>See that you do not refuse Him who [xref]a[/xref]speaks, for if those did not [xref]b[/xref]escape who refused Him who warned [i]them[/i] upon the earth, much more we [i]shall not[/i] [xref]c[/xref][i]escape[/i] who turn away from Him who [i]warns[/i] from heaven,</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 1:2[/link]; [link]2:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Deut. 17:2-6[/link]; [link]Heb. 10:28[/link]; [link]2:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 10:29[/link]; [link]2:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>Whose voice at that time [xref]a[/xref]shook the earth but now has promised, saying, [xref]b[/xref]"Yet once more I will shake not only the earth but also heaven."</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 19:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Hag. 2:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>And this [i]word,[/i] "Yet once more," shows clearly the [xref]a[/xref]removal of the things being shaken as being of things having been made, that the things which are not shaken may [xref]b[/xref]remain.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 1:10-12[/link]; [link]Matt. 24:35[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 3:10[/link]; [link]Rev. 21:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 1:11-12[/link]; [link]13:8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>Therefore receiving an unshakable [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]kingdom, let us [note]2[/note]have [xref]b[/xref]grace, through which we may [xref]c[/xref]serve God [xref]d[/xref]well-pleasingly with piety and [xref]e[/xref]fear;</text>
        <note num="1">The gospel that the New Testament has preached to us is the gospel of the kingdom ([link]Matt. 3:1-2[/link]; [link]4:17[/link], [link]23[/link]; [link]10:7[/link]; [link]24:14[/link]). We were regenerated into the kingdom ([link]John 3:5[/link]) and were transferred into the kingdom ([link]Col. 1:13[/link]). Now we are in the kingdom ([link]Rev. 1:9[/link]), which today is the proper church life ([link]Rom. 14:17[/link]). However, what we are in now and what is in the church today is the kingdom in its reality, whereas what will come with Christ's return in the future will be the kingdom in its manifestation.[br][br]The kingdom in its reality, or the reality of the kingdom, is an exercise and a discipline to us ([link]Matt. 5:3[/link], [link]10[/link], [link]20[/link]; [link]7:21[/link]) in the church today whereas the kingdom in its manifestation, or the manifestation of the kingdom, will be a reward and an enjoyment to us ([link]Matt. 16:27[/link]; [link]25:21[/link], [link]23[/link]) in the millennial kingdom in the coming age. If we take the Spirit's exercise and God's discipline in the reality of the kingdom today, we will receive the Lord's reward and enter into the enjoyment of the coming Sabbath rest ([link]4:9[/link]) in the manifestation of the kingdom in the coming age; otherwise, we will miss the coming kingdom, we will not be rewarded with the manifestation of the kingdom at the Lord's coming back, we will have no right to enter into the glory of the kingdom to participate in Christ's reign in the millennial kingdom, and we will lose our birthright and therefore will be unable to inherit the earth in the coming age, to be the royal priests serving God and Christ in His manifested glory, and to be Christ's co-kings ruling all the nations with His divine authority ([link]Rev. 20:4[/link], [link]6[/link]). To miss the coming kingdom and to forfeit our birthright does not mean that we will perish. It means that we will lose the reward but not our salvation. (See note [link]35[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 10[/link].) We will suffer loss but still will be saved, yet so as through fire ([link]1 Cor. 3:14-15[/link]). This is the basic concept on which all five warnings in this book are given and with which they are all pervaded. All the negative points of these warnings are related to the suffering of the loss of the reward in the coming kingdom, whereas all the positive points are related to the reward and enjoyment of the kingdom. All seven epistles in [link]Rev. 2[/link] and [link book="Rev."]3[/link] conclude with this same concept &amp;#8212; the reward of the kingdom or the loss of it. Only in light of this concept can we rightly understand and properly apply the word in [link]Matt. 5:20[/link]; [link]7:21-23[/link]; [link]16:24-27[/link]; [link]19:23-30[/link]; [link]24:46-51[/link]; [link]25:11-13[/link], [link]21[/link], [link]23[/link], [link]26-30[/link]; [link]Luke 12:42-48[/link]; [link]19:17[/link], [link]19[/link], [link]22-27[/link]; [link]Rom. 14:10[/link], [link]12[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 3:8[/link], [link]13-15[/link]; [link]4:5[/link]; [link]9:24-27[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 5:10[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 4:7-8[/link]; [link]Heb. 2:3[/link]; [link]4:1[/link], [link]9[/link], [link]11[/link]; [link]6:4-8[/link]; [link]10:26-31[/link], [link]35-39[/link]; [link]12:16-17[/link], [link]28-29[/link]; and [link]Rev. 2:7[/link], [link]10-11[/link], [link]17[/link], [link]26-27[/link]; [link]3:4-5[/link], [link]11-12[/link], [link]20[/link]; [link]22:12[/link]. If we do not have this concept, the interpretation of these verses falls into either the extreme objectiveness of the Calvinist school or the extreme subjectiveness of the Arminian school. Neither of these schools recognizes the reward of the kingdom; even more, they do not see the suffering of the loss of the kingdom reward. Hence, both consider all the negative points in these verses as referring to perdition. The Calvinist school, believing in eternal salvation (i.e., that once a person is saved, he will never perish), regards all these negative points as applying to the perdition of false believers; while the Arminian school, believing that a saved person will perish if he falls, regards these points as applying to the perdition of believers who have fallen. But the complete revelation of the Bible shows that these negative points refer to the suffering of the loss of the kingdom reward. God's salvation is eternal; once we obtain it, we will never lose it ([link]John 10:28-29[/link]). But we may suffer the loss of the kingdom reward, even though we still will be saved ([link]1 Cor. 3:8[/link], [link]14-15[/link]). The warnings in Hebrews do not refer to the loss of eternal salvation but to the loss of the kingdom reward. The Hebrew believers had received the kingdom, but they risked losing the reward in the manifestation of the kingdom if they shrank back from the grace of God, from God's new covenant way. This was the writer's main concern in warning the staggering Hebrew believers.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, take. To have grace, especially for the Hebrew believers, was to remain in the new covenant to enjoy Christ.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]John 3:5[/link]; [link]Rom. 14:17[/link]; [link]Rev. 1:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 4:16[/link]; [link]12:15[/link]; [link]13:9[/link], [link]25[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 9:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 13:21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]2 Cor. 7:1[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:17[/link]; [link]3:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>For our God is also a [note]1[/note]consuming [xref]a[/xref]fire.</text>
        <note num="1">God is holy; holiness is His nature. Whatever does not correspond with His holy nature, He, as the consuming fire, will consume. If the Hebrew believers had turned aside to Judaism, which was common (unholy) in the sight of God, they would have become unholy, and the holy God as the consuming fire would consume them. God is not only righteous but also holy. To satisfy God's righteousness we need to be justified through the redemption of Christ. To meet the demands of His holiness we need to be sanctified, to be made holy by the heavenly, present, and living Christ. Romans stresses more the matter of justification ([link]Rom. 3:24[/link]) for God's righteousness ([link]Rom. 3:25-26[/link]), whereas Hebrews emphasizes more the matter of sanctification ([link]2:11[/link]; [link]10:10[/link], [link]14[/link], [link]29[/link]; [link]13:12[/link]) for God's holiness ([link]v. 14[/link]). For their sanctification, it was necessary that the Hebrew believers separate themselves from the unholy Judaism unto the holy God, who has fully expressed Himself in the Son under the new covenant; otherwise, they would have defiled themselves with their old, profane religion and would be dealt with by the holy God as the consuming fire. That would be fearsome ([link]10:31[/link])! It is no wonder that Paul was very concerned about the fear of the Lord ([link]2 Cor. 5:11[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Deut. 4:24[/link]; [link]9:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="13">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Let [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]brotherly love [note]2[/note]continue.</text>
        <note num="1">As indicated by its content, this chapter was written with a view to a proper church life. Nearly everything mentioned here, such as brotherly love and hospitality, is for the church life, not only for the Christian life.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, remain.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 12:10[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 4:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Do not forget [xref]a[/xref]hospitality, for through this some, without knowing it, have [xref]b[/xref]entertained angels.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 12:13[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 4:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Gen. 18:2-8[/link]; [link]19:1-3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Remember those who are imprisoned as bound with [i]them,[/i] those who are [xref]a[/xref]ill-treated as being yourselves also [i]likewise treated[/i] in body.</text>
        <note num="1">This is to suffer with the suffering members of the Body of Christ, the church ([link]1 Cor. 12:26[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 11:25[/link], [link]37[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>[i]Let[/i] [note]1[/note]marriage [i]be held[/i] in honor [note]2[/note]among all, and the bed undefiled; for [xref]a[/xref]fornicators and adulterers God will [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]judge.</text>
        <note num="1">In the church life, contact between brothers and sisters is unavoidable. Hence, to be protected from falling into defilement, we must hold marriage in honor and not behave loosely. This is a matter that seriously affects our birthright in God's economy. Reuben lost the birthright because of his defilement ([link]Gen. 49:3-4[/link]; [link]1 Chron. 5:1[/link]), and Joseph received it because of his purity ([link]1 Chron. 5:1[/link]; [link]Gen. 39:7-12[/link]; see note [link book="Heb."]16[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 12[/link]). God will judge fornicators and adulterers, and the church too must judge them ([link]1 Cor. 5:1-2[/link], [link]11-13[/link]). Nothing damages the saints and the church life as much as this defilement.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, in every way.</note>
        <note num="3">This book concerns God's holiness. The holy God will not tolerate any defilement among us. He will judge His people ([link]10:30[/link]; [link]12:23[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 12:16[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 5:11[/link]; [link]6:9[/link], [link]10[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:19[/link], [link]21[/link]; [link]Eph. 5:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. [link]1 Thes. 4:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Let your way of life be without the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]love of money, being [xref]b[/xref]satisfied with the things which are at hand; for He Himself has said, [xref]c[/xref]"I shall by no means give you up, neither by any means shall I abandon you";</text>
        <note num="1">Surely money lovers cannot enter into the reality of the church life. We should always be satisfied with what we have so that we cannot be distracted from the church life by mammon. Since we have the Lord as our Helper, we should be content and at peace that we may be kept fully in the enjoyment of the church life.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]2 Tim. 3:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Phil. 4:11[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 6:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Deut. 31:6[/link]; [link]Josh. 1:5[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>So that being of good courage, we say, [xref]a[/xref]"The Lord is my Helper, and I will not fear. What shall man do to me?"</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 118:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Remember the ones [xref]a[/xref]leading you, who have [xref]b[/xref]spoken to you the word of God; and considering the issue of their [xref]c[/xref]manner of life, [xref]d[/xref]imitate their faith.</text>
        <note num="1">This is essential in the church life. The ministers of the word of God should have a manner of life that issues in an example of faith for the church members, the receivers of the word of God, to imitate. Then the church members not only will receive the word that the ministers minister but also will imitate the ministers' faith, which is expressed in their manner of life.[br][br][link]Verse 7[/link] is a continuation of [link]vv. 5-6[/link]. [i]Manner of life[/i] must refer to the living and behavior pursued by those ministers of the word of God, in which they had no love of money and were satisfied with what they had ([link]v. 5a[/link]). [i]Their faith[/i] must refer to the fact that they trusted in the Lord, their Helper, for their living ([link]vv. 5b-6[/link]). The word that they ministered and the life that they lived must have been entirely Christ, and their faith must have been the faith in Christ, of which Christ is both the Author and the Perfecter ([link]12:2[/link]). Such a manner of life and such a faith were surely worthy to be imitated by the believers, who received the word of God that the ministers ministered and who considered the issue of their manner of life.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 13:17[/link], [link]24[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 5:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 4:31[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Thes. 1:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 6:12[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 4:16[/link]; [link]11:1[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 1:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Jesus Christ is the [xref]a[/xref]same yesterday and today, [i]yes,[/i] even forever.</text>
        <note num="1">Christ, who is the word that the ministers of the word of God in [link]v. 7[/link] preached and taught, who is the life that they lived, and who is the Author and Perfecter of their faith, is perpetual, unchangeable, and unchanging. He remains the same forever ([link]1:11-12[/link]). There must not be another Jesus and another gospel preached in the church ([link]2 Cor. 11:4[/link]; [link]Gal. 1:8-9[/link]). For a true and steadfast church life, we must hold on to the Christ who is the same yesterday and today, and even forever, and must not be carried away by various strange teachings ([link]v. 9[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 1:12[/link]; [link]Rev. 1:18[/link]; [link]22:13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Do not be [xref]a[/xref]carried away by [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]various strange teachings, for it is good for the heart to be [note]2[/note]confirmed by [xref]c[/xref]grace, not by the [note]3[/note][xref]d[/xref]food [i]of sacrifices,[/i] by which those who walk were not profited.</text>
        <note num="1">Various strange teachings are always used by Satan to cause dissension and even division in the church. Because of this, the apostle charged people not to teach different things ([link]1 Tim. 1:3[/link]). The various strange teachings must have been taught at that time by the Judaizers. The writer warned the Hebrew believers not to let the teachings of the Judaizers carry them away from the church life under the new covenant.</note>
        <note num="2">At that time, to be confirmed by grace was to remain in the new covenant to enjoy Christ as grace ([link]Gal. 5:4[/link]) and not to be carried away back to Judaism to participate in the eating of food (sacrifices) in the Jews' religious ceremonies.</note>
        <note num="3">The food mentioned here, being in contrast to grace, is the food used in the ceremonial observances of the old covenant ([link]9:10[/link]; [link]Col. 2:16[/link]). The Judaizers attempted to use such food to carry away the Hebrew believers from the enjoyment of grace, which is the participation in Christ in the new covenant.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 4:14[/link]; cf. [link]Acts 20:30[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 1:3[/link]; [link]Gal. 1:6-9[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 11:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 12:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Heb. 9:9-10[/link]; [link]Col. 2:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>We have an [note]1[/note]altar from which they who are serving the tabernacle have no right to [xref]a[/xref]eat.</text>
        <note num="1">This altar must be the cross on which the Lord Jesus offered Himself as the sacrifice for our sins ([link]10:12[/link]). According to the regulations concerning the offerings in the Old Testament, the sacrifice for sin, or the sin offering, the blood of which was brought into the Holy of Holies or the Holy Place to make expiation, afforded the offering priest or the offerer nothing to eat; the entire offering had to be burned up ([link]Lev. 4:2-12[/link]; [link]16:27[/link]; [link]6:30[/link]). Hence, those who serve the tabernacle have no right to eat from the altar of the sin offering (which in the New Testament fulfillment is the Lord's cross). [link]Verse 10[/link] is a strong argument against the Judaizers' using of food in their strange teachings to attempt to carry away the new covenant believers from the enjoyment of Christ. The Judaizers' emphasis was on the food that they enjoyed in their religious services. But the writer of this book argued that in the sin offering, the basic offering for yearly expiation ([link]Lev. 16[/link]), there was nothing for anyone to eat. With the sin offering, it is not a matter of eating it but a matter of receiving its efficacy. Now the real sin offering is Christ, who offered Himself to God for our sin and accomplished full redemption (better than expiation &amp;#8212; see note [link]12[sup]2[/sup] in ch. 9[/link]) for us that we may be brought into the enjoyment of God's grace in Him under the new covenant. What we need today is not to eat the food of the old covenant services but to receive the efficacy of Christ's offering and follow Him in the new covenant grace outside the camp, outside the Jewish religion.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]1 Cor. 10:18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>For the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]bodies of those animals whose [xref]b[/xref]blood is brought into the [i]Holy of[/i] Holies for sin by the high priest are burned up outside the camp.</text>
        <note num="1">The blood of the sin offering being brought into the Holy of Holies on the Day of Expiation to make expiation for the people and the bodies of the animals being burned up outside the camp ([link]Lev. 16:14-16[/link], [link]27[/link]) typify the blood of Christ, who is the real sin offering, being brought into the true Holy of Holies to accomplish redemption for us and the body of Christ being sacrificed for us outside the gate of the city of Jerusalem ([link]v. 12[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Lev. 16:27[/link]; [link]4:21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Lev. 16:14-16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Therefore also Jesus, that He might [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]sanctify the people through His own [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]blood, suffered [xref]c[/xref]outside the [note]3[/note]gate.</text>
        <note num="1">This book unveils to us that God's heavenly calling is to make us a holy people ([link]3:1[/link]), a people sanctified unto God. Christ is the Sanctifier ([link]2:11[/link]). He suffered death on the cross, shedding His blood, and entered the Holy of Holies with His blood ([link]9:12[/link]) that by the heavenly ministry ([link]8:2[/link], [link]6[/link]) of His heavenly priesthood ([link]7:26[/link]) He might be able to do the sanctifying work, and that we might enter within the veil by His blood to participate in Him as the heavenly Sanctifier. By participating in Him in this way, we are enabled to follow Him outside the camp by the sanctifying pathway of the cross. See notes [link]12[sup]2[/sup][/link] and [link]13[sup]1[/sup][/link].</note>
        <note num="2">The Lord's blood, through which He entered into the Holy of Holies ([link]9:12[/link]), opened the new and living way, enabling us to enter within the veil to enjoy Him in the heavens as the glorified One ([link]10:19-20[/link]); and His body, which was sacrificed for us on the cross, cut the narrow way of the cross, enabling us to go outside the camp to follow Him on earth as the suffering One ([link]v. 13[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">This is the gate of the city of Jerusalem. The city signifies the earthly realm, while the camp signifies human organization. Together, the two signify one thing, the Jewish religion with its two aspects, the earthly and the human. Judaism is both earthly and human.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 2:11[/link]; [link]10:14[/link], [link]29[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 9:12[/link], [link]14[/link]; [link]10:19[/link]; [link]12:24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]John 19:17-18[/link], [link]20[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Let us therefore go forth [xref]a[/xref]unto Him [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]outside the [note]2[/note]camp, bearing His [xref]c[/xref]reproach.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Outside the camp[/i] and [i]within the veil[/i] ([link]6:19[/link]) are two very striking points in this book. To enter within the veil means to enter into the Holy of Holies, where the Lord is enthroned in glory, and to go outside the camp means to come out of religion, whence the Lord was cast in rejection. This signifies that we must be in our spirit, where experientially the practical Holy of Holies is today, and outside religion, where the practical camp is today. The more we are in our spirit, enjoying the heavenly Christ, the more we will come outside the camp of religion, following the suffering Jesus. Being in our spirit to enjoy the glorified Christ enables us to come outside the camp of religion to follow the rejected Jesus. The more we remain in our spirit to contact the heavenly Christ, who is in glory, the more we will go forth outside the camp of religion unto the lowly Jesus to suffer with Him. By contacting Christ in the heavens and enjoying His glorification, we are energized to take the narrow pathway of the cross on earth and bear the reproach of Jesus. First, this book gives us a clear vision of the heavenly Christ and the heavenly Holy of Holies, and then it shows us how to walk on the earth in the pathway of the cross, i.e., how to go forth unto Jesus outside the camp, outside religion, bearing His reproach. Even Moses, after the children of Israel worshipped the golden calf ([link]Exo. 32[/link]), moved to a place outside the camp, where everyone who sought the Lord went to meet with him; for both the Lord's presence and the Lord's speaking were there ([link]Exo. 33:7-11[/link]). We must go outside the camp that we may enjoy the Lord's presence and hear His speaking. All these things are necessary for the practical and proper church life.[br][br]The Holy of Holies, the pathway of the cross (signified by the going forth unto Jesus outside the camp, bearing His reproach), and the kingdom are three crucial matters set forth in this book. The Holy of Holies with its rich supply enables us to take the narrow, difficult pathway of the cross, and the pathway of the cross ushers us into the kingdom in its manifestation that we may obtain the reward of glory.</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]12[sup]3[/sup][/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 12:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 13:11[/link]; [link]Exo. 33:7-11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 11:26[/link]; [link]Rom. 15:3[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 4:14[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 12:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>For we do not have here a [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]remaining city, but [note]2[/note]we [xref]b[/xref]seek after the [xref]c[/xref]one to come.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, permanent.</note>
        <note num="2">The writer of this book considered himself and his readers real river-crossing Hebrews, like the Patriarchs ([link]11:9-10[/link], [link]13-16[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Heb. 10:34[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 11:10[/link], [link]14[/link], [link]16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rev. 21:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Through Him then let us [xref]a[/xref]offer up a sacrifice of [xref]b[/xref]praise continually to God, that is, the [xref]c[/xref]fruit of lips [xref]d[/xref]confessing His name.</text>
        <note num="1">[link]Verse 15[/link] is a continuation of [link]vv. 8-14[/link]. Since in the church life we enjoy the unchanging Christ as grace and follow Him outside religion, we should offer through Him spiritual sacrifices to God. First, in the church we should offer up through Him a sacrifice of praise to God continually. In the church He sings in us hymns of praise unto God the Father ([link]2:12[/link]). In the church we too should praise God the Father through Him. Eventually, in the church He and we, we and He, praise the Father together in the mingled spirit. He, as the life-giving Spirit, praises the Father in our spirit, and we, by our spirit, praise the Father in His Spirit. This is the best and highest sacrifice that we can offer to God through Him. This is greatly needed in the church meetings.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Pet. 2:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Heb. 2:12[/link]; [link]Eph. 5:19-20[/link]; [link]Col. 3:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Hosea 14:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Phil. 2:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>But do not forget doing good and [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]sharing [i]with others,[/i] for with such [xref]b[/xref]sacrifices God is well pleased.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., fellowshipping. Doing good refers to giving, and fellowshipping refers to sharing, i.e., having fellowship in the needs of the saints. This kind of doing good and fellowshipping with others also are sacrifices that we should offer to God. These too are necessary for a proper church life. It is truly improper if in the church some needy saints are not well cared for and ministered to. This means that the fellowshipping with others is absent or inadequate.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 6:10[/link]; [link]Rom. 12:13[/link]; [link]Phil. 4:15-16[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 8:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Phil. 4:18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Obey the ones [xref]a[/xref]leading you and [xref]b[/xref]submit to [i]them,[/i] for they [xref]c[/xref]watch over your souls as those who will render an account, that they may do this with joy and not groaning; for this would be unprofitable to you.</text>
        <note num="1">This is vitally necessary in the church life.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 13:7[/link], [link]24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Cor. 16:16[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 5:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Acts 20:28-31[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 5:2[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>[note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Pray for us, for we are persuaded that we have a [xref]b[/xref]good conscience, desiring in all things to conduct ourselves honorably.</text>
        <note num="1">Praying for the apostles is another aspect of the church life.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 6:19[/link]; [link]Col. 4:3[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 5:25[/link]; [link]2 Thes. 3:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 23:1[/link]; [link]24:16[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 1:5[/link], [link]19[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 3:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And I exhort [i]you[/i] much more to do this that I may be restored to you more quickly.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Now the [xref]a[/xref]God of peace, He who [xref]b[/xref]brought up from the dead our Lord Jesus, the great [xref]c[/xref]Shepherd of the [note]1[/note][xref]d[/xref]sheep, in the [xref]e[/xref]blood of an [note]2[/note]eternal [xref]f[/xref]covenant,</text>
        <note num="1">The sheep here are the flock, which is the church. This confirms the view that the things covered in this chapter, with the experience of the unchanging Christ as our sin offering, through whom we were redeemed, and as our great Shepherd, by whom we are now being fed, are all for the church life.</note>
        <note num="2">This book does not concern temporal things, such as the things of the old covenant, but eternal things, things that are beyond the limit of time and space, such as eternal salvation ([link]5:9[/link]), eternal judgment ([link]6:2[/link]), eternal redemption ([link]9:12[/link]), the eternal Spirit ([link]9:14[/link]), the eternal inheritance ([link]9:15[/link]), and the eternal covenant ([link]13:20[/link]).[br][br]The new covenant is not only a better covenant ([link]7:22[/link]; [link]8:6[/link]) but also an eternal covenant. It is eternally effective because of the eternal efficacy of Christ's blood, with which it was enacted ([link]Matt. 26:28[/link]; [link]Luke 22:20[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 15:33[/link]; [link]16:20[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 13:11[/link]; [link]Phil. 4:9[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 5:23[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 2:24[/link]; [link]3:15[/link]; [link]4:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]John 10:11[/link], [link]14[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 2:25[/link]; [link]5:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]John 10:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Heb. 9:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]Heb. 8:6[/link], [link]8[/link]; [link]9:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Perfect you in every [xref]b[/xref]good work for the doing of His [xref]c[/xref]will, [note]1[/note]doing [xref]d[/xref]in us that which is well [xref]e[/xref]pleasing in His sight through Jesus Christ; to Him be the [xref]f[/xref]glory forever and ever. Amen.</text>
        <note num="1">God is doing in us that which is well pleasing in His sight through Jesus Christ that we may be able to do His will. God works in us both the willing and the working for His good pleasure ([link]Phil. 2:13[/link]). From beginning to end this book presents to us a heavenly Christ. Only here, with the word "God...doing in us...through Jesus Christ," does this book imply the indwelling of Christ. It is through the indwelling Christ that God works in us so that we can do His will.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 4:12[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 3:10[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 5:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Eph. 2:10[/link]; [link]Col. 1:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rom. 12:2[/link]; [link]Col. 1:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Phil. 2:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Heb. 12:28[/link]; [link]1 John 3:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">[link]Rom. 16:27[/link]; [link]Eph. 3:21[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 3:18[/link]; [link]Rev. 5:13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Now I beseech you, brothers, [note]1[/note]bear with the word of this [xref]a[/xref]exhortation, for indeed I have written to you in few words.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., endure and receive. To bear with the word of the apostle also is needed in the church life ([link]Acts 2:42[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Pet. 5:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Know that our brother [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Timothy has been released, with whom, if he comes soon, I will see you.</text>
        <note num="1">The mentioning of Timothy in such an intimate way is a strong proof that this book was written by the apostle Paul. See [link]1 Tim. 1:2[/link] and [link]2 Tim. 1:2[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 16:1[/link]; [link]Rom. 16:21[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 16:10[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 3:2[/link], [link]6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Greet all the ones [xref]a[/xref]leading you and all the saints. Those from Italy greet you.</text>
        <note num="1">The greetings in this verse are a form of fellowship in the church and among the churches.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Heb. 13:7[/link], [link]17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>[note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Grace be with you all. Amen.</text>
        <note num="1">To realize and participate in all the things unveiled in this book, we need grace. To have grace ([link]12:28[/link]) we need to come forward to the throne of grace that we may find grace for timely help ([link]4:16[/link]). It is when we touch the throne of grace in the Holy of Holies through the exercise of our spirit that we enjoy the Spirit of grace ([link]10:29[/link]) and that our heart is confirmed by grace ([link]v. 9[/link]). By such an enjoyment of grace we run the race set before us ([link]12:1[/link]) that we may reach the goal of God's economy.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 16:20[/link]; [link]Gal. 6:18[/link]; [link]Eph. 6:24[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 4:22[/link]; [link]Titus 3:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    </chapters>
</book>
