<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="yes"?>
<book name="Hosea">
    <info title="Author">Hosea ([link]1:1[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Time of His Ministry">A period of about sixty years, from approximately 785 B.C., during the reign of Uzziah (Azariah), king of Judah, to approximately 725 B.C., during the reign of Hezekiah, king of Judah ([link]1:1[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Place of His Ministry">The northern kingdom of Israel.</info>
    <info title="Object of His Ministry">The northern kingdom of Israel.</info>
    <subject>Jehovah as Salvation to the Adulterous and Apostate Israel in Receiving Her Back and Restoring Her</subject>
    <outlines>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="1" ref="1:1">The introductory word</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="2" ref="1:2-3:5">A wife of harlotries</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="1:2-9">The prophet Hosea taking a wife of harlotries</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="1:10-2:1">Promise of restoration</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="2:2-13">The harlotries of the wife of the prophet Hosea</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="4" ref="2:14-23">Jehovah's restoration of the adulterous and apostate Israel</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="5" ref="3:1-5">The confirmation of God's faithful restoration of Israel</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="3" ref="4:1-13:16">A people of apostasy</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="4:1-5:14; 6:4-10">The sins of Israel and the punishments of Jehovah</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="1" ref="4:1-3">Concerning the people in general</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="2" ref="4:4-10">Concerning the priests</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="3" ref="4:11-14">Concerning fornication, wine, and harlotries</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="4" ref="4:15-19">Concerning Israel's stubbornness</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="5" ref="5:1-14; 6:4-10">Mainly concerning the priests, the house of the king, and the princes</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="5:15-6:3, 11">The return of the apostate people</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="7:1-16">The sins of Israel in forsaking Jehovah</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="4" ref="8:1-14">Jehovah's punishments on Israel because of their forsaking of Him</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="5" ref="9:1-10:15">The idolatry of Israel against Jehovah and the punishments of Jehovah upon Israel</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="6" ref="11:1-13:16">Jehovah's unchanging love subduing Israel's stubborn unchastity</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="4" ref="14:1-9">The restoration of Israel</outline>
    </outlines>
    <chapters>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[note]1[/note]The word of Jehovah which came to [note]2[/note]Hosea the son of Beeri in the days of [xref]a[/xref]Uzziah, [xref]b[/xref]Jotham, [xref]c[/xref]Ahaz, [i]and[/i] [xref]d[/xref]Hezekiah, kings of Judah, and in the days of [xref]e[/xref]Jeroboam the son of Joash the king of Israel.</text>
        <note num="1">The Minor Prophets are composed of twelve books, from Hosea to Malachi. In ancient times these books might have been considered one book. "The book of the prophets" mentioned by Stephen in [link]Acts 7:42[/link], in his quoting of [link]Amos 5:25-27[/link], might refer to this collective book. These twelve books complete the divine revelation concerning God's economy in His dealings with His elect (Israel) and the nations, which is covered in detail in the books of the Major Prophets &amp;#8212; Isaiah, Jeremiah, Ezekiel, and Daniel. All the books of both the Major Prophets and the Minor Prophets were called by the Lord Jesus "the Prophets," in which things were written concerning Him ([link]Luke 24:44[/link]). Thus, the central point of all the Prophets is Christ (cf. [link]Luke 24:27[/link]; [link]John 5:39[/link]).[br/][br/]Like the Major Prophets, the Minor Prophets unveil that God's economy in His loving chastisement of Israel, in His governmental dealing with Israel, and in His judgment upon the nations issues in the manifestation of Christ as the centrality and universality in God's economy to bring in the kingdom, the age of restoration ([link]Matt. 19:28[/link]; [link]Acts 3:21[/link]), which will usher the old and ruined universe into the new heaven and new earth with the New Jerusalem ([link]Rev. 21:1-2[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Meaning salvation, or deliverance (cf. [link]Num. 13:16[/link]). The object of Hosea's ministry was the adulterous and apostate kingdom of Israel. As to Israel's condition, they were adulterous; as to their position, they were apostate. This book reveals that regardless of how adulterous Israel is as the wife to Jehovah and how apostate Israel is as the people to Him, He still desires that she would return to Him. If she would return to Him, He would still receive her, bring her back, and restore her.</note>
        <xref num="a">2 Chron. 26:1; Isa. 1:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">2 Kings 15:5, 7; Micah 1:1</xref>
        <xref num="c">2 Kings 16:1</xref>
        <xref num="d">2 Kings 18:1</xref>
        <xref num="e">2 Kings 14:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>At the beginning of Jehovah's speaking to Hosea, Jehovah said to Hosea,[br/]Go, take to yourself a [note]1[/note]wife of [note]2[/note]harlotries / And children of harlotries, / For the land is entirely given over to [xref]a[/xref]harlotry, / [i]And thus departs[/i] from Jehovah.</text>
        <note num="1">The crucial emphasis of the revelation released by all the prophets from Isaiah to Malachi is that God wants to have an organic union with His chosen people. In this union God is His people's life and they are His expression. In this way God and His chosen people become a universal couple ([link]Rev. 22:17[/link] and note 1, par. 2). Because this is God's intention in His eternal economy, both the Major Prophets and the Minor Prophets speak of God as the Husband and of God's chosen people as the wife. This thought is fully developed in the New Testament. See note [link]6[sup]2[/sup], par. 2, in Exo. 20[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">The prophet Hosea took Gomer, a wife of harlotries ([link]vv. 2-3[/link]). This symbolized that God took Israel as His wife, one who gave herself to harlotries and who departed from Jehovah. God told Hosea to do what He Himself had done, and Hosea did what God commanded him.</note>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 31:16; Psa. 73:27; Jer. 2:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>So he went and took Gomer the daughter of Diblaim. And she conceived and bore him a son.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And Jehovah said to him,[br/]Call his name [note]1[/note]Jezreel, / For yet a little while / And I will [note]2[/note]avenge the [xref]a[/xref]bloodshed of Jezreel / Upon the house of Jehu / And will bring an [xref]b[/xref]end to the kingdom of the house of Israel.</text>
        <note num="1">Symbolizing that God would avenge the bloodshed at Jezreel ([link]2 Kings 10:1-11[/link]) upon the house of Jehu and would bring an end to the kingdom of the house of Israel ([link]2 Kings 15:10-12[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Or, visit (i.e., in order to avenge).</note>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 10:7-11</xref>
        <xref num="b">2 Kings 15:10, 12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And in that day / I will break the [xref]a[/xref]bow of Israel / In the valley of Jezreel.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 15:29</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And she conceived again and bore a daughter. And He said to him,[br/]Call her name [note]1[/note]Lo-ruhamah, / For I will no longer have compassion / On the [xref]a[/xref]house of Israel, / That I should forgive them at all.</text>
        <note num="1">Meaning she has not obtained compassion and symbolizing that God would no longer have compassion on the house of Israel.</note>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 17:6, 23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>But on the [xref]a[/xref]house of Judah I will have compassion and will save them by Jehovah their God, and I will not save them by bow or by sword or by battle, by horses or by horsemen.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 19:35</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>When she had weaned Lo-ruhamah, she conceived and bore a son.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And He said,[br/]Call his name [note]1[/note]Lo-ammi, / For you are [xref]a[/xref]not My people, / And I will not belong to you.</text>
        <note num="1">Meaning not My people and symbolizing that Israel was not God's people and God would not belong to her.</note>
        <xref num="a">Rom. 9:25; cf. Exo. 6:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>But the [note]1[/note]number of the children of Israel will be like the [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]sand of the sea, / Which cannot be measured or numbered; / [xref]b[/xref]And in the place where it will be said to them, You are not My people, / It will be said to them, [i]You are[/i] the [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]sons of the living God.</text>
        <note num="1">The word in [link]1:10-2:1[/link] is God's promise of restoration to the children of Israel. This promise is a matter of grace. Grace follows sin. Where sin abounds, grace abounds even more ([link]Rom. 5:20[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]17[sup]1[/sup] in Gen. 22[/link].</note>
        <note num="3">Sons of the living God indicates regeneration. When God fulfills His new covenant with Israel ([link]Jer. 31:31-34[/link] and note [link]31[sup]1[/sup][/link]), He will regenerate them, putting Himself into them as their life to make them the sons of God. Thus, Israel will be not merely the people of God but also the sons of God.</note>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 32:12; Rom. 9:27-28</xref>
        <xref num="b">Rom. 9:26; 1 Pet. 2:10</xref>
        <xref num="c">2 Cor. 6:18; Rev. 21:7; cf. Matt. 16:16; John 1:12; 1 John 3:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And the children of Judah and the children of Israel will be [xref]a[/xref]gathered together, / And they will appoint for themselves one head, and they will go up from the land, / For great will be the day of [note]1[/note]Jezreel.</text>
        <note num="1">Meaning God sows, or God will sow. The day of Jezreel is the day for the people of Israel to be sown in the Holy Land by God ([link]v. 11[/link]; [link]2:22-23[/link]). Today God has sown the children of Israel back in their fathers' land, and no one can pluck them out again.</note>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 3:18; Ezek. 34:23; 37:16-25</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Say to your brothers, [note]1[/note]Ammi, / And to your sisters, [note]2[/note]Ruhamah.</text>
        <note num="1">Meaning My people.</note>
        <note num="2">Meaning she has obtained compassion. The two names in this verse indicate that ultimately Israel will be perfected by God. Under the victory of God's love, Israel will become God's people and obtain His compassion. See note [link]1[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 11[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Contend with your [xref]a[/xref]mother; contend. / For she is [note]1[/note]not my wife, / And I am [note]1[/note]not her husband. / And let her turn away her [xref]b[/xref]harlotries from her face, / And her adulteries from between her breasts,</text>
        <note num="1">The harlotries of Gomer, the wife of the prophet Hosea, symbolize the adulteries of Israel as the unchaste wife of Jehovah ([link]vv. 2-13[/link]). In a sense, God divorced Israel, but He did this with the strong intention of receiving her back again.</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 50:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">Ezek. 16:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Lest I strip her naked / And set her out as in the day she was [xref]a[/xref]born / And make her a wilderness / And make her a dry land / And slay her with thirst.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezek. 16:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And on her children I will not have compassion, / For they are the children of harlotries.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>For their mother has gone about as a [xref]a[/xref]harlot; / She who conceived them has acted shamefully; / For she has said, / I will go after my [note]1[/note]lovers, / Who give [i]me[/i] my bread and my water, / My wool and my flax, / My oil and my drink.</text>
        <note num="1">Israel's lovers were her idols.</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 1:21; Jer. 3:1, 6, 8-9; Ezek. 16:15-16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Therefore I will now hedge up / [note]1[/note]Her way with thorns; / And I will build up a wall against her, / So that she will not find her paths.</text>
        <note num="1">Following the Septuagint; the Hebrew text reads, your.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And she will pursue her lovers / But will not overtake them; / And she will seek them but not find [i]them;[/i] / And she will say, [note]1[/note]I will go / And [xref]a[/xref]return to my first [xref]b[/xref]husband, / For it was better for me then than now.</text>
        <note num="1">This indicates that although Israel would stubbornly pursue her lovers (her idols), eventually she would return to God as her first Husband.</note>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 5:15; 6:1; 14:1; Jer. 3:22; 31:18; Lam. 3:40; Luke 15:18</xref>
        <xref num="b">Jer. 2:2; 31:32; Ezek. 23:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>For she [xref]a[/xref]did not know / That it was I who gave her / The grain and the new wine and the fresh oil, / And who multiplied to her silver / And gold, which they [note]1[/note]used for Baal.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, made into Baal.</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 1:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Therefore I will take back / My grain in its time / And My new wine in its appointed season, / And I will snatch away My wool and My flax, / [i]Which were[/i] to cover her nakedness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And now I will uncover her lewdness / In the sight of her lovers, / And no one will deliver her from My hand.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And I will bring all her mirth to an end, / Her [xref]a[/xref]feasts, her new moons, and her Sabbaths, / And all her appointed assemblies.</text>
        <xref num="a">Amos 8:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And I will desolate her vine and her fig tree, / Of which she said, / These are my payments / That my lovers have given me; / And I will make them a forest, / And the beasts of the field will devour them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And I will visit the days of the Baals upon her, / In which she burned incense to them / And adorned herself with her nose rings and her jewels / And went after her lovers / And forgot Me, / Declares Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Therefore I am now luring her, / And I will bring her into the [xref]a[/xref]wilderness / And will [xref]b[/xref]speak to her heart.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezek. 20:35</xref>
        <xref num="b">Isa. 40:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And I will give her her vineyards from there / And the valley of [xref]a[/xref]Achor as a door of hope; / And she will respond there as in the days of her [xref]b[/xref]youth / And as in the day when she came up out of the land of Egypt.</text>
        <xref num="a">Josh. 7:26; Isa. 65:10</xref>
        <xref num="b">Jer. 2:2; Ezek. 16:22, 60</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And in that day, declares Jehovah, / You will call [i]Me[/i] My [xref]a[/xref]Husband / And will no longer call Me [note]1[/note]Baali.</text>
        <note num="1">Meaning my Master. Also the name of a Canaanite god.</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 54:5; Jer. 3:14; Rev. 21:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>For I will take away the names of the Baals from her mouth, / And they will no longer be remembered by their name.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And I will make a [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]covenant for them / In that day / With the beasts of the field / And with the birds of heaven / And the creeping things of the earth; / And bow and sword and battle / I will [xref]b[/xref]break from the land, / And I will cause them to lie down in [xref]c[/xref]safety.</text>
        <note num="1">Just as God made a covenant for us with the living things at Noah's time ([link]Gen. 9:8-11[/link]), so He will make such a covenant for Israel at the time of restoration. Because of this latter covenant, the beasts, the birds, and the creeping things will be in a good order. Also, God will break bow, sword, and battle from the land and will cause Israel to lie down in safety.</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 11:6-9; Ezek. 34:25</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 46:9; Isa. 2:4; Ezek. 39:9-10</xref>
        <xref num="c">Lev. 26:5; Jer. 23:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And I will [xref]a[/xref]betroth you to Myself forever; / Indeed I will betroth you to Myself / In righteousness and justice / And in lovingkindness and compassions;</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 62:4-5; 2 Cor. 11:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Indeed I will betroth you to Myself in faithfulness, / And you will know Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And in that day / I will answer, declares Jehovah; / I will answer the heavens, / And they will answer the earth,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And the earth will answer the [note]1[/note]grain / And the [note]1[/note]new wine and the [note]1[/note]fresh oil, / And they will answer Jezreel.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]11[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 6[/link] and notes [link]26[sup]1[/sup] in Isa. 30[/link] and [link]18[sup]1[/sup] in Joel 3[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>And I will sow her for Myself in the land; / And I will have compassion on [note]1[/note]Lo-ruhamah, / And I will say to [note]2[/note]Lo-ammi, [xref]a[/xref]You are My people; / And they will say, My God.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]6[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 1[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]9[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Rom. 9:25</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Then Jehovah said to me, Go [note]1[/note]again, love a woman who is loved by her companion yet who is an adulteress, even as Jehovah has [xref]a[/xref]loved the children of Israel, though they turn to other gods and love raisin cakes.</text>
        <note num="1">Jehovah told Hosea to love Gomer, a woman of adulteries, again, symbolizing that Jehovah will love the children of Israel again, though they have turned to other gods (other lovers) and loved raisin cakes (pleasures for self). What Hosea did in obedience to God's command regarding Gomer was a confirmation of what God promised to do regarding Israel.</note>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 7:7; Jer. 3:1, 14; Hosea 11:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>So I bought her for myself for fifteen pieces of silver and a homer of barley and a half-homer of barley.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And I said to her, You will abide for me for [note]1[/note]many days; you shall not go about as a harlot nor be [i]another[/i] man's; and I will be the same toward you.</text>
        <note num="1">Gomer's abiding with Hosea many days without going about as a harlot nor being another man's symbolizes that the children of Israel would abide for many days without king, without prince, without sacrifice, without pillar (for worship), and without ephod and teraphim (idols in homes) ([link]v. 4[/link]). These "many days" began when the Babylonians burned the temple ([link]2 Chron. 36:19[/link]). From that time Israel has been without king and without prince; furthermore, from that time until the present the Jews have not worshipped idols.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>For the children of Israel will [xref]a[/xref]abide for many days without king and without prince and without sacrifice and without pillar and without ephod and teraphim.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 15:29; 17:6, 23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Afterward the children of Israel will return and [xref]a[/xref]seek Jehovah their God and [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]David their King, and they will come with fear to Jehovah and to His goodness in the [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]last days.</text>
        <note num="1">This is Christ in the millennium ([link]Rev. 20:6b[/link]). See note [link]11[sup]1[/sup] in Amos 9[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">I.e., in the age of restoration ([link]Matt. 19:28[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 50:4-5; Hosea 5:5-6</xref>
        <xref num="b">Isa. 9:7; 16:5; Jer. 30:9; Ezek. 34:23-24; 37:22-25</xref>
        <xref num="c">Isa. 2:2; Jer. 30:24; Ezek. 38:8, 16</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Hear the word of Jehovah, / O children of Israel; / For Jehovah has a [xref]a[/xref]controversy / With the inhabitants of the land. / For there is no [note]1[/note]faithfulness or kindness / And [xref]b[/xref]no knowledge of God in the land.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, truth. As the unchaste wife of Jehovah, Israel became evil. Once a wife becomes unchaste, all kinds of evils follow. Once we forsake God, we too can do any kind of evil.</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 3:13-14; Jer. 25:31; Hosea 12:2</xref>
        <xref num="b">Jer. 2:8; 4:22; 5:4; Hosea 5:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>[i]Rather[/i] there are swearing and deceiving and murder / And stealing and adultery; / They are violent, / And bloodshed follows bloodshed.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Because of this the land mourns, / And all the inhabitants languish within it, / With the beasts of the field / And with the birds of heaven; / Indeed, even the fish of the sea will be taken away.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Yet let no man contend, / And let no man reprove; / For your people are like those who contend with the priest.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And [note]1[/note]you will stumble in the day, / And the prophet also will stumble / With you in the night; / And I will destroy your mother.</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to the priest ([link]v. 6[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>My people are destroyed / Because of a [xref]a[/xref]lack of [note]1[/note]that knowledge. / For you have rejected [note]1[/note]that knowledge, / And I will reject you, so that you will not be a priest to Me; / Since you have forgotten the law of your God, / I also will forget your children.</text>
        <note num="1">Referring back to [link]v. 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 5:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>The more [note]1[/note]they were multiplied, the more they sinned against Me; / I will change their glory into [xref]a[/xref]shame.</text>
        <note num="1">Referring again to the priests.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 2:30; Mal. 2:9; Phil. 3:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>They feed on the sin of My people, / And [note]1[/note]their soul desires their iniquity.</text>
        <note num="1">The priests desired that the people would sin, because the more the people sinned, the more sin offerings there would be for the priests to eat.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And it will be that as it is with the people, [note]1[/note]so it will be with the priest; / Thus I will visit their ways upon them, / And I will recompense their doings to them.</text>
        <note num="1">The priests, who had been sanctified, separated, to be a special group among the people, made themselves the same as the people, becoming low and common.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And they will eat but will [xref]a[/xref]not be filled; / And they will commit fornication but will not increase; / For they have ceased giving heed to Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 26:26; Micah 6:14; Hag. 1:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Fornication and wine / And new wine [note]1[/note]take away [i]their[/i] heart.</text>
        <note num="1">The people of Israel had no heart for anything but fornication, wine, and new wine.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>My people inquire at their [note]1[/note]wooden post, / And their rod informs them of [i]things;[/i] / For a spirit of harlotries makes [i]them[/i] err, / And they have gone about as [xref]a[/xref]harlots away from their God.</text>
        <note num="1">Instead of praying to God and inquiring of Him, God's people inquired at their wooden post (idol).</note>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 31:16; Judg. 2:17; 1 Chron. 5:25; Psa. 73:27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Upon the tops of the mountains they offer sacrifices, / And upon the hills they burn incense, / Under oak, poplar, and terebinth, / Because its shade is good. / Therefore your daughters go about as harlots, / And your brides commit adultery.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>I will not [note]1[/note]punish your daughters when they go about as harlots / Nor your brides when they commit adultery; / For [i]the men[/i] themselves go off with harlots, / And they offer sacrifices with the [note]2[/note]prostitutes; / And the people who have no understanding will be cast down.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, visit (i.e., for punishment). So throughout the book.</note>
        <note num="2">Technically, cult prostitutes (cf. [link]Deut. 23:17[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Though you, Israel, go about as a harlot, / Let not Judah trespass; / And do not come to [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Gilgal, / Nor go up to [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]Beth-aven, / Nor swear, As Jehovah lives.</text>
        <note num="1">Gilgal was the center of idolatry ([link]9:15[/link]; [link]12:11[/link]; [link]Amos 4:4[/link]; [link]5:5[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Meaning house of nothingness, or house of idolatry. It was probably applied contemptuously to Bethel, which had become a seat of idolatry ([link]1 Kings 12:26-33[/link]; cf. [link]Hosea 5:8[/link]; [link]10:5[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 9:15; 12:11; Amos 4:4; 5:5; Judg. 3:19</xref>
        <xref num="b">Hosea 5:8; 10:5; cf. 1 Kings 12:28-29</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>For Israel is [xref]a[/xref]stubborn, / Like a stubborn heifer; / Will Jehovah now pasture them / Like a lamb in a spacious place?</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 5:23; 7:24; 9:14; Zech. 7:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Ephraim is joined to idols; / Leave him alone.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Their liquor has ended; / They have given themselves up to harlotry; / Their [note]1[/note]rulers dearly love shame.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., shields.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>The wind has wrapped her up in its wings, / And they will be ashamed because of their sacrifices.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="5">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Hear this, O priests; / And listen, O house of Israel; / And, O house of the king, give ear. / For to you belongs the judgment, / For you have been a snare at Mizpah / And a net spread over Tabor.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And the revolters have gone deep [note]1[/note]into slaughtering, / Though I am a chastisement to them all.</text>
        <note num="1">Others read, in corruption.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>I know Ephraim, / And Israel is not hidden from Me; / For now, Ephraim, you have gone about as a [xref]a[/xref]harlot; / Israel is defiled.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezek. 23:5; Hosea 4:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Their doings do not permit them / To turn to their God; / For a spirit of harlotries is within them, / And they do not know Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And the pride of Israel testifies to his face, / And Ephraim and Israel will stumble in their iniquity; / Judah also will stumble with them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>With their flocks and with their herds they will go / To [xref]a[/xref]seek Jehovah, / But they will not find Him; / He has withdrawn Himself from them.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 1:28; Jer. 11:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>They have acted treacherously against Jehovah, / For they have begotten strange children. / Now the new moon will devour them / With their apportionments.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Blow the horn in Gibeah, / The trumpet in Ramah; / Sound an alarm at [xref]a[/xref]Beth-aven: / Behind you, O Benjamin!</text>
        <xref num="a">Josh. 7:2; Hosea 4:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Ephraim will be a desolation / In the day of correction; / Among the tribes of Israel / I have made known what is sure.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>The princes of Judah have become / Like those who move a [xref]a[/xref]boundary mark. / I will pour out upon them / My overflowing wrath like water.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 19:14; 27:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Ephraim is oppressed, / Crushed by judgment, / For he was determined to walk / After [i]man's[/i] command.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Therefore I am like a moth to Ephraim / And like rottenness to the house of Judah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>When Ephraim saw his sickness, / And Judah his [xref]a[/xref]wound, / Ephraim went to [xref]b[/xref]Assyria / And sent [i]word[/i] to the warrior king; / But he cannot heal you, / And the wound will not depart from you.</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 30:12</xref>
        <xref num="b">2 Kings 15:19; Hosea 7:11; 10:6; 12:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>For I will be like a lion to Ephraim / And like a young lion to the house of Judah. / I, I will tear [i]them[/i] and go away; / I will carry [i]them[/i] off, and there will be no one to deliver [i]them.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>I will go away, I will return to My place, / [xref]a[/xref]Until they acknowledge their offense / And seek My face; / In their affliction they will seek Me [note]1[/note]earnestly.</text>
        <note num="1">Eventually, in their affliction Israel will seek God earnestly. Thus, the divine chastisement of Israel will be effective.</note>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 14:1-3; 1 Kings 8:47-48; Jer. 29:13-14</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="6">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Come and let us [xref]a[/xref]return to Jehovah; / For He has torn [i]us,[/i] but He will [xref]b[/xref]heal us, / And He has stricken [i]us,[/i] but He will bind us up.</text>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 2:7</xref>
        <xref num="b">Exo. 15:26; Deut. 32:39; Job 5:18; Jer. 30:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>He will enliven us after [note]1[/note]two days; / On the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]third day He will raise us up, / And we will live in His presence.</text>
        <note num="1">With the Lord one day is like a thousand years ([link]2 Pet. 3:8[/link]). According to this principle, the two days here may signify the first two periods of a thousand years each, counting from A.D. 70, when the Roman prince Titus destroyed Jerusalem and the temple, cruelly killed thousands of Jews, and scattered the Jews among the nations. From that time the Jews have been without king, without prince, without sacrifice, and without the temple, fulfilling Hosea's prophecy in [link]3:4[/link]. For two thousand years God has left Israel in a dead condition. After this two thousand-year period, the third thousand years will come. The third day may signify a third period of a thousand years, that is, the millennium, the age of restoration, which will be in the reality of Christ's resurrection ([link]Rev. 20:6[/link]). At that time Israel will be raised up, that is, restored.[br/][br/]Christ was resurrected on the third day ([link]1 Cor. 15:4[/link]), and as the pneumatic Christ, the life-giving Spirit, in resurrection ([link]1 Cor. 15:45[/link]), He is the reality of the third day ([link]John 11:25[/link]). Whenever we contact such a Christ, we are brought from the desolation of the two days to the resurrection of the third day. Cf. note [link]2[sup]1[/sup] in Hab. 3[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Cor. 15:4; cf. Luke 13:32[br/]See note 2[sup]1[/sup].</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Therefore let us know, let us pursue knowing Jehovah: / [note]1[/note]His going forth is as sure as the [xref]a[/xref]dawn, / And He will come to us as the rain, / As the late rain which [xref]b[/xref]waters the earth.</text>
        <note num="1">In His second coming Christ will go forth as the dawn and come to Israel as the late rain that waters the earth. At that time, in the restoration, the millennium ([link]Matt. 19:28[/link]), the people of Israel will be the earth watered by Christ as the late rain (cf. [link]Psa. 72:6[/link] and note). See notes [link]2[sup]1[/sup] in Micah 5[/link] and [link]23[sup]1[/sup] in Joel 2[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 23:4</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 72:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>What shall I do with you, O [note]1[/note]Ephraim? / What shall I do with you, O Judah? / For your lovingkindness is like a morning cloud / And like dew that departs early.</text>
        <note num="1">Another term for the northern kingdom of Israel. So also throughout the book.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Therefore I hewed [i]them[/i] to pieces by the prophets; / I slew them by the [xref]a[/xref]words of My mouth, / And [note]1[/note]My judgments went forth as light.</text>
        <note num="1">According to the Septuagint; the Hebrew text reads, the judgments on you were light that went forth.</note>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 5:14; 23:29; Heb. 4:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]For I delight in lovingkindness and not [xref]b[/xref]sacrifice, / And the knowledge of God more than burnt offerings.</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 9:13; 12:7</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 15:22; Prov. 21:3; Eccl. 5:1; Isa. 1:11; Micah 6:6-7; Mark 12:33</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>But they like Adam have transgressed the covenant; / There they have acted treacherously against Me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Gilead is a city of those who commit iniquity; / It is tracked with blood.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And like bands of robbers lying in wait for a man, / The company of priests murder on the way to Shechem; / Indeed they commit wickedness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>In the house of Israel I have seen a horrid thing: / The harlotry of Ephraim is there; / Israel has defiled itself.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Also, O Judah, there is a [note]1[/note]harvest appointed for you, / When I will [xref]a[/xref]turn the captivity of My people.</text>
        <note num="1">In the restoration all the Israelites, including the northern kingdom of Israel and the southern kingdom of Judah, will be very rich in all kinds of produce from the earth. The earth was created by God to produce a rich harvest, but because of the fall of man the earth was cursed to grow thorns, and man has had to labor with sweat for food ([link]Gen. 3:17-19[/link]). In the restoration the earth will be restored to its original condition and will be rich, fertile, and productive. Thus, a harvest will be apportioned to Judah for their enjoyment. See notes [link]26[sup]1[/sup] in Isa. 30[/link] and [link]18[sup]1[/sup] in Joel 3[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 126:1; Zeph. 2:7</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="7">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>When I would [xref]a[/xref]heal Israel, / Then the [note]1[/note]iniquity of Ephraim is discovered / As well as the evil deeds of Samaria; / For they practice falsehood. / And the thief comes inside; / The band of robbers makes raids outside.</text>
        <note num="1">The sins of Israel were in two categories: sins in their social life among the people and the rulers ([link]vv. 1-7[/link]) and evils in their relationship with Jehovah ([link]vv. 8-16[/link]). Israel was wrong with man and also with God.</note>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 6:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And they do not say in their hearts / That I [xref]a[/xref]remember all their evil. / Now their doings are all around them; / They are before My [xref]b[/xref]face.</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 14:10; 17:1; Hosea 9:9; Rev. 18:5</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 90:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>They make the king glad with their evil, / And the princes, with their lies.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>All of them practice adultery; / They are like an oven heated by the baker: / He ceases from stirring [i]the fire,[/i] / After kneading the dough, until it is [xref]a[/xref]leavened.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Cor. 5:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>On the [i]feast[/i] day of our king / The princes made themselves sick with the heat of wine; / He stretched out his hand with scorners.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>For they have made their heart ready / Like an oven while they lie in wait: / All night long / Their baker sleeps, / [i]But[/i] in the morning [note]1[/note]the oven burns / Like a flaming fire.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., it.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>All of them are hot like an oven, / And they devour their [note]1[/note]judges; / All their kings fall; / There is no one among them who [xref]a[/xref]calls on Me.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., the priests.</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 64:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Ephraim &amp;#8212; among the peoples / He mixes himself; / Ephraim is a cake / [note]1[/note]Not turned.</text>
        <note num="1">This symbolizes that Israel was stubborn, remaining in a "charcoaled" condition and being unwilling to turn to Jehovah.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Strangers have devoured his strength, / And he himself does not know [i]it;[/i] / Indeed gray hairs are all over him, / And he himself does not know [i]it.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And the pride of Israel testifies to his face; / Yet they have not returned to Jehovah their God, / And they have not sought [i]Him,[/i] because of all this.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And Ephraim has become like a silly dove / Without [note]1[/note]understanding: / They call to [xref]a[/xref]Egypt; / They go to Assyria.</text>
        <note num="1">Israel's being likened to a silly dove symbolizes that they were lacking the proper knowledge of God in His economy.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. 2 Kings 15:19; 17:4; Isa. 30:2-3; Hosea 5:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>When they go, / I will spread My net over them; / I will bring them down like the birds of heaven; / I will chasten them according to the report [i]given[/i] to their assembly.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Woe to them! For they have wandered from Me. / Devastation to them! For they have transgressed against Me. / And I would have redeemed them, / But they have spoken lies against Me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And they did not cry unto Me in their heart / When they howled in their beds. / For grain and new wine they assemble themselves; / They rebel against Me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Though I trained [i]them and[/i] strengthened their arms, / They devise evil against Me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>They return, [i]but[/i] not to [i]Him who is[/i] on high; / They are like a [note]1[/note]deceitful bow. / Their princes will fall by the sword / Because of the rage of their tongue. / This will be their derision / In the land of [xref]a[/xref]Egypt.</text>
        <note num="1">Israel's being likened to a deceitful bow symbolizes that they were rebellious toward God and were not faithful to fight the battle for God's kingdom.</note>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 9:3, 6</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="8">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>A trumpet to your lips! / Like an [xref]a[/xref]eagle [i]he comes[/i] against the house of Jehovah, / Because they have trespassed My [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]covenant / And have transgressed against My [note]1[/note]law.</text>
        <note num="1">Jehovah's covenant is His binding of Israel in His holy requirements and righteous terms, and Jehovah's law is His regulating of Israel according to what He is: love, light, holiness, and righteousness (see note [link]1[sup]1[/sup] in Exo. 20[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 28:49; Jer. 4:13; Hag. 1:8</xref>
        <xref num="b">Hosea 6:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>They will cry unto Me, / My God, we &amp;#8212; Israel &amp;#8212; know You.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Israel has cast off what is good; / The enemy will pursue him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>They have set up [xref]a[/xref]kings, but not by Me; / They have set up princes, but I did not acknowledge [i]it.[/i] / With their silver and their gold they made / Idols for themselves, / That they might be cut off.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 15:13, 17, 25</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Your [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]calf has cast [i]you[/i] off, O [note]1[/note]Samaria; / My anger burns against them. / How long will they be incapable of [note]2[/note]innocence?</text>
        <note num="1">Samaria was a capital of the northern kingdom of Israel ([link]1 Kings 16:29[/link]), and her calf was an idol ([link]v. 6[/link]), a golden calf image (cf. [link]1 Kings 12:28[/link]; [link]Exo. 32:4[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Here innocence means not making idols.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 12:28-29; 2 Kings 17:16-18; Acts 7:41</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>For from Israel is this! / A workman made it; / Thus it is no God. / The calf of Samaria / Will be [i]shattered to[/i] pieces.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>For they have [xref]a[/xref]sown wind, / And they will reap a whirlwind. / It has no stalk; [i]should there be[/i] a sprout, / It will not produce flour; / If it should produce, / Strangers will swallow it up.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 22:8; Hosea 10:12-13; Gal. 6:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Israel has been swallowed up; / Now they have become among the nations / Like a vessel in which no one takes pleasure.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>For they have gone up to [xref]a[/xref]Assyria / [i]Like[/i] a wild ass gone alone by itself; / Ephraim has [xref]b[/xref]hired lovers.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 15:19</xref>
        <xref num="b">Ezek. 16:33-34</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Indeed though they have hired [i]such[/i] among the nations, / I will now [xref]a[/xref]gather them; / And they will begin to be diminished because of the burden / Of the [xref]b[/xref]king of the princes.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezek. 16:37; 23:22-24; Hosea 10:10</xref>
        <xref num="b">Ezek. 26:7; Dan. 2:37</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Because Ephraim has multiplied altars for sin, / Altars will be to him for sin.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>I wrote for him the ten thousand things of My law, / [i]But[/i] they are considered as a strange thing.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>As for the sacrifices of My offerings, / They sacrifice flesh and eat [i]it,[/i] / [i]But[/i] Jehovah has [xref]a[/xref]no delight in them. / Now He will [xref]b[/xref]remember their iniquity, / And He will punish their sins; / They will return to [xref]c[/xref]Egypt.</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 14:10; Hosea 9:4; Amos 5:22</xref>
        <xref num="b">Hosea 7:2; 9:9; Rev. 18:5</xref>
        <xref num="c">Deut. 28:68; Hosea 9:3, 6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>For Israel has forgotten his [xref]a[/xref]Maker / And has built palaces, / And Judah has multiplied fortified cities; / But I will send [note]1[/note]fire into his cities, / And it will devour its citadels.</text>
        <note num="1">The minor prophets spoke concerning the evils, the rottenness, and the corruption of Israel, but Israel was stubborn and would not listen to them. Eventually, God was forced to send the Assyrians and the Babylonians as the fire to judge, to punish, and to chastise His rebellious and apostate people.</note>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 32:18; Isa. 29:23; 54:5</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="9">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Do not rejoice, O Israel, / To exult like the nations. / For you have gone as a [xref]a[/xref]harlot away from your God; / You have loved payment / Upon every grain floor.</text>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 4:12; 5:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>The threshing floor and the winepress will not feed them, / And the new wine will fail her.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>They will not dwell in the land of Jehovah; / But Ephraim will return to [xref]a[/xref]Egypt, / And in Assyria they will eat [xref]b[/xref]what is unclean.</text>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 8:13; 11:5</xref>
        <xref num="b">Ezek. 4:13; Dan. 1:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>They will not pour out offerings of wine to Jehovah, / Neither will their sacrifices be pleasing to Him; / They will be to them as the bread of mourning; / All who eat them will be unclean, / For their bread will be for themselves; / It will not come into the house of Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>What will you do / In the day of assembly / And in the day of the feast of Jehovah?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>For they will go because of destruction; / Egypt will gather them; / [note]1[/note]Moph will bury them. / As for their desirable [note]2[/note]things of silver, nettles will dispossess them; / Thistles will be in their tents.</text>
        <note num="1">Probably Memphis, an Egyptian city near the Nile; elsewhere called Noph.</note>
        <note num="2">Idols made of silver.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>The days of the visitation have come; / The days of the recompense have come; / Israel will know [i]it.[/i] / The prophet is a fool, / The [note]1[/note]inspired man is mad, / Because of the greatness of your iniquity / And [i]because of[/i] the greatness of the enmity.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., man of the spirit. Israel's considering a prophet as a fool and considering a man of the spirit, an inspired one, as mad indicates that they did not care for God's interests. On the contrary, they thought that caring for God's interests was foolishness.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Ephraim was a [note]1[/note]watchman / With my God. / As for the [note]2[/note]prophet, a fowler's trap / Is in all his ways; / Enmity is in the house of his God.</text>
        <note num="1">This indicates that in the past the northern kingdom of Israel was quite good.</note>
        <note num="2">This may mean that the prophets had become so evil that wherever they went they were a trap to snare the people. In the temple the prophets created enmity; they did not have love or sympathy.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>They have deeply corrupted themselves / As in the days of [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Gibeah; / He will remember their iniquity; / He will punish their sins.</text>
        <note num="1">The corruption of Israel was so great that it matched the corruption in the days of Gibeah as described in [link]Judges 19:15-30[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 10:9; Judg. 19:22; 20:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>I [note]1[/note]found Israel / Like grapes in the wilderness; / I saw your fathers / As the first ripe fruit on the fig tree at its beginning. / They went to [xref]a[/xref]Baal-peor / And sanctified themselves unto the shameful thing, / And they became detestable, like the thing that they loved.</text>
        <note num="1">This refers to the time of the exodus from Egypt, when God considered Israel a young wife ([link]Jer. 2:2[/link]). However, when this wife grew up, she left God for Baal and went to Baal-peor (a city named after the idol Baal of Peor &amp;#8212; [link]Num. 25:3[/link]; [link]Psa. 106:28[/link]) and sanctified herself unto the shameful thing (idol) and became an abomination, like the thing (idol) that she loved.</note>
        <xref num="a">Num. 25:3; Psa. 106:28</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>As for Ephraim, their glory / Will fly away like a bird &amp;#8212; / No birth, no pregnancy, and no conception!</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>For even if they bring up their children, / I will bereave them, [i]so that[/i] not a man [i]is left.[/i] / Indeed woe also to them / When I [xref]a[/xref]turn away from them.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 31:17; Hosea 5:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Ephraim, as I have seen [i]him,[/i] / Is planted like Tyre in a meadow; / But Ephraim will bring forth / His children to the slayer.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Give them, O Jehovah &amp;#8212; / What will You give [i]them?[/i] / Give them a miscarrying womb / And dry breasts.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>All their evil is in [xref]a[/xref]Gilgal, / For there I hated them. / Because of the evil of their doings / I will drive them from My house, / I will love them no more; / All their princes are rebels.</text>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 4:15; 12:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Ephraim is stricken; / Their root is dried up; / They will not bear fruit. / Indeed though they bring forth, / I will kill the beloved [i]fruit[/i] of their womb.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>My God has rejected them, / For they did not listen to Him. / And they will be [xref]a[/xref]wanderers among the nations.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 28:64-65</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="10">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Israel is a luxuriant [xref]a[/xref]vine; / He brings forth fruit for [note]1[/note]himself. / According to the abundance of his fruit / He has multiplied altars; / According to the goodness of their land / They have made pillars well.</text>
        <note num="1">The fruit of the vine should have been offered to God as a drink offering (see note [link]13[sup]2[/sup] in Lev. 23[/link]), but Israel used the vines to bring forth fruit for themselves, not for God. They became rich, but they used their produce to build up altars and to make idols.</note>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 80:8-11; Isa. 5:1-7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Their heart is [xref]a[/xref]divided; / Now they will be found guilty. / He Himself will break down their altars; / He will destroy their pillars.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 18:21; cf. Matt. 6:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>For now they will say, / We have [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]no king, / For we did not fear Jehovah; / And the king, what can he do for us?</text>
        <note num="1">Because they did not fear Jehovah, Israel was not able to be in a proper situation, with God's deputy authority (a king) among them. This refers to the headship, the leadership, representing God as His authority among His people.</note>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 3:4; 10:7; 11:5; Micah 4:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>They speak [i]mere[/i] words, / Swearing falsely / While making a covenant; / And judgment sprouts forth like poisonous weeds / In the furrows of the field.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>The inhabitants of Samaria will fear / For the [xref]a[/xref]calves of [note]1[/note]Beth-aven; / For its people will mourn over it, / And its idol priests [note]2[/note]will tremble for it, / For its glory, / Because it has departed from it.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]15[sup]2[/sup] in ch. 4[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Others translate, who rejoiced over it.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 12:28-29; Hosea 4:15; 8:5-6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Indeed it will be carried to [xref]a[/xref]Assyria: / A present to the warrior king. / Ephraim will be taken in shame, / And Israel will be ashamed of his own counsel.</text>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 5:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Samaria will be cut off [i]with[/i] her king / [i]And will be[/i] like twigs on the surface of the water.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 17:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And the high places of Aven, the sin of Israel, / Will be destroyed. / The thorn and the thistle will come up / Upon their altars; / And they will say to the [xref]a[/xref]mountains, Cover us! / And to the hills, Fall on us!</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 2:19; Luke 23:30; Rev. 6:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Since the days of [xref]a[/xref]Gibeah / You have sinned, O Israel; / There they have stood. / Did not the [xref]b[/xref]battle / Overtake them in Gibeah / Because of the children of iniquity?</text>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 9:9</xref>
        <xref num="b">Judg. 20:17-48</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>When I so desire, I will chastise them; / And the peoples will be [xref]a[/xref]gathered against them, / When they are bound for their [note]1[/note]double iniquity.</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to Israel's two evils in forsaking Jehovah and turning to idols ([link]Jer. 2:13[/link] and note).</note>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 16:16; Ezek. 23:46-47; Hosea 8:1, 10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And Ephraim is a trained heifer / That loves to tread [i]the grain;[/i] / But I have passed [i]the yoke[/i] / Over her fair neck: / I will make Ephraim draw [i]the plow;[/i] / Judah will plow; / Jacob will break his clods.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>[note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Sow unto righteousness for yourselves; / Reap according to lovingkindness; / Break up your [note]2[/note]fallow ground; / For it is time to seek Jehovah / Until He comes and rains / Righteousness on you.</text>
        <note num="1">Here to sow means to seek Jehovah. To seek Jehovah rightly is to sow rightly. Thus, Hosea charged the children of Israel to sow unto righteousness. If they did this, they would reap according to lovingkindness. Otherwise, if they plowed wickedness, they would reap injustice. Cf. [link]Gal. 6:7-8[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Fallow ground is ground that has been plowed but has not been sown. The children of Israel were the fallow ground. They had been plowed by God but had not been sown with righteousness. They were to break up the fallow ground; i.e., they were to seek God until Christ came as righteousness to rain righteousness upon them.</note>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 8:7; Gal. 6:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>You have plowed wickedness; / You have reaped injustice; / You have eaten the fruit of lying. / For you have trusted in your way, / In the multitude of your mighty men.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And a [note]1[/note]tumult will arise among your peoples; / And all your fortresses will be devastated, / As [xref]a[/xref]Shalman devastated Beth-arbel / In the day of battle: / The mother was dashed in pieces with the children.</text>
        <note num="1">Hosea's prophecy in [link]vv. 14-15[/link] was fully fulfilled by Titus and his Roman army in A.D. 70.</note>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 18:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Thus Bethel will cause this to happen to you / Because of your great evil: / At [note]1[/note]dawn the king of Israel / Will be utterly cut off.</text>
        <note num="1">This word indicates that Israel was in the night, in darkness. They were a people who were altogether lacking in righteousness and justice. They forsook God and they were evil to one another.</note>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="11">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>When Israel was a [xref]a[/xref]child, I [note]1[/note]loved him, / And [xref]b[/xref]out of Egypt I called My [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]son.</text>
        <note num="1">The last four chapters of this book concern Jehovah's unchanging love versus Israel's stubborn unchastity. Israel is depicted as the wife of Jehovah throughout this book ([link]2:7[/link], [link]19[/link]). But when God's everlasting and unchanging love is touched, Israel is called God's son ([link]Exo. 4:22-23[/link]), indicating that in God's view Israel has the Father's life (cf. [link]1:10[/link] and note 3). God's everlasting love is not a love in affection, like the love of a husband toward a wife, but a love in life, like the love of a father toward a son. On the one hand, God loves us as His wife, and the Lord Jesus is our Husband ([link]John 3:29[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 11:2[/link]). On the other hand, God is our Father, and we are sons of the Father ([link]Gal. 3:26[/link]; [link]4:6[/link]).[br/][br/]Although God is loving, He is also a God of purity and righteousness. He cannot tolerate any kind of uncleanness or unrighteousness. Wherever these things are found among God's people, God comes in to chastise them. Nevertheless, when God's people are chastised by Him, they are still loved by Him (cf. [link]Heb. 12:6[/link]; [link]Rev. 3:19[/link]). God's everlasting love ([link]Jer. 31:3[/link]) is always victorious. Eventually, in spite of our failures and mistakes, God's love will gain the victory (cf. [link]Rom. 8:35-39[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Implying Christ in His union with Israel as the Son of God, who is loved by God and was called out of Egypt by God ([link]Matt. 2:13-15[/link]). This indicates that although Israel became exceedingly evil, Christ still became organically one with Israel through incarnation to be a real Israelite. Christ joined Himself to Israel in the matter of being a son of God.[br/][br/]This verse implies Christ as the Son of God. It also implies that all God's chosen people become sons of God by virtue of their being organically united with Christ (cf. [link]Rom. 11:17[/link] and notes; [link]Gal. 3:26[/link] and note 2). This is possible because Christ is the Son of God in two aspects: the aspect of His being the only begotten Son of God and the aspect of His being the firstborn Son of God. In eternity Christ was God's only begotten Son ([link]John 3:16[/link]; [link]1 John 4:9[/link]), possessing only divinity without humanity. As such, He was unique. However, one day Christ was incarnated to be a man, taking on human nature and joining Himself with humanity ([link]John 1:14[/link]). After dying an all-inclusive, vicarious death on the cross, He entered into resurrection. In resurrection and through resurrection He was begotten of God in His humanity to be the firstborn Son of God, possessing both divinity and humanity ([link]Acts 13:33[/link] and note; [link]Rom. 1:3-4[/link] and notes). Hence, in addition to His being the unique, only begotten Son of God from eternity, Christ, after His incarnation and through His resurrection, has become the Son of God in another sense, in the sense of being the firstborn Son of God ([link]Heb. 1:5-6[/link]). Furthermore, in Christ's resurrection all His believers were begotten of God, regenerated ([link]1 Pet. 1:3[/link]), to be the many sons of God ([link]Heb. 2:10[/link]), Christ's many brothers ([link]Rom. 8:29[/link]), to be His members for the constituting of His organic Body. All this is implied in this verse.</note>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 2:15</xref>
        <xref num="b">Matt. 2:15</xref>
        <xref num="c">Exo. 4:22-23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>As [note]1[/note]they called them, / So they went from them; / To the [xref]a[/xref]Baals they sacrificed, / And to the idols they burned incense.</text>
        <note num="1">The prophets. God sent the prophets to call Israel again and again, but the more the prophets called them, the farther they went away from the prophets. From the time Titus destroyed Jerusalem and the temple in A.D. 70 until now, God has not raised up any prophets among the Jews. According to the Lord's word in [link]Matt. 21:43[/link], the kingdom of God has been taken from the Jews and has been given to the church. In the church every regenerated believer is a priest ([link]1 Pet. 2:5[/link], [link]9[/link]; [link]Rev. 1:6[/link]), and every believer should endeavor to prophesy ([link]1 Cor. 14:1[/link], [link]31[/link], [link]39[/link]; cf. [link]Num. 11:29[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 17:16; Hosea 2:13; 13:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And it was I who taught Ephraim to walk / (He [xref]a[/xref]took them in His arms), / But they did not know that I [xref]b[/xref]healed them.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 1:31; 8:2; 32:10-12; Isa. 46:3</xref>
        <xref num="b">Exo. 15:26</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>I drew them [note]1[/note]with cords of a man, / With bands of love;[br/]And I was to them like those / Who lift off the [note]2[/note]yoke on their jaws; / And I gently caused them to [note]2[/note]eat.</text>
        <note num="1">The phrase with cords of a man, with bands of love indicates that God loves us with His divine love not on the level of divinity but on the level of humanity. God's love is divine, but it reaches us in the cords of a man, i.e., through Christ's humanity. The cords through which God draws us include Christ's incarnation, human living, crucifixion, resurrection, and ascension. It is by all these steps of Christ in His humanity that God's love in His salvation reaches us ([link]Rom. 5:8[/link]; [link]1 John 4:9-10[/link]). Apart from Christ, God's everlasting love, His unchanging, subduing love, could not be prevailing in relation to us. God's unchanging love is prevailing because it is a love in Christ, with Christ, by Christ, and for Christ.</note>
        <note num="2">This yoke was Pharaoh's yoke in Egypt, and this eating was the eating of the manna, a type of Christ as our heavenly food ([link]John 6:31-35[/link]), in the wilderness. Pharaoh had put a strong yoke on Israel, but God took off that yoke and gently caused them to eat by bringing them into the wilderness, where God fed them with manna in a gentle way morning by morning ([link]Exo. 16:14-18[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>They will not return to the land of Egypt, / But the Assyrian will be their king, / For they refused to return [i]to Me.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And the sword will whirl about in their cities / And will consume their bars, / And it will devour [i]them[/i] because of their own counsels.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Indeed My people are bent upon turning away from Me; / Though they call them to [i]Him who is[/i] on high, / None at all exalts [i]Him.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>How shall I give you up, O Ephraim? / [i]How[/i] shall I deliver you up, O Israel? / How can I make you like [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Admah? / [i]How[/i] can I treat you like [note]1[/note]Zeboim? / My heart is turned within Me; / All My [xref]b[/xref]compassions have warmed.</text>
        <note num="1">Admah and Zeboim were destroyed with Sodom and Gomorrah ([link]Deut. 29:23[/link]). Israel had become even more evil than Sodom and Gomorrah. However, because of His everlasting love, God would not destroy Israel ([link]v. 9[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 14:8; Deut. 29:23</xref>
        <xref num="b">Deut. 32:36; Isa. 63:15; Jer. 31:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>I will not execute the fierceness of My anger; / I will not return to destroy Ephraim; / For I am God and [xref]a[/xref]not man, / The [xref]b[/xref]Holy One in the midst of you, / And I will not come in wrath.</text>
        <xref num="a">Num. 23:19; cf. Isa. 55:8-9; Mal. 3:6</xref>
        <xref num="b">Isa. 12:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>They will walk after Jehovah; / He will [xref]a[/xref]roar like a lion. / For He will roar, / And the children will come trembling from the [xref]b[/xref]west.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 31:4; Joel 3:16; Amos 1:2; Rev. 10:3</xref>
        <xref num="b">Zech. 8:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>They will come trembling like a bird from Egypt / And like a [xref]a[/xref]dove from the land of Assyria. / And I will cause them to [xref]b[/xref]dwell in their houses, / Declares Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 60:8; Hosea 7:11</xref>
        <xref num="b">Ezek. 28:25-26; 37:25</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Ephraim encompasses Me with lies, / And the house of Israel, with deceit; / And Judah is yet unsteadfast with God / And with the Holy One, the Faithful One.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="12">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Ephraim feeds on wind / And follows the east wind continually; / He multiplies lies and violence. / They make a covenant with [xref]a[/xref]Assyria, / And oil is carried into Egypt.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 15:19; 17:4; Hosea 5:13; 7:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Jehovah has also a [xref]a[/xref]controversy with Judah / And will punish Jacob according to his ways; / According to his doings He will recompense him.</text>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 4:1; Micah 6:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>In the womb he [xref]a[/xref]grasped his brother by the heel, / And in his full strength he contended with God.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 25:26</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Indeed he [xref]a[/xref]contended with the [note]1[/note]Angel and prevailed; / He wept and made supplication to Him. / At [xref]b[/xref]Bethel he found Him; / And there He spoke with us,</text>
        <note num="1">The Angel with whom Jacob contended was Christ ([link]Gen. 32:24-32[/link] and notes).</note>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 32:28</xref>
        <xref num="b">Gen. 28:19; 35:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Even Jehovah the God of hosts; / Jehovah is His memorial.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And you, [xref]a[/xref]return [i]there[/i] to your God; / Keep lovingkindness and justice, / And [xref]b[/xref]wait on your God continually.</text>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 14:1; Micah 6:8</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 37:7; Isa. 40:31</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>[i]He is[/i] a merchant; / In his hand are balances of deceit; / He loves to extort.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And Ephraim said, / I have surely become rich; / I have found wealth for myself. / In all my labors / They will find with me / No iniquity, which would be sin.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]But I have been Jehovah your God / Since the land of Egypt; / Yet again I will cause you to dwell in [xref]b[/xref]tents / As in the days of the appointed feast.</text>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 13:4</xref>
        <xref num="b">Lev. 23:42-43; Neh. 8:17; Zech. 14:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>I have also spoken unto the prophets: / And I have multiplied vision, / And through the prophets I have used similitudes.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Is [xref]a[/xref]Gilead iniquity? They are altogether vanity. / In [xref]b[/xref]Gilgal they sacrifice oxen; / Indeed their altars are like heaps / In the furrows of a field.</text>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 6:8</xref>
        <xref num="b">Hosea 4:15; 9:15; Amos 4:4; 5:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And Jacob fled into the country of [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Aram; / And Israel [xref]b[/xref]served for a wife, / And for a wife he kept [i]sheep.[/i]</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., Syria.</note>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 28:5; Deut. 26:5</xref>
        <xref num="b">Gen. 29:20, 27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And by a [xref]a[/xref]prophet Jehovah brought Israel up from Egypt, / And by a prophet he was kept.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 12:50-51; 13:3; Deut. 18:15; Psa. 77:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Ephraim [xref]a[/xref]provoked [i]Him[/i] to bitter anger; / Therefore his Lord will leave his bloodshed upon him / And will recompense him with his own reproach.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 17:11-18</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="13">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>When Ephraim spoke, there was trembling. / He exalted himself in Israel; / But he trespassed through [xref]a[/xref]Baal and died.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 17:16; Hosea 11:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And now they sin more and more / And make molten images for themselves out of their silver, / Idols according to their own understanding, / All of it the work of craftsmen. / Of them they say, / Let the men who sacrifice / Kiss the calves.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Therefore they will be like a morning cloud / And like dew that departs early, / Like chaff driven by a storm wind from the threshing floor / And like smoke from a window vent.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>But I have been Jehovah your God / Since the land of Egypt; / And you were to know no god except Me, / For there is no [xref]a[/xref]savior besides Me.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 43:11; 45:21</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>I knew you in the [xref]a[/xref]wilderness, / In the land of great drought.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 8:15; 32:10; Jer. 2:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>According to their pasturage they became [xref]a[/xref]full; / They became full, and their heart was exalted; / Therefore they have [xref]b[/xref]forgotten Me.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 8:12, 14; 32:15</xref>
        <xref num="b">Hosea 8:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Thus I will be to them like a [xref]a[/xref]lion; / Like a leopard I will watch [i]them[/i] along the way.</text>
        <xref num="a">Lam. 3:10; Hosea 5:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>I will meet them like a bear robbed of her cubs, / And I will tear away the covering of their heart; / And I will devour them there like a lioness; / The beast of the field will tear them to pieces.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>[i]It is[/i] your destruction, O Israel, / That you are against Me, against your help.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Where then is your king, / That he may save you in all your cities, / And your judges of whom you said, / [xref]a[/xref]Give me a king and some princes?</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 8:5-6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>I gave you a [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]king in My anger / And [xref]b[/xref]took [i]him[/i] away in My overflowing wrath.</text>
        <note num="1">The king given by Jehovah in His anger might have been Saul, who was eventually taken away by Jehovah in His overflowing wrath ([link]1 Sam. 8:4-7[/link]; [link]9:17[/link]; [link]10:1[/link]; [link]31:1-13[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 8:7; 10:19; Hosea 10:3</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 15:22-23; Acts 13:22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>The iniquity of Ephraim is bound up; / His sin is laid up in store.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>The [xref]a[/xref]pains of a woman giving birth will come upon him. / He is an unwise son; / For he should not delay at the time / The children break forth.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 13:8; Jer. 30:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>From the power of [note]1[/note]Sheol I will ransom them; / From [xref]a[/xref]death I will redeem them. / [xref]b[/xref]Where are your plagues, O death? / Where is your destruction, O [note]1[/note]Sheol? / [note]2[/note]Repentance will be hidden from My eyes.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]23[sup]1[/sup] in Matt. 11[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">God's love for Israel is everlasting (see note [link]1[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 11[/link]; [link]Jer. 31:3[/link]), and He will never repent of this love (cf. [link]Rom. 11:28-29[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 25:8; Ezek. 37:12</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Cor. 15:55; cf. 1 Cor. 15:26</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Even if he should be fruitful among [i]his[/i] brothers, / An east wind will come, / A wind of Jehovah / Coming up from the wilderness, / And his spring will become dry, / And his fountain will be dried up. / He will plunder the treasure / Of every desirable vessel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Samaria will be guilty, / For she rebelled against her God. / They will fall by the sword; / Their children will be dashed in pieces, / And their pregnant women will be ripped up.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 17:6</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="14">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Return, O Israel, / To Jehovah your God, / For you have fallen by your iniquity.</text>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 6:1; 12:6; Joel 2:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Take words with you, / And return to Jehovah; / Say to Him, / Forgive all iniquity, / And take [i]us[/i] graciously; / Thus we will render [note]1[/note]our [xref]a[/xref]lips [i]as[/i] bulls.</text>
        <note num="1">The Septuagint translates, the fruit of our lips (cf. [link]Heb. 13:15[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Heb. 13:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Assyria will not save us; / We will not ride upon horses. / Neither will we say again to the work of our hands, Our God! / Because in You the orphan finds compassion.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>[note]1[/note]I will [xref]a[/xref]heal their apostasy; / I will love them freely; / For My anger has turned away from him.</text>
        <note num="1">[link]Verses 4-8[/link] portray Israel in the restoration ([link]Matt. 19:28[/link]), as revealed in [link]2:15-23[/link]; [link]3:5[/link]; [link]6:1-3[/link]; [link]10:12[/link]. Israel's transformation as described in [link]vv. 4-7[/link] is based on the factor of love in life (see note [link]1[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 11[/link]). Love in affection does not transform, but love in life transforms people through the growth in life. Our relationship with God is of the divine, eternal life of God ([link]1 John 5:11[/link]). This life enlivens us, regenerates us, sanctifies us positionally and dispositionally, renews us, transforms us, conforms us, matures us, and glorifies us, making us the same as God in life, nature, appearance, and glory. At the beginning of this book Israel was a harlot, but at the end of this book, Israel has become a son ([link]11:1[/link]). Thus, the outcome of this book is transformation in life by God's love (cf. [link]Rom. 8:28-39[/link]; [link]Heb. 12:5-10[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 15:26; Isa. 57:18; Jer. 3:22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>I will be like the [xref]a[/xref]dew to Israel; / He will bud like the [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]lily / And will send forth his roots like [i]the[/i] [note]2[/note][i]trees of[/i] Lebanon.</text>
        <note num="1">Signifying a pure life that trusts in God ([link]Matt. 6:28[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Signifying standing steadily in the uplifted humanity (cf. [link]S.S. 3:9[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 32:2</xref>
        <xref num="b">S.S. 2:1-2; Matt. 6:28</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>His [note]1[/note]shoots will go forth; / And his [note]2[/note]splendor will be like [i]that of[/i] the [xref]a[/xref]olive tree, / And his [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]fragrance, like [i]that of the trees of[/i] Lebanon.</text>
        <note num="1">Signifying flourishing and spreading.</note>
        <note num="2">Signifying glory in faithfulness.</note>
        <note num="3">Signifying the sweet odor of a life in the uplifted humanity.</note>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 52:8; 128:3</xref>
        <xref num="b">Gen. 27:27; S.S. 4:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Those who [note]1[/note]sit under his shade will return; / They will revive [i]like[/i] [note]2[/note]grain / And will [note]3[/note]bud like the vine; / His [note]4[/note]renown will be like the wine of Lebanon.</text>
        <note num="1">Signifying being overshadowed by the sufficient grace enjoyed by them ([link]2 Cor. 12:9[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Signifying being full of life for producing satisfying food.</note>
        <note num="3">Signifying blossoming for producing cheering drink.</note>
        <note num="4">Signifying a good name spreading like tasteful wine.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Ephraim [i]says,[/i] What have I yet to do with idols? / I respond and look on him. / I am like a [note]1[/note]green [xref]a[/xref]fir tree; / [note]2[/note]From Me your fruit is found.</text>
        <note num="1">Symbolizing God's being living and evergreen.</note>
        <note num="2">Ephraim's bearing fruit from Jehovah indicates Israel's oneness with Jehovah. This is more than an organic union; it is the oneness of two in one life, in one nature, and in one living.</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 41:19; 55:13; 60:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Who is wise? / Then let him understand these things. / [i]Who is[/i] intelligent? Then let him know them. / For the [xref]a[/xref]ways of Jehovah are right, / And the righteous will walk in them, / But the transgressors will stumble in them.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 32:4; Psa. 145:17</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    </chapters>
</book>
