<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book name="James" description="THE EPISTLE OF JAMES" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="..\bible.xsd">
    <info title="Author">James, a slave of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ; the Lord's flesh brother ([link]1:1[/link]; [link]Matt. 13:55[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Time of Writing">Perhaps around A.D. 50, prior to the decline of the church, which is never alluded to in this book.</info>
    <info title="Place of Writing">Probably Jerusalem, from which James apparently never departed.</info>
    <info title="Recipients">The twelve tribes in dispersion (see [link]1:1[/link] and notes 3 and 4).</info>
    <subject>Practical Christian Perfection</subject>
    <outlines>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="1" ref="1:1">Introduction &amp;#8212; To the Twelve Tribes in Dispersion</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="2" ref="1:2-5:20">Practical Virtues of Christian Perfection</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="1:2-12">Enduring Trials by Faith</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="1:13-18">Resisting Temptation as God-born Ones</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="1:19-27">Living a God-fearing Life by the Implanted Word according to the Perfect Law of Freedom</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="4" ref="2:1-13">Having No Respect of Persons among the Brothers</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="5" ref="2:14-26">Being Justified by Works in Relations with the Believers</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="6" ref="3:1-12">Bridling the Tongue</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="7" ref="3:13-18">Behaving in Wisdom</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="8" ref="4:1-10">Dealing with Pleasures, the World, and the Devil</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="9" ref="4:11-12">Not Speaking against the Brothers</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="10" ref="4:13-17">Confiding Not in Self-will but in the Lord</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="" ref="5:1-6">(Warning to the Rich)</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="11" ref="5:7-11">Awaiting the Lord's Coming with Long-suffering</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="12" ref="5:12">Speaking Honestly without Swearing</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="13" ref="5:13-20">Healthy Practices in the Church Life</outline>
    </outlines>
    <chapters>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[note]1[/note]James, a [xref]a[/xref]slave of God and of the [note]2[/note]Lord Jesus Christ, to the [note]3[/note]twelve [xref]b[/xref]tribes in the [note]4[/note][xref]c[/xref]dispersion: [note]5[/note]Rejoice!</text>
        <note num="1">A flesh brother of the Lord Jesus ([link]Matt. 13:55[/link]) and of Jude ([link]Jude 1[/link]). He was not one of the twelve apostles chosen by the Lord while He was on earth, but he became an apostle after the Lord's resurrection ([link]Gal. 1:19[/link]), and he became the leading elder in the church at Jerusalem ([link]Acts 12:17[/link]; [link]15:2[/link], [link]13[/link]; [link]21:18[/link]). Reputed to be, with Peter and John, a pillar of the church, he was mentioned by Paul as the first among the three pillars (Gal. [link]2:9[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">James ranked the Lord Jesus as equal with God. This was contrary to Judaism, which did not recognize the deity of the Lord ([link]John 5:18[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">The tribes of Israel. This indicates that this Epistle was written to the Jewish Christians, who had the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ of glory ([link]2:1[/link]) and were justified by faith ([link]2:24[/link]), regenerated by the word of truth ([link]v. 18[/link]), and indwelt by the Spirit of God ([link]4:5[/link]), and who were members of the church ([link]5:14[/link]), awaiting the Lord's coming back ([link]5:7-8[/link]). However, for the writer to call these believers in Christ "the twelve tribes," as God's chosen people were called in His Old Testament economy, indicates that he lacked a clear view concerning the distinction between Christians and Jews, between God's New Testament economy and the Old Testament dispensation. Apparently, he did not see that in the New Testament God had delivered and separated the Jewish believers in Christ from the Jewish people, who were then considered by God a perverse generation ([link]Acts 2:40[/link]). In His New Testament economy, God does not consider the Jewish believers to be Jews set apart for Judaism but Christians set apart for the church. As members of the church of God, they should be as distinct and separate from the Jews as they are from the Gentiles ([link]1 Cor. 10:32[/link]). Yet James, a pillar of the church, in his Epistle to the Christian brothers still called them "the twelve tribes." (This might have been the reason that he addressed the word in [link]5:1-6[/link] to the rich class in general among the Jews.) This was contrary to God's New Testament economy. See note [link]2[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 2[/link].</note>
        <note num="4">See note [link]1[sup]4[/sup] in 1 Pet. 1[/link]. This dispersion must have included the scattering of the Jewish believers from Jerusalem caused by the persecution after Pentecost ([link]Acts 8:1[/link], [link]4[/link]).</note>
        <note num="5">See note [link]10[sup]3[/sup] in 2 John[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 1:1[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 1:1[/link]; [link]Jude 1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 26:7[/link]; [link]Luke 22:30[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Deut. 32:26[/link]; [link]Ezek. 20:23[/link]; [link]John 7:35[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Count [i]it[/i] all [xref]a[/xref]joy, my [xref]b[/xref]brothers, whenever you fall into various [note]1[/note][xref]c[/xref]trials,</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]12[sup]1[/sup][/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Matt. 5:12[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 4:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]James 1:16[/link], [link]19[/link]; [link]2:1[/link], [link]5[/link], [link]14[/link]; [link]3:1[/link], [link]10[/link], [link]12[/link]; [link]4:11[/link]; [link]5:7[/link], [link]9[/link], [link]10[/link], [link]12[/link], [link]19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]James 1:12[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Knowing that the [xref]a[/xref]proving of your [note]1[/note]faith works out [xref]b[/xref]endurance.</text>
        <note num="1">The Christian faith, given by God in Christ ([link]2 Pet. 1:1[/link]; [link]James 2:1[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 1:12[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 5:3[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 1:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And let [xref]a[/xref]endurance have [i]its[/i] perfect work that you may be [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]perfect and entire, lacking in nothing.</text>
        <note num="1">Although James did not have a clear view concerning the distinction between grace and law, his Epistle is distinguished and remarkable in its presentation of Christian conduct, emphasizing practical Christian perfection that the believers might be perfect and entire, lacking in nothing. This may be considered the main subject of this Epistle. Such perfection in Christian behavior requires the trials of God's governmental dealing and the believers' endurance by the virtue of the divine birth through regeneration by the implanted word ([link]vv. 18[/link], [link]21[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 5:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]James 3:2[/link]; [link]Matt. 5:48[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 5:23[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>But if any one of you lacks [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]wisdom, let him [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]ask of God, who gives to all [note]3[/note]liberally and does [note]4[/note]not reproach, and it will be given to him.</text>
        <note num="1">It was by His wisdom that God, in Christ, made His eternal plan and carried it out ([link]1 Cor. 2:7[/link]; [link]Eph. 3:9-11[/link]; [link]Prov. 8:12[/link], [link]22-31[/link]). And in His New Testament economy God made Christ first our wisdom ([link]1 Cor. 1:24[/link], [link]30[/link]). The wisdom of God is needed for practical Christian perfection. Hence, we need to ask God for it.[br][br]In light of the content of this Epistle, it is apparent that James did not have a clear vision concerning God's New Testament economy. However, he did have the wisdom to portray matters that concern the practical Christian life.</note>
        <note num="2">James was reputed to be a man of prayer. Here he charged the recipients of his Epistle to pray for wisdom, implying that his wisdom was given to him by God through prayer. In his Epistle he stressed prayer ([link]5:14-18[/link]). Prayer is a virtue of practical Christian perfection.</note>
        <note num="3">Or, with simplicity, generously, without reserve ([link]Rom. 12:8[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 8:2[/link]).</note>
        <note num="4">A stingy man would not give; if he were to give, he would give with reproaches, with stinging words. God, who gives to all liberally, is not like such a man.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 3:13[/link], [link]17[/link]; [link]1 Kings 3:9-12[/link]; [link]Prov. 2:2[/link], [link]6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Prov. 28:5[/link]; [link]Mark 11:24[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>But let him ask in [xref]a[/xref]faith, [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]doubting nothing, for he who [note]1[/note]doubts is like the surge of the [xref]c[/xref]sea, driven by the [xref]d[/xref]wind and tossed about.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, wavering...wavers.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Mark 11:24[/link]; [link]Matt. 9:29[/link]; [link]15:28[/link]; [link]Heb. 11:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Matt. 21:21[/link]; [link]Rom. 4:20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">cf. [link]Isa. 57:20[/link]; [link]Jude 13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">cf. [link]Eph. 4:14[/link]; [link]Jude 12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>For that man must not suppose that he will receive anything from the Lord;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>[i]He is[/i] a [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]double-souled man, unstable in all his ways.</text>
        <note num="1">God made man only one soul, with one mind and one will. When a believer doubts in prayer, he makes himself double-souled, like a boat with two rudders, uncertain in direction. Faith in prayer also is a virtue of practical Christian perfection.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 4:8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And let the lowly brother [note]1[/note]boast in his [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]exaltation,</text>
        <note num="1">Or, glory, rejoice. When a lowly brother boasts and rejoices in exaltation, spontaneously he is led to praise the Lord ([link]5:13[/link]). He should not boast in the secular way, i.e., without praising the Lord.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, elevation, high estate.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 4:10[/link]; [link]Luke 1:52[/link]; [link]14:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And the [note]1[/note]rich in his being brought low, because like a [xref]a[/xref]flower of the grass he will [xref]b[/xref]pass away.</text>
        <note num="1">It is easy for a lowly brother to boast, rejoice, and praise the Lord in his exaltation. It is not easy for a rich one to do so in his being brought low. Whether in exaltation or in being brought low, to rejoice and praise is a virtue of practical Christian perfection.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Job 14:2[/link]; [link]Psa. 103:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Cor. 7:31[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>For the [note]1[/note]sun rises with its [note]2[/note]scorching heat and withers the [xref]a[/xref]grass, and its flower falls off, and the [xref]b[/xref]beauty of its appearance is destroyed; so also the [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]rich man will fade away in his pursuits.</text>
        <note num="1">In [link]v. 6[/link] James used the surge of the sea to illustrate a doubting heart, and in [link]v. 10[/link] he used the flower of the land to portray the fading rich man. Here he used the sun in the heavens with its scorching heat to illustrate the factor that causes man's riches to fade under God's governmental dealing. In [link]v. 17[/link] he used even the turning of the planets to illustrate variableness, which is in contrast to the invariableness of God the Father. In dealing with the problem of our tongue in [link]3:3-12[/link], he used twenty kinds of things for illustrations. Moreover, in [link]4:14[/link] he used vapor to portray the brief appearing of our life, and in [link]5:7-8[/link] he used the farmer's long-suffering to teach us how to await the Lord's coming. James was a wise and experienced man, having not only the experience of human life but also wisdom from the divine source through his seeking by prayer ([link]v. 5[/link]; [link]3:13[/link], [link]17[/link]). Yet his sympathy for and compromise with Judaism frustrated him from seeing a thorough vision of the wisdom concerning God's New Testament economy, a vision that Paul saw and unveiled in his Epistles. See notes [link chapter="3"]12[sup]1[/sup][/link] and [link]17[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 3[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Or, hot wind.</note>
        <note num="3">What a sobering word to those who pursue riches! Yet it is a soothing word to the rich who are being brought low through the loss of their riches.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 37:2[/link]; [link]90:5-6[/link]; [link]102:11[/link]; [link]Isa. 40:6-8[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:24[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. [link]Matt. 6:28-30[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Luke 12:16-20[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 6:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Blessed is the man who endures [note]1[/note]trial, because when he has become [note]2[/note]approved by testing, he will receive the [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]crown of [note]4[/note]life, which He [xref]c[/xref]promised to those who [note]5[/note][xref]d[/xref]love Him.</text>
        <note num="1">[link]Verses 2-12[/link] deal with trials (see note [link]13[sup]1[/sup][/link]). Trials come from the believers' environment to prove their faith ([link]vv. 2-3[/link]) through suffering ([link]vv. 9-11[/link]). The believers should endure the trials with all joy ([link]v. 2[/link]) because of their love for the Lord, that they may receive the blessing of the crown of life.</note>
        <note num="2">I.e., the approving of the believers' faith ([link]v. 3[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">The glory, the expression, of life. The believers endure trials by means of the divine life, and this will become their glory, their expression, the crown of life, as a reward to them at the Lord's appearing, for their enjoyment in the coming kingdom ([link]2:5[/link]).</note>
        <note num="4">The crown of life in this verse, the begetting Father and His begetting us, His making us the firstfruits of His creatures ([link]vv. 17-18[/link], [link]27[/link]), and the implanted word ([link]v. 21[/link]), all point to the believers' need for the divine life.</note>
        <note num="5">To believe in the Lord is to receive the divine life for our salvation; to love the Lord is to grow in the divine life for our maturity that we may be qualified for a reward &amp;#8212; the crown of life &amp;#8212; and enjoy the glory of the divine life in the kingdom.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 5:11[/link]; [link]Job 5:17[/link]; [link]Psa. 94:12[/link]; [link]Matt. 5:10-11[/link]; [link]Luke 6:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rev. 2:10[/link]; cf. [link]1 Cor. 9:25[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 4:8[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 5:4[/link]; [link]Rev. 3:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]James 2:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Cor. 2:9[/link]; [link]8:3[/link]; [link]Mark 12:30[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Let no one say when he is [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]tempted, I am tempted [note]2[/note]of God; for God [note]3[/note]cannot be tempted of evil, and He Himself [note]4[/note]tempts no one.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, tried, tested. The Greek word for [i]trials[/i] and [i]trial[/i] in [link]vv. 2[/link] and [link]12[/link] is the noun form of the word for [i]tempted[/i] here and in [link]v. 14[/link]. The two words are very similar in form; both refer to being tried, tested, proved. To be tried, tested, proved, by outward suffering in the environment is a trial ([link]v. 2[/link]). To be tried, tested, proved, by the inward enticing of lust is a temptation ([link]v. 14[/link]). The trial is dealt with in [link]vv. 2-12[/link]; the temptation is dealt with in [link]vv. 13-21[/link]. As for the trial, we should endure it by loving the Lord that we may obtain the blessing &amp;#8212; the crown of life. As for the temptation, we should resist it by receiving the implanted word that we may obtain salvation &amp;#8212; the salvation of our souls ([link]v. 21[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., from.</note>
        <note num="3">The Greek word means both [i]is untried[/i] and [i]is untriable;[/i] hence, not temptable, not to be tempted, incapable of being tempted.</note>
        <note num="4">The devil, not God, is the tempter ([link]Matt. 4:3[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 3:5[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Matt. 6:13[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 10:13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>But each one is tempted when he is drawn away and enticed by his own [xref]a[/xref]lusts;</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 2:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Then the lust, having conceived, [note]1[/note]gives birth to sin; and the sin, when it is fully grown, brings forth [xref]a[/xref]death.</text>
        <note num="1">The tempter, the devil, is the begetting father of sin ([link]1 John 3:8[/link], [link]10[/link]), having the might of death ([link]Heb. 2:14[/link]) through sin ([link]1 Cor. 15:56[/link]). He injected sin into Adam, and through sin death passed on to all men ([link]Rom. 5:12[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 5:12[/link]; [link]6:21[/link], [link]23[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Do not be deceived, my beloved brothers.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>All good [note]1[/note]giving and every perfect [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]gift is from [xref]b[/xref]above, coming down from the [note]2[/note]Father of lights, with whom is no [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]variation or shadow cast by turning.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Giving[/i] refers to the act of giving; [i]gift[/i] refers to the thing given.</note>
        <note num="2">[i]Lights[/i] here refers to the heavenly luminaries. The Father is the Creator, the source, of these shining bodies. With Him there is no shadow cast by turning (in contrast to the situation with the heavenly orbs, where the moon waxes and wanes by its revolving, and the sun can be eclipsed by the moon), for He is not variable, not changeable. As such, He is incapable of being tempted by evil, nor does He tempt anyone.</note>
        <note num="3">Or, variableness.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 85:12[/link]; [link]John 3:27[/link][br/]See note 17[sup]1[/sup].</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]James 3:15[/link]; [link]John 8:23[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Psa. 102:27[/link]; [link]Mal. 3:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>He [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]brought us forth by the [note]2[/note]word of [xref]b[/xref]truth, [note]3[/note]purposing that we might be a kind of [note]4[/note][xref]c[/xref]firstfruits of His creatures.</text>
        <note num="1">Sin, the source of darkness, brings forth death ([link]v. 15[/link]). But the Father of lights brought us forth to be the firstfruits of His creatures, full of the vigorous life that matures first. This refers to the divine birth, our regeneration ([link]John 3:5[/link], [link]6[/link]), which is carried out according to God's eternal purpose.</note>
        <note num="2">The word of the divine reality, of what the Triune God is ([link]John 1:14[/link], [link]17[/link]). This word is the seed of life, by which we have been regenerated ([link]1 Pet. 1:23[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">Of His own will, by His intention, to carry out His purpose by begetting us that we may become the firstfruits of His creatures.</note>
        <note num="4">God will renew His entire creation to have a new heaven and new earth with the New Jerusalem as the center ([link]Rev. 21:1-2[/link]). He first regenerated us to be the firstfruits of His new creation by imparting His divine life into our being that we might live a life of perfection. This must be the seed of practical Christian perfection. This life will consummate in the New Jerusalem as the living center of God's eternal new universe.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Pet. 1:3[/link], [link]23[/link]; [link]John 1:13[/link]; [link]1 John 2:29[/link]; [link]3:9[/link]; [link]5:1[/link], [link]18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]James 3:14[/link]; [link]5:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">cf. [link]Jer. 2:3[/link]; [link]Rev. 14:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>[note]1[/note]You know [i]this,[/i] my beloved brothers; but let every man be quick to hear, [note]2[/note]slow to [xref]a[/xref]speak, slow to [xref]b[/xref]wrath;</text>
        <note num="1">Or, Know [i]this.[/i]</note>
        <note num="2">Hearing tempts us to speak, and speaking is the fire that kindles wrath (cf. [link]3:6[/link]). If we bridle our speaking (cf. [link]v. 26[/link]), we will quench our wrath. James's word here, given to strengthen his view of practical Christian perfection, has the tone of the Old Testament proverbs ([link]Prov. 10:19[/link]; [link]14:17[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eccl. 5:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Prov. 14:17[/link], [link]29[/link]; [link]16:32[/link]; [link]Eccl. 7:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>For the [note]1[/note]wrath of man does not accomplish the righteousness of God.</text>
        <note num="1">The righteousness of God does not need the help of man's wrath, which is of no use in the carrying out of God's righteousness.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Therefore [xref]a[/xref]putting away all [xref]b[/xref]filthiness and the abundance of malice, receive in [xref]c[/xref]meekness the [note]1[/note]implanted [xref]d[/xref]word, which is able to [note]2[/note]save your souls.</text>
        <note num="1">This likens the word of God to a living plant that is planted into our being and grows in us to bring forth fruit for the salvation of our souls. We need to receive such a word in meekness, in all submission, without any resistance.</note>
        <note num="2">The salvation of our souls, according to the context of this chapter, implies the enduring of trials raised up by the environment ([link]vv. 2-12[/link]) and the resisting of the temptation of lust ([link]vv. 13-21[/link]). James's view concerning the salvation of our souls was somewhat negative and was not as positive as that of Paul, who said that our soul can be transformed by the renewing Spirit, even into the image of the Lord from glory to glory ([link]Rom. 12:2[/link]; [link]Eph. 4:23[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 3:18[/link]). See notes [link]5[sup]5[/sup] in 1 Pet. 1[/link] and [link]39[sup]3[/sup] in Heb. 10[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 4:22[/link]; [link]Heb. 12:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]2 Cor. 7:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]James 3:13[/link]; [link]Matt. 5:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 Pet. 1:23[/link]; [link]Matt. 13:19[/link], [link]23[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And become [xref]a[/xref]doers of the word and not [xref]b[/xref]hearers only, who [xref]c[/xref]delude themselves.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 2:14-20[/link]; [link]Luke 8:21[/link]; [link]John 13:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Luke 11:28[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]James 1:26[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Because if anyone is a hearer of the word and not a [xref]a[/xref]doer, this one is like a man considering in a [xref]b[/xref]mirror the face he was born with;</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 4:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Cor. 13:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>For he considers himself and goes away, and immediately forgets what kind of person he is.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>But he who [note]1[/note]looks into the [note]2[/note]perfect law, the [xref]a[/xref][i]law[/i] of [xref]b[/xref]freedom, and continues in [i]it,[/i] becoming not a forgetful hearer but a doer of the work, this one will be [xref]c[/xref]blessed in his doing.</text>
        <note num="1">The same word as in [link]1 Pet. 1:12[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Here James refers to the Mosaic law as "the perfect law, the law of freedom (or liberty)" (cf. [link]2:12[/link]). His use of this expression might have been based on [link]Psa. 19:7-8[/link], which says that the law is perfect, that it restores the soul, i.e., gives people freedom, and that it makes the heart joyous, implying release and freedom, and on [link]Psa. 119:11[/link], which says that keeping the law in our hearts frees us from sin. James uplifted the Old Testament law of letters to the uttermost, mixing God's New Testament economy with the outdated Old Testament economy ([link]Acts 21:18-20[/link]). In his consideration the law was a primary means of Christian perfection. In contrast, the apostle Paul said that the law can do nothing to perfect us ([link]Heb. 7:19[/link]; cf. [link]Gal. 3:3[/link]). Cf. note [link]12[sup]2[/sup] in ch. 2[/link].[br][br]In God's New Testament dispensation Christ has ended the law ([link]Rom. 10:4[/link]; [link]Heb. 10:9[/link]), and the believers have been freed by Christ from the yoke of slavery of the law ([link]Gal. 5:1[/link]), have died to the law ([link]Gal. 2:19[/link]), and are no longer under the law but under grace ([link]Rom. 6:14[/link]; cf. [link]John 1:17[/link]). Moreover, the law of letters written on tablets of stone outside us has been replaced by the law of life inscribed on our hearts ([link]Heb. 8:10[/link]), the moral standard of which corresponds with that of the kingdom's constitution, decreed by the Lord on the mount ([link]Matt. 5-7[/link]). Since the law of letters was not able to give man life ([link]Gal. 3:21[/link]) but was able only to expose man's weakness and failure and keep him in slavery ([link]Gal. 5:1[/link] and note 4), it was a law of bondage. Since the law of life is the function of the divine life, which was imparted into our being at regeneration and supplies us throughout our Christian life with the unsearchable riches of the divine life to free us from the law of sin and death and fulfill all the righteous requirements of the law of letters ([link]Rom. 8:2[/link], [link]4[/link]), it should be considered the law of freedom. This law is the law of Christ ([link]1 Cor. 9:21[/link]), even Christ Himself, who lives within us to regulate us by imparting the divine nature into our being, that we may live a life that expresses God's image. It is this law that should be considered the basic rule of the Christian life for practical Christian perfection.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 2:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]John 8:32[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]John 13:17[/link]; [link]Luke 11:28[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>If anyone thinks himself to be [note]1[/note]religious [i]and yet[/i] does [note]2[/note]not bridle his [xref]a[/xref]tongue but [xref]b[/xref]deceives his heart, this one's [note]1[/note]religion is vain.</text>
        <note num="1">In Greek, [i]religious[/i] (adjective) and [i]religion[/i] (noun) refer to ceremonial service and worship to God (implying the fear of God). The adjective is used only here. The noun is used in a positive sense here and in [link]v. 27[/link], in a negative sense in [link]Col. 2:18[/link] (for [i]worship[/i]), and in a general sense in [link]Acts 26:5[/link]. James's writing concerning God's New Testament economy is not as striking as Paul's, Peter's, and John's. Paul focuses on Christ living and being formed in us ([link]Gal. 2:20[/link]; [link]4:19[/link]) and Christ being magnified in us and lived out of us ([link]Phil. 1:20-21[/link]) that we as the church, His Body, may become His fullness, His expression ([link]Eph. 1:22-23[/link]). Peter stresses the fact that God regenerated us through the resurrection of Christ ([link]1 Pet. 1:3[/link]), making us partakers of His divine nature, that we may live a life of godliness ([link]2 Pet. 1:3-7[/link]) and be built up as a spiritual house to express His virtues ([link]1 Pet. 2:5[/link], [link]9[/link]). John emphasizes the eternal life, given to us for our fellowship with the Triune God ([link]1 John 1:2-3[/link]), and the divine birth, which brings into us the divine life as the divine seed that we may live out a life that is like God ([link]1 John 2:29[/link]; [link]3:9[/link]; [link]4:17[/link]) and be the church, a lampstand, which bears the testimony of Jesus ([link]Rev. 1:9[/link], [link]11-12[/link]) and which will consummate in the New Jerusalem for God's expression unto eternity ([link]Rev. 21:2-3[/link], [link]10-11[/link]). Of the matters that are characteristic of the New Testament, James stresses only God's begetting of us ([link]v. 18[/link]), the indwelling Spirit ([link]4:5[/link]), and a minor aspect of the church ([link]5:14[/link]). He does not speak of Christ as our life or of the church as the expression of Christ, the two most outstanding and dispensational characteristics of the New Testament. This Epistle shows that James must have been very religious. It might have been because of this and his practical Christian perfection that he was reputed to be, along with Peter and John, a pillar, even the first, in the church at Jerusalem (Gal. [link]2:9[/link]). However, he was not strong in the revelation of God's New Testament economy in Christ but was still under the influence of the background of the old Judaic religion, the primary elements of which were to worship God by ceremonies and to live a life in the fear of God. This is proved by the words in [link]Acts 21:20-24[/link] and in [link]2:2-11[/link] of this Epistle. Because his spiritual sight was covered by Judaism, he could not fully enter into the revelation of God's New Testament economy as Paul, Peter, and John were able to do.</note>
        <note num="2">Not to bridle the tongue is to speak quickly (cf. [link]v. 19[/link]) and loosely without restriction. This always deceives the speaking one's own heart, deceiving his conscience &amp;#8212; the consciousness of his heart.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 34:13[/link]; [link]39:1[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 3:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]James 1:22[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 3:13[/link]; [link]Titus 1:10[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>This is pure and undefiled religion before our God and Father: to visit [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]orphans and widows in their affliction [i]and[/i] to keep oneself [note]2[/note]unspotted from the [note]3[/note]world.</text>
        <note num="1">In this word of James's, given to strengthen his view of practical Christian perfection, an element of the Old Testament charges is implied ([link]Deut. 14:29[/link]; [link]24:19-21[/link], [link]12-13[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Not to be worldly, not to be stained by worldliness. This too is a part of James's God-fearing view of practical Christian perfection. To visit orphans and widows is to act according to God's loving heart, a characteristic of perfection on the positive side, and to keep oneself unspotted from the world is to be separated from the world according to God's holy nature, a characteristic of perfection on the negative side.</note>
        <note num="3">See note [link]4[sup]3[/sup] in ch. 4[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Isa. 1:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>My [xref]a[/xref]brothers, do not hold the [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]faith of our Lord Jesus Christ [note]2[/note]of [xref]c[/xref]glory with [xref]d[/xref]respect of persons.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, faith in our Lord...; cf. note [link]22[sup]1[/sup] in Rom. 3[/link]. This indicates that this Epistle, and especially this chapter, was written to the New Testament believers in the Lord Jesus Christ of glory.</note>
        <note num="2">Most translators add, the Lord.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 2:5[/link], [link]14[/link]; [link]1:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 3:22[/link]; [link]Gal. 2:15-16[/link]; [link]3:22[/link], [link]26[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Cor. 2:8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]James 2:9[/link]; [link]Deut. 1:17[/link]; [link]16:19[/link]; [link]Matt. 22:16[/link]; [link]Rom. 2:11[/link]; [link]Job 34:19[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>For if there comes into your [note]1[/note]synagogue a man with [xref]a[/xref]gold rings in splendid clothing, and there also comes in a [xref]b[/xref]poor man in filthy clothing,</text>
        <note num="1">The Greek word is composed of [i]together[/i] and [i]to bring;[/i] hence, a collecting, gathering, congregating; and thence, the place of gathering. It was used in the New Testament to denote the congregation of the Jews ([link]Acts 13:43[/link]; [link]9:2[/link]; [link]Luke 12:11[/link]) and their congregating place ([link]Luke 7:5[/link]), where they sought the knowledge of God by studying the Holy Scriptures ([link]Luke 4:16-17[/link]; [link]Acts 13:14-15[/link]). In Jerusalem there were numerous synagogues for different groups of Jews ([link]Acts 6:9[/link]). James's use of this word here may indicate that the Jewish believers considered their assembly and assembling place as another of the synagogues among the Jews. If so, this bears, as does the whole Epistle, a Jewish character and may indicate that the Jewish Christians regarded themselves as still a part of the Jewish people, the chosen people of God according to the Old Testament, and that they lacked a clear vision concerning the distinction between God's chosen people of the Old Testament and the believers in Christ of the New Testament. See note [link]1[sup]3[/sup] in ch. 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 2:9[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 3:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Gal. 2:10[/link]; [link]Prov. 18:23[/link]; [link]19:17[/link]; [link]22:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And you look upon the one wearing the splendid clothing and say, You sit here in a good place, and to the poor man you say, You stand there, or sit under my footstool;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Have you not made [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]distinctions [note]2[/note]among yourselves and become judges with evil reasonings?</text>
        <note num="1">The distinctions that existed between the rich and the poor among the Christian brothers and that resulted in discrimination were a shame to the Lord and to the salvation of His divine life.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, in.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]James 3:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Listen, my beloved brothers: Did not God [xref]a[/xref]choose the poor [note]1[/note]in the world [i]to be[/i] [xref]b[/xref]rich in faith and heirs of the [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]kingdom, which He [xref]d[/xref]promised to those who [note]3[/note][xref]e[/xref]love Him?</text>
        <note num="1">Or, to; i.e., in the world's esteem.</note>
        <note num="2">The kingdom of God here is also the kingdom of Christ, which will be inherited by the overcoming believers in the coming age ([link]Eph. 5:5[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:21[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 6:10[/link]; [link]Rev. 20:4[/link], [link]6[/link]). The reality of this kingdom (see note [link]3[sup]4[/sup] in Matt. 5[/link]) should be practiced not in the Jewish synagogue but in the Christian church, which is the Body of Christ ([link]Rom. 14:17[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">We believe in the Lord for our salvation ([link]Acts 16:31[/link]); we love God ([link]1 John 2:5[/link], [link]15[/link]) for our overcoming, that we may receive the promised kingdom as a reward (see notes [link]28[sup]1[/sup] in Heb. 12[/link] and [link]35[sup]1[/sup] in Heb. 10[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 1:27-28[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Luke 12:21[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 8:9[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 6:18[/link]; [link]Rev. 2:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Luke 12:32[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]James 1:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]1 Cor. 2:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>But you have [xref]a[/xref]dishonored the poor. Is it not the [xref]b[/xref]rich [i]who[/i] oppress you and [i]is it not[/i] they [i]who[/i] [xref]c[/xref]drag you to the [note]1[/note]courts?</text>
        <note num="1">Or, tribunals.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 11:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]James 5:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Acts 8:3[/link]; [link]16:19[/link]; [link]18:12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Is it not they [i]who[/i] blaspheme the [note]1[/note]honorable [xref]a[/xref]name [note]2[/note]by which you are called?</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., good. This is the honorable name of Jesus Christ.</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., which is called upon you. See [link]Acts 15:17[/link] and note.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Isa. 63:19[/link]; [link]65:1[/link]; [link]Amos 9:12[/link]; [link]Acts 15:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>If indeed you are fulfilling the [note]1[/note]royal law according to the Scripture, "You shall [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]love your neighbor as yourself," you do well;</text>
        <note num="1">The royal law is the commandment, "You shall love your neighbor as yourself." This is the king of all laws, and it covers and fulfills all laws ([link]Gal. 5:14[/link]; [link]Rom. 13:8-10[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Loving God ([link]v. 5[/link]) and loving one's neighbor are the greatest requirements of the law. All the law hangs on these ([link]Matt. 22:36-40[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Lev. 19:18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>But if you [xref]a[/xref]respect persons, you [note]1[/note]commit sin, being convicted by the law as transgressors.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., work.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 2:1[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>For whoever [note]1[/note]keeps the whole [xref]a[/xref]law yet stumbles in [xref]b[/xref]one [i]point[/i] has become guilty of all.</text>
        <note num="1">The word in [link]vv. 8-11[/link] indicates that the Jewish believers at James's time were still practicing the keeping of the Old Testament law. This corresponds with the word in [link]Acts 21:20[/link] spoken to Paul by James and the elders in Jerusalem. James, the elders in Jerusalem, and many thousands of Jewish believers were still in a mixture of the Christian faith and the Mosaic law. They even advised Paul to practice such a semi-Judaic mixture ([link]Acts 21:17-26[/link]). They were unaware that the dispensation of law was altogether over and that the dispensation of grace should be fully honored, and that any disregard of the distinction between these two dispensations would be against God's dispensational administration and would be a great damage to God's economical plan for the building up of the church as the expression of Christ. Thus, this Epistle was written under the cloud of a semi-Judaic mixture, under a background that was obscured. Many who practice religion according to their natural concept neglect the background seen in this book.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Deut. 27:26[/link]; [link]Gal. 3:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Matt. 5:19[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>For He who said, Do not commit [xref]a[/xref]adultery, also said, Do not murder. Now if you do not commit adultery, but you murder, you have become a transgressor of the law.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Exo. 20:13-14[/link]; [link]Deut. 5:17-18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>[note]1[/note]So speak and so do as those who are to be [xref]a[/xref]judged by the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]law of freedom.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]So[/i] refers to what follows, not to what has gone before.</note>
        <note num="2">Based on [link]vv. 8-11[/link], which refer to the keeping of the law of letters, the law of freedom here and in [link]1:25[/link] refers to the same law, the law of Moses. According to the context the royal law ([link]v. 8[/link]), the Mosaic law, and the law of freedom are the same law. Thus, James taught the Jewish believers to keep the law of the Old Testament ([link]4:11[/link]; cf. [link]Acts 15:21[/link]; [link]21:20-25[/link]). However, according to God's New Testament economy the believers should speak and do things according to the law of life, which transcends the law of letters. They should live according to the law of life. This kind of living surpasses the keeping of the law of letters. The unbelievers will be judged at the great white throne ([link]Rev. 20:11-15[/link]) by the law of letters, which is the law of Moses; the believers will be judged at Christ's judgment seat ([link]2 Cor. 5:10[/link]) by the law of life, which is the law of Christ.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 3:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]James 1:25[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>For the judgment is without [xref]a[/xref]mercy to him who has shown no mercy; mercy [note]1[/note]triumphs over judgment.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, boasts over, boasts against.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 3:17[/link]; cf. [link]Job 22:6-11[/link]; [link]Psa. 18:25-26[/link]; [link]Prov. 21:13[/link]; [link]Ezek. 25:12-14[/link]; [link]Matt. 18:32-35[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>What is the profit, my brothers, if anyone says he has faith but does not have works? Can that faith [note]1[/note]save him?</text>
        <note num="1">According to the context, this is to be saved from the judgment at Christ's judgment seat that is without mercy ([link]v. 13[/link]). We must have works of mercy and love toward the believers. Only then can we be saved from the judgment that is without mercy.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>If a brother or sister [note]1[/note]is [xref]a[/xref]without clothing and lacks daily food,</text>
        <note num="1">The verb indicates that they have been in this condition for some time.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Job 31:19-20[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And any one of you says to them, [note]1[/note]Go in peace, be warmed and filled, yet you do [xref]a[/xref]not give them the [note]2[/note]necessities of the body, what is the profit?</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., Go away.</note>
        <note num="2">It is shameful for the necessities of the poor saints to be neglected in the church life. However, James's word here, given to strengthen his view of practical Christian perfection, carries the flavor of the Old Testament concern for needy people ([link]Deut. 15:7-8[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 John 3:17-18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>So also [note]1[/note]faith, if it does not have works, is [xref]a[/xref]dead [note]2[/note]in itself.</text>
        <note num="1">Faith is of life; it is living and operates through love ([link]Gal. 5:6[/link]). Otherwise, it is a dead faith and is not genuine ([link]vv. 20[/link], [link]26[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., according to.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 2:26[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>But someone will say, You have faith, and I have works; show me your faith without the works, and I will show you my faith by my [xref]a[/xref]works.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 3:13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>You believe that God is [xref]a[/xref]one. You do well; the [xref]b[/xref]demons also believe and shudder.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Deut. 6:4[/link]; [link]Rom. 3:30[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 8:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Matt. 8:28-29[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>But are you willing to know, O vain man, that faith without its works is [note]1[/note]useless?</text>
        <note num="1">Or, barren. Some MSS read, dead.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Was not Abraham our father justified by works in that he offered up [xref]a[/xref]Isaac his son upon the altar?</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 22:9[/link]; [link]Heb. 11:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>You see that [xref]a[/xref]faith worked together with his works, and by these works faith was perfected.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Thes. 1:3[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>And the Scripture was fulfilled which says, "And Abraham [xref]a[/xref]believed God, and it was [xref]b[/xref]accounted to him as righteousness"; and he was called the [xref]c[/xref]friend of God.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 15:6[/link]; [link]Rom. 4:3[/link]; [link]Gal. 3:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. [link]Psa. 106:31[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Chron. 20:7[/link]; [link]Isa. 41:8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>You see that a man is [note]1[/note]justified by [xref]a[/xref]works and not by [xref]b[/xref]faith only.</text>
        <note num="1">To be justified by faith is for the receiving of the divine life ([link]Rom. 5:18[/link]); to be justified by works is through living the divine life. Since the living is the issue of life, to be justified by works is the issue of being justified by faith. Abraham's offering of Isaac and Rahab's receiving of the messengers and sending them out are works that issued from their living faith. A living tree surely brings forth fruit. Being justified by works is not inconsistent with being justified by faith. The latter is the cause, bringing forth the former; the former is the effect, the outcome and proof, of the latter.[br][br]This chapter begins with the matter of having no respect of persons ([link]vv. 1-13[/link]) and arrives at the practical care for the necessities of the poor saints, which is the justifying work of faith ([link]vv. 14-26[/link]). These virtues, according to James's view, can be considered characteristics of practical Christian perfection.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]Rom. 3:20[/link], [link]28[/link]; [link]Gal. 2:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 3:30-31[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>And in like manner was not also [xref]a[/xref]Rahab the harlot justified by works in that she received the messengers and [note]1[/note]sent [i]them[/i] out by a different way?</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., thrust [i]them[/i] out.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Josh. 2:1-21[/link]; [link]6:23[/link]; [link]Heb. 11:31[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>For just as the body without the [note]1[/note]spirit is dead, so also faith without works is [xref]a[/xref]dead.</text>
        <note num="1">The spirit gives life to the body ([link]Gen. 2:7[/link]); the works indicate and express the life that is in the faith.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 2:17[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Do not become many [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]teachers, my [xref]b[/xref]brothers, knowing that we will receive greater [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]judgment.</text>
        <note num="1">Teachers tend to bring in different teachings, producing different opinions and causing trouble and division (cf. [link]2 Tim. 4:3[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 1:3-4[/link], [link]7[/link]; [link]Eph. 4:14[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Whatever we say will be judged, and we will be judged by our word ([link]Matt. 12:36-37[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rom. 2:20-21[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]James 1:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]James 2:12[/link], [link]13[/link]; [link]5:9[/link], [link]12[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>For in many things we all stumble. If anyone does not stumble in [xref]a[/xref]word, this one is a [xref]b[/xref]perfect man, able to [xref]c[/xref]bridle the whole body as well.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Matt. 12:37[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]James 1:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]James 1:26[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Now if we put [xref]a[/xref]bridles into the mouths of horses that they would obey us, we direct their whole body as well.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 32:9[/link]; [link]Prov. 26:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Behold, the ships also, though they are so great and are driven by rough winds, are directed by a very small rudder wherever the impulse of the pilot wills.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>So also the [xref]a[/xref]tongue is a little member yet boasts great things. Behold, how great a forest so little a [note]1[/note]fire ignites!</text>
        <note num="1">A wildfire with the power to spread.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 12:3-4[/link]; [link]73:8-9[/link]; [link]120:2-4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And the tongue is a [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]fire; the [i]very[/i] world of unrighteousness, the tongue is set among our members as that which [xref]b[/xref]contaminates the whole body and sets on fire the [note]2[/note]course of life and is set on fire by [note]3[/note]Gehenna.</text>
        <note num="1">An evil fire from Gehenna that contaminates us. Like the wildfire, the tongue spreads its destruction, and like the evil fire, it contaminates our whole body with evils from Gehenna.</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word for [i]course[/i] refers generally to anything round or circular that runs or rolls like a wheel. Used figuratively, it indicates a circuit of physical effects, a course, like an orbit around the sun. The word for [i]life[/i] means [i]origin, birth, generation.[/i] Hence, the phrase can be rendered [i]the wheel of birth,[/i] referring figuratively to our human life, which is set in motion at its birth and runs on to its close. The tongue as an evil fire from Gehenna sets on fire our human life, which rolls like a wheel from our birth to our death, with the result that the course of our entire life is wholly under the tongue's evil contamination and corruption.</note>
        <note num="3">Signifying the lake of fire ([link]Rev. 20:15[/link]). See note [link]22[sup]8[/sup] in Matt. 5[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Prov. 16:27[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Matt. 15:18[/link], [link]20[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>For every nature, both of beasts and of birds, both of reptiles and of creatures of the sea, is tamed and has been tamed by the human [note]1[/note]nature;</text>
        <note num="1">The natures of beasts on the land, birds in the air, reptiles in the dust, and creatures in the water have been tamed by the nature of man, which is stronger than all the animal natures. However, even the stronger human nature is not able to tame the tongue.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>But the tongue no one among men is able to tame; [i]it is[/i] a [note]1[/note]restless evil, full of deadly [xref]a[/xref]poison.</text>
        <note num="1">As a restless evil, the tongue never ceases to do evil. It is full of deadly poison. Evil and death go together with the tongue, which spreads evil and death to contaminate and poison all human beings. It is the same even among Christians.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 140:3[/link]; [link]Rom. 3:13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>With it we bless the Lord and Father, and with it we curse men, who have been made according to the [xref]a[/xref]likeness of God.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Gen. 1:26[/link]; cf. [link]1 Cor. 11:7[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Out of the same mouth come forth blessing and cursing. These things, my brothers, ought not to be so.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Does the spring, out of the same [note]1[/note]opening, gush forth the sweet and the bitter?</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to a hole, a cave.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Can a fig tree, my brothers, produce olives? Or a vine, [xref]a[/xref]figs? Neither [i]can[/i] [note]1[/note]salt water produce sweet.</text>
        <note num="1">In [link]vv. 3-12[/link], in dealing with the problem of the tongue, James, in his wisdom concerning human life, used twenty different items as illustrations: bridles of horses, rudders of ships, a wildfire, the world of unrighteousness, fire from Gehenna, the wheel of birth, beasts, birds, reptiles, creatures of the sea, the human nature, a restless evil, a deadly poison, a spring, a fig tree, olives, a vine, figs, salt (bitter) water, and sweet water. James was rich in wisdom concerning human life, somewhat like Solomon, the wise king of the Old Testament ([link]1 Kings 4:29-34[/link]), but not so in wisdom concerning the divine economy. See note [link]11[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Matt. 7:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Who is [xref]a[/xref]wise and understanding among you? Let him show [note]1[/note]by his [xref]b[/xref]good manner of life his [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]works in [note]3[/note][xref]d[/xref]meekness of [xref]e[/xref]wisdom.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., out of.</note>
        <note num="2">Conduct ([link]Phil. 1:27[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">According to the context, [i]meekness of wisdom[/i] should refer here to restraint in speaking. This corresponds with [link]Prov. 10:19[/link]. Such meekness equals forbearance and compliance ([link]v. 17[/link]), which are in contrast to bitter jealousy and selfish ambition in boasting and lying ([link]v. 14[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Psa. 107:43[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Pet. 3:13[/link], [link]16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]James 2:18[/link], [link]22[/link], [link]24[/link], [link]26[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]James 1:21[/link]; [link]Gal. 6:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]James 3:17[/link]; [link]1:5[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>But if you have bitter [xref]a[/xref]jealousy and selfish ambition in your heart, do not boast and lie against the [xref]b[/xref]truth.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 4:2[/link]; [link]Rom. 13:13[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 12:20[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:20[/link]; [link]Phil. 1:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]James 1:18[/link]; [link]5:19[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 2:4[/link] and note 2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>[note]1[/note]This wisdom is not that which descends from [xref]a[/xref]above, but is [note]2[/note]earthly, [xref]b[/xref]soulish, [xref]c[/xref]demonic.</text>
        <note num="1">The wisdom of having bitter jealousy and selfish ambition in boasting and lying against the truth ([link]v. 14[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">[i]Earthly[/i] refers to the world, [i]soulish[/i] to the natural man, and [i]demonic[/i] to the devil and his demons. These three are always linked to one another.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 1:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Cor. 2:14[/link]; [link]Jude 19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]1 Tim. 4:1[/link]; [link]Rev. 16:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>For where jealousy and selfish ambition are, there [xref]a[/xref]disorder and every worthless practice are.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]1 Cor. 14:40[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>But the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]wisdom from above is first [xref]b[/xref]pure, then [xref]c[/xref]peaceable, [note]2[/note]forbearing, [note]3[/note]compliant, full of [xref]d[/xref]mercy and good [xref]e[/xref]fruit, [xref]f[/xref]impartial, [xref]g[/xref]without hypocrisy.</text>
        <note num="1">This wisdom includes meekness ([link]v. 13[/link]) and the human virtues mentioned in the rest of this verse. All these are characteristics of practical Christian perfection according to James's view, which was under the influence of Old Testament precepts concerning man's behavior, morality, and ethics ([link]Prov. 4:5-8[/link]). Such wisdom does not attain to the height of the wisdom concerning the hidden mystery of God's New Testament economy regarding Christ and the church ([link]1 Cor. 2:6-8[/link]; [link]Eph. 3:9-11[/link]). See note [link]11[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 1[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Or, gentle, lenient, sweetly reasonable ([link]Phil. 4:5[/link] and note 2). I.e., amiable.</note>
        <note num="3">Or, yielding; i.e., willing to yield, satisfied with less than is due, easily entreated. Being forbearing and compliant equals being meek ([link]v. 13[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 3:13[/link]; [link]1:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Phil. 4:8[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 3:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Gal. 5:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]James 2:13[/link]; [link]Matt. 9:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="e">[link]Heb. 12:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="f">cf. [link]James 2:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="g">[link]2 Cor. 6:6[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 1:5[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 1:5[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:22[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]fruit of righteousness is [xref]b[/xref]sown in [xref]c[/xref]peace [note]2[/note]by those who [xref]d[/xref]make peace.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]11[sup]1[/sup] in Heb. 12[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Or, for.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Phil. 1:11[/link]; [link]Heb. 12:11[/link]; [link]Isa. 32:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Prov. 11:18[/link]; [link]Hosea 10:12[/link]; [link]Gal. 6:7-8[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Heb. 12:14[/link]; [link]Rom. 12:18[/link]; [link]Gal. 5:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Matt. 5:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Where [i]do[/i] wars and fightings among you [i]come from?[/i] Are they not from this, from your [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]pleasures that [xref]b[/xref]war in your members?</text>
        <note num="1">The same Greek word as in [link]v. 3[/link]. Here it refers to the lusts of the pleasures of the flesh (members), whereas in [link]v. 3[/link] it refers to the pleasures that satisfy the lusts of the flesh.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 4:3[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 3:4[/link]; [link]Titus 3:3[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 2:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rom. 7:23[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 2:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>You [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]lust and do not have; you [xref]b[/xref]murder and are [xref]c[/xref]jealous and are not able to obtain; you fight and make war. You do not have because you do not ask;</text>
        <note num="1">Or, covet.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 2:3[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Isa. 1:15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]James 3:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>You [xref]a[/xref]ask and do not receive because you ask evilly that you may spend [i]it[/i] on your [xref]b[/xref]pleasures.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Zech. 7:13[/link]; cf. [link]1 John 5:14-15[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]James 4:1[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>[note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Adulteresses, do you not know that the [note]2[/note]friendship of the [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]world is enmity with God? Therefore whoever determines to be a [xref]c[/xref]friend of the world is constituted an [note]4[/note]enemy of God.</text>
        <note num="1">God and Christ are our Husband ([link]Isa. 54:5[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 11:2[/link]). We should be chaste and love Him alone with our entire being ([link]Mark 12:30[/link]). If our heart is divided by loving the world, we become adulteresses.</note>
        <note num="2">I.e., love of the world for the pleasures of the flesh ([link]vv. 1[/link], [link]4[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">The satanic system, which is enmity with God. See note [link]15[sup]2[/sup] in 1 John 2[/link].</note>
        <note num="4">Loving the world constitutes God's lover an enemy of God.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Hosea 1:2[/link]; [link]2:2[/link]; [link]3:1[/link], [link]3[/link]; [link]4:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]John 15:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">cf. [link]James 2:23[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Or do you think that the Scripture says in vain: The [note]1[/note]Spirit, whom He has caused to [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]dwell in us, longs to envy?</text>
        <note num="1">When God acquired us to be His spouse, He put His Spirit into us to make us one with Him ([link]1 Cor. 6:19[/link], [link]16-17[/link]). He is a jealous God ([link]Exo. 20:5[/link]), and His Spirit is jealous over us with the jealousy of God ([link]2 Cor. 11:2[/link]), longing, jealously desiring, that we not make friends with His enemy and be His lover at the same time. This is the only time James mentioned God's indwelling Spirit, and it was from the negative side, concerning the abolishing of the friendship of the world, not from the positive side, concerning the building up of the Body of Christ.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, make His home. The indwelling Spirit makes His home in us that He may occupy our entire being (cf. [link]Eph. 3:17[/link]) for God, causing us to be wholly for our Husband.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 6:19[/link]; [link]Rom. 8:9[/link], [link]11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>But He gives [xref]a[/xref]greater grace; therefore [note]1[/note]it says, [note]2[/note]"God resists the [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]proud but gives grace to the [xref]c[/xref]humble."</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to the Scripture in [link]v. 5[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">A quotation of [link]Prov. 3:34[/link] from the Septuagint.</note>
        <note num="3">According to the context, this refers to our being proud toward God, which causes Him to resist us. Our being humble also is toward God and causes Him to give us grace, which He desires to do.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 4:33[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Pet. 5:5[/link]; [link]Psa. 138:6[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Job 22:29[/link]; [link]Prov. 29:23[/link]; [link]Isa. 57:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Be subject therefore to God; but [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]withstand the [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]devil, and he will flee from you.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., be humble toward God ([link]v. 10[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 5:6[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">To be proud toward God is to side with God's enemy, the devil; to be humble toward God, i.e., to be subject to God, is to withstand, i.e., to stand against, the devil. This is the best strategy for fighting God's enemy; it always causes him to flee from us.</note>
        <note num="3">The flesh implied in [link]v. 1[/link], the world in [link]v. 4[/link], and the devil here are the three major enemies of the believers. They are related to one another: the flesh is against the Spirit ([link]Gal. 5:17[/link]), the world is against God ([link]1 John 2:15[/link]), and the devil is against Christ ([link]1 John 3:8[/link]). The flesh indulges in pleasures by loving the world, and the world usurps us for the devil. This annihilates God's eternal purpose in us.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Eph. 6:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Eph. 4:27[/link]; [link]6:11[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 5:8-9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Draw near to God, and He will [xref]b[/xref]draw near to you. [xref]c[/xref]Cleanse [i]your[/i] hands, sinners, and [xref]d[/xref]purify [i]your[/i] hearts, [i]you[/i] [note]1[/note]double-souled!</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., double-minded (see note [link]8[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 1[/link]), having the heart divided between two parties &amp;#8212; God and the world. This makes people adulteresses ([link]v. 4[/link]) and sinners, those who need their hearts purified and their hands cleansed that they may draw near to God and God may then draw near to them.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. [link]2 Chron. 15:2[/link]; [link]Zech. 1:3[/link]; [link]Mal. 3:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Lam. 3:57[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]2 Cor. 7:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]1 John 3:3[/link]; [link]Jer. 4:14[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Endure [xref]a[/xref]misery and [xref]b[/xref]mourn and [xref]c[/xref]weep. Let your laughter be turned into mourning, and your joy into dejection.</text>
        <note num="1">This verse is a solemn admonition to God's adulterous spouse, who indulges herself in fleshly pleasures by loving the world under the usurpation of the devil.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Rev. 3:17[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Matt. 5:4[/link]; [link]Luke 6:25[/link]; [link]Job 5:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]James 5:1[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Be [xref]a[/xref]humbled before the Lord, and He will [xref]b[/xref]exalt you.</text>
        <note num="1">This word, as a conclusion to this section ([link]vv. 1-10[/link]), is an exhortation against the fightings and desires mentioned in [link]vv. 1-3[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Pet. 5:6[/link]; cf. [link]James 4:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]James 1:9[/link]; [link]Matt. 23:12[/link]; [link]Luke 1:52[/link]; [link]14:11[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Do not speak against [xref]a[/xref]one another, brothers. He who speaks against a brother or [xref]b[/xref]judges his brother speaks against the law and judges the law. But if you judge the law, you are not a [note]1[/note][xref]c[/xref]doer of the law but a judge.</text>
        <note num="1">James's words here and in [link]1:25[/link] and [link]2:8-12[/link] regarding the Old Testament law indicate that, in his view, the New Testament believers should keep the Old Testament law that they might be perfect according to the law. But according to the divine revelation in the entire New Testament, there is a definite, clear distinction between keeping the law and living by the inner law of life. Keeping the Old Testament law merely makes us right with God and men that we may be justified by the law. But living by the inner law of life ([link]Heb. 8:10-11[/link]; [link]Rom. 8:2[/link]) is to live and magnify Christ ([link]Phil. 1:20-21[/link]) for the building up of His Body to express Him ([link]Eph. 1:22-23[/link]) and for the building up of God's house to satisfy Him ([link]1 Tim. 3:15[/link]). This is for the accomplishing of God's eternal goal according to His New Testament economy. Though we become perfect by keeping the Old Testament law, we still cannot reach God's eternal goal. Only our living by the inner law of life avails for this. Such a living spontaneously and automatically fulfills more than is required under the Old Testament law ([link]Rom. 8:4[/link]), even to the standard of the constitution of the kingdom, as revealed in [link]Matt. 5-7[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 5:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Matt. 7:1[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 4:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]James 1:23[/link], [link]25[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>One is [xref]a[/xref]Lawgiver and [xref]b[/xref]Judge, who is able to save and [xref]c[/xref]destroy. But who are you who [xref]d[/xref]judge your neighbor?</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Isa. 33:22[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Psa. 58:11[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 4:4[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Matt. 10:28[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Rom. 14:4[/link], [link]13[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Come now, you who say, Today or tomorrow we [note]1[/note]will go into this or that city and spend a year there and do business and make a profit;</text>
        <note num="1">Fighting for fleshly pleasures ([link]v. 1[/link]), having a friendship with the world ([link]v. 4[/link]), speaking against a brother, i.e., judging the law ([link]v. 11[/link]), going to do business according to one's own will, and boasting in arrogance ([link]v. 16[/link]) are all signs of the ungodly and presumptuous confidence of a God-forgetting person. James's teaching on all these matters was based, probably, on his view concerning practical Christian perfection.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Whereas you do not know the matter of [xref]a[/xref]tomorrow, what your [xref]b[/xref]life will be; for you are a [note]1[/note][xref]c[/xref]vapor, which appears for a little while and then disappears.</text>
        <note num="1">The tone of James's word here also is like the tone of the Old Testament (cf. [link]Psa. 90:3-10[/link]). In any case, his word arouses a fear of one's self-will and instills a confidence in God, as expressed in [link]v. 15[/link]. This kind of word always comes out of the mouth of a God-fearing person.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Prov. 27:1[/link]; [link]Matt. 6:30[/link], [link]34[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Job 7:7[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Job 7:9[/link]; [link]30:15[/link]; [link]Psa. 102:3[/link]; [link]Hosea 6:4[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Instead you [i]ought[/i] to say, If the Lord [xref]a[/xref]wills, we will both live and do this or that.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 18:21[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 4:19[/link]; [link]16:7[/link]; [link]Heb. 6:3[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>But now you [xref]a[/xref]boast in your [note]1[/note]arrogance; all such boasting is evil.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, pretentiousness, vainglory.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 5:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Therefore to him who [xref]a[/xref]knows to do good and does not do [i]it,[/i] to him it is [xref]b[/xref]sin.</text>
        <note num="1">A concluding word to all the charges in the preceding verses. It says that if the recipients of this Epistle are helped by James's writing and yet will not do as he wrote, to them it is sin.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Luke 12:47-48[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]John 9:41[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="5">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Come now, you [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]rich, [xref]b[/xref]weep, [xref]c[/xref]howling over your miseries, which are coming upon you!</text>
        <note num="1">[link]Verses 1-6[/link] could be considered a parenthetical section, and it might have been addressed, in light of its contents, to the rich class in general among the Jews, since James considered the recipients of his Epistle to be the twelve tribes of the Jews ([link]1:1[/link]). See notes [link]1[sup]3[/sup] in ch. 1[/link] and [link]2[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 2[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 2:6[/link]; [link]Luke 6:24[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 6:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]James 4:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Isa. 13:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Your [xref]a[/xref]riches have rotted and your garments have become [xref]b[/xref]moth-eaten;</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Prov. 11:28[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Job 13:28[/link]; [link]Isa. 50:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Your gold and your silver have [xref]a[/xref]rusted, and their rust will be a testimony against you and will eat your flesh like fire. You have stored up [xref]b[/xref]treasure in the last days.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]Matt. 6:19-20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Luke 12:21[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Behold, the [xref]a[/xref]wages of the workmen who mowed your fields, which have been withheld by you, cry out; and the [note]1[/note]cries of those who reaped have entered into the ears of the [note]2[/note]Lord of hosts.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, imploring.</note>
        <note num="2">As in [link]Rom. 9:29[/link], this is equivalent to the divine title in Hebrew, [i]Jehovah-Sabaoth[/i] (Jehovah of hosts, Jehovah of armies &amp;#8212; [link]1 Sam. 1:3[/link]). Such a title bears a Jewish character.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Lev. 19:13[/link]; [link]Deut. 24:15[/link]; [link]Jer. 22:13[/link]; [link]Mal. 3:5[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>You have lived [xref]a[/xref]luxuriously on the earth and have [xref]b[/xref]given yourselves to pleasure; you have [note]1[/note]nourished your hearts in a day of slaughter.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., satiated their gluttonous desire in indulgence, even in a day of slaughter ([link]Jer. 12:3[/link]), i.e., in a day of judgment, when they were to be slaughtered like animals by God's judgment. This implies that they were in a stupor, unaware of their coming miseries, their miserable destiny ([link]v. 1[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Luke 16:19[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 2:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Tim. 5:6[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>You condemned, you murdered the [note]1[/note]righteous; he does not [xref]a[/xref]resist you.</text>
        <note num="1">The collective singular, with the article used to indicate the class. It does not refer directly to any individual but portrays the death of the Lord Jesus, who is the Righteous ([link]Acts 7:52[/link]; [link]3:14[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Matt. 5:39[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Therefore be [note]1[/note]long-suffering, [xref]a[/xref]brothers, until the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]coming of the Lord. Behold, the farmer eagerly [xref]c[/xref]awaits the precious fruit of the earth, exercising long-suffering over it until it receives the early and late [xref]d[/xref]rain.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]10[sup]2[/sup][/link].</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word means [i]presence[/i] (see note [link]3[sup]3[/sup] in Matt. 24[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 1:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]John 21:22[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 11:26[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 2:19[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">cf. [link]Titus 2:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Deut. 11:14[/link]; [link]Jer. 5:24[/link]; [link]Joel 2:23[/link]; [link]Zech. 10:1[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>You also be [note]1[/note]long-suffering; [xref]a[/xref]establish your hearts because the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]coming of the Lord has drawn [xref]c[/xref]near.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]10[sup]2[/sup][/link]. While we are awaiting with long-suffering the Lord's coming, He, as the real Farmer ([link]Matt. 13:3[/link]), is awaiting with patience our maturity in life as the firstfruits and harvest of His field ([link]Rev. 14:4[/link], [link]14-15[/link]). Our maturing in life can shorten the period of our long-suffering and His patience.</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]7[sup]2[/sup][/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Thes. 3:13[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Rev. 22:12[/link], [link]20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Rom. 13:11[/link]; [link]Heb. 10:25[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 4:7[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Do not [note]1[/note]complain, brothers, against [xref]a[/xref]one another lest you be [xref]b[/xref]judged. Behold, the [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]Judge stands before the [xref]d[/xref]doors.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., groan.</note>
        <note num="2">The Lord will come back not only as the Bridegroom to meet the bride ([link]Matt. 25:1[/link], [link]6[/link]; [link]Rev. 19:7-8[/link]) but also as the Judge to judge all peoples, judging first His believers at His judgment seat ([link]1 Cor. 4:4-5[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 5:10[/link]). We need to pursue maturity in life in order to meet the Lord and be prepared to be judged by Him.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 4:11[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]James 5:12[/link]; [link]3:1[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]John 5:22[/link]; [link]Acts 10:42[/link]; [link]17:31[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 4:1[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 4:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Matt. 24:33[/link]; [link]Mark 13:29[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>As an example, brothers, of [note]1[/note]suffering evil and of [note]2[/note]long-suffering, take the [xref]a[/xref]prophets, who spoke [note]3[/note]in the [xref]b[/xref]name of the Lord.</text>
        <note num="1">This is a further development of [link]vv. 7-8[/link], which concern the suffering and long-suffering of the faithful believers.</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word &amp;#8212; in noun form here and in [link]Heb. 6:12[/link]; [link]Rom. 2:4[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 4:2[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 3:20[/link], and in verb form in [link]vv. 7-8[/link] &amp;#8212; connotes patience toward persons, such as the patience the prophets had toward those who persecuted them.</note>
        <note num="3">Speaking in the name of the Lord indicates that the prophets were one with the Lord. Hence, their suffering and long-suffering were with the Lord and for the Lord. The faithful believers' suffering and long-suffering should be the same.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Matt. 5:12[/link]; [link]23:34[/link]; [link]Acts 7:52[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Jer. 11:21[/link]; [link]14:15[/link]; [link]26:9[/link], [link]20[/link]; [link]44:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Behold, we call those who [note]1[/note]endured [xref]a[/xref]blessed. You have heard of the endurance of [xref]b[/xref]Job, and you have seen his [xref]c[/xref]end from the Lord, that the Lord is very tenderhearted and [xref]d[/xref]compassionate.</text>
        <note num="1">The Greek word &amp;#8212; in verb form here and in noun form in [link]Rom. 5:3[/link] and [link]2 Cor. 1:6[/link] &amp;#8212; connotes patience toward things, such as the patience that Job had toward the things that afflicted him.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 1:12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Job 1:20-22[/link]; [link]2:10[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Job 42:10[/link], [link]12[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Exo. 34:6[/link]; [link]Psa. 103:8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>But [note]1[/note]above all things, my brothers, do [note]2[/note]not swear, neither by heaven nor by earth nor with any other oath; but let your [note]3[/note]yes be yes, and your no, no, [note]4[/note]lest you fall under [xref]a[/xref]judgment.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., before.</note>
        <note num="2">We should not swear, because we are nothing, and nothing is under our control or up to us ([link]Matt. 5:34-36[/link]). Swearing displays the acting of our self-will and our forgetting of God. But to let our yes be yes and our no be no is to act according to our divine nature, in the consciousness of the presence of God, denying our self-will and sinful nature.</note>
        <note num="3">See note [link]37[sup]1[/sup] in Matt. 5[/link].</note>
        <note num="4">Our being genuinely faithful and sincere in our words according to the divine nature, of which we partake, will keep us from God's judgment (cf. [link]Matt. 12:36[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 5:9[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Does anyone among you suffer evil? Let him [note]1[/note]pray. Is anyone cheerful? Let him [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]sing praise.</text>
        <note num="1">Praying brings us the strength of the Lord to endure suffering, and singing praise keeps us in the joy of the Lord.</note>
        <note num="2">The Greek word means primarily [i]play on a stringed instrument,[/i] and thence, [i]make melody.[/i] Hence, it denotes to sing a hymn, to sing praise. Whether we pray or sing praise, we contact God. In any environment and under any circumstance, humble or exalted, grievous or joyful, we need to contact the Lord.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Cor. 14:15[/link], [link]26[/link]; [link]Eph. 5:19[/link]; [link]Col. 3:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Is anyone among you [note]1[/note]ill? Let him [note]2[/note]call for the [xref]a[/xref]elders of the [xref]b[/xref]church, and let them pray over him, [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]anointing him with oil [note]4[/note]in the [xref]d[/xref]name of the Lord.</text>
        <note num="1">Ill because of weakness. Weakness leads to illness ([link]1 Cor. 11:30[/link]), and illness causes more weakness.</note>
        <note num="2">To call the elders of the church to pray regarding one's illness implies (1) that there is no problem between the calling one and the church, represented by the elders; (2) that a normal relationship has been restored between the calling one and the church, if the illness is due to the calling one's having offended the church (cf. [link]1 Cor. 11:29-32[/link]); and (3) that the sick one and the elders have thoroughly confessed to one another their sins ([link]v. 16[/link]). The barriers in the church must be cleared away before the elders can represent the church in praying for the sick ones.</note>
        <note num="3">Two Greek words are translated [i]anoint: aleipho,[/i] the word used here and in [link]John 12:3[/link], is the common term used for applying oil; [i]chrio[/i] means [i]to anoint officially for office,[/i] as a priest ([link]Acts 10:38[/link]), king ([link]Heb. 1:9[/link]), or prophet ([link]Luke 4:18[/link]). [i]Chrio,[/i] related to [i]Christos[/i] (Christ), is used for the anointing of the Son by the Father ([link]Acts 10:38[/link]). To anoint with oil signifies to impart the Spirit of life, who has been poured upon the Body of Christ as the anointing oil ([link]Psa. 133:2[/link]), to the sick member of the Body through the elders as representatives of the church, for the healing of the sick one (cf. [link]1 John 5:16[/link] and notes 3 and 4).</note>
        <note num="4">[i]In the name of the Lord[/i] signifies oneness with the Lord. The elders do not do the anointing alone; rather, by being one with the Lord, they represent both the Body and the Head to do the anointing.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]Acts 14:23[/link]; [link]15:2[/link], [link]6[/link], [link]22[/link]; [link]20:17[/link], [link]28[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 5:17[/link]; [link]Titus 1:5[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 5:1-2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Matt. 18:17[/link]; [link]Acts 8:1[/link]; [link]13:1[/link]; [link]Rom. 16:1[/link], [link]4[/link], [link]5[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 14:34[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 3:15[/link]; [link]Rev. 1:11[/link], [link]20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Mark 6:13[/link]; cf. [link]Exo. 30:25-26[/link], [link]30[/link]; [link]1 John 2:20[/link], [link]27[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]John 14:13-14[/link]; [link]15:16[/link]; [link]16:23-24[/link], [link]26[/link]; [link]Mark 16:17[/link]; [link]Luke 10:17[/link]; [link]Acts 16:18[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And the [note]1[/note]prayer of [xref]a[/xref]faith will save the one who is [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]sick, and the Lord will raise him up; and if he has [note]3[/note]committed sins, it will be [xref]c[/xref]forgiven him.</text>
        <note num="1">Not the usual form of the word for [i]prayer.[/i] It is translated [i]vow[/i] in [link]Acts 18:18[/link] and [link]21:23[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Or, weary.</note>
        <note num="3">The committing of sins is often the cause of illness ([link]John 5:14[/link]). In such cases forgiveness is always the cause of healing ([link]Matt. 9:2[/link], [link]5-7[/link]; [link]Mark 2:5[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 1:6[/link]; [link]Luke 5:20[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Mark 16:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]Isa. 33:24[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Therefore [xref]a[/xref]confess your sins to one another and pray for one another that you may be [xref]b[/xref]healed. The [xref]c[/xref]petition of a righteous man [note]1[/note]avails much in its working.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, is very effective.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 John 1:9[/link]; cf. [link]Matt. 3:6[/link]; [link]Acts 19:18[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Cor. 12:9[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">cf. [link]Gen. 20:17[/link]; [link]1 Kings 13:6[/link]; [link]2 Kings 20:2-5[/link]; [link]Job 42:8[/link]; [link]Prov. 15:29[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Elijah was a man of [xref]b[/xref]like feeling with us, and he [note]1[/note]earnestly prayed that it would not rain; and it did not rain on the earth for three years and six months.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., prayed in prayer. This indicates that a prayer from the Lord was given to Elijah, in which he prayed. He did not pray in his feeling, thought, intention, or mood, or in any kind of motivation, arising from circumstances or situations, to fulfill his own purpose. He prayed in the prayer given to him by the Lord for the accomplishing of His will.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Kings 17:1[/link]; [link]Luke 4:25[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Acts 14:15[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And he prayed again, and heaven gave [xref]a[/xref]rain, and the earth sprouted forth [i]with[/i] its fruit.</text>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Kings 18:42-45[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>My [xref]a[/xref]brothers, if any one among you is [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]led astray from the [xref]c[/xref]truth and someone [xref]d[/xref]turns him back,</text>
        <note num="1">This may imply that the ill one in [link]v. 14[/link] had been led astray from the truth and needed to be turned back.</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]James 5:12[/link]; [link]1:2[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]Mark 13:5[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="c">[link]James 1:18[/link]; [link]3:14[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="d">[link]Gal. 6:1[/link]; cf. [link]Mal. 2:6[/link]; [link]Luke 1:16[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Let him know that he who turns a [note]1[/note]sinner back from the error of his way will [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]save that one's soul from [note]3[/note]death and will [note]4[/note][xref]b[/xref]cover a multitude of [note]5[/note]sins.</text>
        <note num="1">According to the context of these two verses, this is not an unbelieving sinner but a believing brother who has been led astray from the truth and is turned back from his error to the truth. Hence, the salvation of his soul does not refer to the eternal salvation of the person but to the dispensational salvation of his soul from the suffering of physical death under God's discipline. James may also have considered all the virtues covered in [link]vv. 7-20[/link] to be aspects of practical Christian perfection.</note>
        <note num="2">See notes [link]21[sup]2[/sup] in ch. 1[/link], [link]5[sup]5[/sup] in 1 Pet. 1[/link], and [link]39[sup]3[/sup] in Heb. 10[/link].</note>
        <note num="3">Not eternal perdition but dispensational discipline by physical death (see note [link]16[sup]5[/sup] in 1 John 5[/link]). [i]From death[/i] here should equal [i]raise...up[/i] in [link]v. 15[/link].</note>
        <note num="4">This is an Old Testament expression ([link]Psa. 32:1[/link]; [link]85:2[/link]; [link]Prov. 10:12[/link]) used by James to indicate that turning an erring brother back is to cover his sins so that he is not condemned. [i]Cover...sins[/i] here should equal [i]sins...forgiven[/i] in [link]v. 15[/link], as in [link]Psa. 32:1[/link]; [link]85:2[/link].</note>
        <note num="5">Sins committed by the sinning brother, which brought forth death to him ([link]1:15[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 4:16[/link]</xref>
        <xref num="b">[link]1 Pet. 4:8[/link]</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    </chapters>
</book>
