<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="yes"?>
<book name="Jonah">
    <info title="Author">Jonah ([link]1:1[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Time of His Ministry">About 862 B.C., at the time of the prophet Elisha (896-838 B.C.).</info>
    <info title="Place of His Ministry">Nineveh, the capital of Assyria.</info>
    <info title="Object of His Ministry">The people of Nineveh ([link]1:2[/link]; [link]3:2[/link]).</info>
    <subject>Jehovah's Salvation Reaching Even unto the Gentile City Nineveh</subject>
    <outlines>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="1" ref="1:1">The introductory word</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="2" ref="1:2-17">Jonah's fleeing from Jehovah's commission</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="3" ref="2:1-10">Jonah's repenting</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="4" ref="3:1-10">Jonah's preaching</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="5" ref="4:1-11">Jonah's prejudice</outline>
    </outlines>
    <chapters>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Now the word of Jehovah came to [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Jonah the son of Amittai, saying,</text>
        <note num="1">Meaning dove. This indicates that God wanted Jonah to go out like a dove to preach the gospel of peace (cf. [link]Eph. 2:17[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 14:25</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Arise, go to [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Nineveh, the great city, and cry out against it, for their evil has come up before Me.</text>
        <note num="1">The capital of Assyria, located on the east bank of the Tigris River, first built by Nimrod ([link]Gen. 10:11[/link]; see note [link]8[sup]1[/sup][/link] there). God intended to judge Nineveh, but He also intended to extend His salvation of love to that evil Gentile city. For this reason He commissioned Jonah to go to Nineveh to cry out against the city.[br/][br/]In his being sent by God to Nineveh, Jonah typifies Christ, who was sent by God to preach the gospel of peace to the Gentiles ([link]Matt. 12:41[/link]). Jonah was a prophet who turned from Israel to the Gentiles. In this he was a type of Christ, who turned from Israel to the Gentiles ([link]Matt. 21:43[/link]; [link]Luke 4:25-27[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 10:11-12; Jonah 3:2-3; 4:11; Nahum 1:1; Zeph. 2:13; Matt. 12:41; Luke 11:32</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>But Jonah rose up to flee to [note]1[/note]Tarshish from the presence of Jehovah, and he went down to [xref]a[/xref]Joppa and found a ship going to Tarshish. So he paid the fare for it and went down into it to go with them to Tarshish [xref]b[/xref]from the presence of Jehovah.</text>
        <note num="1">Probably a Phoenician port on the Mediterranean Sea in present-day Spain. Jonah knew that God was "a gracious and compassionate God, long-suffering and abundant in lovingkindness and repentant of evil" ([link]4:2[/link]) and that God would change His mind and not judge Nineveh if the city repented. Anticipating this and not agreeing with God, Jonah fled from God's presence to Tarshish.</note>
        <xref num="a">2 Chron. 2:16; Acts 9:36</xref>
        <xref num="b">Gen. 4:16; Job 1:12; 2:7; Psa. 139:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>But Jehovah hurled a great [xref]a[/xref]wind toward the sea, and there was a great tempest on the sea, and the ship seemed to be about to break up.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 107:25</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Then the mariners became afraid, and each called out to his god. And they [xref]a[/xref]cast out the equipment that was on the ship into the sea to lighten themselves [i]of it.[/i] But Jonah had gone down into the innermost part of the vessel and lain down and fallen fast [xref]b[/xref]asleep.</text>
        <xref num="a">Acts 27:18-19, 38</xref>
        <xref num="b">Mark 4:38</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>So the ship captain approached him and said to him, How can you be fast asleep? Arise, call on your God. Perhaps God will give thought to us, and we will not perish.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And each man said to his companion, Come, let us [xref]a[/xref]cast lots that we may know on whose account this misfortune [i]has befallen[/i] us. So they cast lots, and the lot fell on Jonah.</text>
        <xref num="a">Josh. 7:14, 16; 1 Sam. 10:20-21; 14:41-42; Prov. 16:33</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Then they said to him, Tell us now, On whose account [i]has[/i] this misfortune [i]befallen[/i] us? What is your occupation? And where do you come from? What is your country? And of what people are you?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And he said to them, I am a [xref]a[/xref]Hebrew, and I fear Jehovah, the God of the heavens, who [xref]b[/xref]made the sea and the dry land.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 14:13; 39:14</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 95:5; 146:6; Neh. 9:6; Acts 17:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And the men became greatly afraid and said to him, What is this that you have done? For the men knew that he was fleeing from the presence of Jehovah, because he had told them [i]so.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And they said to him, What shall we do with you that the sea may be quiet for us? For the sea grew more and more tempestuous.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Then he said to them, Lift me up and cast me into the sea, and the sea will be quiet for you. For I know that [i]it is[/i] on my account [i]that[/i] this great tempest [i]has come[/i] upon you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Nevertheless the men rowed hard to get back to the dry land, but they could not, because the sea grew more and more tempestuous against them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And they cried out to Jehovah and said, Ah, Jehovah, let us not perish, we pray, for this man's life, and do not put innocent blood upon us; for You, Jehovah, have done as You pleased.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Then they lifted Jonah up and cast him into the sea, and the sea [xref]a[/xref]ceased its raging.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 89:9; Luke 8:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And the men were greatly afraid of Jehovah, and they offered a sacrifice to Jehovah and vowed vows.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And Jehovah prepared a great fish to swallow Jonah up, and Jonah was in the [xref]a[/xref]stomach of the fish for [note]1[/note]three days and three nights.</text>
        <note num="1">Jonah was swallowed by a great fish and was vomited out of it ([link]2:10[/link]) for the spreading of God's salvation to the Gentile Ninevites. Jonah is a type of Christ in His death and resurrection for the spreading of God's salvation to sinners, even to the Gentiles ([link]Matt. 12:39-41[/link]). Jonah's staying in the great fish three days and three nights typifies Christ's staying in the heart of the earth three days and three nights ([link]Matt. 12:40[/link] and note). Christ died and entered into Hades in the lower parts of the earth ([link]Acts 2:27a[/link]; [link]Eph. 4:9[/link]). He came forth from there in resurrection ([link]Acts 2:31-32[/link]), and in resurrection He became the life-giving Spirit ([link]1 Cor. 15:45b[/link]) for the preaching, the spreading, of the gospel to all the Gentile nations, as seen in the book of Acts.</note>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 12:40; 16:4; Luke 11:30</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Then Jonah prayed to Jehovah his God from the stomach of the fish,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And he said,[br/]I [xref]a[/xref]called out because of my distress / To Jehovah, and He answered me; / From the belly of [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]Sheol I cried out for help; / You heard my voice.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]23[sup]1[/sup] in Matt. 11[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 120:1; 130:1; 142:1; Lam. 3:55-56</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 16:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>You flung me into the [xref]a[/xref]depths, into the heart of the sea, / And the flood surrounded me; / [xref]b[/xref]All Your breakers and Your billows / Passed over me.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 69:2; 88:6-7; Lam. 3:54</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 42:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Therefore I said, I [xref]a[/xref]have been driven out / From before Your eyes; / Yet I will look again / [xref]b[/xref]Toward Your holy temple.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 31:22</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Kings 8:38</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Water encompassed me, [i]even[/i] to my soul; / The deep surrounded me; / Seaweed was wrapped about my head.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>To the bottom of the [i]sea[/i] mountains I went down; / The earth [i]with[/i] its bars was around me forever. / Then You [xref]a[/xref]have brought up my life from the [note]1[/note]pit, / O Jehovah my God.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, corruption.</note>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 16:10; Isa. 38:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>When my soul fainted within me, / I remembered Jehovah, / And my prayer [xref]a[/xref]came to You / In Your holy temple.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 18:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Those who regard empty vanities / Forsake the lovingkindness to them;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>But I will [xref]a[/xref]sacrifice to You / With the voice of thanksgiving; / That which I have vowed I will fully pay. / [xref]b[/xref]Salvation is of Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 50:14, 23; 116:17-18; Hosea 14:2; Heb. 13:15</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 3:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And Jehovah spoke to the fish, and it vomited Jonah out onto the dry land.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Then the word of Jehovah came to Jonah a second time, saying,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Arise, go to Nineveh, the great city; and proclaim to it the proclamation that I will speak to you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>So Jonah [note]1[/note]arose and went to Nineveh according to the word of Jehovah. Now Nineveh was an [note]2[/note]exceedingly great city, a three days' journey [i]in size.[/i]</text>
        <note num="1">After Jonah was adjusted, corrected, and subdued, he was willing to go along with God and receive His commission.</note>
        <note num="2">Lit., great to God.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And Jonah began to go through the city a day's journey and cried out and said, Yet [xref]a[/xref]forty days and Nineveh will be overturned!</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 7:4; 8:6; Exo. 24:18; Num. 13:25; 14:34; 1 Sam. 17:16; 1 Kings 19:8; Ezek. 4:6; Matt. 4:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And the men of [xref]a[/xref]Nineveh believed God, and they proclaimed a fast and put on sackcloth, from the greatest of them even to the least of them.</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 12:41; Luke 11:32</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And the word reached the king of Nineveh, and he arose from his throne and put away his majestic clothes from him and covered himself with [xref]a[/xref]sackcloth and sat in ashes.</text>
        <xref num="a">Esth. 4:1; Jer. 6:26; Dan. 9:3; Matt. 11:21; Luke 10:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And he issued a proclamation and declared in Nineveh by the decree of the king and his great men, saying, Let neither man nor beast nor herd nor flock taste anything; let them not feed, nor let them drink water.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And let man and beast be covered in sackcloth, and let them call to God strongly. And let each turn from his evil way and from the violence that is in his hands.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Who knows whether God will turn and repent, and will turn from His burning anger so that we do not perish?</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 12:22; Joel 2:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And God saw their deeds, that they turned from their evil way, and God [xref]a[/xref]repented for the evil that He said He would do to them; and He did not do [i]it.[/i]</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 18:8; Joel 2:13; Amos 7:3, 6</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>But it displeased Jonah greatly, and he was angry.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And he prayed to Jehovah and said, Ah, Jehovah, was this not what I said when I was still in my land? Therefore I anticipated [i]it[/i] by fleeing to Tarshish, for I know that You are a [xref]a[/xref]gracious and compassionate God, long-suffering and abundant in lovingkindness and repentant of evil.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 34:6; Psa. 86:15; 145:8; Joel 2:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And now, Jehovah, [xref]a[/xref]take my life, I pray, from me, for it is better for me to die than to live.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 19:4; Num. 11:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And Jehovah said, Do you do well to be angry?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Then Jonah went out from the city and sat to the east of the city. And he made a booth for himself there and sat underneath it in the shade until he could see what would happen to the city.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And Jehovah God prepared a [note]1[/note]castor-oil tree; and it came up over Jonah to be a shade over his head, that it might deliver him from his misfortune. And Jonah was exceedingly glad because of the tree.</text>
        <note num="1">A tree known for its broad leaves. So throughout this chapter where tree is used.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>But God prepared a worm when the dawn came up the next day, and it struck the tree, and [i]the tree[/i] withered.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And when the sun rose, God prepared a sultry east wind. And the sun beat down on Jonah's head, and he fainted. And he requested for himself that he might die, and said, It is better for me to die than to live.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And God said to Jonah, Do you do well to be angry about the tree? And he said, I do well to be angry unto death.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And Jehovah said, You had pity on the tree that you did not labor for nor cause to grow, which came into being overnight and perished overnight;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And I, should I not have [note]1[/note]pity on [xref]a[/xref]Nineveh, the great city, in which are more than a hundred and twenty thousand people who cannot discern between their right hand and their left, and many [note]2[/note]cattle?</text>
        <note num="1">This book indicates particularly that God is not the God only of a certain people; He is the God of all peoples ([link]Rom. 3:29[/link]). The Jews thought that they were the unique people of God. They considered themselves the firstborn son with the right to be the first to enjoy all that is of God ([link]Exo. 4:22[/link]; [link]Luke 15:11-32[/link]). But because the Jews responded to God wrongly, the Gentiles, not the Jews, became the first to enjoy God in His salvation ([link]Matt. 21:28-32[/link]; [link]Acts 13:45-48[/link]; [link]Rom. 11:11[/link], [link]17[/link], [link]25[/link]).[br/][br/]The book of Jonah indicates that while God was angry with Assyria, He would still be gracious and compassionate toward a great and sinful city such as Nineveh. This indicates that God's economy is to do things through Israel, His suffering people, and the nations, the consuming "locusts" ([link]Joel 1:4[/link] and note), to extend His salvation to all the peoples on earth ([link]Matt. 28:19[/link]; [link]Acts 1:8[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">In having pity on the evil Gentile city of Nineveh, God cared even for their cattle.</note>
        <xref num="a">Jonah 1:2; 3:2-3</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    </chapters>
</book>
