<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book name="Jude" description="THE EPISTLE OF JUDE" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="..\bible.xsd">
    <info title="Author">Jude, a slave of Jesus Christ and a flesh brother of James (the author of the Epistle of James) and of the Lord ([link]v. 1[/link] and note 1).</info>
    <info title="Time of Writing">Approximately A.D. 69, before the destruction of Jerusalem and around the same time as the writing of 2 Peter, as indicated by allusions to the decline of the church similar to those found in [link]2 Pet. 2[/link].</info>
    <info title="Place of Writing">Jerusalem or Judea, though this is difficult to establish with certainty.</info>
    <info title="Recipients">The Jewish believers, as indicated by the book's Jewish tone.</info>
    <subject>Contending for the Faith</subject>
    <outlines>
	<outline type="upper-roman" num="1" ref="vv. 1-2">Introduction &amp;#8212; To Those Called, Beloved, and Kept</outline>
	<outline type="upper-roman" num="2" ref="v. 3">Contending for the Faith</outline>
	<outline type="upper-roman" num="3" ref="v. 4">Heresies of the Apostates</outline>
	<outline type="upper-roman" num="4" ref="vv. 5-7">Historical Examples of the Lord's Judgment upon Apostasy</outline>
	<outline type="upper-roman" num="5" ref="vv. 8-19">The Evils of the Apostates and Their Punishment under the Lord's Judgment</outline>
	<outline type="upper-roman" num="6" ref="vv. 20-23">Charges to the Believers</outline>
	    <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="vv. 20-21">To Build Up Themselves upon the Most Holy Faith and to Live in the Triune God</outline>
	    <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="vv. 22-23">To Care for Others with Mercy in Fear</outline>
	<outline type="upper-roman" num="7" ref="vv. 24-25">Conclusion &amp;#8212; Praise to Him Who Is Able to Guard and Set the Believers before His Glory</outline>
    </outlines>
    <chapters>
	<chapter num="1">
	    <verse num="1">
		<text>[note]1[/note]Jude, a slave of Jesus Christ and a brother of [note]1[/note]James, to those who are [xref]a[/xref]called, [xref]b[/xref]beloved in God the Father, and [xref]c[/xref]kept [note]2[/note]by Jesus Christ:</text>
		<note num="1">Both Jude and James, who wrote the Epistle of James ([link]James 1:1[/link]), were brothers of the Lord Jesus in the flesh ([link]Matt. 13:55[/link]).</note>
		<note num="2">Or, for. [i]By[/i] points to the strength for and means of keeping; [i]for[/i] points to the purpose for and object of keeping. All the believers have been given to the Lord by the Father ([link]John 17:6[/link]). They are being kept for Him and by Him.</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]Rom. 1:6[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 1:24[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:15[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]Rom. 1:7[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 1:4[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="c">[link]Jude 24[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:5[/link]; [link]John 17:12[/link], [link]15[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 5:23[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="2">
		<text>[note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Mercy to you and [xref]b[/xref]peace and [xref]c[/xref]love be multiplied.</text>
		<note num="1">That mercy is mentioned instead of grace in the greeting may be due to the church's degradation and apostasy (cf. [link]vv. 21-22[/link]). See note [link]2[sup]1[/sup] in 2 Tim. 1[/link].</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]Matt. 9:13[/link]; [link]Rom. 9:15-16[/link], [link]18[/link], [link]23[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 1:16[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]1 Pet. 1:2[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 1:2[/link]; [link]2 John 3[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="c">[link]Eph. 6:23[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="3">
		<text>Beloved, while using all diligence to write to you concerning our [note]1[/note]common salvation, I found it necessary to write to you [i]and[/i] exhort [i]you[/i] to earnestly [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]contend for the [note]3[/note]faith once for all delivered to the [xref]b[/xref]saints.</text>
		<note num="1">General salvation, common to and held by all believers, like the common faith ([link]Titus 1:4[/link]).</note>
		<note num="2">Lit., struggle.</note>
		<note num="3">Not subjective faith as our believing but objective faith as our belief, referring to the things we believe in, the contents of the New Testament as our faith ([link]Acts 6:7[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 1:19[/link]; [link]3:9[/link]; [link]4:1[/link]; [link]5:8[/link]; [link]6:10[/link], [link]21[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 3:8[/link]; [link]4:7[/link]; [link]Titus 1:13[/link]), in which we believe for our common salvation. This faith, not any doctrine, has been delivered once for all to the saints. For this faith we should earnestly contend ([link]1 Tim. 6:12[/link]).</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]1 Tim. 6:12[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]Rom. 1:7[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 1:2[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="4">
		<text>[note]1[/note]For certain men have [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]crept in unnoticed, who of old have been [note]3[/note]written of beforehand for [note]4[/note]this judgment, [xref]b[/xref]ungodly men, [note]5[/note]perverting the [xref]c[/xref]grace of our God into [note]6[/note][xref]d[/xref]licentiousness and [note]5[/note][xref]e[/xref]denying [note]7[/note]our only Master and Lord, Jesus Christ.</text>
		<note num="1">[link]Verses 4-19[/link] closely parallel [link]2 Pet. 2[/link]. This indicates that this Epistle was written in the time of the church's apostasy and degradation.</note>
		<note num="2">Lit., gotten in by the side, or, slipped in by a side door (cf. [i]secretly bring in[/i] in [link]2 Pet. 2:1[/link], and note 2 there).</note>
		<note num="3">I.e., in the prophecies.</note>
		<note num="4">The judgment, unfolded in the succeeding verses, on the apostates' creeping in unnoticed. Judgment here is condemnation for punishment; it refers to being condemned to be punished.</note>
		<note num="5">The evil of the heretical apostates was (1) their perverting of the grace of God into wantonness, into the abusing of freedom (cf. [link]Gal. 5:13[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 2:16[/link]), and (2) their denying of the headship and lordship of the Lord. These two go together. Turning the grace of God into an abuse of freedom for the purpose of wantonness requires denying the Lord's rule and authority.</note>
		<note num="6">Or, wantonness; the same Greek word as for [i]licentiousness[/i] in [link]1 Pet. 4:3[/link] and [link]2 Pet. 2:2[/link].</note>
		<note num="7">Or, the only Master and our Lord Jesus Christ.</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]Gal. 2:4[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]Jude 15[/link], [link]18[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 2:5-6[/link]; [link]3:7[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="c">[link]1 Pet. 1:10[/link], [link]13[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 3:18[/link]; [link]Acts 11:23[/link]; [link]Heb. 12:15[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="d">[link]2 Pet. 2:2[/link], [link]7[/link], [link]18[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="e">[link]2 Pet. 2:1[/link][br/]See note 4[sup]5[/sup].</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="5">
		<text>But I intend to [xref]a[/xref]remind you, though you know all things once for all, that [note]1[/note]the Lord, having saved a people [xref]b[/xref]out of the land of Egypt, [note]2[/note]afterward [note]3[/note][xref]c[/xref]destroyed those who did not believe;</text>
		<note num="1">Some MSS read, Jesus.</note>
		<note num="2">Lit., secondly.</note>
		<note num="3">See note [link]1[sup]5[/sup], point 1, in 2 Pet. 2[/link].</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 1:12-13[/link]; [link]3:1[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]Exo. 13:3[/link], [link]9[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="c">[link]1 Cor. 10:5-11[/link]; [link]Heb. 3:16-18[/link]; [link]Jude 11[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="6">
		<text>And [xref]a[/xref]angels who did not keep their own [note]1[/note]principality but abandoned their [note]2[/note]own dwelling place, He has kept in eternal [xref]b[/xref]bonds under [note]3[/note]gloom for the [note]4[/note][xref]c[/xref]judgment of the great day;</text>
		<note num="1">The Greek word means [i]beginning[/i] (of power), [i]first place[/i] (of authority); hence, original dignity in a high position. The fallen angels did not keep their original dignity and position but abandoned their own dwelling place, which is in heaven, to come to earth at Noah's time to commit fornication with the daughters of men ([link]Gen. 6:2[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 3:19[/link] and note 3).</note>
		<note num="2">I.e., heaven.</note>
		<note num="3">In the gloomy pits of Tartarus ([link]2 Pet. 2:4[/link]).</note>
		<note num="4">Probably the final judgment of the great white throne (see note [link]4[sup]4[/sup] in 2 Pet. 2[/link]).</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 2:4[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">cf. [link]Rev. 20:2[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 2:9[/link]; [link]Rev. 20:12-13[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="7">
		<text>How [xref]a[/xref]Sodom and Gomorrah and the cities around them, who [note]1[/note]in like manner with these gave themselves over to fornication and went after [xref]b[/xref]different flesh, are set forth as an [xref]c[/xref]example, undergoing the [xref]d[/xref]penalty of eternal fire.</text>
		<note num="1">I.e., in the same manner as the fallen angels mentioned in the preceding verse. This proves that the angels in the preceding verse were the sons of God in [link]Gen. 6:2[/link], who, putting on human bodies, took humans as wives and committed fornication with different flesh, i.e., with human beings, who are different from angels. The males of Sodom, Gomorrah, and the surrounding cities indulged their lust with males ([link]Rom. 1:27[/link]; [link]Lev. 18:22[/link]), with flesh that was different from what God had ordained, according to the nature of His creation, for human marriage ([link]Gen. 2:18-24[/link]). By committing fornication with different flesh in this way, they acted in the same manner as the angels in the preceding verse and, consequently, underwent the penalty of eternal fire.</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 2:6[/link]; [link]Gen. 19:24[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]Rom. 1:27[/link]; [link]Lev. 18:22-23[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="c">cf. [link]Num. 26:10[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="d">[link]2 Thes. 1:9[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="8">
		<text>Nevertheless in like manner [note]1[/note]these dreamers also [xref]a[/xref]defile the flesh and despise [note]2[/note]lordship and revile [note]3[/note]dignities.</text>
		<note num="1">The ungodly men spoken of in [link]v. 4[/link] were dreamers, bearing the name of Christian yet doing things as in dreams, such as perverting the grace of God into licentiousness to defile their flesh, and denying Jesus Christ as our only Master and Lord, despising His lordship and reviling the authorities in His heavenly government.</note>
		<note num="2">See note [link]10[sup]2[/sup] in 2 Pet. 2[/link].</note>
		<note num="3">See note [link]10[sup]4[/sup] in 2 Pet. 2[/link].</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 2:10[/link], [link]20[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="9">
		<text>But [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Michael the [xref]b[/xref]archangel, when he contended with the [xref]c[/xref]devil and disputed concerning the [note]2[/note]body of Moses, [note]3[/note]did not dare to bring a [xref]d[/xref]reviling judgment against [i]him[/i] but said, The Lord [xref]e[/xref]rebuke you.</text>
		<note num="1">See note [link]11[sup]1[/sup] in 2 Pet. 2[/link].</note>
		<note num="2">Moses' body was buried by the Lord in a valley in the land of Moab, in a place known by no man ([link]Deut. 34:6[/link]). It must have been done purposely in this manner by the Lord. When Moses and Elijah appeared with Christ on the mount of transfiguration ([link]Matt. 17:3[/link]), Moses must have been manifested in his body, which had been kept by the Lord and resurrected. In view of this, probably, the devil attempted to do something to Moses' body, and the archangel argued with him concerning this. The reference in [link]2 Pet. 2:11[/link] is general, but this is a definite case, concerning the body of Moses.</note>
		<note num="3">See note [link]11[sup]2[/sup] in 2 Pet. 2[/link]. This indicates that in the Lord's heavenly government the devil, Satan, was even higher than the archangel Michael. God appointed him and set him so ([link]Ezek. 28:14[/link]). In any case, Satan was under the Lord, so Michael said to him, "The Lord rebuke you." Michael kept his position in the order of divine authority.</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]Dan. 10:13[/link], [link]21[/link]; [link]12:1[/link]; [link]Rev. 12:7[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]1 Thes. 4:16[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="c">[link]Matt. 4:1[/link]; [link]Rev. 12:9[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="d">[link]2 Pet. 2:11[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="e">[link]Zech. 3:2[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="10">
		<text>But [note]1[/note]these revile the things that they do not [note]2[/note]know; and the things that they [note]2[/note]understand [note]3[/note]naturally, like [note]4[/note][xref]a[/xref]animals [note]5[/note]without reason, [note]6[/note]in these they are being [note]7[/note]corrupted.</text>
		<note num="1">Referring to the dreamers in [link]v. 8[/link].</note>
		<note num="2">[i]Know[/i] denotes a deeper sensing of invisible things, and [i]understand[/i] denotes a superficial realization of visible objects.</note>
		<note num="3">Or, instinctively. These dreamers revile what they do not know but should know; and what they understand they understand naturally, instinctively, without reason, like animals of instinct. They do not use reason to exercise man's deeper and higher knowledge, which includes the consciousness of man's conscience. What they practice is shallow and base instinctive understanding, like that of animals, which are without human reason. By behaving in this way, they are being corrupted, or destroyed.</note>
		<note num="4">Lit., living creatures (including men); indicating men who live like animals.</note>
		<note num="5">See note [link]12[sup]2[/sup] in 2 Pet. 2[/link].</note>
		<note num="6">Or, by.</note>
		<note num="7">See note [link]1[sup]5[/sup], point 3, in 2 Pet. 2[/link].</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 2:12[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="11">
		<text>[xref]a[/xref]Woe to them! For they have gone in the [note]1[/note]way of [xref]b[/xref]Cain and have [note]2[/note]rushed out in the [note]3[/note]error of [xref]c[/xref]Balaam for reward and have [note]4[/note][xref]d[/xref]perished in the [note]5[/note]rebellion of Korah.</text>
		<note num="1">The way of religiously serving God according to one's own will, heretically rejecting the redemption by blood required and ordained by God, and according to the flesh envying God's true people because of their faithful testimony to God ([link]Gen. 4:2-8[/link]).</note>
		<note num="2">Lit., been poured out. I.e., gave themselves up to, rushed headlong into, ran riotously in.</note>
		<note num="3">The error of teaching wrong doctrine for reward, while knowing it to be contrary to the truth and against the people of God, and abusively using the influence of certain gifts to lead the people of God astray from the pure worship of the Lord to idolatrous worship ([link]Num. 22:7[/link], [link]21[/link]; [link]31:16[/link]; [link]Rev. 2:14[/link]). Coveting for reward will cause the coveting ones to rush headlong into the error of Balaam.</note>
		<note num="4">I.e., were destroyed ([link]v. 5[/link]). See note [link]1[sup]5[/sup], point 1, in 2 Pet. 2[/link].</note>
		<note num="5">Lit., contradiction, speaking against. This is rebellion against God's deputy authority in His government and against His word spoken by His deputy (such as Moses). This brings in destruction ([link]Num. 16:1-40[/link]).</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]Matt. 23:13[/link]; [link]Rev. 8:13[/link]; [link]12:12[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]1 John 3:12[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 2:15[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="d">[link]2 Pet. 3:6[/link], [link]9[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="12">
		<text>These are the [note]1[/note]hidden reefs in your [note]2[/note]love feasts, [xref]a[/xref]feasting together with [i]you[/i] without fear, [note]3[/note][xref]b[/xref]shepherding themselves; [note]4[/note][xref]c[/xref]waterless clouds being carried off by [xref]d[/xref]winds; [note]5[/note]autumn trees [xref]e[/xref]without fruit, having died twice, [xref]f[/xref]rooted up;</text>
		<note num="1">The Greek word means [i]a rock.[/i] It "may allude here to a sunken rock with the sea over it" (Darby); hence, hidden reefs. The Greek word for [i]spots[/i] in [link]2 Pet. 2:13[/link] is very similar to the word here for [i]hidden reefs;[/i] hence, some translations render this word [i]spots.[/i] Actually, these two words refer to two different things. The spots are defects on the surface of precious stones; the hidden reefs are at the bottom of the water. The early heretics were not only spots on the surface but also hidden reefs at the bottom, both of which were a damage to the believers in Christ.</note>
		<note num="2">Feasts of love motivated by God's love (the higher love &amp;#8212; [link]1 John 4:10-11[/link], [link]21[/link]). In early days the believers often ate together in love for fellowship and worship ([link]Acts 2:46[/link]). This kind of feasting was joined to the Lord's supper ([link]1 Cor. 11:20-21[/link], [link]33[/link]) and was called a love feast.</note>
		<note num="3">The pleasure-seeking heretics ([link]2 Pet. 2:13[/link]) pretended to be shepherds, but at the love feasts they fed only themselves, having no concern for others. Toward others, they were waterless clouds, having no life supply to render.</note>
		<note num="4">Cf. [link]2 Pet. 2:17[/link] and note 1.</note>
		<note num="5">Autumn is a season for reaping fruit. The self-seeking apostates seemed to be fruit trees in season, but they had no fruit to satisfy others. They had died twice, not only outwardly, in appearance, as most trees do in autumn, but also inwardly, in nature. They were thoroughly dead; hence, it was right that they were uprooted.</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 2:13[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]Ezek. 34:2[/link], [link]8[/link], [link]10[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="c">[link]Prov. 25:14[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="d">[link]Eph. 4:14[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="e">[link]Matt. 21:19[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="f">[link]Matt. 15:13[/link]; cf. [link]Luke 13:6-9[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="13">
		<text>[note]1[/note]Wild [xref]a[/xref]waves of the sea, foaming out their own [xref]b[/xref]shames; [note]2[/note]wandering stars, for whom the [xref]c[/xref]gloom of darkness is kept for eternity.</text>
		<note num="1">Shepherds, clouds, trees, and stars are positive figures in biblical metaphor, but hidden reefs, waves, and the sea are negative. These apostates were false shepherds, empty clouds, dead trees, and wandering stars; they were also hidden reefs and wild, raging waves of the sea, foaming out, without restraint, their own shames.</note>
		<note num="2">The metaphor of wandering stars indicates that the erratic teachers, the apostates, were not solidly fixed in the unchanging truths of the heavenly revelation but were wandering about among God's starlike people ([link]Dan. 12:3[/link]; [link]Rev. 1:20[/link]). Their destiny is the gloom of darkness, which has been kept for them for eternity. The erratic apostates are wandering stars today, but they will be imprisoned in the gloom of darkness.</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]Isa. 57:20[/link]; [link]James 1:6[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]Rom. 6:21[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 4:2[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 2:17[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="14">
		<text>And [xref]a[/xref]Enoch, the seventh from Adam, [xref]b[/xref]prophesied also of these, saying, Behold, the Lord [note]1[/note][xref]c[/xref]came [note]2[/note]with [note]3[/note]myriads of His saints</text>
		<note num="1">This must be the manifestation of the Lord's parousia (coming) as mentioned in [link]2 Thes. 2:8[/link] and note 3, [link]Matt. 24:27[/link], [link]30[/link], and [link]Zech. 14:4-5[/link].</note>
		<note num="2">Lit., in, or, among.</note>
		<note num="3">Probably including, as in [link]Zech. 14:5[/link], the saints ([link]1 Thes. 3:13[/link]) and the angels ([link]Matt. 16:27[/link]; [link]25:31[/link]; [link]Mark 8:38[/link]).</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]Gen. 5:18[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]1 Pet. 1:10[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 1:19[/link]; [link]3:2[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="c">cf. [link]Deut. 33:2[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="15">
		<text>To execute [note]1[/note]judgment against all and to convict all the [xref]a[/xref]ungodly concerning all their ungodly works which they have done in ungodliness, and concerning all the hard things which ungodly sinners have [xref]b[/xref]spoken against Him.</text>
		<note num="1">The Lord's coming is for the carrying out of God's governmental judgment, which will deal with all the ungodly ones. See note [link]17[sup]2[/sup], par. 2, in 1 Pet. 1[/link].</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]Jude 4[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 1:9[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]Mal. 3:13[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="16">
		<text>These are [xref]a[/xref]murmurers, complainers, going on according to their own [xref]b[/xref]lusts; and their mouth speaks [xref]c[/xref]great swelling things, [xref]d[/xref]flattering [note]1[/note]persons for the sake of [xref]e[/xref]advantage.</text>
		<note num="1">Lit., faces.</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]Exo. 15:24[/link]; [link]17:3[/link]; [link]Num. 16:11[/link], [link]41[/link]; [link]Psa. 106:25[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]Jude 18[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 4:2[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 1:4[/link]; [link]2:10[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="c">[link]2 Pet. 2:18[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="d">cf. [link]Psa. 5:9[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 2:5[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="e">[link]2 Pet. 2:3[/link], [link]15[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="17">
		<text>But you, beloved, [xref]a[/xref]remember the words spoken before by the [xref]b[/xref]apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ,</text>
		<xref num="a">[link]2 Pet. 1:15[/link]; [link]3:2[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 3:2[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:1[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="18">
		<text>That they said to you, In the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]last time there will be [xref]b[/xref]mockers, going on according to their own [xref]c[/xref]lusts for [xref]d[/xref]ungodliness.</text>
		<note num="1">See note [link]1[sup]2[/sup] in 2 Tim. 3[/link].</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]1 Pet. 1:5[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 3:1[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 3:3[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="c">[link]Jude 16[/link]; [link]James 1:14-15[/link]; [link]4:1[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="d">[link]Jude 4[/link], [link]15[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="19">
		<text>These are those who make [xref]a[/xref]divisions, [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]soulish, having no [note]2[/note]spirit.</text>
		<note num="1">The adjective form of [i]soul.[/i] "The [i]psyche[/i] [soul] is the center of the personal being, the 'I' of each individual. It is in each man bound to the spirit, man's higher part, and to the body, man's lower part; drawn upwards by the one, downwards by the other. He who gives himself up to the lower appetites, is fleshly: he who by communion of his spirit with God's Spirit is employed in the higher aims of his being, is spiritual. He who rests midway, thinking only of self and self's interests, whether animal or intellectual, is the [i]psychikos,[/i] the selfish man, the man in whom the spirit is sunk and degraded into subordination to the subordinate [i]psyche[/i] [soul]" (Alford).</note>
		<note num="2">The human spirit, not the Spirit of God. The apostates are devoid of spirit. They "have not indeed ceased to have a spirit, as a part of their own tripartite nature &#91;[link]1 Thes. 5:23[/link]]: but they have ceased to possess it in any worthy sense: it is degraded beneath and under the power of the [i]psyche[/i] [soul], the personal life, so as to have no real vitality of its own" (Alford). They do not care for their spirit or use it. They do not contact God by their spirit in communion with the Spirit of God; neither do they live and walk in their spirit. They have been drawn downward by their flesh and have become fleshy, so that they have lost the consciousness of their conscience (see note [link]12[sup]2[/sup] in 2 Pet. 2[/link]) and have become like animals without reason ([link]v. 10[/link]).</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]Rom. 16:17[/link]; [link]2:8[/link]; cf. [link]1 Cor. 11:19[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]1 Cor. 2:14[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="20">
		<text>But you, beloved, [xref]a[/xref]building up yourselves [note]1[/note]upon your most holy [note]2[/note]faith, praying in the Holy [xref]b[/xref]Spirit,</text>
		<note num="1">Or, in.</note>
		<note num="2">Objective faith, referring to the precious things of the New Testament in which we believe for our salvation in Christ (see note [link]3[sup]3[/sup][/link]). On the foundation of this holy faith, and in the sphere of it, by praying in the Holy Spirit, we build up ourselves. The truth of the faith in our apprehension and the Holy Spirit enjoyed through our prayer are necessary for our building up. Both the faith and the Spirit are holy.</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]Col. 2:7[/link]; [link]1 Thes. 5:11[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]Rom. 8:26[/link]; cf. [link]Eph. 6:18[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="21">
		<text>[note]1[/note]Keep yourselves in the [xref]a[/xref]love of God, [xref]b[/xref]awaiting the [note]2[/note]mercy of our [note]3[/note]Lord Jesus Christ [note]4[/note]unto [xref]c[/xref]eternal life.</text>
		<note num="1">We should keep ourselves in the love of God by building up ourselves upon our holy faith and praying in the Holy Spirit ([link]v. 20[/link]); thus we await and look for the mercy of our Lord that we may not only enjoy eternal life in this age but also inherit it for eternity ([link]Matt. 19:29[/link]).</note>
		<note num="2">See note [link]2[sup]1[/sup][/link].</note>
		<note num="3">The entire Blessed Trinity is employed and enjoyed by the believers in their praying in the Holy Spirit, keeping themselves in the love of God, and awaiting the mercy of our Lord unto eternal life.</note>
		<note num="4">Referring to the inheritance and enjoyment of eternal life, the life of God, which is the goal of our spiritual seeking. Because we aim at this goal, we desire to be kept in the love of God and await the mercy of our Lord.</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]John 15:10[/link]; [link]Rom. 5:5[/link]; [link]8:39[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 13:14[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]2 Pet. 3:12[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="c">[link]John 3:15[/link], [link]36[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 6:12[/link], [link]19[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="22">
		<text>And [note]1[/note]on some have mercy, on those who are [note]2[/note]wavering;</text>
		<note num="1">Some MSS read, some convince, those who are wavering.</note>
		<note num="2">Or, disputing.</note>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="23">
		<text>[xref]a[/xref]Save [i]them[/i] by [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]snatching [i]them[/i] out of the [note]2[/note]fire. On others have mercy [note]3[/note]in [xref]c[/xref]fear, hating even the inner garment [xref]d[/xref]spotted from the [xref]e[/xref]flesh.</text>
		<note num="1">This metaphor is probably adopted from [link]Zech. 3:2[/link].</note>
		<note num="2">The fire of God's holiness for His judgment ([link]Matt. 3:10[/link], [link]12[/link]; [link]5:22[/link]).</note>
		<note num="3">While we are having mercy on others, we should be in fear of the awful contagion of sin, hating even the things spotted by the lust of the flesh. On [i]fear,[/i] see note [link]17[sup]4[/sup] in 1 Pet. 1[/link].</note>
		<xref num="a">cf. [link]James 5:20[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]Zech. 3:2[/link]; [link]Amos 4:11[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="c">[link]1 Pet. 3:2[/link], [link]15[/link]; [link]Psa. 2:11[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="d">cf. [link]Rev. 3:4[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="e">[link]Jude 8[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 2:10[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="24">
		<text>[note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]But to Him who is [xref]b[/xref]able to [xref]c[/xref]guard you from [xref]d[/xref]stumbling and to set [i]you[/i] before His [note]2[/note]glory [xref]e[/xref]without blemish [note]3[/note]in [note]4[/note][xref]f[/xref]exultation,</text>
		<note num="1">In this concluding praise the writer indicated clearly that although he had charged the believers to endeavor in the things mentioned in [link]vv. 20-23[/link], only God our Savior was able to guard them from stumbling and set them before His glory without blemish in exultation. To Him be glory...!</note>
		<note num="2">The glory of our great God and Savior, Jesus Christ, which will be manifested at His appearing ([link]Titus 2:13[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 4:13[/link]) and in which He will come ([link]Luke 9:26[/link]).</note>
		<note num="3">In the element of.</note>
		<note num="4">"The word signifies the exuberance of triumphant joy" (Alford).</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]1 Pet. 5:10[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]Rom. 16:25[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="c">[link]1 Pet. 1:5[/link]; [link]John 17:11-12[/link], [link]15[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="d">[link]2 Pet. 1:10[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="e">[link]2 Pet. 3:14[/link]; [link]Eph. 1:4[/link]; [link]5:27[/link]; [link]Phil. 2:15[/link]; [link]Rev. 14:5[/link]; cf. [link]1 Pet. 1:19[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="f">[link]1 Pet. 1:6[/link]; [link]4:13[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	    <verse num="25">
		<text>To the [xref]a[/xref]only [note]1[/note]God our [xref]b[/xref]Savior through [note]1[/note]Jesus Christ our Lord be [note]2[/note][xref]c[/xref]glory, majesty, might, and authority [note]3[/note]before all time and now and unto all eternity. [i]Amen.[/i]</text>
		<note num="1">The only God is our Savior, and the man Jesus Christ is our Lord. To such a Savior, through such a Lord, be glory, majesty, might, and authority throughout all ages.</note>
		<note num="2">Glory is the expression in splendor; majesty, the greatness in honor; might, the strength in power; and authority, the power in ruling.</note>
		<note num="3">[i]Before all time[/i] refers to eternity past; [i]now,[/i] to the present age; and [i]unto all eternity,[/i] to eternity future. Thus, this is from eternity past, through time, unto eternity future.</note>
		<xref num="a">[link]John 5:44[/link]; [link]Rom. 16:27[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 1:17[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="b">[link]Luke 1:47[/link]; [link]1 Tim. 1:1[/link]; [link]2:3[/link]; [link]Titus 2:13[/link]</xref>
		<xref num="c">[link]Rom. 11:36[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 4:11[/link]</xref>
	    </verse>
	</chapter>
    </chapters>
</book>
