<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="yes"?>
<book name="Nehemiah">
    <info title="Author">Nehemiah, who was cupbearer to Artaxerxes the king of Persia and Babylon ([link]1:11[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Time of Writing">After 433 B.C.</info>
    <info title="Place of Writing">Jerusalem.</info>
    <info title="Time Period Covered">This book covers a period of at least twelve years, from 445 B.C. to 433 B.C., from the twentieth year ([link]1:1[/link]) to some time after the thirty-second year of Artaxerxes the king of Persia and Babylon ([link]13:6-7[/link]).</info>
    <subject>The Rebuilding of the Wall of the City of Jerusalem as a Continual Recovery among God's Elect for His Testimony for the Accomplishment of His Economy</subject>
    <outlines>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="1" ref="1:1-7:73">The rebuilding of the city of Jerusalem under Nehemiah</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="1:1-3">The report of the condition of Jerusalem</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="1:4-11">Nehemiah's prayer by fasting</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="2:1-8">The king's favor in giving permission to Nehemiah</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="4" ref="2:9-16">Nehemiah's journey to Jerusalem and his personal observation</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="5" ref="2:17-20">The rebuilding of the wall of Jerusalem</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="6" ref="3:1-32">A record of the building of the wall</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="7" ref="4:1-23">The frustration of the enemy</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="8" ref="5:1-19">The settlement of the interior problem</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="1" ref="vv. 1-5">The people's complaint concerning the nobles' and rulers' imposing interest on the people</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="2" ref="vv. 6-13">Nehemiah's rebuke and resolution</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="3" ref="vv. 14-19">Nehemiah's good example</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="9" ref="6:1-14">The further frustration of the enemy</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="10" ref="6:15-7:4">The completion of the building</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="11" ref="7:5-73">Enrolling the returned captives for the increase of the population of Jerusalem</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="2" ref="8:1-13:31">The reconstitution of the nation of God's elect</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="8:1-10:39">The renewing of the covenant under Ezra</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="1" ref="8:1-18">Coming back to God by coming back to His law, His word</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="2" ref="9:1-10:39">Making a clear confession to God of their past and making a firm covenant with God</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="11:1-13:31">The reforming of the nation</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="1" ref="11:1-36">The arrangement of the dwellings and the appointment of the officers</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="2" ref="12:1-26">A record of the priests and Levites</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="3" ref="12:27-43">The dedication of the rebuilt wall</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="4" ref="12:44-47">The appointment of the services of the priests and Levites and the supply of their needs</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="5" ref="13:1-30a">The clearance exercised on Israel as God's elect</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="6" ref="13:30b-31">Nehemiah appointing duties for the priests and Levites for the wood offering and the firstfruits</outline>
    </outlines>
    <chapters>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>The words of [note]1[/note]Nehemiah the son of Hacaliah. [note]2[/note]Now in the month Chislev, in the twentieth year, while I was in Susa the capital,</text>
        <note num="1">Meaning [i]comfort of Jehovah[/i]. Nehemiah was the king's cupbearer ([link]v. 11[/link]) and was eventually appointed to be the governor of Judah ([link]5:14[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">The book of Ezra is a history of the return of Israel's captivity and the rebuilding of the house of God as the initiation of God's recovery among His elect for His testimony on the earth according to His economy. The book of Nehemiah is a history of the rebuilding of the wall of the city of Jerusalem and the further recovery of Israel's services and worship to God, as a continued recovery among God's elect for His testimony for the accomplishing of His economy.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Hanani, one of my brothers, came, he and some men from Judah; and I asked them about the Jews who had escaped, who were left from the captivity, and about [note]1[/note]Jerusalem.</text>
        <note num="1">The city of Jerusalem was a safeguard and protection for the house of God, which was in the city. This signifies that the house of God as His dwelling and home on the earth needs His kingdom to be established as a realm to safeguard His interests on the earth for His administration, that He may carry out His economy. The rebuilding of the house of God typifies God's recovery of the degraded church, and the rebuilding of the wall of the city of Jerusalem typifies God's recovery of His kingdom. God's building of His house and His building of His kingdom go together ([link]Matt. 16:18-19[/link]). See note [link]1[sup]3[/sup], par. 2, in Psa. 42[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And they said to me, The remnant who are left from the captivity there in the province are in an exceedingly bad state and reproach, and the [xref]a[/xref]wall of Jerusalem is broken down and its gates have been burned with fire.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 2:17; cf. 2 Kings 25:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And when I heard these words, I sat down and wept, and I mourned for some days; and I fasted and [xref]a[/xref]prayed before the [xref]b[/xref]God of heaven,</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 10:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">Neh. 2:4; Dan. 2:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And said, I beseech You, O Jehovah the God of heaven, the great and awesome God, who keeps covenant and lovingkindness with those who love Him and keep His commandments:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Let Your ear be attentive and Your [xref]a[/xref]eyes open to hear the prayer of Your servant, which I pray before You now day and night, concerning the children of Israel, Your servants, while I [xref]b[/xref]confess the sins of the children of Israel that we have sinned against You. Indeed, I and the house of my father have sinned;</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Chron. 6:40</xref>
        <xref num="b">Ezra 10:1; Dan. 9:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>We have been most corrupt toward You and have not kept the [note]1[/note]commandments and the statutes and the ordinances that You commanded Moses Your servant.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]6[sup]4[/sup] in Luke 1[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Remember now the [note]1[/note]word that You commanded Moses Your servant, saying, If you are unfaithful, I will [xref]a[/xref]scatter you among the peoples;</text>
        <note num="1">In his prayer to God, Nehemiah stood on God's word and prayed according to it ([link]vv. 8-9[/link]). Thus, God was bound by His own word.</note>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 26:33; Deut. 4:27; 28:64</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>But if you [xref]a[/xref]return to Me and keep My commandments and perform them, though your outcasts are under the [xref]b[/xref]ends of heaven, from there I will gather them and bring them to the place where I have chosen to cause My name to dwell.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 4:30-31; 30:2-3</xref>
        <xref num="b">Deut. 30:4; Mark 13:27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Now these are Your servants and Your people, whom You have redeemed by Your great power and by Your strong hand.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>I beseech You, O Lord, let Your ear be attentive to the prayer of Your servant and to the prayer of Your servants, who take delight in fearing Your name; and cause Your servant to prosper today, and grant him [i]to find[/i] compassion before this man. Now I was cupbearer to the king.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Then in the month of Nisan, in the [xref]a[/xref]twentieth year of [xref]b[/xref]Artaxerxes the king, while wine [i]was being set[/i] before him, I took up the wine and gave [i]it[/i] to the king. Now I had never been sad in his presence.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 1:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">Ezra 7:1; Neh. 5:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And the king said to me, Why is your face sad, since you are not ill? This is nothing other than sadness of heart. Then I was greatly frightened.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And I said to the king, [note]1[/note]May the king live forever! Why should my face not be sad, when the [xref]a[/xref]city, the place of my fathers' graves, lies in waste and its gates are consumed with fire?</text>
        <note num="1">Being an aggressive person, Nehemiah took advantage of this opportunity to speak to the king. Although he was a common man, a servant of the king, he was aggressive to volunteer himself to God for his burden concerning the building up of Jerusalem. He was also aggressive in making his requests known to the king ([link]vv. 4-8[/link]). His aggressiveness was very much used by God. In type, Nehemiah's aggressiveness, as a virtue in his human conduct, shows that our natural capacity, natural ability, and natural virtues must pass through the cross of Christ and be brought into resurrection, i.e., into the Spirit as the consummated Triune God ([link]John 11:25[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 15:45[/link]), to be useful to God in the accomplishing of His economy.[br/][br/]Nehemiah was one who lived not in his natural man but in resurrection. He was aggressive, but his aggressiveness was accompanied by other characteristics. In His relationship with God, He was one who loved God and also loved God's interests on the earth, including the Holy Land (signifying Christ), the holy temple (signifying the church), and the holy city (signifying the kingdom of God). As a person who loved God, Nehemiah prayed to God to contact Him in fellowship ([link]1:4[/link]; [link]2:4b[/link]; [link]4:4-5[/link], [link]9[/link]). Furthermore, Nehemiah trusted in God and even became one with God. As a result, he became the representative of God. In his relationship with the people, Nehemiah was altogether unselfish; with him, there was no self-seeking or self-interest. He was always willing to sacrifice what he had for the people and for the nation ([link]5:10[/link], [link]14-19[/link]). See also notes [link]18[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 4[/link], [link]14[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 5[/link], [link]2[sup]1[/sup], par. 2, in ch. 8[/link], and [link]30[sup]1[/sup], par. 2, in ch. 13[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. Neh. 1:3; Psa. 102:14; 137:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And the king said to me, What do you request? So I prayed to the [xref]a[/xref]God of heaven.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 5:12; Neh. 1:4-5; 2:20; Dan. 2:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And I said to the king, If it please the king and if your servant has found favor before you, that you would send me to Judah to the city of my fathers' graves that I may [xref]a[/xref]rebuild it.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Psa. 51:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And the king said to me (and the queen was sitting beside him), How long will your going be, and when will you return? So it pleased the king to send me, and I gave him a date.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Then I said to the king, If it please the king, let letters be given to me for the governors beyond the [note]1[/note]River, so that they will let me pass through until I come to Judah;</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., the Euphrates. So throughout the book.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And a letter to Asaph, the keeper of the Park, which belongs to the king, so that he would give me timber to make beams for the gates of the palace that belongs to the house and for the wall of the city and for the house that I will be entering. And the king gave [i]these[/i] to me according to the good [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]hand of my God, which was upon me.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]6[sup]2[/sup] in Ezra 7[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 7:6, 9, 28; 8:18, 22, 31; Neh. 2:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>So I went to the governors beyond the River and gave them the king's letters. And the king had sent with me captains of the army and horsemen.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And when [xref]a[/xref]Sanballat the Horonite and Tobiah the Ammonite [note]1[/note]servant heard of [i]this,[/i] it displeased them greatly that a man had come seeking the good of the children of Israel.</text>
        <note num="1">Probably referring to an official position under the Persian king. So also in [link]v. 19[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. Ezra 4:4-8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Thus I came to [xref]a[/xref]Jerusalem and was there three days.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Ezra 8:32</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And I arose at night, I and some few men with me. And I told no man what my [xref]a[/xref]God had put into my heart to do for Jerusalem. And there was no animal with me except the animal I rode on.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Ezra 7:27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And I went out at night by the Valley Gate, toward the Jackals' Spring and the Dung Gate, and inspected the walls of Jerusalem, which had been broken down and whose gates had been consumed with fire.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Then I passed on to the Fountain Gate and to the King's Pool, but there was no place for the animal under me to pass through.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And I went up at night by the brook and inspected the wall, and turned back and went in by the Valley Gate and [i]so[/i] returned.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And the rulers did not know where I had gone or what I had been doing; and I had not as yet told [i]it[/i] to the Jews and the priests and the nobles and the rulers and the rest who were to do the work.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Then I said to them, You see the bad state we are in, that Jerusalem lies in waste and its gates are burned with fire. Come and let us [xref]a[/xref]build up the wall of Jerusalem so that we will no longer be a [xref]b[/xref]reproach.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Psa. 51:18</xref>
        <xref num="b">Neh. 1:3; Psa. 44:13; 79:4; Jer. 24:9; Ezek. 5:14-15; 22:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And I told them about the hand of my God, which was good upon me, and also about the king's words, which he had spoken to me. And they said, Let us rise up and build; and they strengthened their hands for the good [i]work.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>But when Sanballat the Horonite and Tobiah the Ammonite servant and Geshem the Arabian heard of [i]it,[/i] they [xref]a[/xref]mocked us and despised us; and they said, What is this thing that you will do? Will you rebel against the king?</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 4:1; Psa. 44:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And I answered them and said to them, [note]1[/note]The [xref]a[/xref]God of heaven Himself will make us prosper; therefore we His servants will rise up and build. But you have no portion nor right nor memorial in Jerusalem.</text>
        <note num="1">Nehemiah's response indicates that as a servant of God he was not cowardly but was very aggressive. See note [link]3[sup]1[/sup][/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 1:4-5; 2:4</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Then [xref]a[/xref]Eliashib the high priest rose up with his brothers the priests and built the [xref]b[/xref]Sheep Gate. They consecrated it [i]and[/i] erected its doors; even as far as the Tower of the Hundred they consecrated it and as far as the [xref]c[/xref]Tower of Hananel.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 3:20-21; 13:4, 7, 28</xref>
        <xref num="b">Neh. 3:32; 12:39; John 5:2</xref>
        <xref num="c">Jer. 31:38; Zech. 14:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And next to him the men of Jericho built. And next to them Zaccur the son of Imri built.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And the sons of Hassenaah built the [xref]a[/xref]Fish Gate: They laid its beams and set up its doors, its bolts, and its bars.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Chron. 33:14; Neh. 12:39; Zeph. 1:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And next to them Meremoth the son of Uriah, the son of Hakkoz made repairs. And next to them Meshullam the son of Berechiah, the son of Meshezabel made repairs. And next to them Zadok the son of Baana made repairs.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And next to them the Tekoites made repairs, but their nobles would not put their necks to the service of their [note]1[/note]Lord.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, masters.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And Joiada the son of Paseah and Meshullam the son of Besodeiah repaired the Old Gate: They laid its beams and set up its doors and its bolts and its bars.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And next to them Melatiah the Gibeonite and Jadon the Meronothite [i]with[/i] the men of Gibeon and of Mizpah made repairs to the throne of the governor beyond the River.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Next to him Uzziel the son of Harhaiah, one of the goldsmiths, made repairs. And next to him Hananiah, [i]one of the[/i] perfumers, made repairs, and they fortified Jerusalem even unto the Broad Wall.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And next to them Rephaiah the son of Hur, the ruler of half the district of Jerusalem, made repairs.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And next to them Jedaiah the son of Harumaph, opposite his house. And next to him Hattush the son of Hashabneiah made repairs.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Malchijah the son of Harim and Hasshub the son of Pahath-moab repaired another section, including the Tower of the Furnaces.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And next to him Shallum the son of Hallohesh, the ruler of half the district of Jerusalem, made repairs, he and his daughters.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Hanun and the inhabitants of Zanoah repaired the Valley Gate: They built it and set up its doors, its bolts, and its bars, as well as one thousand cubits of the wall to the Dung Gate.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And Malchijah the son of Rechab, the ruler of the district of Beth-haccherem repaired the Dung Gate: He built it and set up its doors, its bolts, and its bars.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And Shallum the son of Colhozeh, the ruler of the district of Mizpah, repaired the Fountain Gate: He built it and covered it and set up its doors, its bolts, and its bars, as well as the wall of the Pool of [xref]a[/xref]Shelah by the King's Garden, even to the stairs that go down from the City of David.</text>
        <xref num="a">Luke 13:4; John 9:7, 11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>After him Nehemiah the son of Azbuk, the ruler of half the district of Beth-zur, made repairs, from a place opposite the [xref]a[/xref]Sepulchres of David and as far as the pool that was made and as far as the House of the Mighty Men.</text>
        <xref num="a">Acts 2:29</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>After him the Levites, [i]under[/i] Rehum the son of Bani, made repairs. Next to him Hashabiah, the ruler of half the district of Keilah, made repairs for his district.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>After him their brothers, [i]under[/i] Bavvai the son of Henadad, the ruler of half the district of Keilah, made repairs.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And next to him Ezer the son of Jeshua, the ruler of Mizpah, repaired another section, opposite the ascent to the armory at the turning [i]of the wall.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>After him Baruch the son of Zabbai diligently repaired another section, from the turning [i]of the wall[/i] to the door of the house of Eliashib the high priest.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>After him Meremoth the son of Uriah the son of Hakkoz repaired another section, from the door of the house of Eliashib even to the end of the house of Eliashib.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And after him the priests, the men from the plain, made repairs.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>After them Benjamin and Hasshub made repairs opposite their house. After them Azariah the son of Maaseiah the son of Ananiah made repairs beside his own house.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>After him Binnui the son of Henadad repaired another section, from the house of Azariah to the turning [i]of the wall,[/i] then to the corner.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Palal the son of Uzai [i]made repairs[/i] from in front of the turning [i]of the wall,[/i] and on the tower that projects out from the upper house of the king, which is by the court of the guard. After him was Pedaiah the son of Parosh.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>(Now the temple servants dwelt on the Ophel, as far as the point opposite the Water Gate on the east, and the tower that projects out.)</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>After him the Tekoites repaired another section, opposite the great tower that projects out and to the wall of the Ophel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>Above the [xref]a[/xref]Horse Gate the priests made repairs, each one opposite his own house.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Chron. 23:15; Jer. 31:40</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>After them Zadok the son of Immer made repairs opposite his own house. And after him Shemaiah the son of Shecaniah, the keeper of the East Gate, made repairs.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>After him Hananiah the son of Shelemiah and Hanun the sixth son of Zalaph repaired a second section. After him Meshullam the son of Berechiah made repairs, opposite his quarters.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>After him Malchijah, one of the goldsmiths, made repairs as far as the house of the temple servants and the merchants, opposite the Muster Gate and as far as the ascent of the corner.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>And between the ascent of the corner and the [xref]a[/xref]Sheep Gate the goldsmiths and the merchants made repairs.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 3:1</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And when [xref]a[/xref]Sanballat heard that we were building the wall, he became angry and was greatly enraged; and he mocked the Jews.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 2:19; 4:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And he spoke to his brothers and the army of Samaria and said, What are these feeble Jews doing? Will they restore [i]it[/i] for themselves? Will they sacrifice? Will they finish in a day? Will they revive the stones out of the dust heaps, though they are burned?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And Tobiah the Ammonite was beside him, and he said, Even their stone wall that they are building, if a fox were to go up [i]on it,[/i] he would breach [i]it.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Hear, O our God, for we are despised; and turn their reproach upon their own head, and give them as spoil in the land of captivity;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And do not cover their iniquity and do not let their sin be blotted out before You, for they made provocations before the builders.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>So we built the [xref]a[/xref]wall; and all the wall was joined together to half its [i]height,[/i] for the people had a heart to work.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 51:18; Neh. 6:1, 6; 12:27; Isa. 60:18; Psa. 122:7; cf. Rev. 21:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And when Sanballat and Tobiah and the Arabians and the Ammonites and the Ashdodites heard that the restoration of the walls of Jerusalem was advancing, that the breaches were beginning to be closed up, they became very angry;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And all of them [xref]a[/xref]conspired together to come [i]and[/i] fight against Jerusalem and cause confusion in it.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 83:3-5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>But we prayed to our God, and because of them we set a watch against them day and night.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And Judah said, / The strength of the burden bearers fails, / And the debris is great; / And we are not able / To build the wall.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And our adversaries said, They will not know, nor [i]even[/i] see, until we come into their midst and slay them and cause the work to stop.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And when the Jews who dwelt near them came, they said to us ten times, [i]They will come up[/i] against us from all the places that you turn to.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>So I set [i]men[/i] in the lowest places behind the wall, on the exposed areas, and I set the people by families with their swords, their spears, and their bows.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And when I saw [i]the situation,[/i] I rose up and said to the nobles and the rulers and the rest of the people, Do not be afraid of them; remember the great and awesome Lord, and [note]1[/note]fight for your brothers, your sons and your daughters, your wives and your houses.</text>
        <note num="1">On the one hand, the children of Israel were prepared to fight; on the other hand, they trusted in God, believing that He would fight for them ([link]v. 20b[/link]). In this matter they too were aggressive (cf. note [link]20[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 2[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And when our enemies heard that their counsel was known to us and [i]that[/i] God frustrated [i]it,[/i] we all returned to the wall, each man to his work.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And from that day half of my servants labored in the work, and half of them held the spears and the shields and the bows and the armor; and the rulers were behind all the house of Judah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Those who built the wall and those who carried burdens took the loads with one hand doing the work and with the other holding a weapon.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And as for the builders, each [i]had[/i] his sword strapped to his side, and [i]so[/i] they built; and he who sounded the trumpet was beside [note]1[/note]me.</text>
        <note num="1">As the commander-in-chief, Nehemiah was among those who were ready to fight against the enemy, and he took part in the night watch ([link]vv. 17-23[/link]). He did not leave these matters to others but participated in them himself.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And I said to the nobles, the rulers, and the rest of the people, The work is great and large, and we are separated on the wall, each far from the other.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>In whatever place you hear the sound of the trumpet, gather yourselves to us there. Our God will [xref]a[/xref]fight for us.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 14:14; Deut. 1:30; 3:22; 20:4; Josh. 10:14, 42; 23:3, 10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>So we labored in the work; and half of them held spears from the start of dawn until the stars came out.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>I also said to the people at that time, Let every man and his servant spend the nights inside Jerusalem so that they may be a guard for us by night and work by day.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>So neither I nor my brothers nor my servants nor the men of the guard who followed me, none of us took off our clothes; [note]1[/note]each [i]had[/i] his weapon at his right hand.</text>
        <note num="1">The Hebrew text is obscure.</note>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="5">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And there was a great [xref]a[/xref]cry of the people and their wives against their brothers the Jews,</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Exo. 2:23; 3:7, 9; Isa. 5:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>For there were some who said, With our sons and our daughters we are many; therefore we must get grain that we may eat and live.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And there were some who said, We have [xref]a[/xref]pledged our fields and our vineyards and our houses that we might get grain in this famine.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Lev. 25:35-39; Deut. 15:7-8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And there were some who said, We have borrowed money against our fields and our vineyards for the king's tribute.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Yet now our flesh is like the flesh of our brothers, our children like their children; and now we are bringing our sons and daughters into [xref]a[/xref]bondage as slaves. And some of our daughters have [i]already[/i] been brought into bondage; and it is not in our power [i]to deliver them,[/i] for our fields and vineyards belong to others.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 4:1; Matt. 18:25; Exo. 21:7; cf. Lev. 25:39</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And I was very angry when I heard their cry and these words.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And when I had considered [i]this matter[/i] in my heart, I rebuked the nobles and the rulers and said to them, You men are charging [xref]a[/xref]interest, each man against his brother! And I set a great assembly against them.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 22:25; Lev. 25:37; Psa. 15:5, Ezek. 22:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And I said to them, We have [xref]a[/xref]bought back our brothers the Jews who have been sold to the nations according to the best of our ability. So would you even sell your brothers that they would have to be sold [i]back[/i] to us? And they held their peace and could find not a word [i]to answer.[/i]</text>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 25:47-49</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Then I said, The thing that you are doing is not good. Should you not walk in the [xref]a[/xref]fear of our God because of the reproach of the nations our enemies?</text>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 25:36; 1 Sam. 12:14; Neh. 5:15; Acts 9:31</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And even I, my brothers, and my servants lend them money and grain. Let us now abandon such taking of interest.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Restore now to them, as of today, their fields, their vineyards, their olive groves, and their houses, as well as the hundredth part of the money and of the grain, new wine, and fresh oil that you charge them as interest.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Lev. 25:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And they said, We will restore [i]it,[/i] and we will require nothing from them; so will we do, even as you say. Then I called for the priests and took an oath from them that they would do according to this promise.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>I also [xref]a[/xref]shook out the lap [i]of my garment[/i] and said, May God shake out in the same way every man from his house and from his possessions who does not perform this promise; even so may he be shaken out and emptied. And all the assembly said, [xref]b[/xref]Amen; and they praised Jehovah. And the people acted according to this promise.</text>
        <xref num="a">Acts 18:6; cf. Mark 6:11; Luke 9:5; Acts 13:51</xref>
        <xref num="b">Deut. 27:15; 1 Chron. 16:36; Neh. 8:6; Psa. 106:48; 1 Cor. 14:16; Rev. 22:21</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Moreover from the time that [i]the king[/i] appointed me to be governor in the land of Judah, from the twentieth year even to the thirty-second year of [xref]a[/xref]Artaxerxes the king, twelve years, I and my brothers did [note]1[/note]not eat the food [i]appointed[/i] for the governor.</text>
        <note num="1">Nehemiah, as the governor, in the position of a king, was a man with a pure heart for the rebuilding of Jerusalem's wall in the carrying out of God's economy. Unlike many of the kings of Israel and Judah, he was not selfish, he did not seek his own interests, and he was not indulgent in sexual lust. Therefore, he was qualified to enjoy the top portion, the kingship of the good land promised by God to His elect. Instead of being self-seeking, he lent money and grain without interest ([link]v. 10[/link]), and he fed others for the purpose of building up the wall. As a result, he was used by God and received help from Him to carry out the work of rebuilding the wall of the city of Jerusalem ([link]6:15-7:4[/link]). Nehemiah was a pattern of what a leader among God's people should be (cf. [link]1 Tim. 3:2-7[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 2:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>But the former governors, who were before me, laid heavy burdens on the people and took from them food and wine, besides forty shekels of silver; even their servants tyrannized the people. But I did not do so, because of the [xref]a[/xref]fear of God.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 5:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And I also applied myself to the work on this wall. And we did not acquire fields, and all my servants were gathered there for the work.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And there were at my table one hundred fifty men, Jews and rulers, besides those who came to us from the nations that surrounded us.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And what was prepared for one day was one ox [i]and[/i] six choice sheep; also fowl was prepared for me, as well as all kinds of wine in abundance every ten days. Yet for this I did not demand the food [i]appointed[/i] for the governor, for the service was heavy upon this people.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Remember me, O my God, for good, [i]according to[/i] all that I have done for this people.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="6">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And when it was reported to Sanballat and Tobiah and Geshem the Arabian and the rest of our enemies that I had built the [xref]a[/xref]wall and that no breach remained in it (though as yet I had not set up the doors in the gates),</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 6:15; cf. Neh. 7:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Sanballat and Geshem sent [i]word[/i] to me, saying, Come; let us meet together among the villages in the plain of Ono. But they intended to do me harm.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And I sent messengers to them, saying, I am doing a great work and cannot come down. Why should the work cease while I leave it to come down to you?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And they sent [i]word[/i] to me four times in this way, and I answered them in this way.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Then Sanballat sent his servant to me in this way the fifth time, with an open letter in his hand,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>In which was written: It is reported among the nations, and Geshem says [i]it,[/i] that you and the Jews intend to rebel; therefore you are building the wall. And, according to these words, you are to be their king.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And you have also set up prophets to declare in Jerusalem concerning you, saying, There is a king in Judah! And now a report will be made to the king according to these words. Come now therefore, and let us take counsel together.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Then I sent [i]word[/i] to him, saying, None of these things that you are saying have happened; rather you have invented them in your own heart.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>For all of them tried to frighten us, thinking, Their hands will be weakened from working, and it will not be done. But now strengthen my hands!</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And I went to the house of Shemaiah the son of Delaiah, the son of Mehetabel, who had shut himself up. And he said, Let us meet together in the house of God, within the temple; and let us shut the doors of the temple, for they are coming to slay you; indeed at night they are coming to slay you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>But I said, Should a man like me flee? And who, [i]being[/i] like me, would go into the temple [note]1[/note]to save his life? I will not go in.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., and live.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Then I perceived that surely God had not sent him but that he spoke this prophecy against me and that Tobiah and Sanballat had hired him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>He had been hired for this reason, that I would be frightened and that I would act in such a way as to sin; then they would have [i]cause[/i] for an evil report in order to reproach me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Remember, O my God, Tobiah and Sanballat according to these works of theirs, and also the prophetess Noadiah and the rest of the prophets, who tried to frighten me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>So the [xref]a[/xref]wall was completed on the twenty-fifth day of [i]the month[/i] of Elul, in fifty-two days.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 6:1; 7:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And when all our enemies heard of [i]it,[/i] all the nations that surrounded us were afraid and fell very low in their own eyes, for they knew that this work was done [i]with the help[/i] of our God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Moreover in those days the nobles of Judah sent many letters unto Tobiah, and [i]the letters[/i] of Tobiah came to them;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>For many in Judah were sworn to his cause because he was the son-in-law of Shecaniah the son of Arah; and his son Jehohanan had taken the daughter of Meshullam the son of Berechiah as [i]his[/i] wife.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>They also spoke of his good deeds before me and reported my words to him. [i]And[/i] Tobiah sent letters to intimidate me.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="7">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And when the [xref]a[/xref]wall was built and I had set up the doors, and the gatekeepers and the singers and Levites had been appointed,</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 6:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>I gave my brother Hanani, as well as Hananiah the commander of the citadel, charge over Jerusalem, for he was a faithful man and feared God more than most.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And I said to them, Do not let the gates of Jerusalem be opened until the sun is hot; and while some are standing [i]guard,[/i] let them shut the doors, and you bar [i]them;[/i] and appoint watches from the inhabitants of Jerusalem, each at his own watch and each opposite his own house.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Now the city was wide and large; but the people were few in it and no houses had been built.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Then my God put it into my heart to assemble the nobles and the rulers and the people to be enrolled by genealogy. And I found the book of the genealogy of those who had first come up, and I found [i]this[/i] written in it:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]These are the children of the province who went up out of the captivity of those who had been carried away, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away and who returned to Jerusalem and to Judah, each man to his city;</text>
        <xref num="a">vv. 6-73: Ezra 2:1-70</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Who came with Zerubbabel, Jeshua, Nehemiah, Azariah, Raamiah, Nahamani, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispereth, Bigvai, Nehum, Baanah. The number of the men of the people of Israel:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>The children of Parosh, two thousand one hundred seventy-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>The children of Shephatiah, three hundred seventy-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>The children of Arah, six hundred fifty-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>The children of Pahath-moab, of the children of Jeshua and Joab, two thousand eight hundred eighteen.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>The children of Elam, one thousand two hundred fifty-four.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>The children of Zattu, eight hundred forty-five.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>The children of Zaccai, seven hundred sixty.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>The children of Binnui, six hundred forty-eight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>The children of Bebai, six hundred twenty-eight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>The children of Azgad, two thousand three hundred twenty-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>The children of Adonikam, six hundred sixty-seven.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>The children of Bigvai, two thousand sixty-seven.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>The children of Adin, six hundred fifty-five.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>The children of Ater, of Hezekiah, ninety-eight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>The children of Hashum, three hundred twenty-eight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>The children of Bezai, three hundred twenty-four.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>The children of Hariph, one hundred twelve.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>The children of Gibeon, ninety-five.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>The men of Bethlehem and Netophah, one hundred eighty-eight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>The men of Anathoth, one hundred twenty-eight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>The men of Beth-azmaveth, forty-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>The men of Kiriath-jearim, Chephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred forty-three.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>The men of Ramah and Geba, six hundred twenty-one.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>The men of Michmas, one hundred twenty-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>The men of Bethel and Ai, one hundred twenty-three.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>The men of the other Nebo, fifty-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>The children of the other Elam, one thousand two hundred fifty-four.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>The children of Harim, three hundred twenty.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
        <text>The children of Jericho, three hundred forty-five.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
        <text>The children of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred twenty-one.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
        <text>The children of Senaah, three thousand nine hundred thirty.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
        <text>The priests: the children of Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred seventy-three.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
        <text>The children of Immer, one thousand fifty-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
        <text>The children of Pashhur, one thousand two hundred forty-seven.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
        <text>The children of Harim, one thousand seventeen.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
        <text>The Levites: the children of Jeshua, of Kadmiel, of the children of Hodevah, seventy-four.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
        <text>The singers: the children of Asaph, one hundred forty-eight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
        <text>The gatekeepers: the children of Shallum, the children of Ater, the children of Talmon, the children of Akkub, the children of Hatita, the children of Shobai, one hundred thirty-eight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
        <text>The temple servants: the children of Ziha, the children of Hasupha, the children of Tabbaoth,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="47">
        <text>The children of Keros, the children of Sia, the children of Padon,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="48">
        <text>The children of Lebanah, the children of Hagaba, the children of Salmai,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="49">
        <text>The children of Hanan, the children of Giddel, the children of Gahar,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="50">
        <text>The children of Reaiah, the children of Rezin, the children of Nekoda,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="51">
        <text>The children of Gazzam, the children of Uzza, the children of Paseah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="52">
        <text>The children of Besai, the children of Meunim, the children of Nephushesim,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="53">
        <text>The children of Bakbuk, the children of Hakupha, the children of Harhur,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="54">
        <text>The children of Bazlith, the children of Mehida, the children of Harsha,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="55">
        <text>The children of Barkos, the children of Sisera, the children of Temah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="56">
        <text>The children of Neziah, the children of Hatipha.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="57">
        <text>The children of Solomon's servants: the children of Sotai, the children of Sophereth, the children of Perida,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="58">
        <text>The children of Jaala, the children of Darkon, the children of Giddel,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="59">
        <text>The children of Shephatiah, the children of Hattil, the children of Pochereth-hazzebaim, the children of Amon.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="60">
        <text>All the temple servants and the children of Solomon's servants were three hundred ninety-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="61">
        <text>And these were those who went up from Tel-melah, Tel-harsha, Cherub, Addon, and Immer; but they could not give evidence of their fathers' houses nor their descendants, whether they were of Israel:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="62">
        <text>The children of Delaiah, the children of Tobiah, the children of Nekoda, six hundred forty-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="63">
        <text>And of the priests: the children of Hobaiah, the children of Hakkoz, the children of Barzillai, who took a wife from among the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite and was called after their name.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="64">
        <text>These sought their registry among those who were enrolled by genealogy, but they were not found; therefore they were considered defiled [i]and were excluded[/i] from the priesthood.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="65">
        <text>And the governor told them that they should not eat of the most holy things until a priest stood up with [xref]a[/xref]Urim and Thummim.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 28:30; Ezra 2:63</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="66">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]The whole assembly together was forty-two thousand three hundred sixty,</text>
        <xref num="a">vv. 66-72: Ezra 2:64-69</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="67">
        <text>Besides their male servants and their female servants, of whom there were seven thousand three hundred thirty-seven; and they had two hundred forty-five male singers and female singers.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="68">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Their horses were seven hundred thirty-six; their mules, two hundred forty-five;</text>
        <note num="1">Some MSS omit this verse, but cf. [link]Ezra 2:66[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="69">
        <text>[i]Their[/i] camels, four hundred thirty-five; [i]their[/i] donkeys, six thousand seven hundred twenty.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="70">
        <text>And some from among the heads of fathers' [i]houses[/i] gave to the work. The governor gave to the treasury one thousand darics of gold, fifty basins, [i]and[/i] five hundred thirty priests' garments.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="71">
        <text>And some of the heads of fathers' [i]houses[/i] gave into the treasury of the work twenty thousand darics of gold and two thousand two hundred minas of silver.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="72">
        <text>And that which the rest of the people gave was twenty thousand darics of gold and two thousand minas of silver and sixty-seven priests' garments.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="73">
        <text>So the priests and the Levites and the gatekeepers and the singers and some of the people and the temple servants and all Israel dwelt in their cities. And when the seventh month came, the children of Israel were in their cities.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="8">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And all the people gathered as [xref]a[/xref]one man in the open area that was before the Water Gate. And they told Ezra the scribe to bring the book of the [note]1[/note]law of Moses, which Jehovah had commanded to Israel.</text>
        <note num="1">God's intention with Israel was to have on earth a divinely constituted people to be His testimony. However, most of those who had returned to Jerusalem from the captivity in Babylon had been born and raised not in Israel but in Babylon. The Babylonian element had been wrought into them and constituted into their being. Therefore, after they returned to the land of their fathers to be citizens of the nation of Israel, they needed to be reconstituted. In order to be reconstituted, they needed to come back to God by coming back to His law, that is, His word. Under Ezra and Nehemiah the returned people of Israel were collectively constituted by and with God through His word to be a nation as God's testimony. See note [link]30[sup]1[/sup], par. 1, in ch. 13[/link].[br/][br/]In order to reconstitute the people of God, there is the need to educate them with the word that comes out of the mouth of God and which expresses God. To reconstitute the people of God is to educate them by putting them into the Word of God that they may be saturated with the word. The word of God is one with the Spirit ([link]John 6:63[/link]; [link]Eph. 6:17[/link]). Through our daily reading of the divine Word, the word of God works within us, and the Spirit, through the word, spontaneously dispenses God's nature with God's element into our being, causing us to be constituted with God.</note>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 3:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And [note]1[/note]Ezra the priest brought the law before the assembly, both men and women, and all who could hear with understanding, on the first day of the seventh month.</text>
        <note num="1">For the reconstituting of God's people, Ezra was very useful, for he was one through whom the people could be reconstituted with the word of God. See note [link]1[sup]1[/sup] in Ezra 7[/link].[br/][br/]In recognizing his need of Ezra, Nehemiah, the governor, the ruler, of the nation of Israel, indicated that he was altogether not ambitious. In reconstituting the nation, Nehemiah realized that he did not know God's Word. But Ezra, who was renowned for his knowledge of the Word of God, was still alive, and Nehemiah was willing to turn to Ezra for help. Nehemiah knew that without Ezra he could not reconstitute the people of God.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And he [xref]a[/xref]read in it before the open area that was before the Water Gate from [i]first[/i] light until midday in the presence of the men and the women and those who could understand. And the ears of all the people were [i]attentive[/i] to the book of the law.</text>
        <xref num="a">Josh. 8:34; Deut. 31:11; Neh. 13:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And Ezra the [xref]a[/xref]scribe stood upon a wooden platform that had been made for that purpose; and beside him stood Mattithiah and Shema and Anaiah and Uriah and Hilkiah and Maaseiah at his right hand; and at his left hand, Pedaiah and Mishael and Malchijah and Hashum and Hashbaddanah, Zechariah, [i]and[/i] Meshullam.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 7:6; Matt. 23:2; Mark 12:35</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And Ezra opened the book in the sight of all the people (for he was above all the people); and when he opened it, all the people stood up.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And Ezra blessed Jehovah the great God; and all the people answered, [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Amen, Amen, lifting up their hands. And they bowed their heads and worshipped Jehovah with [i]their[/i] faces to the ground.</text>
        <note num="1">This indicates that rebellious Israel had been fully convinced and fully subdued by the word of God spoken through Moses.</note>
        <xref num="a">Num. 5:22; Neh. 5:13; 1 Cor. 14:16; Rev. 22:21</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Also Jeshua and Bani and Sherebiah, Jamin, Akkub, Shabbethai, Hodiah, Maaseiah, Kelita, Azariah, Jozabad, Hanan, Pelaiah, and the Levites helped the people understand the law; and the people [i]stood[/i] in their place.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And they read in the book, in the law of God, interpreting and giving the sense, so that they understood the reading.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And Nehemiah, who was the [xref]a[/xref]governor, and Ezra the priest [i]and[/i] scribe, and the Levites who helped the people understand said to all the people, This day is [xref]b[/xref]holy unto Jehovah your God; do not mourn or weep. For all the people wept when they heard the words of the law.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 2:63; Neh. 7:65, 70; 10:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">Lev. 23:24; Num. 29:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Then he said to them, Go your way; eat the fat, and drink the sweet [i]wine,[/i] and send portions to him for whom nothing has been prepared; for this day is holy to our Lord. And do not be grieved, for the joy of Jehovah is your strength.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>So the Levites stilled all the people, saying, Be quiet, for the day is holy; and do not be grieved.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And all the people went their way to eat and to drink and to send portions and to make great rejoicing, because they had understood the words that were declared to them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And on the second day the heads of fathers' [i]houses[/i] of all the people, the priests, and the Levites were gathered to Ezra the scribe, that is, in order to gain [note]1[/note]insight into the words of the law.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Insight[/i] here refers to apprehending the intrinsic significance of the words of the law.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And they found it written in the law that Jehovah had commanded through Moses that the children of Israel dwell in [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]booths during the feast in the seventh month,</text>
        <note num="1">Or, tabernacles. So throughout this chapter.</note>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 23:34, 42</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And that they publish and proclaim in all their cities and in Jerusalem, saying, Go out to the mountain and bring olive branches and wild olive branches and myrtle branches and palm branches and branches of [i]other[/i] leafy trees to make [xref]a[/xref]booths, as it is written.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 16:16; cf. Luke 9:33</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>So the people went out and brought [i]them,[/i] and all made booths for themselves on their [xref]a[/xref]roofs and in their courts and in the courts of the house of God and in the open area [i]before[/i] the Water Gate and in the open area [i]before[/i] the Gate of Ephraim.</text>
        <xref num="a">Judg. 16:27; 1 Sam. 9:25; Acts 10:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And all the assembly of those who returned from the captivity made booths and dwelt in the [xref]a[/xref]booths, for since the days of Jeshua the son of Nun to that day the children of Israel had not done so; and there was very great rejoicing.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Chron. 8:13; Ezra 3:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And day by day, from the first day to the last day, he [xref]a[/xref]read in the book of the law of God. And they held the feast seven days, and on the eighth day there was a solemn assembly, according to the [note]1[/note]ordinance.</text>
        <note num="1">Israel did everything according to the complete law, with the commandments, the statutes, and the ordinances (see note [link]6[sup]4[/sup] in Luke 1[/link]). They had a revival and became a new nation, constituted through and with the word of God.</note>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 31:10-11</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="9">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Now on the [xref]a[/xref]twenty-fourth day of this month the children of Israel were assembled with fasting and in sackcloth, with earth [note]1[/note]on their heads.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., on them.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. Lev. 23:39; 2 Chron. 7:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And the descendants of Israel [xref]a[/xref]separated themselves from all foreigners, and they stood and confessed their sins and the iniquities of their fathers.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 10:28; 13:30; cf. Ezra 6:21; 9:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And they stood up in their place and read in the book of the law of Jehovah their God for a fourth part of the day, and for [i]another[/i] fourth part they confessed and worshipped Jehovah their God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Then Jeshua and Bani, Kadmiel, Shebaniah, Bunni, Sherebiah, Bani, [i]and[/i] Chenani stood up on the Levites' platform and cried out with a loud voice to Jehovah their God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Then the Levites, Jeshua, and Kadmiel, Bani, Hashabneiah, Sherebiah, Hodiah, Shebaniah, [i]and[/i] Pethahiah, said, Stand up and bless Jehovah your God from eternity to eternity:[br/]And may Your glorious name be blessed, / Which is exalted above all blessing and praise.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>You are Jehovah, / You alone; / You have [xref]a[/xref]made heaven, / The heaven of heavens with all its host, / The earth and all that is on it, / The seas and all that is in them; / And You give life to all of them; / And the host of heaven worships You.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 1:1; 2:4; 2 Kings 19:15; Rev. 10:6; 14:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>You are Jehovah God, / Who chose [xref]a[/xref]Abram / And brought him forth from Ur of the Chaldees / And gave him the name [xref]b[/xref]Abraham.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 11:31; Acts 7:2-4</xref>
        <xref num="b">Gen. 17:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And You found his heart faithful before You / And made a [xref]a[/xref]covenant with him, / To give [i]him[/i] the land of the Canaanites, / The Hittites, the Amorites, / And the Perizzites and the Jebusites and the Girgashites, / To give [i]it[/i] to his seed. / And You have fulfilled Your promises, / For You are righteous.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 15:18; 17:7-9; 12:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And You saw the [xref]a[/xref]affliction of our fathers in Egypt / And heard their [xref]b[/xref]cry by the Red Sea,</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 3:7</xref>
        <xref num="b">Exo. 14:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And You performed [xref]a[/xref]signs and wonders on Pharaoh, / And on all his servants, and on all the people of his land; / For You knew that they acted arrogantly toward them; / And You made Yourself a name, as [i]it is to[/i] this day.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Exo. 7-14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And You [xref]a[/xref]divided the sea before them, / So that they might pass through the midst of the sea on the dry land; / But their pursuers You threw into the [xref]b[/xref]depths, / Like a stone into mighty waters.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 14:21-22; Psa. 78:13</xref>
        <xref num="b">Exo. 15:4-5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Then in a [xref]a[/xref]pillar of cloud You led them by day, / And in a pillar of fire by night, / To light the way for them, / On which they should go.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 13:21-22; Num. 14:14; Neh. 9:19; 1 Cor. 10:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And You came down upon Mount [xref]a[/xref]Sinai / And spoke with them from heaven. / And You gave them just ordinances and true laws, / Good statutes and commandments.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 19:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And You made known to them / Your holy [xref]a[/xref]Sabbath / And prescribed commandments and statutes and a law for them / Through Moses Your servant.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 2:2-3; Exo. 16:23; 20:8-11; Ezek. 20:12, 20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And You gave them [xref]a[/xref]bread from heaven / For their hunger, / And You made water come forth from a [xref]b[/xref]rock for them / For their thirst. / And You told them to enter / In order to possess the land, / Which You swore / To give them.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 16:4; Psa. 78:24-25; 105:40; John 6:31</xref>
        <xref num="b">Exo. 17:6; Num. 20:10; Psa. 78:15-16; 1 Cor. 10:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>But they and our fathers acted arrogantly / And stiffened their neck and would not listen to Your commandments.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And they refused to listen / And would not remember Your wondrous acts, / Which You had done among them. / And they stiffened their neck and appointed a [xref]a[/xref]leader / To return to their slavery in Egypt. / But You are a God of forgiveness, / Gracious and compassionate, / Long-suffering and abounding in lovingkindness; / So You did not forsake them.</text>
        <xref num="a">Num. 14:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Indeed when they made for themselves / A molten [xref]a[/xref]calf, / And said, This is your God, / Who brought you up out of Egypt, / And showed great contempt;</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 32:4; Psa. 106:19-20; Acts 7:41</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>You, in Your great compassion, / Did not forsake them in the wilderness; / The pillar of cloud did not depart from over them by day, / To guide them on their way; / Nor the pillar of fire by night, / To light the way for them, on which they should go.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And You gave Your good [xref]a[/xref]Spirit / To instruct them, / And did not withhold Your [xref]b[/xref]manna from their mouth, / And gave them water for their thirst.</text>
        <xref num="a">Num. 11:17; Isa. 63:11</xref>
        <xref num="b">Exo. 16:35</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Indeed for [xref]a[/xref]forty years You sustained them in the wilderness; / They did not lack; / [xref]b[/xref]Their clothes did not wear out, / And their feet did not swell.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 2:7; 29:5</xref>
        <xref num="b">Deut. 8:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And You gave them kingdoms and peoples, / And divided [i]these[/i] to them as boundaries. / So they took possession of the land of [xref]a[/xref]Sihon, even the land of the king of Heshbon, / And the land of [xref]b[/xref]Og the king of Bashan.</text>
        <xref num="a">Num. 21:21-31</xref>
        <xref num="b">Num. 21:33-35</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>And their children You multiplied / Like the [xref]a[/xref]stars of heaven, / And You brought them into the land / That You told their fathers / To enter [i]and[/i] [xref]b[/xref]possess.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 15:5; 22:17; Deut. 10:22</xref>
        <xref num="b">Acts 7:45; 13:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And the children entered / And possessed the land; / And You subdued before them / The inhabitants of the land, the Canaanites; / And You gave them into their hand, / With their kings and the peoples of the land, / That they might do with them as they pleased.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>And they [xref]a[/xref]took their fortified cities / And a fertile land, / And took possession of [i]their[/i] houses, / Full of every good thing, / Hewn cisterns, vineyards, and olive groves, / And fruit trees in abundance; / And they ate and were satisfied and grew fat, / And they delighted in Your great goodness.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 6:10-11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>But they were disobedient and rebelled against You / And cast Your law behind their back. / And they [xref]a[/xref]slew Your prophets, / Who had testified against them / In order to turn them back to You; / And they showed great contempt.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 18:4; 19:10; Matt. 23:37; Acts 7:52; Matt. 21:35; Mark 12:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>Therefore You [xref]a[/xref]delivered them into the hand of their oppressors, / And they oppressed them; / But when they [xref]b[/xref]cried out to You in the time of their oppression, / You heard from heaven, / And according to Your great compassions You gave them [xref]c[/xref]deliverers, / Who delivered them from the hand of their oppressors.</text>
        <xref num="a">Judg. 2:14; Neh. 9:30; Psa. 106:41-42</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 106:44-45</xref>
        <xref num="c">Judg. 2:16; 3:9, 15; 2 Kings 13:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>Then after they had rest, / They again did evil before You; / And You abandoned them to the hand of their enemies, / And they had dominion over them. / But when they cried out to You again, / You heard from heaven / And delivered them [xref]a[/xref]many times / According to Your compassions.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 106:43</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>And You testified against them in order to turn them back to Your law, / But they acted arrogantly and would not listen to Your commandments; / And they sinned against Your ordinances / (By which, if a man [xref]a[/xref]does [i]them,[/i] he will live), / And they turned a stubborn shoulder / And stiffened their neck and would not listen.</text>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 18:5; Ezek. 20:11; Rom. 10:5; Gal. 3:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>Yet You bore with them / For many years / And testified to them by Your [xref]a[/xref]Spirit / Through Your prophets, / But they would not give heed; / So You delivered them / Into the hand of the peoples of the lands.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Pet. 1:10-11; 2 Pet. 1:21</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>Nevertheless in Your abundant compassions / You did not make an end of them; / And You did not forsake them, / For You are a gracious and compassionate God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>And now, our God, / The great, the mighty, and the awesome God, / Who keeps covenant and lovingkindness, / Do not let all the hardship seem small in Your sight / Which has come upon us, on our kings, on our rulers, / And on our priests and on our prophets / And on our fathers and on all Your people, / Since the days of the kings of [xref]a[/xref]Assyria / Until this day.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 17:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>But You are righteous / In all that has come upon us, / For You have acted faithfully / While we have acted wickedly;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>And our kings, our rulers, our priests, and our fathers / Have not performed Your law / Nor heeded Your commandments and Your testimonies, / By which You testified against them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>But they, in their kingdom and in Your great goodness, / Which You gave them, / And in the broad and [xref]a[/xref]fat land / That You put before them, / Did not serve You, nor did they turn / From their evil works.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 9:25; Deut. 8:7-10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
        <text>Here we are, slaves today; / And as for the land that You gave to our fathers / To eat of its fruit and its goodness, / Here we are, slaves upon it.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
        <text>And its abundant [xref]a[/xref]produce is for the kings / Whom You have put over us because of our sins; / And they rule over our bodies and over our cattle at their pleasure, / And we are in great distress.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 28:33, 51</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
        <text>And because of all this we are making a firm covenant and setting [i]it[/i] in writing, and upon the sealed document are [i]the names of[/i] our rulers, our Levites, [i]and[/i] our priests.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="10">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And those who are upon the sealed document are: [xref]a[/xref]Nehemiah the governor, the son of Hacaliah, and Zedekiah,</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 1:1; 8:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Seraiah, Azariah, Jeremiah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Pashhur, Amariah, Malchijah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Hattush, Shebaniah, Malluch,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Harim, Meremoth, Obadiah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Daniel, Ginnethon, Baruch,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Meshullam, Abijah, Mijamin,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Maaziah, Bilgai, Shemaiah; these were the priests.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And the Levites: namely, Jeshua the son of Azaniah, Binnui of the sons of Henadad, Kadmiel;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And their brothers, Shebaniah, Hodiah, Kelita, Pelaiah, Hanan,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Mica, Rehob, Hashabiah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Zaccur, Sherebiah, Shebaniah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Hodiah, Bani, Beninu.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>The heads of the people: Parosh, Pahath-moab, Elam, Zattu, Bani,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Bunni, Azgad, Bebai,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Adonijah, Bigvai, Adin,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Ater, Hezekiah, Azzur,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Hodiah, Hashum, Bezai,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Hariph, Anathoth, Nebai,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Magpiash, Meshullam, Hezir,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Meshezabel, Zadok, Jaddua,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Pelatiah, Hanan, Anaiah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Hoshea, Hananiah, Hasshub,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>Hallohesh, Pilha, Shobek,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Rehum, Hashabnah, Maaseiah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>And Ahiah, Hanan, Anan,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>Malluch, Harim, Baanah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>And the rest of the people, the priests, the Levites, gatekeepers, the singers, the temple servants, and all those who had [xref]a[/xref]separated themselves from the peoples of the lands unto the law of God, their wives, their sons, and their daughters, all who had knowledge [i]and[/i] who had understanding,</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 9:2; 13:30; cf. Ezra 6:21; 9:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>Join with their brothers, their nobles, and enter into a [note]1[/note]curse and an oath, to walk in the law of God, which was given through Moses the servant of God, and to keep and do all the commandments of Jehovah our Lord, as well as His ordinances and His statutes;</text>
        <note num="1">For them to enter into a curse meant that they would curse themselves if they did not keep the covenant. For them to enter into an oath meant that they could not cancel the covenant which they had made.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>And [i]swear[/i] that we will not [xref]a[/xref]give our daughters to the peoples of the land nor take their daughters for our sons;</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 7:3; Ezra 9:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>And if the peoples of the land bring in wares or any grain on the [xref]a[/xref]Sabbath day to sell, we will not buy [i]it[/i] from them on the Sabbath or on [i]any[/i] holy day; and we will forego [i]the crops of[/i] the [xref]b[/xref]seventh year and the exaction of every debt.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 20:10; Lev. 23:3; Deut. 5:12; cf. Neh. 13:15-22</xref>
        <xref num="b">Exo. 23:10-11; Lev. 25:4; Deut. 15:1-2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>We also lay upon ourselves obligations to [xref]a[/xref]charge ourselves one-third shekel yearly for the service of the house of our God,</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Matt. 17:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>For the rows of bread, and for the continual meal offering, and for the continual burnt offering, for the Sabbaths, for the new moons, for the appointed feasts, and for the holy things, and for the sin offerings, to make expiation for Israel, and for all the work of the house of our God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>And we the priests, the Levites, and the people have cast lots for the wood offering, in order to bring [i]it[/i] to the house of our God, according to our fathers' houses, at appointed times year by year, to burn on the altar of Jehovah our God as it is written in the law;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>And in order to bring the [xref]a[/xref]firstfruits of our land and the firstfruits of all the fruit of every tree year by year to the house of Jehovah,</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 23:19; 34:26; Lev. 2:12; Num. 18:12; Deut. 26:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
        <text>As well as the [xref]a[/xref]firstborn of our sons and of our cattle, as it is written in the law; and in order to bring the firstlings of our herds and of our flocks to the house of our God, to the priests who minister in the house of our God.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 13:2, 12-13; Lev. 27:26; Num. 18:15, 17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
        <text>We will also bring the [xref]a[/xref]first of our dough and our heave offerings and [i]of[/i] the fruit of every tree [i]and[/i] the new wine and the fresh oil to the priests at the chambers of the house of our God, and the [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]tithe of our land to the Levites; for they, the Levites, are those who receive the tithes in all our rural towns.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]28[sup]1[/sup] in Num. 18[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 23:17; Num. 15:20-21</xref>
        <xref num="b">Deut. 12:6, 11; Num. 18:26; 2 Chron. 31:12; Neh. 13:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
        <text>And the priest, the son of Aaron, shall be with the Levites when the Levites receive the tithes; and the Levites shall bring the tithe of the tithes up to the house of our God, to the chambers of the storehouse.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
        <text>For the children of Israel and the sons of Levi shall bring the heave offering of the grain, of the new wine, and of the fresh oil to the chambers, where the vessels of the sanctuary, the priests who minister, and the gatekeepers and the singers are; and we will not forsake the house of our God.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="11">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And the rulers of the people dwelt in Jerusalem, and the rest of the people cast lots in order to bring one in ten to dwell in Jerusalem, the [xref]a[/xref]holy city, while nine-tenths [i]remained[/i] in the [i]other[/i] cities.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 11:18; Isa. 48:2; 52:1; Matt. 4:5; 27:53</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And the people [note]1[/note]blessed all the men who offered themselves willingly to dwell in Jerusalem.</text>
        <note num="1">At that time it was a burden for anyone to dwell in Jerusalem. Because of the constant threat of foreign invasion, not many were willing to live in Jerusalem. Therefore, to have a sufficient number of people living in Jerusalem, there was the need of some arrangement by casting lots. The ones whose lot was to live in Jerusalem were required to move there. However, some were willing to volunteer to dwell in Jerusalem, and all the people blessed them.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Now these are the heads of the province who dwelt in Jerusalem (but in the cities of Judah all dwelt in their possession in their cities, [i]that is,[/i] Israel, the priests, and the Levites, and the temple servants, and the children of Solomon's servants):</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And in Jerusalem some of the children of Judah and some of the children of Benjamin dwelt. Of the children of Judah: Athaiah the son of Uzziah, the son of Zechariah, the son of Amariah, the son of Shephatiah, the son of Mahalalel, of the children of Perez;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And Maaseiah the son of Baruch, the son of Col-hozeh, the son of Hazaiah, the son of Adaiah, the son of Joiarib, the son of Zechariah, the son of the Shilonite.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>All the sons of Perez who dwelt in Jerusalem were four hundred sixty-eight valiant men.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And these are the sons of Benjamin: Sallu the son of Meshullam, the son of Joed, the son of Pedaiah, the son of Kolaiah, the son of Maaseiah, the son of Ithiel, the son of Jeshaiah;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And after him Gabbai [i]and[/i] Sallai: nine hundred twenty-eight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And Joel the son of Zichri was their overseer; and Judah the son of Hassenuah was second over the city.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Of the priests: Jedaiah the son of Joiarib, Jachin,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Seraiah the son of Hilkiah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, the ruler of the house of God,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And their brothers who did the work of the house, eight hundred twenty-two; and Adaiah the son of Jeroham, the son of Pelaliah, the son of Amzi, the son of Zechariah, the son of Pashhur, the son of Malchijah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And his brothers, heads of fathers' [i]houses,[/i] two hundred forty-two; and Amashsai the son of Azarel, the son of Ahzai, the son of Meshillemoth, the son of Immer,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And their brothers, mighty men of valor, one hundred twenty-eight; and their overseer was Zabdiel the son of Haggedolim.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And of the Levites: Shemaiah the son of Hasshub, the son of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Bunni;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And Shabbethai and Jozabad, of the heads of the Levites, who were over the outside work of the house of God;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And Mattaniah the son of Mica, the son of Zabdi, the son of Asaph, who was the first to begin the thanksgiving in prayer, with Bakbukiah, the second among his brothers; and Abda the son of Shammua, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>All the Levites in the [xref]a[/xref]holy city were two hundred eighty-four.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 11:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And the gatekeepers, Akkub, Talmon, and their brothers, who kept watch at the gates, were one hundred seventy-two.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And the rest of Israel, the priests [i]and[/i] the Levites, were in all the cities of Judah, every one in his own inheritance.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>But the temple servants dwelt on the Ophel. And Ziha and Gishpa were over the temple servants.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And the overseer of the Levites at Jerusalem was Uzzi the son of Bani, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Mica, of the sons of Asaph, the singers, for the work of the house of God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>For there was a commandment from the king concerning them and fixed provisions for the singers, as each day required.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And Pethahiah the son of Meshezabel, of the children of Zerah the son of Judah, was at the king's hand in all matters concerning the people.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>And as for the villages, with their fields, some of the children of Judah dwelt in Kiriath-arba and its villages, and in Dibon and its villages, and in Jekabzeel and its outlying villages,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>And in Jeshua, and in Moladah, and Beth-pelet,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>And in Hazar-shual, and in Beer-sheba and its villages,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>And in Ziklag, and in Meconah and in its villages,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>And in En-rimmon, and in Zorah, and in Jarmuth,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>Zanoah, Adullam, and their villages, Lachish and its fields, Azekah and its villages. So they encamped from Beer-sheba as far as the valley of Hinnom.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>And the children of Benjamin [i]dwelt[/i] from Geba [i]onward,[/i] at Michmash and Aija, and at Beth-el and its villages,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>At Anathoth, Nob, Ananiah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>Hazor, Ramah, Gittaim,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>Hadid, Zeboim, Neballat,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>Lod, and Ono, the valley of craftsmen.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
        <text>And certain courses of the Levites in Judah [i]were joined[/i] to Benjamin.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="12">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Now these are the [note]1[/note]priests and the Levites who went up with [xref]a[/xref]Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel and Jeshua: [xref]b[/xref]Seraiah, Jeremiah, Ezra,</text>
        <note num="1">The main serving ones in the worship of God, which is the main thing in God's kingdom, were not the kings but the priests with the Levites, who were the servants of the priests ([link]Num. 18:2[/link], [link]6[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Chron. 3:19; Ezra 2:2; 3:2; Neh. 12:47; Matt. 1:12</xref>
        <xref num="b">vv. 1b-21: Neh. 10:2-27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Amariah, Malluch, Hattush,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Shecaniah, Rehum, Meremoth,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Iddo, Ginnethoi, Abijah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Mijamin, Maadiah, Bilgah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Shemaiah, and Joiarib, Jedaiah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Sallu, Amok, Hilkiah, Jedaiah. These were the heads of the priests and of their brothers in the days of Jeshua.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And the Levites: Jeshua, Binnui, Kadmiel, Sherebiah, Judah, [i]and[/i] Mattaniah, who was over the thanksgiving, he and his brothers.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And Bakbukiah and Unno, their brothers, were opposite them, by [i]their[/i] service groups.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And Jeshua begot Joiakim, and Joiakim begot Eliashib, and Eliashib [i]begot[/i] Joiada,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And Joiada begot Jonathan, and Jonathan begot Jaddua.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And in the days of Joiakim, the priests, the heads of fathers' [i]houses,[/i] were: of Seraiah, Meraiah; of Jeremiah, Hananiah;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Of Ezra, Meshullam; of Amariah, Jehohanan;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Of Malluchi, Jonathan; of Shebaniah, Joseph;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Of Harim, Adna; of Meraioth, Helkai;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Of Iddo, Zechariah; of Ginnethon, Meshullam;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Of Abijah, Zichri; of Miniamin, of Moadiah, Piltai;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Of Bilgah, Shammua; of Shemaiah, Jehonathan;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And of Joiarib, Mattenai; of Jedaiah, Uzzi;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Of Sallai, Kallai; of Amok, Eber;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Of Hilkiah, Hashabiah; of Jedaiah, Nethanel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>As for the Levites, in the days of Eliashib, Joiada, and Johanan and Jaddua, the heads of fathers' [i]houses[/i] were recorded, as well as the priests, in the reign of Darius the Persian.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>The sons of Levi, the heads of fathers' [i]houses,[/i] were written in the book of the chronicles until the days of Johanan the son of Eliashib.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And the heads of the Levites: Hashabiah, Sherebiah, and Jeshua the son of Kadmiel, with their brothers opposite them, to praise and give thanks, according to the commandment of David the [xref]a[/xref]man of God, service group next to service group.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Chron. 8:14; Neh. 12:36</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Mattaniah and Bakbukiah, Obadiah, Meshullam, Talmon, Akkub were gatekeepers keeping the watch at the storehouses of the gates.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>These were in the days of Joiakim the son of Jeshua, the son of Jozadak, and in the days of [xref]a[/xref]Nehemiah the governor and of Ezra the priest, the scribe.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 8:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>And at the [xref]a[/xref]dedication of the wall of Jerusalem they sought the Levites from all their places, to bring them to Jerusalem in order to hold the dedication with rejoicing and thanksgiving and singing with cymbals, harps, and lyres.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Num. 7:10; 1 Kings 8:63; Psa. 30:1; Ezra 6:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>So the sons of the singers gathered together from the plain around Jerusalem and from the villages of the Netophathites</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>And from Beth-gilgal and from the fields of Geba and Azmaveth; for the singers had built outlying villages for themselves around Jerusalem.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>And the priests and the Levites purified themselves; and they purified the people and the gates and the wall.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>Then I brought the leaders of Judah up onto the wall and appointed two great companies that gave thanks and went in procession. [i]One went to[/i] the right upon the wall toward the Dung Gate;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>And after them went Hoshaiah, and half of the leaders of Judah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>And Azariah, Ezra, and Meshullam,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>Judah, and Benjamin, and Shemaiah, and Jeremiah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>And some of the priests' sons with trumpets: Zechariah the son of Jonathan, the son of Shemaiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Micaiah, the son of Zaccur, the son of Asaph;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
        <text>And his brothers, Shemaiah and Azarel, Milalai, Gilalai, Maai, Nethanel and Judah, Hanani, with the musical instruments of David the [xref]a[/xref]man of God; and Ezra the scribe was before them.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 12:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
        <text>And at the Fountain Gate, and straight in front of them, they went up by the stairs of the city of David, at the ascent of the wall, above the house of David, to the Water Gate on the east.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
        <text>And the second company that gave thanks went to meet [i]them,[/i] and I after them, with half of the people, upon the wall, above the Tower of the Furnaces, to the Broad Wall,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
        <text>And above the Gate of Ephraim, and by the Old Gate, and by the [xref]a[/xref]Fish Gate and the Tower of Hananel and the Tower of the Hundred, to the [xref]b[/xref]Sheep Gate; and they stopped at the Gate of the Guard.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Chron. 33:14; Neh. 3:3; Zeph. 1:10</xref>
        <xref num="b">Neh. 3:1, 32</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
        <text>So the two companies that gave thanks stood in the house of God, as well as I and half of the rulers with me;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
        <text>And the priests, Eliakim, Maaseiah, Miniamin, Micaiah, Elioenai, Zechariah, and Hananiah, with trumpets;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
        <text>And Maaseiah and Shemaiah and Eleazar and Uzzi and Jehohanan and Malchijah and Elam and Ezer. And the singers sang loud, with Jezrahiah as the overseer.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
        <text>And they offered great sacrifices that day and rejoiced, for God had caused them to rejoice greatly; and the women and children also rejoiced. And the joy of Jerusalem was heard from afar.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
        <text>And on that day men were appointed over the chambers for the stores, for the heave offerings, for the firstfruits, and for the tithes, to gather into them, according to the cities' fields, the [note]1[/note]portions assigned by the law for the priests and the Levites, for Judah rejoiced over the priests and Levites who served.</text>
        <note num="1">Nehemiah not only brought the serving Levites and priests into function; he also supplied their daily necessities ([link]vv. 44-47[/link]). Before that time, no one had taken care of this matter properly. See notes on [link]Num. 18:8-32[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
        <text>And they kept the charge of their God and the charge of the purification, as did the singers and the gatekeepers, according to the command of David [i]and[/i] Solomon his son.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
        <text>For in the days of David and Asaph, long ago, there were leaders of the singers, and [i]there were[/i] songs of praise and thanksgiving to God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="47">
        <text>And in the days of Zerubbabel and in the days of Nehemiah all Israel gave the portions for the singers and the gatekeepers as each day required; and they consecrated [i]portions[/i] for the [xref]a[/xref]Levites, and the Levites consecrated [i]portions[/i] for the sons of [xref]b[/xref]Aaron.</text>
        <xref num="a">Num. 18:21, 24</xref>
        <xref num="b">Num. 18:26-28</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="13">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>On that day they [xref]a[/xref]read in the book of Moses in the hearing of the people; and it was found written in it that [xref]b[/xref]no [note]1[/note]Ammonite or Moabite should enter the assembly of God forever,</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]37[sup]2[/sup], par. 1, in Gen. 19[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 31:11-12; 2 Kings 23:2; Neh. 8:3, 8, 18; 9:3</xref>
        <xref num="b">Deut. 23:3-5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>For they did not meet the children of Israel with bread and water, but hired [xref]a[/xref]Balaam against them to curse them; yet our God turned the [xref]b[/xref]curse into a blessing.</text>
        <xref num="a">Num. 22:5; Josh. 24:9-10; 2 Pet. 2:15</xref>
        <xref num="b">Num. 23:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And when they heard the law, they [xref]a[/xref]separated all the [xref]b[/xref]mixed multitude from Israel.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Neh. 9:2</xref>
        <xref num="b">Exo. 12:38; Num. 11:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Now before this, Eliashib the priest, who had been appointed over the chambers of the house of our God, because he was related to [xref]a[/xref]Tobiah,</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 2:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Had prepared for him a large chamber where previously they had put the meal offering, the frankincense, and the vessels, as well as the tithes of the grain, the new wine, and the fresh oil, [i]as[/i] commanded for the Levites and the singers and the gatekeepers, and the heave offerings for the priests.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>But during all this [i]time[/i] I was not in Jerusalem, for in the [xref]a[/xref]thirty-second year of Artaxerxes the king of Babylon I went to the king; then after some time I asked leave from the king.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 5:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And I came to Jerusalem and perceived the evil that Eliashib had done for Tobiah by preparing him a chamber in the courts of the house of God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And it grieved me much; therefore I cast all the household utensils of Tobiah out of the chamber.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Then I gave commands, and they [xref]a[/xref]purified the chambers; and I returned the vessels of the house of God, the meal offering, and the frankincense there.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 2 Chron. 29:15-16, 18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>I also found out that the [xref]a[/xref]portions of the Levites had not been given [i]to them[/i] and thus the Levites and the singers, who performed the service, had gone back, each to his own fields.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 10:37</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>So I contended with the rulers and said, Why has the house of God been forsaken? Then I gathered them together and set them in their stations.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And all Judah brought the tithe of the grain and the new wine and the fresh oil to the storehouses.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And I appointed treasurers over the storehouses, Shelemiah the priest, and Zadok the scribe, and of the Levites, Pedaiah; and next to them was Hanan the son of Zaccur, the son of Mattaniah; for they were counted faithful, and it was their charge to distribute to their brothers.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Remember me, O my God, concerning this, and do not blot out my loyal deeds, which I have done for the house of my God and for its services.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>In those days I saw some in Judah treading wine presses on the [xref]a[/xref]Sabbath and bringing in heaps of grain and loading [i]them[/i] on their donkeys, as well as wine, grapes and figs, and every kind of load, and they were bringing [i]them[/i] into Jerusalem on the Sabbath day; and I protested on the day that they sold food.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 20:10; Neh. 10:31</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And Tyrians who dwelt there were also bringing in fish and every kind of merchandise, and selling [i]it[/i] on the Sabbath to the children of Judah and in Jerusalem.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Then I contended with the nobles of Judah and said to them, What is this evil thing that you are doing, profaning the Sabbath day?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Did not your fathers act this way, and did not our God bring all this trouble upon us and upon this city? But you bring more wrath upon Israel by profaning the Sabbath.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And when the gates of Jerusalem began to be dark before the Sabbath, I commanded that the doors be shut and commanded that they not be opened until after the Sabbath; and I set some of my servants at the gates [i]so that[/i] no load could enter on the [xref]a[/xref]Sabbath day.</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 17:21; John 5:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Then the merchants and sellers of all kinds of merchandise spent the night outside Jerusalem once or twice.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>But I testified against them and said to them, Why do you spend the night in front of the wall? If you do so again, I will lay hands on you. From that time on they did not come on the Sabbath.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And I commanded the Levites that they should purify themselves and that they should come and keep the gates, in order to sanctify the Sabbath day. For this also remember me, O my God, and spare me according to the greatness of Your lovingkindness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>In those days I also saw that the Jews had [xref]a[/xref]married women of Ashdod, Ammon, and Moab;</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 9:2; 10:2, 10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>And as for their children, half spoke in the language of Ashdod; and none of them could speak the language of Judah, but [i]they spoke[/i] the language of the respective peoples.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>And I contended with them and cursed them and struck some of them and pulled out their hair; and I made them swear by God, [i]saying,[/i] You shall [xref]a[/xref]not give your daughters to their sons nor take their daughters for your sons or for yourselves.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 10:30; Deut. 7:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>Did not Solomon the king of Israel sin in these matters? And among the many nations there was no king like him, and he was [xref]a[/xref]beloved of his God, and God made him king over all Israel; yet the [xref]b[/xref]foreign wives caused even him to sin.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 12:24-25</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. 1 Kings 11:1-8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>Shall we then listen to you and do all this great evil by acting unfaithfully against our God in marrying foreign women?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>And one of the sons of Joiada the son of Eliashib the high priest was the son-in-law of Sanballat the Horonite, so I chased him away from me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>Remember them, O my God; for they have [xref]a[/xref]defiled the priesthood and the covenant of the priesthood and of the Levites.</text>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 11:44; Heb. 12:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>Thus I [note]1[/note]cleansed them from everything foreign.[separator]And I appointed duties for the priests and the Levites, each in his work,</text>
        <note num="1">Nehemiah, with the help of Ezra, fully reconstituted the returned captives of the nation of Israel (Neh. 8:1-13:31). Consequently, Israel became a particular nation, a nation that was sanctified and separated unto God and that expressed God. They were transfused with the thought of God, with the considerations of God, and with all that God is, making them God's reproduction. As a result, they became a divine nation on earth expressing the divine character. They were reconstituted personally and corporately to be God's testimony.[br/][br/]The central and crucial point of the books of Ezra and Nehemiah is the matter of proper, adequate leadership. Whereas the record of the leadership in Judges, 1 and 2 Samuel, 1 and 2 Kings, and 1 and 2 Chronicles is, for the most part, dark, the record in Ezra and Nehemiah is altogether bright. In the books of Ezra and Nehemiah three leaders are mentioned: Zerubbabel, Ezra, and Nehemiah. They were all excellent leaders, but the best and the highest was Nehemiah. Only under the leadership of persons like Zerubbabel, Ezra, and Nehemiah could Israel be reconstituted to be the testimony, the expression, of God on earth, a people absolutely different from the Gentile nations. Such a testimony of God is a type of what God wants the church to be today.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>And for the wood offering, at the appointed times, and for the firstfruits. Remember me, O my God, for good.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    </chapters>
</book>
