<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="yes"?>
<book name="Obadiah">
    <info title="Author">Obadiah ([link]v. 1[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Time of His Ministry">About 880 or 587 B.C.; it is hard to determine which date is correct.</info>
    <info title="Place of His Ministry">The southern kingdom of Judah.</info>
    <info title="Object of His Ministry">The southern kingdom of Judah.</info>
    <subject>Jehovah's Dealing with Esau, and Jacob's Victory for the Kingdom of Jehovah</subject>
    <outlines>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="1" ref="v. 1a">The introductory word</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="2" ref="vv. 1b-9">Jehovah's dealing with Edom</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="3" ref="vv. 10-14">The evils of Edom</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="4" ref="vv. 15-16">The day of Jehovah upon all the nations</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="5" ref="vv. 17-21">The issue of Jehovah's dealing</outline>
    </outlines>
    <chapters>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>The vision of [note]1[/note]Obadiah.[separator]Thus says the Lord Jehovah concerning [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]Edom, / [xref]b[/xref]We have heard a report from Jehovah, / And an envoy has been sent among the nations: / Arise, and let us rise up against it for battle.</text>
        <note num="1">Meaning [i]the servant of Jah; Jah[/i] being a shortened form of [i]Jehovah.[/i] The central thought of the book of Obadiah is that Jehovah's dealing with Esau issues in Jacob's victory and possession for the kingdom of God in the age of restoration.</note>
        <note num="2">[i]Edom[/i] refers to Esau ([link]Gen. 36:1[/link]). Whereas Esau is the name of a person, the twin brother of Jacob, Edom is the name of a country.</note>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 49:7-22; Ezek. 25:12-14; Joel 3:19; Amos 1:11-12</xref>
        <xref num="b">vv. 1b-4: Jer. 49:14-16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Indeed I have made you small among the nations; / You are very despised.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>The arrogance of your heart has beguiled you, / O you who dwell in the clefts of the rock, / Whose habitation is lofty, / Who says in his heart, / Who will bring me down to the ground?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Though you set yourself on high like the eagle / And though you make your nest among the stars, / I will [xref]a[/xref]bring you down from there, / Declares Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 14:13-15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>If [xref]a[/xref]thieves came to you, / If spoilers in the night &amp;#8212; / How you would be cut off! &amp;#8212; / Would they not steal [i]only[/i] their fill? / If grape gatherers came to you, / Would they not leave gleanings?</text>
        <xref num="a">vv. 5-6: Jer. 49:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>How thoroughly searched Esau is! / [i]How[/i] sought out his hidden treasures are!</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>All the men of your [note]1[/note]confederacy / Have sent you away to the border; / The men who were at peace with you / Have deceived you; they have prevailed against you. / They make your bread / A snare under you. / There is no understanding in him.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., covenant. Some nations formed a confederacy with Edom, but eventually they were unfaithful to Edom.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Will I not in that day, / Declares Jehovah, / Destroy the wise men from Edom, / And understanding from the mountain of Esau?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And your mighty men will be dismayed, O Teman, / So that each one is cut off from the mountain of Esau by slaughter.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Because of the [xref]a[/xref]violence against your [note]1[/note]brother Jacob, / Shame will cover you, and you will be cut off [xref]b[/xref]forever.</text>
        <note num="1">Jacob and Esau were brothers ([link]Gen. 25:25-26[/link]). God's recompensing Edom for his ill-treatment of his brother Jacob (i.e., Israel) was very human. God judged the nation of Edom concerning a matter of human affection.</note>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 27:41; Psa. 137:7; Ezek. 25:12</xref>
        <xref num="b">Ezek. 35:9; Mal. 1:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>In the day that you stood on the side, / In the day that strangers took his substance captive / And foreigners entered into his gates / And [xref]a[/xref]cast lots over Jerusalem, / You also were like one of them.</text>
        <xref num="a">Joel 3:3; Nahum 3:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>But do not look to the day of your brother, / To the day of his misfortune; / [xref]a[/xref]Neither rejoice concerning the children of Judah / In the day of their destruction, / Nor boast / In the day of distress.</text>
        <xref num="a">Micah 7:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Do not enter the gate of My people / In the day of their calamity; / Do not look, even you, on his affliction / In the day of his calamity, / Nor send forth [i]your hands[/i] on his substance / In the day of his calamity.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And do not stand at the crossroads / To cut off those of his who escape, / Nor deliver those of his who survive / In the day of distress.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>For the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]day of Jehovah is near / Upon all the nations: / [note]2[/note]As you have done, it [xref]b[/xref]will be done to you; / Your recompense will return upon your head.</text>
        <note num="1">The day of Jehovah is a matter of God's judgment on all the nations. See note [link]15[sup]1[/sup] in Joel 1[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">The principle of God's judgment on Edom is that as Edom has done to others, it will be done to them. The principle for judging the nations ([link]v. 16[/link]) is that because of the profane action of the nations in enjoying themselves upon the holy mountain of God's sanctuary, God would cause the other nations to drink continually at the places of those nations who participated in that profane action. In this way God would recompense the nations who drank at His holy mountain.</note>
        <xref num="a">Ezek. 30:3; Joel 3:14</xref>
        <xref num="b">Ezek. 35:15; Hab. 2:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>For as you have [xref]a[/xref]drunk [i]the cup of wrath[/i] upon My holy mountain, / All the nations will drink [i]the same[/i] continually; / Indeed they will drink and swallow down, / And they will be as though they had not been.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 51:22; Jer. 25:28-29; 49:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>[note]1[/note]But in Mount [xref]a[/xref]Zion / There will be those who have escaped, / And it will be holy. / And the house of Jacob will possess / Their possessions.</text>
        <note num="1">[link]Verses 17-21[/link] portray the issue of Jehovah's dealing: Jehovah will save the house of Jacob and sanctify them ([link]v. 17a[/link]); the house of Jacob will overcome Edom ([link]v. 18[/link]) and will possess Edom's possessions ([link]vv. 17b[/link], [link]19-20[/link]); and saviors will come up on Mount Zion to judge the mountain of Esau, and the kingdom will be Jehovah's ([link]v. 21[/link]). All the aforementioned items were fulfilled at the time of the Maccabees, and they will be much more fulfilled in glory at the time of restoration for the kingdom of God ([link]Matt. 19:28[/link]; [link]Rev. 11:15[/link]). The Maccabees, taking Mount Zion as their ground to judge Edom, gained a victory over Antiochus Epiphanes in about 165 B.C. ([link]Dan. 8:9-14[/link] and notes; [link]Zech. 9:11-17[/link] and notes). The victory of the Maccabees was a type of the victory Israel will gain immediately before the age of restoration.[br/][br/]The Minor Prophets, including Obadiah, reveal that the nations used by God to chastise sinful Israel do things in excess. Therefore, God will come in to judge the nations. This judgment will issue in Israel's gaining the victory and enlarging their territory for the kingdom of God on earth, especially for God's kingdom in the time of restoration. Cf. note [link]18[sup]1[/sup] in Gen. 15[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Joel 2:32</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And the house of Jacob will be a fire, / And the house of Joseph a flame; / And the house of Esau will be as stubble, / And they will burn among them and devour them; / And there will be no survivor / To the house of Esau, / For Jehovah has spoken.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And those of the south will possess the mountain of Esau, / And those of the lowlands, the Philistines; / Indeed they will possess the field of Ephraim / And the field of Samaria, / And Benjamin [i]will possess[/i] Gilead.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>And the captivity of this host of the children of Israel, / Who are among the Canaanites, [i]will possess[/i] as far as Zarephath; / And the captivity of Jerusalem, who are in Sepharad, / Will possess the cities of the south.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And saviors will come up on Mount Zion / To judge the mountain of Esau, / And the [xref]a[/xref]kingdom will be Jehovah's.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 22:28; Dan. 2:44; 7:14, 27; Zech. 14:9; Matt. 6:13; Luke 1:33; Rev. 11:15; 19:6</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    </chapters>
</book>
