<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="yes"?>
<book name="Proverbs">
    <info title="Author">The main writers and collectors are Solomon ([link]1:1[/link]; [link]10:1[/link]; [link]25:1[/link]; cf. [link]1 Kings 4:32[/link]; [link]Eccl. 12:9[/link]) and Hezekiah ([link]25:1[/link]), who added some proverbs of the forefathers in [link]chs. 25-29[/link]. [link]Chapter 30[/link] is attributed to Agur, and [link]ch. 31[/link] to King Lemuel; nothing definite is known concernng either man.</info>
    <info title="Time of Writing">About 1000 B.C. (Solomon's portion, [link]chs. 1-24[/link]) and about 700 B.C. (Hezekiah's portion, [link]chs. 25-29[/link]). The time of writing for [link]chs. 30-31[/link] is unknown.</info>
    <info title="Place of Writing">Probably Jerusalem.</info>
    <subject>Words of Wisdom Teaching People How to Behave and How to Build Up Their Character in the Human Life</subject>
    <outlines>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="1" ref="1:1-24:34">The collection of Solomon</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="1:1-9:18">The principles for man to live a proper human life</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="10:1-19:29">A contrast between doing righteousness in wisdom and doing wickedness in folly</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="20:1-24:34">Admonitions and teachings</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="2" ref="25:1-29:27">The collection of Hezekiah &amp;#8212; admonitions and teachings</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="3" ref="30:1-33">The word of Agur &amp;#8212; general words of wisdom</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="4" ref="31:1-31">The word of King Lemuel</outline>
    </outlines>
    <chapters>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>The [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]proverbs of Solomon the son of David, the king of Israel:</text>
        <note num="1">Heb. [i]mishle,[/i] meaning [i]similitudes, proverbs, parables,[/i] to represent general truths. Proverbs is a collection of the words of the wise. It stresses the wisdom that man receives of God through his contacting of God and that teaches man how to behave and build up his character in his human life. Since the proverbs were collected mainly by two kings of Judah (Solomon and Hezekiah) in the age of the law, the book of Proverbs may be considered a subsidiary to the law. The law is the portrait of God; as such, it demands that God's people keep it so that they may be made copies of God for His expression and glorification (see note [link]1[sup]1[/sup] in Exo. 20[/link]). Proverbs, as a subsidiary to the law, instructs people how to behave and how to build themselves up according to God's attributes, i.e., according to what God is.[br/][br/]As a part of the holy word in God's Holy Scriptures, Proverbs should be considered the breath of God for us to breathe in that we may receive the life supply from God ([link]2 Tim. 3:16[/link]). Hence, we should read Proverbs by being filled with the fullness of God in our spirit ([link]Eph. 5:18[/link]; [link]3:19[/link]). Furthermore, we should read Proverbs in the New Testament Spirit of life ([link]Rom. 8:2[/link]), with our regenerated spirit, mingling prayer with our reading ([link]Eph. 6:17-18[/link]) in order to mingle the words with spirit and life (cf. [link]John 6:63[/link]). While we are still living in this body, we need Proverbs to give us instructions on how to live rightly in many aspects. However, according to God's economy Proverbs should not be used to build up the old man by cultivating our self and our natural man. Rather, we should reject self-cultivation and condemn the building up of the natural man (cf. [link]Matt. 16:24[/link]; [link]Rom. 6:6[/link]; [link]Gal. 2:20[/link]) and come to Proverbs as a new man ([link]Eph. 4:22-24[/link]) by exercising our spirit with the Spirit to contact the word in the spirit of prayer. Then the word in Proverbs will become spirit and life to us, not to cultivate our natural man but to cultivate our regenerated new man. We must be persons who love the Lord and pursue Christ, not self-perfection (cf. [link]Phil. 3:3-14[/link]), and who love the Lord's word in the entire Bible and read it with a praying spirit, not to seek the doctrine of letters but to seek the Spirit and word of life (cf. [link]John 5:39-40[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 3:6[/link]), and not to gain any help for self-cultivation but to nourish our spirit that we may live a Christian life that is perfect in the divine virtues, which are the expressions of the divine attributes. If we are such persons, this book will render us nuggets and gems to strengthen our life of pursuing Christ for the fulfillment of God's economy in producing and building up the Body of Christ, which consummates the New Jerusalem as God's heart's desire and ultimate goal.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 4:32; Prov. 10:1; 25:1; Eccl. 12:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>For knowing wisdom and instruction; / For discerning words of understanding;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>For receiving instruction in wise conduct, / Righteousness, justice, and equity;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>For giving prudence to the simple, / Knowledge and discretion to the young man;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>That the wise man may hear and increase in learning, / And he who has understanding may acquire sound counsel;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>For understanding proverb and figure, / The words of the wise and their difficult sayings.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>The [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]fear of Jehovah is the beginning of knowledge; / Fools despise wisdom and instruction.</text>
        <note num="1">Proverbs presents the principles for man to live a proper human life. The major principles are revering God ([link]1:7[/link]; [link]3:5-10[/link]), needing wisdom ([link]vv. 20-33[/link]; [link]3:13-24[/link]; [link]4:5-9[/link]), honoring one's parents ([link]1:8-9[/link]; [link]3:1-2[/link]; [link]6:20[/link]; [link]30:17[/link]), and holding marriage in honor ([link]5:1-20[/link]; [link]31:10-31[/link]).[br/][br/]To revere God is to consider and regard Him in everything, never forgetting that He is the wonderful God who created us. To revere God is to fear God ([link]1:7[/link]; [link]2:4-5[/link]; [link]8:13[/link]; [link]9:10[/link]; [link]10:27[/link]; [link]14:2[/link], [link]26-27[/link]; [link]15:16[/link], [link]33a[/link]), to trust in Him ([link]3:5-8[/link], [link]26[/link]; [link]16:20[/link]; [link]30:5-6[/link]), and to honor Him ([link]3:9-10[/link]). Revering God stops us from doing evil. It also causes us to be touched by the sufferings of others and to show mercy and compassion to them.</note>
        <xref num="a">Job 28:28; Psa. 111:10; Prov. 9:10; 1 Pet. 2:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Hear, my son, the instruction of your [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]father, / And do not reject the teaching of your [note]1[/note]mother;</text>
        <note num="1">Revering God and honoring one's parents are mentioned together in Proverbs ([link]vv. 7-9[/link]). In the Ten Commandments the fifth, concerning honoring one's parents, is ranked with the first four, concerning God (see note [link]12[sup]1[/sup] in Exo. 20[/link]). To honor one's parents is nearly equal to revering God. If we revere God, we will honor our parents. See [link]Eph. 6:2[/link] and notes.</note>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 4:1; 6:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>For they will be a wreath of grace for your head / And ornaments for your neck.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>My son, if sinners entice you, / Do not consent.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>If they say, Come with us; let us lie in wait for blood; / Let us ambush the innocent without cause;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Let us swallow them alive like [note]1[/note]Sheol, / And whole, like those who go down into the pit.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]23[sup]1[/sup] in Matt. 11[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>We will find all [i]manner[/i] of precious goods; / We will fill our houses with booty;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Throw in your lot with us; / We will all have one purse &amp;#8212;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>My son, do not walk with them on [i]this[/i] way; / Keep your foot from their path.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>For their [xref]a[/xref]feet run toward evil, / And they hasten to shed blood.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 59:7; Rom. 3:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>For in vain is the net spread / In the eyes of any bird;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Yet they lie in wait for their own blood; / They ambush their own lives!</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Such are the ways of everyone greedy for gain; / It takes away the life of its owners.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Wisdom [xref]a[/xref]cries out in the street; / [note]2[/note]She utters her voice in the open squares.</text>
        <note num="1">Man's need of wisdom to live a proper human life is one of the main principles in Proverbs. See note [link]7[sup]1[/sup][/link], par. 1.</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]12[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 8[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">vv. 20-21: Prov. 8:1-4; cf. John 7:37</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>At the head of the tumultuous [i]street[/i] she cries; / At the entrance of the gates in the city she utters her sayings:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>How long, O simple ones, will you love simpleness, / And will scoffers delight themselves in scoffing, / And will fools hate knowledge?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Turn yourselves at my reproof &amp;#8212; / Immediately I will [xref]a[/xref]pour out my spirit on you; / I will make my words known to you.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 44:3; Joel 2:28; Zech. 12:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>Because I [xref]a[/xref]called and you refused; / I stretched out my hand and no one heeded,</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 65:12; Jer. 7:13; cf. Matt. 11:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>And you neglected all my counsel / And would have none of my reproof;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>I also will laugh at your calamity; / I will mock when what you dread comes,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>When what you dread comes like a storm, / And your calamity comes like a whirlwind, / When distress and anguish come upon you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>Then they will call on me, but I will not answer; / They will seek me diligently, but they will not find me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>Because they hated knowledge / And did not choose the fear of Jehovah,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>[i]And[/i] would have none of my counsel / And despised all my reproof;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>They shall eat of the fruit of their own way / And be filled with their own devices.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>For the turning away of the simple will kill them, / And the prosperity of the foolish will cause them to perish;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>But he who listens to me will dwell securely / And will live at ease, without the dread of evil.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]My son, if you receive my words / And treasure up my commandments within you,</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 7:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Making your ear attentive to wisdom / And inclining your heart to understanding;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Indeed, if you cry out for discernment / And lift up your voice for understanding;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>If you seek her like silver / And search for her like hidden treasures,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Then you will understand the fear of Jehovah / And find the knowledge of God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>For Jehovah [xref]a[/xref]gives wisdom; / From His mouth [i]come[/i] knowledge and understanding;</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 3:9, 12; James 1:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>He stores up sound wisdom for the upright; / [i]He is[/i] a shield to those who walk in integrity,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Guarding the paths of justice / And keeping the way of His faithful ones.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Then you will understand righteousness and justice / And equity, [i]indeed,[/i] every good path.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>For wisdom will enter your heart, / And knowledge will be pleasant to your soul;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Discretion will watch over you; / Understanding will keep you:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>To deliver you from the way of evil, / From the man who speaks perverse things,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>[i]From those[/i] who forsake the paths of uprightness / To walk in the ways of darkness,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Who rejoice in doing evil / [i]And[/i] delight in the perverseness of evil,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Whose paths are crooked, / And who are devious in their ways;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>To deliver you from the strange woman, / From the adulteress who flatters with her words,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Who forsakes the companion of her youth / And forgets the covenant of her God;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>For her house sinks down to death, / And her paths [i]lead[/i] to the dead;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>None who go to her [i]ever[/i] return, / Nor do they attain to the [xref]a[/xref]paths of life;</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 16:11; Prov. 5:6; 10:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>That you may walk in the way of good men / And keep the paths of the righteous;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>For the upright will dwell in the [xref]a[/xref]land, / And the perfect will remain in it;</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 37:9, 11, 22, 29, 34</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>But the wicked will be cut off from the land, / And the treacherous will be uprooted from it.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>My son, do not forget my instruction, / But let your heart keep my commandments;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>For length of days and years of life / And peace will they add to you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Do not let lovingkindness and truth forsake you: / Bind them around your neck; / Write them upon the [xref]a[/xref]tablet of your heart.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 7:3; 6:21; Jer. 17:1; 2 Cor. 3:3; cf. Deut. 6:8; 11:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Thus you will find [note]1[/note]favor and [note]2[/note][i]a reputation for[/i] fine understanding / In the sight of God and man.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, grace.</note>
        <note num="2">The Septuagint translates, exercise foresight for what is honorable (cf. [link]Rom. 12:17[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 8:21[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, / And do not rely on your own understanding;</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 37:3-5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>In all your ways acknowledge Him, / And He will make your paths straight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Do not be [xref]a[/xref]wise in your own eyes; / Fear Jehovah, and depart from evil.</text>
        <xref num="a">Rom. 12:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>It will be healing to your body / And refreshment to your bones.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Honor Jehovah with your substance / And with the [xref]a[/xref]firstfruits of all your produce;</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 23:19; Deut. 26:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Then your [xref]a[/xref]barns will be filled with plenty, / And your vats will burst open with new wine.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 28:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>My son, do not despise the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]chastening of Jehovah, / Nor be weary of His discipline;</text>
        <note num="1">Or, instruction, as in [link]v. 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Job 5:17; Psa. 94:12; Heb. 12:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]For whom Jehovah loves He disciplines, / Even as a father, the son in whom he delights.</text>
        <xref num="a">Heb. 12:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Blessed is the man who finds wisdom, / And the man who gains understanding.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, Happy.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>For her profit is better than the profit of silver, / And her income is better than gold.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]She is more precious than corals, / And nothing you desire compares with her.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 8:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Length of days is in her right hand; / In her left hand are riches and honor.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Her ways are ways of pleasantness, / And all her paths are peace.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>She is a [xref]a[/xref]tree of life to those who lay hold of her, / And happy are those who hold her fast.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 2:9; 3:22; Prov. 11:30; 13:12; 15:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Jehovah by [note]1[/note]wisdom founded the [xref]a[/xref]earth; / He established the heavens by understanding;</text>
        <note num="1">This One by whom Jehovah founded the earth and established the heavens is Christ, who is the wisdom of God ([link]1 Cor. 1:24[/link]). See note [link]12[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 8[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 104:24; 136:5; Prov. 8:27-29; Jer. 10:12; cf. John 1:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>By His knowledge the [xref]a[/xref]depths were broken open / And the skies drop down the [xref]b[/xref]dew.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 7:11</xref>
        <xref num="b">Deut. 33:28</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>My son, do not let these depart from your sight: / Keep sound wisdom and discretion;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>And they will be life for your soul / And a graceful ornament for your neck.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Then you will walk on your way securely, / And your foot will not stumble.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>When you lie down, you will not be afraid; / But you will lie down, and your sleep will be sweet.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Do not [xref]a[/xref]be afraid of sudden fear, / Nor of the destruction of the wicked when it comes;</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Pet. 3:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>For Jehovah will be your confidence, / And He will keep your foot from being caught.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>Do not withhold good from those [xref]a[/xref]to whom it is due, / When it is in the power of your hand to do [i]so.[/i]</text>
        <xref num="a">Rom. 13:7; Gal. 6:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>Do not say to your neighbor, Go, and come back; / And tomorrow I will give [i]it[/i] &amp;#8212; when you have [i]it[/i] with you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>Do not devise harm against your neighbor, / While he lives securely beside you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>Do not strive with a man without cause, / If he has done you no harm.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>Do not envy a man of violence, / And do not choose any of his ways;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>For the perverse man is an abomination to Jehovah, / But His intimate counsel is with the upright.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>The curse of Jehovah is in the house of the wicked man, / But He blesses the dwelling place of the righteous.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>To scorners He is scornful, / But to the [xref]a[/xref]humble He gives grace.</text>
        <xref num="a">James 4:6; 1 Pet. 5:5; cf. Luke 1:52</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>The wise will inherit [note]1[/note]honor, / [note]2[/note]But fools increase [i]their own[/i] disgrace.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, glory.</note>
        <note num="2">The Hebrew text is obscure. Another rendering may be, But shame will be the promotion of fools.</note>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Hear, [i]my[/i] sons, the instruction of a father, / And be attentive, that you may gain understanding;</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 1:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>For I give you good teaching; / Do not forsake my instruction.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>For I was a son to my father, / [xref]a[/xref]Tender and the only [i]beloved[/i] in the sight of my mother.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Chron. 29:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And he taught me and said to me, / Let your heart hold fast to my words; / Keep my commandments and live;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Get [xref]a[/xref]wisdom; get understanding; / Do not forget nor turn away from the words of my mouth.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 2:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Do not forsake her, and she will keep you; / Love her, and she will guard you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>The beginning of wisdom [i]is this:[/i] / Get wisdom; and in all your getting, get understanding.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Prize her highly, and she will exalt you; / She will honor you if you embrace her.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>She will give a garland of grace for your head; / A crown of beauty will she bestow on you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Hear, my son, and receive my words, / And the years of your life will be many.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>I have taught you in the way of wisdom; / I have led you in the paths of uprightness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>When you walk, your steps will not be hindered; / And when you run, you will not stumble.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Take hold of instruction; do not let go; / Guard her, for she is your life.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Do not enter the path of the wicked, / And do not walk in the way of the evil.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Avoid it; do not pass by it; / Turn away from it and pass on by.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>For they cannot sleep unless they do evil; / And they are robbed of their sleep unless they cause [i]someone[/i] to stumble.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>For they eat the bread of wickedness / And drink the wine of violence.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>But the path of the righteous is like the [xref]a[/xref]light of [note]1[/note]dawn, / Which shines brighter and brighter until the full day.</text>
        <note num="1">The light of dawn, the sunrise, signifies Christ in His coming ([link]Luke 1:78[/link]; [link]2 Pet. 1:19[/link]). This figure may also signify our being revived every morning. The Christian life is like the dawning of the sun ([link]Judg. 5:31[/link]; [link]Matt. 13:43[/link]). As Christians we should follow the sun to be revived and to have a new beginning every morning. Then we should continue to rise and shine brighter and brighter until the full day.</note>
        <xref num="a">Judg. 5:31; 2 Sam. 23:4; Dan. 12:3; Matt. 13:43</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>The way of the wicked is like deep darkness; / They do not know what they [xref]a[/xref]stumble over.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 John 2:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]My son, be attentive to my words; / Incline your ear to my sayings.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 5:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Do not let them depart from your sight; / Keep them in the midst of your heart.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>For they are life to those who find them, / And [xref]a[/xref]healing to all their flesh.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 12:18; 13:17; 16:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Keep your heart with all vigilance, / For [xref]b[/xref]from it are the issues of life.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Deut. 4:9; Phil. 4:7; 1 Thes. 3:13</xref>
        <xref num="b">Matt. 12:35; cf. Matt. 15:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>Put away from you crooked speech, / And put perverse talk far from you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Let your eyes look directly ahead, / And let your gaze be straight in front of you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>Make straight the path of your feet, / And all your ways will be established.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>Do not turn to the right or to the left; / Turn your foot away from evil.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="5">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]My son, be attentive to my wisdom; / Incline your ear to my understanding,</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 4:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>That you may keep discretion, / And your lips may guard knowledge.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>For the lips of a [note]1[/note]strange woman drip honey, / And her mouth is smoother than oil;</text>
        <note num="1">The charge in [link]vv. 1-20[/link] is to hold marriage in honor ([link]Heb. 13:4[/link] and note 1). In holding marriage in honor, the man's faithfulness is the base, and the woman's virtues are the building up ([link]12:4a[/link]; [link]14:1a[/link]; [link]31:10-31[/link]). This is one of the principles in Proverbs for man to live a proper human life (see note [link]7[sup]1[/sup], par. 1, in ch. 1[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>But in the end she is bitter as wormwood, / Sharp as a [xref]a[/xref]two-edged sword.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Heb. 4:12; Rev. 1:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Her feet go down to death; / Her steps hold fast to Sheol.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>She does not make straight the path of life: / Her ways wander, [i]and[/i] she does not know [i]it.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]And now, [i]my[/i] sons, listen to me, / And do not depart from the words of my mouth.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 7:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Keep your way far from her, / And do not go near the door of her house;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Lest you give your honor to others, / And your years to the cruel;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Lest strangers be filled with your wealth, / And your labors [i]go[/i] to the house of a foreigner,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And you mourn at your end, / When your flesh and your body are consumed,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And you say, How I have hated instruction, / And my heart has despised reproof!</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And I have not listened to the voice of my teachers / Nor inclined my ear to my instructors;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>I was almost into every evil / In the midst of the congregation and assembly.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Drink waters out of your own cistern, / And running water out of your own well.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Should your springs be shed forth, / [i]Like[/i] streams of water in the streets?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Let them be yours alone, / And not for strangers with you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Let your fountain be blessed, / And rejoice in the [xref]a[/xref]wife of your youth,</text>
        <xref num="a">Mal. 2:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>A lovely [xref]a[/xref]hind and a graceful doe. / Let her breasts satisfy you at all times. / May you be ravished with her love always.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 49:21; 2 Sam. 22:34; S.S. 2:7; 3:5; Hab. 3:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>For why should you be ravished, my son, with a strange woman / And embrace the bosom of an adulteress?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>For the ways of a man are before the [xref]a[/xref]eyes of Jehovah, / And He ponders all his paths.</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 16:17; Heb. 4:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>The wicked man is taken by his own iniquities, / And he is held fast by the cords of his own sin.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>He will die for lack of instruction, / And in the greatness of his folly he will go astray.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="6">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>My son, if you have become a surety for your neighbor, / If you have given your hands as a pledge for a stranger,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>You are snared by the words of your mouth; / You are caught by the words of your mouth.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Do this now, my son, and deliver yourself, / Since you have come into the hand of your neighbor: / Go, humble yourself, and plead with your neighbor.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Do not give [xref]a[/xref]sleep to your eyes, / Nor slumber to your eyelids.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 132:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Deliver yourself like a gazelle from the [i]hunter's[/i] hand / And like a bird from the fowler's hand.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Go to the [xref]a[/xref]ant, you sluggard; / Consider its ways, and be wise,</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 30:25</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Which, having no chief, / Officer, or ruler,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Prepares its food in summer / [i]And[/i] gathers its sustenance in the harvest.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>How long, sluggard, will you lie [i]there?[/i] / When will you arise from your sleep?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]A little sleep, a little slumber, / A little folding of the hands to rest,</text>
        <xref num="a">vv. 10-11: Prov. 24:33-34</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And your poverty will come [i]upon you[/i] like a robber, / And your want, like an armed man.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>A worthless man, a wicked man, / Goes around with a perverse mouth,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Winking with his eyes, signaling with his feet, / Pointing with his fingers;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>With perverseness in his [xref]a[/xref]heart, he is devising evil continually; / He injects discord.</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 15:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Therefore his calamity will come suddenly; / In a moment he will be broken, and there will be no remedy.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>There are six things that Jehovah hates; / Indeed, seven that are an abomination to His soul:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Haughty eyes, a lying tongue, / And hands that shed innocent blood,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>A heart that devises wicked schemes, / [xref]a[/xref]Feet that hurry to run to evil,</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 59:7; Rom. 3:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>A false witness who utters lies, / And one who injects [xref]a[/xref]discord among brothers.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 6:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]My son, keep the commandment of your father, / And do not reject the teaching of your mother;</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 1:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Bind them continually on your heart; / Tie them around your neck.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 3:3; 7:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>When you [xref]a[/xref]walk about, it will guide you, / When you lie down, it will watch over you; / And when you awake, it will talk with you.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 3:23-24; cf. Deut. 6:6-8; 11:18-20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>For the commandment is a [xref]a[/xref]lamp, and the teaching a light, / And the reproofs of instruction are the way of life,</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 19:8; 119:105</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>To keep you from the evil woman, / From the smooth tongue of the adulteress.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Do not desire her beauty in your heart, / Nor let her catch you with her eyelids;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>For the price of a harlot is [i]a loaf of[/i] bread, / But the wife of [i]another[/i] man hunts for the precious soul.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>Can a man take fire in his bosom / And his clothes not be burned?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>Can a man walk on hot coals / And his feet not be scorched?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>So [i]it is with[/i] him who goes in to his neighbor's wife; / No one who touches her will be unpunished.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>The thief is not despised if he steals / To satisfy himself when he is hungry;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>But if he is found out, he shall restore sevenfold; / He must give over all the substance of his house.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>He who commits [xref]a[/xref]adultery with a woman lacks sense; / He who does it destroys his own soul.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Cor. 6:18; Heb. 13:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>He will find wounds and dishonor, / And his reproach will not be wiped away.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>For jealousy is the rage of a man, / And he will not spare in the day of vengeance.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>He will not regard any ransom, / Nor will he be content if you give [i]him[/i] great gifts.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="7">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]My son, keep my words, / And treasure up my commandments within you.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 2:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Keep my commandments, and live; / And my teaching, like the apple of your eye.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Bind them on your fingers; / Write them on the [xref]a[/xref]tablet of your heart.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 3:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Say to wisdom, You are my sister, / And call understanding your close friend,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>That they may keep you from the strange woman, / From the adulteress who flatters with her words.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>For at the window of my house / I looked out through my lattice,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And I saw among the simple ones, / I discerned among the youths, / A young man lacking sense,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Passing along the street near her corner; / And he takes the way to her house,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>In the twilight, in the evening of the day, / In the deep of night and darkness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And there [i]comes[/i] a woman to meet him, / Dressed as a harlot and cunning of heart.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>She is rowdy and defiant; / Her feet do not stay at home &amp;#8212;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Now in the street, now in the squares, / And at every corner she lies in wait.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And she grabs him and kisses him; / And with an impudent face she says to him,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>I had to make offerings; / Today I have paid my vows.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Therefore I have come out to meet you, / To earnestly seek your presence; and I have found you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>I have decked my couch with coverings, / Colored spreads of the linen of Egypt;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>I have sprinkled my bed with myrrh, / Aloes, and cinnamon.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Come, let us drink our fill of love until the morning; / Let us delight ourselves with love.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>For my husband is not at home; / He has gone on a long journey.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>He has taken the money bag with him; / He will come home at the full moon.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>With her great persuasiveness she beguiles him; / With her smooth talk she compels him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>He goes after her immediately, / As an ox goes to the slaughter, / Or as [i]someone in[/i] fetters, to the correction of the fool,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Until an arrow pierces through his liver. / As a bird hastens to the snare, / So he does not know that this [i]will cost him[/i] his life.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]And now, [i]my[/i] sons, listen to me, / And pay attention to the words of my mouth.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 5:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Do not let your heart turn aside to her ways; / Do not stray into her paths.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>For many are those whom she has brought down wounded, / And numerous are all who have been slain by her.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>Her house is the way to Sheol, / Going down to the chambers of death.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="8">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Does not wisdom [xref]a[/xref]call, / And understanding lift up her voice?</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 1:20; 9:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>On the top of the heights, by the way, / Where the paths meet, she takes her stand;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Beside the gates, at the entry of the city, / At the entrance of the doors, she cries aloud:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>To you, O men, I call; / And my voice is to the sons of men.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>O simple ones, understand prudence; / And, O fools, be of an understanding heart.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Hear, for I will speak noble things; / And the opening of my lips [i]will yield[/i] right things.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>For my mouth will utter truth, / And wickedness is an abomination to my lips.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>All the [xref]a[/xref]words of my mouth are in righteousness; / There is nothing twisted or crooked in them.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 12:6; Isa. 45:23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>They are all straight to him who understands, / And right to those who find knowledge.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Receive my instruction, and not silver; / And knowledge rather than choice gold.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]For wisdom is better than corals, / And nothing that you desire compares with her.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 3:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>[note]1[/note]I, wisdom, dwell with prudence, / And I find knowledge [i]and[/i] discretion.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, I, wisdom, make prudence my dwelling. In certain portions of this book the wisdom of God is personified ([link]1:20[/link]; [link]3:19[/link]; [link]4:5-9[/link]; [link]7:4[/link]; [link]8:1-36[/link]; [link]9:1-11[/link]). This personification of God's wisdom is a reference to the second of the Divine Trinity, Christ, the Son of God ([link]1 Cor. 1:24[/link]; [link]Col. 2:3[/link]; [link]Matt. 11:19[/link] and note 3), who became wisdom from God to all the New Testament believers ([link]1 Cor. 1:30[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>The fear of Jehovah is to hate evil; / Pride and arrogance and the evil way / And the perverse mouth, I hate.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Counsel is mine and sound wisdom; / I am understanding; I have might.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>By me kings [xref]a[/xref]reign, / And rulers decree justice.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Dan. 2:21; Rom. 13:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>By me princes rule, / And nobles &amp;#8212; all who judge righteously.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>I love those who love me, / And those who [xref]a[/xref]seek me diligently will find me.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Chron. 28:9; 2 Chron. 15:2; Jer. 29:13; Matt. 7:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Riches and honor are with me, / Enduring wealth and righteousness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>My fruit is better than gold, even fine gold; / And my yield than choice silver.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>I walk in the [xref]a[/xref]way of righteousness, / In the midst of the paths of justice,</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 23:3; Matt. 21:32</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>That I may cause those who love me to inherit substance / And that I may fill their treasuries.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Jehovah possessed me in the [xref]a[/xref]beginning of His way, / Before His works of old.</text>
        <xref num="a">John 1:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>I was set up from eternity, / From the beginning, before the earth was.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>When there were no depths, I was [xref]a[/xref]brought forth, / When there were no fountains abounding with water.</text>
        <xref num="a">John 1:14, 18; 3:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Before the mountains were settled, / Before the hills, I was brought forth;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>When He had not yet made the earth and the fields, / Nor the first dust of the world.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>When He [xref]a[/xref]established the heavens, I was there; / When He inscribed a [xref]b[/xref]circle upon the surface of the deep,</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 33:6; 136:5; Jer. 10:12; Col. 1:16; Heb. 1:2</xref>
        <xref num="b">Isa. 40:22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>When He made [xref]a[/xref]firm the skies above, / When the fountains of the deep became strong,</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 1:6-7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>When He set for the sea its [xref]a[/xref]boundary, / That the waters should not transgress His commandment, / When He marked out the foundations of the earth;</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 1:9-10; Job 38:8-11; Psa. 104:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>Then I was by Him, [i]as a[/i] master workman; / And I was daily [i]His[/i] [xref]a[/xref]delight, / Rejoicing always before Him,</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 3:17; Col. 1:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>Rejoicing in His habitable earth; / And my delight was in the sons of men.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>Now therefore, [i]my[/i] sons, listen to me; / For blessed are they who keep my ways.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>Hear instruction, and be wise; / And do not neglect it.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>Blessed is the man who listens to me, / Watching daily at my doors, / Waiting at my doorposts.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>For whoever finds me finds [xref]a[/xref]life, / And will obtain favor from Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 21:21; John 3:36</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
        <text>But he who sins against me wrongs his own soul; / All who hate me love death.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="9">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Wisdom has built her house; / She has hewn out her seven pillars;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>She has slaughtered her beasts; / She has mingled her wine; / She has also set her table;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>She has sent forth her maidens; / She calls from the highest places of the city:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Whoever is simple, let him turn in here; / As for him who lacks sense, she says to him,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Come, eat of my bread, / And drink of the [xref]a[/xref]wine which I have mingled.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 9:2; S.S. 5:1; Isa. 55:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Forsake foolishness, and live, / And walk in the way of understanding.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>He who corrects a scorner gets dishonor for himself, / And he who reproves a wicked man blemishes himself.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Do not reprove a scorner, lest he hate you; / Reprove a wise man, and he will love you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Impart [i]something[/i] to a wise man, and he will become wiser still; / Teach a righteous man, and he will increase in learning.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]The fear of Jehovah is the beginning of wisdom, / And the knowledge of the Holy One is understanding.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 111:10; cf. Job 28:28; Prov. 1:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>For by me your days will be multiplied, / And the years of your life will be increased.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>If you are wise, you are wise for yourself; / And if you are scornful, you alone will bear it.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>The woman Foolishness is rowdy; / [i]She is[/i] simple and knows nothing.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And she sits at the door of her house, / On a seat in the heights of the city,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>To call to those who pass by, / Who go straight on their ways:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Whoever is simple, let him turn in here; / And as for him who lacks sense, she says to him,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Stolen waters are sweet, / And bread [i]gotten[/i] in secret is pleasant.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>But he does not know that the dead are there, / That her guests are in the depths of Sheol.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="10">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>The proverbs of Solomon.[br/][xref]a[/xref]A wise son makes a father glad, / But a foolish son is a grief to his mother.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 15:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Treasures of wickedness profit nothing, / But righteousness delivers from death.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 49:6; Prov. 11:4; Luke 12:19-20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Jehovah will not allow the soul of the righteous man to go hungry, / But He thrusts away the desire of the wicked.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>A slack hand causes poverty, / But the hand of the diligent makes rich.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>He who gathers in summer is a prudent son, / [i]But[/i] he who sleeps at harvest [i]time[/i] is a son who brings shame.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Blessings are upon the head of the righteous man, / [note]1[/note]But the mouth of the wicked conceals violence.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, But violence conceals the mouth of the wicked. So also in [link]v. 11[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>The memory of the righteous man is blessed, / But the name of the wicked will rot.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>The wise in heart will receive commandments, / But the foolish in speech will be cast down.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>He who walks in integrity walks securely, / But he who perverts his ways will be known.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>He who winks with the eye causes grief, / And the foolish in speech will be cast down.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>The mouth of the righteous man is a fountain of life, / But the mouth of the wicked conceals violence.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Hatred stirs up strife, / But love [xref]a[/xref]covers all transgressions.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 17:9; 1 Cor. 13:4, 7; 1 Pet. 4:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>In the lips of one who has understanding wisdom is found, / But a rod is for the back of him who lacks sense.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Wise men treasure up knowledge, / But the mouth of a fool is imminent destruction.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]The rich man's substance is his strong city; / The ruin of the poor is their poverty.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 18:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>The wages of the righteous man [i]lead[/i] to life; / The income of the wicked man, to sin.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>He who heeds instruction is on the path of life, / But he who forsakes reproof goes astray.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>He who conceals hatred has lying lips, / And he who utters slander is a fool.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>When there are many words transgression does not cease, / But he who [xref]a[/xref]restrains his lips is prudent.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 17:27-28; James 1:19; 3:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>The tongue of the righteous man is [i]like[/i] choice silver; / The heart of the wicked is [i]worth[/i] little.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>The lips of the righteous man feed many, / But fools die for lack of sense.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>It is the blessing of Jehovah that makes rich, / And He adds no sorrow with it.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Carrying out a wicked scheme is like sport to a fool, / But [i]so is[/i] wisdom to a man of understanding.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>The fear of the wicked man will come upon him, / And the desire of the righteous will be granted.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>When the whirlwind passes, the wicked man is no more; / But the righteous man is an everlasting foundation.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>Like vinegar to the teeth and like smoke to the eyes, / So is the sluggard to those who send him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>The fear of Jehovah prolongs days, / But the years of the wicked will be shortened.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>The hope of the righteous is joy, / But the expectation of the wicked will perish.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>The way of Jehovah is a stronghold to the upright, / But it is ruin to the workers of iniquity.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>The righteous man will never be moved, / But the wicked will not dwell in the land.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>The mouth of the righteous man brings forth wisdom, / But the perverse tongue will be cut off.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>The lips of the righteous man know what is acceptable, / But the mouth of the wicked is perverse.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="11">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>A false [xref]a[/xref]balance is an abomination to Jehovah, / But a full weight is His delight.</text>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 19:35-36; Deut. 25:13-16; Prov. 20:10, 23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>When pride comes, then comes dishonor; / But wisdom is with the humble.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>The integrity of the upright will guide them, / But the perverseness of the treacherous will destroy them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Riches do not profit in the day of wrath, / But righteousness delivers from death.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 10:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>The righteousness of the perfect man will make his way straight, / But the wicked man will fall by his own wickedness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>The righteousness of the upright will deliver them, / But the treacherous will be taken in their own craving.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>When a wicked man dies, [i]his[/i] expectation will perish; / And the hope of the strong perishes.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>The righteous man is delivered out of trouble, / And the wicked man comes [i]into it[/i] instead of him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>With his mouth the profane man destroys his neighbor, / But through knowledge the righteous will be delivered.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>When it goes well with the righteous, the city exults; / And when the wicked perish, there is a ringing shout.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>By the blessing of the upright the city is exalted, / But it is torn down by the mouth of the wicked.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>He who despises his neighbor lacks sense, / But a man of understanding keeps silent.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]He who goes about as a gossip reveals secrets, / But he who is of a faithful spirit conceals a matter.</text>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 19:16; Prov. 20:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Where no sound counsel is, the people fall; / But in the [xref]a[/xref]multitude of counselors there is safety.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 15:22; 24:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>He who is surety for a stranger will surely be troubled, / But he who hates giving pledges is secure.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>A gracious woman lays hold of honor, / And violent men lay hold of riches.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>The [xref]a[/xref]merciful man rewards his own soul, / But the cruel troubles his own flesh.</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 5:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>The wicked man earns deceitful wages, / But he who [xref]a[/xref]sows righteousness [i]gets[/i] a true reward.</text>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 10:12; Gal. 6:8-9; James 3:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>He who is steadfast in righteousness [i]shall attain[/i] to life, / And he who pursues evil [i]advances[/i] to his own death.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Those who are perverse in heart are an abomination to Jehovah, / But those who are perfect in [i]their[/i] way are His delight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Be assured: The evil man will not go unpunished; / But the seed of the righteous will be delivered.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., Hand to hand; a Hebrew idiom indicating great certainty.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>[i]Like[/i] a nose-ring of gold in a pig's snout, / [i]So is[/i] a beautiful woman who is without discretion.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>The desire of the righteous is only good, / [i]But[/i] the expectation of the wicked is wrath.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>There is one who [xref]a[/xref]scatters and increases yet more, / And there is one who withholds what is appropriate [i]but ends up[/i] only in want.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 112:9; 2 Cor. 9:6-10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>The [xref]a[/xref]blessing soul will prosper, / And he who waters will also be watered himself.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Cor. 9:6-10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>As for him who withholds grain, the people will curse him; / But blessing will be upon the head of him who sells [i]it.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>He who diligently seeks good seeks favor; / But as for him who searches after evil, it will come to him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>He who [xref]a[/xref]trusts in his riches will fall, / But the righteous will flourish like the green leaf.</text>
        <xref num="a">Job 31:24; Psa. 52:7; Mark 10:24; 1 Tim. 6:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>He who troubles his own house will inherit the wind, / And a fool will be servant to the wise in heart.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>The fruit of the righteous man is a tree of life, / And he who is wise wins [xref]a[/xref]souls.</text>
        <xref num="a">Dan. 12:3; James 5:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>If the righteous man will be [xref]a[/xref]recompensed on the earth, / How much more the wicked man and the sinner!</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 25:29; 1 Pet. 4:17-18</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="12">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Whoever loves correction loves knowledge, / But he who hates reproof is stupid.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>A good man will obtain the favor of Jehovah, / But a man of [i]wicked[/i] devices He will condemn.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>A man will not be established by wickedness, / But the root of the righteous will not be moved.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>A [xref]a[/xref]worthy woman is the [xref]b[/xref]crown of her husband, / But she who brings shame is like rottenness in his bones.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 31:10</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. 1 Cor. 11:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>The thoughts of the righteous are just, / [i]But[/i] the counsels of the wicked are deceitful.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>The words of the wicked lie in wait for blood, / But the mouth of the upright will deliver them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>The wicked are overthrown and are no more, / But the house of the righteous will stand.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>A man will be praised according to his prudence, / But he who is of a perverse heart will be despised.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Better is he who is lightly esteemed and has a servant, / Than he who honors himself and lacks bread.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>A righteous man regards the life of his beast, / But the inward parts of the wicked are cruel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]He who tills his land will have plenty of bread, / But he who pursues worthless [i]things[/i] lacks sense.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 3:19; Prov. 28:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>The wicked man desires the catch of evil men, / But the root of the righteous yields [i]fruit.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>In the transgression of the lips there is a snare for the evil man, / But the righteous man will come out of trouble.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>A man will be satisfied with good by the fruit of his mouth, / And the result of man's deeds will be rendered to him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>The way of a fool is right in his [xref]a[/xref]own eyes, / But a wise man listens to counsel.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 3:7; 21:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>A fool's anger is known [note]1[/note]at once, / But a prudent man conceals shame.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., today.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>He who utters truth tells forth righteousness; / But a false witness, deceit.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>There is one who speaks rashly like the piercings of a sword, / But the tongue of the wise brings healing.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>The lip of truth shall be established forever, / But a lying tongue is only for a moment.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Deceit is in the heart of those who devise evil, / But counselors of peace have joy.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>No harm will happen to the righteous man, / But the wicked are filled with trouble.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Lying lips are an abomination to Jehovah, / But those who deal faithfully are His delight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>A prudent man conceals knowledge, / But the heart of fools proclaims folly.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>The hand of the diligent will rule, / But the slothful will be under forced labor.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Anxiety in the heart of a man weighs it down, / But a good [xref]b[/xref]word brings it joy.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Pet. 5:7</xref>
        <xref num="b">Isa. 50:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>The righteous man is a guide to his neighbor, / But the way of the wicked leads them astray.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>The slothful man does not roast his game, / But the precious substance of men [i]is to[/i] the diligent.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>In the way of righteousness is life, / And in [i]its[/i] pathway there is no death.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="13">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>A wise son [note]1[/note][i]hears[/i] his father's instruction, / But a scorner does not listen to rebuke.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, [i]accepts[/i] his father's correction.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>A man will eat good from the fruit of his mouth, / But the desire of the treacherous is violence.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>He who guards his [xref]a[/xref]mouth keeps his soul, / [i]But[/i] he who opens wide his lips will have destruction.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 39:1; Prov. 21:23; James 3:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>The soul of the sluggard desires and has nothing, / But the soul of the diligent will be made fat.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>A righteous man hates what is false, / But a wicked man is odious and is confounded.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Righteousness guards him who is blameless in the way, / But wickedness overthrows the sinner.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>There is one who pretends to be rich yet has nothing; / There is one who pretends to be poor yet has great [xref]a[/xref]wealth.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 2 Cor. 6:10; 8:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>The ransom of a man's life is his riches, / But the poor hears no threatening.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>The light of the righteous rejoices, / But the lamp of the wicked goes out.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Through pride comes nothing but strife, / But wisdom is with those who receive counsel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Wealth [i]obtained[/i] by vanity will be diminished, / But he who gathers by labor increases [i]it.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Hope deferred makes the heart sick, / But when what is desired comes, it is a tree of life.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Whoever despises the word brings destruction on himself, / But he who fears the commandment will be rewarded.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>The teaching of the wise is a [xref]a[/xref]fountain of life, / To turn [i]one[/i] aside from the snares of death.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 36:9; Prov. 10:11; 14:27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Good understanding gives favor, / But the way of the treacherous is hard.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Every prudent man works with knowledge, / But a fool displays [i]his[/i] folly.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>A wicked messenger falls into evil, / But a faithful envoy [i]brings[/i] healing.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Poverty and shame [i]will come to[/i] him who refuses correction, / But he who regards reproof will be honored.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>A desire accomplished is sweet to the soul, / But it is an abomination to fools to depart from evil.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>He who walks with wise men will be wise, / But the [xref]a[/xref]companion of fools will be troubled.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Cor. 15:33</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Evil pursues sinners, / But good recompenses the righteous.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>A good man leaves an inheritance to his children's children, / But the wealth of the sinner is stored up for the righteous man.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>The fallow ground of the poor [i]yields[/i] much food, / But it is destroyed through injustice.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>He who spares his rod hates his son, / But he who loves him [xref]a[/xref]chastens him early.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 3:12; 19:18; Heb. 12:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>The righteous man eats to the satisfying of his soul, / But the belly of the wicked will lack.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="14">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>The wise woman builds her house, / But the foolish one tears it down with her own hands.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>He who walks in his uprightness fears Jehovah, / But he who is perverse in his ways despises Him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>In the mouth of a fool is a rod for [i]his[/i] pride, / But the lips of the wise will preserve them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Where no oxen are, the manger is clean, / But much increase [i]comes[/i] by the strength of the ox.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>A faithful witness will not lie, / But a false witness utters lies.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>A scoffer seeks wisdom and [i]finds[/i] none, / But knowledge comes easily to one who has understanding.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Go from the presence of a foolish man, / For you will not perceive [i]in him[/i] the lips of knowledge.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>The wisdom of the prudent man is to understand his way, / But the folly of fools is deceit.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>[note]1[/note]A trespass offering mocks fools, / But among the upright there is good will.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, Guilt.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>The heart knows its own bitterness, / And a stranger does not share in its joy.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>The house of the wicked will be destroyed, / But the tent of the upright will flourish.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]There is a way which seems right to a man, / But the end of it is the ways of death.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 16:25; cf. Prov. 21:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Even in [xref]a[/xref]laughter the heart is sorrowful, / And the end of joy is grief.</text>
        <xref num="a">Luke 6:25</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>The backslider in heart will be filled with his own ways, / And a good man [i]will be satisfied[/i] from himself.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>The simple man believes every word, / But the prudent man considers his steps.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>A wise man fears and departs from evil, / But the fool is arrogant and is confident.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>He who is quick to [xref]a[/xref]anger will deal foolishly, / And a man of [i]wicked[/i] devices is hated.</text>
        <xref num="a">James 1:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>The simple inherit folly, / But the prudent are crowned with knowledge.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>The evil bow down before the good, / And the wicked, at the gates of the righteous man.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>The poor man is hated even by his own neighbor, / But the [xref]a[/xref]rich man has many friends.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 19:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>He who despises his neighbor sins, / But happy is he who is gracious to the poor.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Do not they who devise evil go astray? / But lovingkindness and truth [i]are with[/i] those who devise good.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>In all labor there is profit, / But mere talk [i]leads[/i] only to poverty.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>The crown of the wise is their riches, / [i]But[/i] the folly of fools is [i]only[/i] folly.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>A truthful witness delivers souls, / But he who utters lies [i]causes[/i] deceit.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>In the fear of Jehovah is strong confidence, / And his children will have a place of refuge.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>The fear of Jehovah is a [xref]a[/xref]fountain of life, / That one may turn aside from the snares of death.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 13:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>In a multitude of people is the king's glory, / But in an absence of people is the ruin of the prince.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>He who is [xref]a[/xref]slow to anger is of great understanding, / But he who has a hasty spirit exalts folly.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 15:18; 16:32; James 1:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>A tranquil heart is life to the flesh, / But envy is rottenness to the bones.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>He who oppresses the poor reproaches his Maker, / But he who is gracious to the needy honors Him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>The wicked man is thrust down in his evildoing, / But the righteous man has a refuge when he dies.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>Wisdom rests [i]quietly[/i] in the heart of one who has understanding, / But in the inward part of fools it makes itself known.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>Righteousness exalts a nation, / But sin is a reproach to any people.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>The king's favor is toward a servant who acts prudently, / But his overflowing wrath will be toward him who causes shame.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="15">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>A [xref]a[/xref]soft answer turns away anger, / But a grievous word stirs up anger.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 15:4; 25:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>The tongue of the wise utters knowledge well, / But the mouth of fools pours out folly.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>The eyes of Jehovah are in every place, / Keeping watch on the evil and the good.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>A soothing tongue is a tree of life, / But perverseness in it is a breaking of the spirit.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>A fool despises his father's correction, / But he who regards reproof gets prudence.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>[i]In[/i] the house of the righteous man there is much treasure, / But in the income of the wicked there is trouble.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>The lips of the wise disperse knowledge, / But the heart of fools [i]does[/i] not [i]do[/i] so.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>The [xref]a[/xref]sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination to Jehovah, / But the prayer of the upright is His delight.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 21:27; Isa. 1:11; Jer. 6:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>The way of the wicked man is an abomination to Jehovah, / But He loves one who [xref]a[/xref]pursues righteousness.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 21:21; 1 Tim. 6:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>There is grievous correction for one who forsakes the way, / And he who hates reproof will die.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Sheol and [note]1[/note]Abaddon [i]lie open[/i] before Jehovah. / How much more the hearts of the children of men!</text>
        <note num="1">Meaning [i]destruction.[/i]</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>A scorner does not love him who reproves him; / He will not go to the wise.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>A [xref]a[/xref]joyful heart makes a cheerful countenance, / But by sorrow of heart the spirit is broken.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 17:22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>The heart of one who has understanding seeks knowledge, / But the mouth of fools feeds on folly.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>All the days of the afflicted are evil, / But he who is of a cheerful heart [i]has[/i] a continual feast.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Better is a little with the fear of Jehovah / Than great treasure and turmoil with it.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 37:16; Prov. 16:8; 1 Tim. 6:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Better is a dinner of vegetables where love is / Than a fattened ox and hatred with it.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>A wrathful man stirs up contention, / But he who is [xref]a[/xref]slow to anger quiets strife.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 14:29</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>The way of the sluggard is like a hedge of thorns, / But the path of the upright is paved.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]A wise son makes a father glad, / But a foolish man despises his mother.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 10:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Folly is joy to him who lacks sense, / But a man of understanding makes straight his going.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Where there is no counsel, plans are frustrated; / But in the multitude of counselors they are established.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>A man has joy in the apt answer of his mouth; / And a [xref]a[/xref]word in its season, how good it is!</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 25:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>To the wise man the way of life [i]leads[/i] upward, / That he may depart from Sheol below.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Jehovah will tear down the house of the proud, / But He will establish the territory of the widow.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>Evil plans are an abomination to Jehovah, / But pleasant words are pure.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>He who is greedy for [xref]a[/xref]gain troubles his own house, / But he who hates bribes will live.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 28:20; 1 Tim. 6:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>The heart of the righteous man ponders how to answer, / But the mouth of the wicked pours out evil things.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>Jehovah is far from the wicked, / But He hears the [xref]a[/xref]prayer of the righteous.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 145:18-19; James 5:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>The light of the eyes rejoices the heart, / [i]And[/i] good news makes the bones fat.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>The ear that listens to the reproof of life / Will lodge among the wise.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>He who ignores instruction despises his own soul, / But he who listens to reproof acquires understanding.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]The fear of Jehovah is the instruction of wisdom, / And humility [i]goes[/i] before honor.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 1:7</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="16">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>The plans of the heart belong to man, / But the answer of the tongue is from Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]All the ways of a man are clean in his own eyes, / But Jehovah weighs the spirits.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Prov. 21:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Commit your works to Jehovah, / And your purposes will be established.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 37:5; cf. Matt. 6:25; Luke 12:22; Phil. 4:6; 1 Pet. 5:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Jehovah has [xref]a[/xref]made everything for its own purpose, / Yes, even the wicked for the day of evil.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 43:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Every one who is proud in heart is an abomination to Jehovah; / [note]1[/note]Be assured: He will not be unpunished.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., Hand to hand; a Hebrew idiom indicating great certainty.</note>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 11:20-21; Luke 16:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>By [xref]a[/xref]lovingkindness and truth iniquity is expiated, / And by the fear of Jehovah men depart from evil.</text>
        <xref num="a">Zech. 7:9; Matt. 23:23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>When a man's ways please Jehovah, / He causes even his enemies to be at peace with him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Better is a little with righteousness, / Than great income with injustice.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 15:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>A man's heart devises his way, / But Jehovah directs his steps.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>A divine decision is on the lips of the king; / His mouth will not transgress in judgment.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>A [xref]a[/xref]just balance and [i]just[/i] scales are Jehovah's; / All the weights of the bag are His work.</text>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 19:36; Prov. 11:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>It is an abomination to kings to commit wickedness, / For the throne is established by righteousness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Righteous lips are the delight of kings, / And they love one who speaks right.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>The wrath of a king is as messengers of death, / But a wise man will appease it.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>In the light of the king's countenance is life, / And his favor is like a cloud of the latter rain.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>How much better it is to acquire wisdom than gold, / And to acquire understanding is to be chosen above silver.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>The highway of the upright is to depart from evil; / He who keeps his way preserves his soul.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Pride [i]goes[/i] before destruction, / And a [xref]a[/xref]haughty spirit before a fall.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 18:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>It is better to be of a [xref]a[/xref]lowly spirit with the poor, / Than to divide the spoil with the proud.</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 5:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>He who gives heed to the word will find good, / And [note]1[/note]blessed is he who trusts in Jehovah.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, happy.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>The wise in heart will be called discerning, / And the sweetness of speech increases persuasiveness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Insight is a fountain of life to him who has it, / But the correction of fools is folly.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>The heart of the wise man instructs his mouth / And adds persuasiveness to his lips.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>Pleasant words are a honeycomb, / Sweet to the soul and healing to the bones.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]There is a way which seems right to a man, / But the end of it is the ways of death.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 14:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>The appetite of the laboring man labors for him; / For his mouth urges him on.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>A worthless man digs up evil, / And on his lips there is a scorching [xref]a[/xref]fire.</text>
        <xref num="a">James 3:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>A perverse man spreads strife, / And a whisperer separates close friends.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>A man of violence entices his neighbor / And leads him in a way that is not good.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>He who shuts his eyes [i]does so[/i] to devise perverse things; / He who compresses his lips brings evil to pass.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>The gray head is a crown of glory; / It will be found in the way of righteousness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>He who is [xref]a[/xref]slow to anger is better than the mighty; / And he who rules his [xref]b[/xref]spirit, than he who captures a city.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 14:29; 15:18; James 1:19</xref>
        <xref num="b">cf. 1 Cor. 14:32</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>The [xref]a[/xref]lot is cast into the lap, / But everything it decides is from Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">Num. 26:55; Neh. 11:1; Jonah 1:7; Acts 1:26</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="17">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Better is a dry morsel and quietness with it / Than a house full of feasting with strife.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 15:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>A servant who deals wisely will rule over a son who causes shame, / And will share in the inheritance among brothers.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>The refining pot is for silver and the furnace for gold, / But Jehovah [xref]a[/xref]tries the hearts.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Chron. 29:17; Psa. 7:9; 26:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>An evildoer gives heed to wicked lips, / [i]And[/i] a liar gives ear to a mischievous tongue.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Whoever mocks the poor reproaches his Maker; / He who rejoices at calamity will not go unpunished.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 14:31</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Grandchildren are the [xref]a[/xref]crown of old men, / And the glory of children is their fathers.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Phil. 4:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Excellent speech is not fitting for a fool; / Much less are lying lips for a noble man.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>A bribe is [i]like[/i] a precious stone in the eyes of its possessor: / Wherever he turns, he prospers.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>He who [xref]a[/xref]covers a transgression seeks love, / But he who repeats a matter separates close friends.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 10:12; 1 Cor. 13:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>A rebuke strikes deeper into him who has understanding / Than a hundred stripes into a fool.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>An evil man seeks only rebellion; / Therefore a cruel messenger will be sent against him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Let a bear robbed of her cubs meet a man / Rather than a fool in his folly.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Whoever rewards evil for good, / Evil will not depart from his house.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>The beginning of contention is [i]like[/i] letting out water; / Therefore abandon strife before it breaks out.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>He who justifies the wicked man, and he who condemns the righteous man, / Both of them are an abomination to Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Why is there a price in the hand of a fool to buy wisdom, / When he has no sense?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>A friend loves at all times, / And a brother is born for adversity.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>A man lacking sense gives his hand as a pledge / And becomes surety in the presence of his neighbor.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>He who loves transgression loves strife; / He who raises high his entrance seeks destruction.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>He who has a crooked heart finds no good, / And he who has a perverse tongue falls into evil.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>He who begets a fool [i]does so[/i] to his sorrow, / And the father of a fool has no joy.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>A [xref]a[/xref]joyful heart is good medicine, / But a broken spirit dries up the bones.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 12:25; 15:13, 15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>A wicked man receives a bribe from the bosom, / To pervert the ways of justice.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>Wisdom is before the face of him who has understanding, / But the eyes of a fool are on the ends of the earth.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>A foolish son is a grief to his father, / And bitterness to her who bore him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>To also punish the righteous man is not good, / Nor to strike nobles for [i]their[/i] uprightness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>He who restrains his words has knowledge, / And he who is cool in spirit is one who has understanding.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>Even a fool, when he keeps silent, is counted wise; / When he shuts his lips, he is [i]counted[/i] prudent.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="18">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>He who separates himself seeks [i]his own[/i] desire / And rages against all sound wisdom.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>A fool has no delight in understanding, / But only that his heart may reveal itself.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>When the wicked man comes, contempt also comes; / And with dishonor [i]comes[/i] reproach.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>The words of a man's mouth are deep waters, / A gushing stream, a fountain of wisdom.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>To respect the person of the wicked man is not good, / [i]Nor[/i] to turn aside the righteous man in judgment.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>A fool's lips bring strife, / And his mouth invites blows.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>A fool's mouth is his ruin, / And his lips are the snare of his soul.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]The words of a whisperer are like dainty morsels, / And they go down into the innermost parts of one's being.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 26:22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>He also who is slack in his work / Is brother to him who is a destroyer.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>The name of Jehovah is a [xref]a[/xref]strong tower; / The righteous man runs into it and is safe.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 61:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]The rich man's substance is his strong city / And like a high wall in his own imagination.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 10:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Before destruction the heart of man is haughty, / [xref]a[/xref]But humility [i]goes[/i] before honor.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 15:33</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>As for him who gives an answer before he hears, / It is folly and shame.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>The spirit of a man can sustain his sickness, / But a broken spirit who can bear?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]The heart of one who has understanding acquires knowledge, / And the ear of the wise seeks knowledge.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 15:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>A man's gift makes room for him / And brings him before great men.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>The first to plead his case [i]seems[/i] just, / [i]Until[/i] his neighbor comes and cross-examines him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>The [xref]a[/xref]lot causes contentions to cease / And decides between the mighty.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 16:33</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>A [xref]a[/xref]brother offended [i]is harder to be gained[/i] than a strong city, / And contentions are like the bars of a castle.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Acts 15:39</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>With the fruit of his mouth a man's stomach will be satisfied; / With the produce of his lips he will be satisfied.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Death and life are in the [xref]a[/xref]power of the tongue, / And those who love it will eat its fruit.</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 12:37; James 3:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Whoever finds a [xref]a[/xref]wife finds a good thing, / And obtains favor from Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 19:14; 31:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>The poor man utters supplications, / But the rich man [xref]a[/xref]answers roughly.</text>
        <xref num="a">James 2:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>A man of [i]many[/i] friends [i]comes[/i] to destruction, / But there is a [i]true[/i] [xref]a[/xref]friend that sticks closer than a brother.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 17:17</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="19">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Better is a poor man who walks in his integrity / Than he who is perverse in his lips and is a fool.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 28:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Also it is not good for a person to be without knowledge, / And he who makes haste with his feet sins.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>The foolishness of a man subverts his way, / And his heart is indignant toward Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Wealth adds many friends, / But the poor man is separated from his friend.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]A false witness will not go unpunished, / And he who utters lies will not escape.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 19:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Many will entreat the favor of the generous man, / And every man is a friend to one who gives gifts.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>All the brothers of the poor man hate him; / How much more do his friends go far from him! / He pursues [i]them[/i] with words, [i]but[/i] they are not there.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>He who acquires sense loves his own soul; / He who keeps understanding will find good.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>A false witness will not go unpunished, / And he who utters lies will perish.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Delicate living is not fitting for a fool; / Much less for a servant to rule over princes.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>The discretion of a man makes him slow to anger, / And it is his glory to overlook a transgression.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>The king's wrath is like the roaring of a lion, / But his favor is like dew upon the grass.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>A foolish son is the ruin of his father, / And the [xref]a[/xref]contentions of a wife are a continual dripping.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 21:9, 19; 25:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>House and [xref]a[/xref]wealth are an inheritance from fathers, / But a prudent [xref]b[/xref]wife is from Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Cor. 12:14</xref>
        <xref num="b">Prov. 18:22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Slothfulness casts into a deep sleep, / And the idle soul will suffer hunger.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>He who keeps the commandment keeps his soul; / He who is careless of his ways will die.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>He who has pity upon a [xref]a[/xref]poor man [xref]b[/xref]lends to Jehovah, / And He will repay him for his good deed.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 15:7, 9, 11; Prov. 18:23; 22:9; 28:27; 2 Cor. 9:9; James 2:2</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 37:26; 112:5; Luke 6:35, 38</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Discipline your son, for there is hope; / But do not set your heart on destroying him.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 13:24; 23:13; Heb. 12:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>A man of great [xref]a[/xref]wrath will bear the penalty; / For if you deliver [i]him,[/i] you will only have to do it again.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 37:8; Matt. 5:22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Listen to counsel, and receive instruction, / That you may be wise at the end of your [i]days.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>There are many devices in a man's heart, / But it is the [xref]a[/xref]counsel of Jehovah that will stand.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 33:11; Isa. 46:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>What is desirable in a man is his kindness, / And a poor man is better than a liar.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>The [xref]a[/xref]fear of Jehovah [i]leads[/i] to life, / And he [i]who has it[/i] will lodge in contentment; / He will not be visited with evil.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 10:27; 14:27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>The [xref]a[/xref]sluggard buries his hand in the dish, / And will not even bring it back to his mouth.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 26:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Strike a scorner, and the simple will learn prudence; / And reprove one who has understanding, [i]and[/i] he will understand / knowledge.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>He who does violence to his father and chases away his mother / Is a son that causes shame and brings reproach.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>Cease listening, my son, to instruction, / [i]And you will[/i] stray from the words of knowledge.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>A worthless witness mocks justice, / And the mouth of the wicked swallows up iniquity.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>Judgments are prepared for scorners, / And blows for the back of fools.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="20">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Wine is a mocker, strong drink a brawler; / And whoever errs by it does not become wise.</text>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 9:21; Prov. 23:29-30; Eph. 5:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>The terror of a king is like the roaring of a lion; / He who provokes him to anger sins [i]against[/i] his own life.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>It is an honor for a man to keep away from strife, / But every fool rushes headlong [i]into it.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>The [xref]a[/xref]sluggard will not plow because of winter; / Therefore he will beg in harvest and have nothing.</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 25:26</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Counsel in the heart of man is [i]like[/i] deep water, / But a man of understanding will draw it out.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Many a man will proclaim his own kindness, / But who can find a faithful man?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>A righteous man who walks in his integrity, / Blessed are his children after him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>A king who sits on the throne of judgment / Scatters away all evil with his eyes.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Who can say, I have made my heart clean; / I am pure from my sin?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Differing weights and differing measures, / Both of them are an abomination to Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 11:1; 20:23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Even a child makes himself known by his deeds, / Whether his work is pure and whether it is upright.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>The hearing [xref]a[/xref]ear and the seeing eye &amp;#8212; / Jehovah has made both of them.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 4:11; Psa. 94:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Do not love [xref]a[/xref]sleep, or else you will come to poverty; / Open your eyes, [i]and[/i] be satisfied with bread.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 6:9; Rom. 12:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>It is bad, it is bad, says the buyer; / But when he has gone away, then he boasts [i]in his purchase.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>There is gold and an abundance of corals, / But the lips of knowledge are a precious jewel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Take his garment when [i]he becomes[/i] surety for a stranger, / And hold the pledge [i]when he becomes surety[/i] for foreigners.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 27:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>The bread of falsehood is sweet to a man, / But afterward his mouth will be filled with gravel.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Every plan is established by counsel, / And by sound counsel make war.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]He who goes about as a gossip reveals secrets; / Therefore do not associate with one who opens his lips wide.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 11:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Whoever [xref]a[/xref]curses his father or his mother, / His lamp will go out in deep darkness.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 21:17; Lev. 20:9; Matt. 15:4; Mark 7:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>An inheritance gained hurriedly at the beginning / Will not be blessed in the end.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Do [xref]a[/xref]not say, I will recompense evil; / Wait for Jehovah, and He will save you.</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 5:39</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Differing weights are an abomination to Jehovah, / And false scales are not good.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 20:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>A man's [xref]a[/xref]steps are [i]ordered[/i] by Jehovah; / How then can man understand his own way?</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 37:23; Jer. 10:23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>It is a snare to a man to rashly say, It is holy, / And after [i]making[/i] the vows [i]to begin[/i] to consider.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>A wise king winnows the wicked / And drives the [i]threshing[/i] wheel over them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>The [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]spirit of man is the [note]2[/note]lamp of Jehovah, / Searching all the innermost parts of the inner being.</text>
        <note num="1">Heb. [i]neshamah;[/i] translated [i]breath[/i] in [link]Gen. 2:7[/link] (see note 5 there) and [link]Job 32:8[/link] (see notes there). </note>
        <note num="2">Man's spirit is God's lamp within man. The light shining within man's regenerated spirit is God Himself ([link]1 John 1:5[/link]). Just as a lamp contains light and expresses it, man's spirit was created to contain God and express Him. In order for the divine light to shine into man's inward parts, God's Spirit as the oil must soak (mingle with) man's spirit as the wick (cf. [link]Rom. 8:16[/link]) and "burn" together with man's spirit ([link]Rom. 12:11[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Rom. 8:16; 1 Cor. 2:11; 1 Thes. 5:23; Heb. 4:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>Lovingkindness and truth preserve the king, / And his throne is upheld by kindness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>The glory of young men is their strength, / And the honor of old men is gray hair.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>Stripes that wound purge away evil, / And strokes [i]reach[/i] the innermost parts of the inner being.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="21">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>The [xref]a[/xref]king's heart is [i]like[/i] streams of water in the hand of Jehovah; / He turns it wherever He wishes.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 7:27</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Every [xref]a[/xref]way of a man is right in his own eyes, / But Jehovah weighs the [xref]b[/xref]hearts.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 16:2, 25; cf. Judg. 17:6; 21:25</xref>
        <xref num="b">1 Sam. 16:7; Psa. 7:9; Prov. 24:12; Jer. 17:10; Luke 16:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>To do righteousness and justice / Is more acceptable to Jehovah than [xref]a[/xref]sacrifice.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 15:22; Hosea 6:6; Micah 6:6-8; Matt. 9:13; Mark 12:33</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>A high look and a proud heart &amp;#8212; / The lamp of the wicked &amp;#8212; is sin.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>The plans of the diligent [i]lead[/i] only to plentifulness, / But everyone who is hasty [i]comes[/i] only to want.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>The getting of treasures by a lying tongue / Is a fleeting vapor, a [note]1[/note]snare of death.</text>
        <note num="1">Following the Septuagint; the Hebrew text reads, seekers.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>The violence of the wicked will sweep them away / Because they refuse to do justice.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>The way of a guilty man is crooked; / But as for the pure, his work is right.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]It is better to dwell in a corner of a housetop / Than in a house shared with a contentious woman.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 25:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>The soul of the wicked man desires evil; / His neighbor finds no favor in his eyes.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>When the scorner is punished, the simple man becomes wise; / And when the wise man is instructed, he receives knowledge.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>The righteous One considers the house of the wicked man, / Overthrowing the wicked to [i]their[/i] ruin.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Whoever [xref]a[/xref]closes his ear to the cry of the poor man / Also will cry and will not be heard.</text>
        <xref num="a">James 2:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>A gift in secret pacifies anger; / And a present in the bosom, strong wrath.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>It is joy to the righteous man to do justice, / But it is destruction to the workers of iniquity.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>The man who wanders from the way of understanding / Will rest in the assembly of the dead.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>He who [xref]a[/xref]loves pleasure will be a poor man; / He who loves wine and oil will not be rich.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 23:21; cf. 2 Tim. 3:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>The wicked man is a ransom for the righteous man, / And the treacherous man is in the place of the upright.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]It is better to dwell in a desert land / Than with a contentious and vexing woman.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Prov. 21:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>There is precious treasure and oil in the dwelling of the wise man, / But a foolish man swallows it up.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>He who pursues righteousness and kindness / Finds life, righteousness, and honor.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>A wise man scales the city of the mighty / And brings down the strength in which they trust.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Whoever [xref]a[/xref]guards his mouth and his tongue / Keeps his soul from troubles.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 13:3; Psa. 141:3; James 3:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>Proud, Haughty, Scorner are the names / Of him who works in the arrogance of pride.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>The desire of the sluggard puts him to death, / For his hands refuse to work.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>All day long one covets greedily, / But the righteous man gives and does not hold back.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]The sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination; / How much more when he brings it with evil intent!</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 15:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>A false witness will perish, / But the man who hears will speak so as to endure.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>A wicked man hardens his face; / But as for the upright, he establishes his ways.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>There is no wisdom nor understanding / Nor [xref]a[/xref]counsel that [i]can avail[/i] against Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 8:10; Acts 5:38</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>The horse is prepared for the day of battle, / But [xref]a[/xref]victory belongs to Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Chron. 29:11; cf. 1 Sam. 17:47</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="22">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>A [i]good[/i] name is to be chosen rather than great riches, / [i]And[/i] favor is better than silver and gold.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>The rich and the poor have this in common: / Jehovah is the [xref]a[/xref]maker of them all.</text>
        <xref num="a">Job 31:15; 34:19; Prov. 14:31</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]A prudent man sees evil and hides himself, / But the simple pass on and suffer punishment [i]for it.[/i]</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 27:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>The reward of humility [i]and[/i] the fear of Jehovah / Are riches and honor and life.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Thorns [i]and[/i] snares are in the way of the perverse; / He who guards his soul will keep far from them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Train up a child according to the way he should go; / Even when he is old, he will not depart from it.</text>
        <xref num="a">Eph. 6:4; 2 Tim. 3:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>The rich man rules over the poor, / And the borrower is servant to the lender.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>He who [xref]a[/xref]sows injustice will reap iniquity, / And the rod of his wrath will fail. [note]1[/note]</text>
        <note num="1">The Septuagint has the additional proverb: "God blesses a cheerful and liberal man, but [i]a man[/i] will fully prove the vanity of his works." The first part of this is the source of the quotation in [link]2 Cor. 9:7[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Job 4:8; Hosea 10:13; Gal. 6:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>He who is [xref]a[/xref]generous will be blessed, / For he gives some of his bread to the poor.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 11:25; 2 Cor. 9:6, 9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Cast out the scorner, and contention will go out; / Indeed, strife and dishonor will cease.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>He who loves [xref]a[/xref]pureness of heart / And whose speech is gracious will have the king as his friend.</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 5:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>The eyes of Jehovah preserve knowledge, / But He overthrows the words of the treacherous man.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]The sluggard says, There is a lion outside! / I will be slain in the streets!</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 26:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>The mouth of strange women is a deep pit; / He with whom Jehovah is indignant will fall in there.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Foolishness is bound up in the heart of a child; / [i]But[/i] the [xref]a[/xref]rod of correction will drive it far from him.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 13:24; 19:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>He who oppresses the poor to multiply his [i]gain,[/i] / [i]And[/i] he who gives to the rich [i]will[/i] only [i]come[/i] to want.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Incline your ear, and hear the words of the wise, / And apply your heart to my knowledge;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>For it is a pleasant thing if you keep them within you; / Let them be ready on your lips.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>So that your trust may be in Jehovah, / I have made [i]them[/i] known to you today, even to you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Have not I written to you [note]1[/note]excellent things / Of counsels and knowledge,</text>
        <note num="1">Or, thirty [i]sayings,[/i] perhaps referring to thirty proverbs, from [link]22:22[/link] through [link]24:22[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>To make you know the certainty of the words of truth, / That you may answer back words of truth to those who send you?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Do not rob the poor, because he is poor; / Nor oppress the afflicted in the gate;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>For Jehovah will [xref]a[/xref]plead their cause, / And rob the life of those who rob them.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 24:12, 15; Psa. 12:5; Jer. 50:34; 51:36</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>Make no friendship with a man [i]who is given[/i] to anger, / And with a wrathful man do not go;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Lest you learn his ways / And get a snare for your soul.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>Do not be one of those who give [i]their[/i] hand as a pledge / [i]Or[/i] one of those who are a surety for debts.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>If you have nothing with which to pay, / Why should your bed be taken away from under you?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>Do not remove the ancient [xref]a[/xref]boundary marker, / Which your fathers have set up.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 19:14; 27:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>Do you see a man skilled in his work? / He will stand before kings; / He will not stand before obscure men.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="23">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>When you sit to eat with a ruler, / Consider carefully [note]1[/note]who is before you;</text>
        <note num="1">Or, what.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And put a knife to your throat / If you are a man of [i]great[/i] appetite.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Do not desire his delicacies, / For they are deceitful food.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Do not weary yourself to become [xref]a[/xref]rich; / Cease from your consideration [i]of it.[/i]</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 28:20; 1 Tim. 6:9-10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>When you set your eyes upon it, it is gone; / For [xref]a[/xref][i]wealth[/i] certainly makes itself wings, / Like an eagle that flies toward heaven.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 27:24; 1 Tim. 6:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Do not eat the bread of one who is envious, / And do not desire his delicacies;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>For as he thinks within himself, so he is. / He says to you, Eat and drink; / But his heart is not with you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>You will vomit up the morsel which you have eaten, / And waste your pleasant words.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Do not speak in the hearing of a fool, / For he will despise the wisdom of your words.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 9:8; cf. Matt. 7:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Do not remove the ancient boundary marker, / Or go into the fields of the fatherless;</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 19:14; 27:17; Prov. 22:28</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>For their [xref]a[/xref]Redeemer is strong; / He will plead their cause against you.</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 50:34</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Apply your heart to instruction, / And your ears to words of knowledge.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Do not withhold [xref]a[/xref]correction from a child; / If you beat him with the rod, he will not die.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 13:24; 19:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>[i]If[/i] you beat him with the rod, / You will deliver his soul from [xref]a[/xref]Sheol.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 27:20; Rev. 20:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>My son, if your heart is wise, / My own heart will also rejoice;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>My inward parts will also exult, / When your lips speak right things.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Do not let your heart envy sinners, / But [i]live[/i] in the fear of Jehovah all day long;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>For surely there is a latter end, / And your hope will not be cut off.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Listen, my son, and be wise, / And direct your heart in the way.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Do not be among those who get drunk with wine, / Among gluttonous eaters of flesh;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>For the drunkard and the glutton will come to poverty, / And drowsiness will clothe [i]them[/i] with rags.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Listen to your [xref]a[/xref]father who begot you, / And do not despise your mother when she is old.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 1:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Buy [xref]a[/xref]truth, and do not sell [i]it;[/i] / Buy wisdom and instruction and understanding.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 3 John 4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>The father of the righteous man will greatly exult, / And he who begets a wise [i]child[/i] will rejoice in him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Let your father and your mother rejoice, / And let her who bore you exult.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>My son, give me your heart, / And let your eyes [note]1[/note]observe my ways.</text>
        <note num="1">Others read, delight in.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>For a harlot is a deep pit, / And an adulteress is a narrow well.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>Indeed, she lies in wait as a robber, / And increases [i]the number of[/i] the treacherous among men.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>Who has woe? Who has sorrow? Who has contentions? / Who has complaining? Who has wounds without cause? Who has redness / of eyes?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>Those who linger late over [xref]a[/xref]wine, / Those who go to seek out mixed wines.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 20:1; Eph. 5:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>Do not look upon the wine when it is red, / When it sparkles in the cup, / When it goes down smoothly;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>In the end it bites like a serpent, / And stings like an adder.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>Your eyes will see strange things, / And your heart will utter perverse things;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>And you will be like one who lies down while at sea, / Or like one who lies down at the top of a mast.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
        <text>They struck me, [i]you will say, but[/i] I was not hurt; / They beat me, [i]but[/i] I did not feel [i]it;[/i] / When will I awake? I will seek another drink.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="24">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Do not be envious of evil men, / Nor desire to be with them;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>For their heart meditates violence, / And their lips talk of mischief.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Through [xref]a[/xref]wisdom a house is built, / And by understanding it is established,</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 7:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And by knowledge the rooms are filled / With all precious and pleasant riches.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>A wise man is strong, / And a man of knowledge increases power.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>For by sound counsel you can wage your war, / And in the multitude of [xref]a[/xref]counselors there is [note]1[/note]victory.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, salvation.</note>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 11:14; 15:22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Wisdom is too high for a fool; / He does not open his mouth in the gate.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>He who devises to do evil, / Men will call him a mischief-maker.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>The devising of folly is sin, / And the scorner is an abomination to men.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>If you faint in the day of adversity, / Your strength is limited.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Deliver those who are being taken away to death, / And those who are staggering to be slain, oh, hold back!</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>If you say, Look, we did not know this &amp;#8212; / Does not He who weighs the hearts consider [i]it?[/i] / And He who keeps your soul, does He not know [i]it?[/i] / And will He not render to every man according to his work?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>My son, eat [xref]a[/xref]honey, for it is good, / And the drippings from the honeycomb, which are sweet to your taste:</text>
        <xref num="a">S.S. 5:1; Isa. 7:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Know [i]that[/i] wisdom is such for your soul; / If you find [i]it,[/i] then there will be a latter end, / And your hope will not be cut off.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Do not lie in wait, O wicked man, against the dwelling of the righteous man; / Do not destroy his resting place;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>For a righteous man falls seven times and [xref]a[/xref]rises up again, / But the wicked are overthrown by calamity.</text>
        <xref num="a">Micah 7:8; cf. 2 Cor. 4:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Do [xref]a[/xref]not rejoice when your enemy falls, / And do not let your heart exult when he is overthrown;</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 17:5; Obad. 12; 1 Cor. 13:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Lest Jehovah see [i]it,[/i] and it displease Him, / And He turn away His anger from him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Do not be incensed because of evildoers; / Do not be envious of the wicked;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>For there will be no future for the evil man; / The lamp of the wicked will be put out.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>My son, [xref]a[/xref]fear Jehovah and the king, / [i]And[/i] do not associate with those who are given to change;</text>
        <xref num="a">Rom. 13:7; 1 Pet. 2:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>For their calamity will rise suddenly, / And who knows the misfortune of both of them?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>These also are [i]sayings[/i] of the wise: / It is not good to have respect of persons in [xref]a[/xref]judgment.</text>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 19:15; Deut. 1:17; John 7:24</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>He who says to the wicked man, You are righteous, / Peoples will curse him; nations will abhor him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>But those who rebuke [i]the wicked man[/i] will have delight, / And a good blessing will come upon them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>He who gives an honest answer / Kisses the lips.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>Prepare your work outside, / And make it ready for yourself in the field, / And afterward build your house.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>Do not be a [xref]a[/xref]witness against your neighbor without cause, / And do not deceive with your lips.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 20:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>Do not say, I will do to him as he has done to me; / I will render to the man according to his work.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>I passed by the field of the sluggard, / And by the vineyard of the man lacking sense;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>And there it was, all overgrown with thorns; / Its surface was covered with nettles, / And its stone wall was broken down.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>When I looked, I considered [i]it;[/i] / I saw [i]it[/i] and received instruction:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]A little sleep, a little slumber, / A little folding of the hands to rest,</text>
        <xref num="a">vv. 33-34: Prov. 6:10-11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
        <text>And your poverty will come [i]upon you[/i] like a robber, / And your want, like an armed man.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="25">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>These also are [xref]a[/xref]proverbs of Solomon, which the men of Hezekiah the king of Judah copied.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 4:32</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>It is the glory of God to [xref]a[/xref]conceal a matter, / But the glory of kings is to search a matter out.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 29:29; Rom. 11:33; cf. Isa. 45:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>[i]As[/i] the heavens for height, and the earth for depth, / So the heart of kings is unsearchable.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Take away the dross from the silver, / And a vessel comes out for the smith;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Take away the wicked man [i]from[/i] before the king, / And his throne will be established in righteousness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Do not claim honor for yourself in the presence of the king, / And do [xref]a[/xref]not stand in the place of great men;</text>
        <xref num="a">Luke 14:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>For it is better that it is said to you, Come up here, / Than that you should be put lower in the presence of the noble, / Whom your eyes have seen.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Do not go out hastily to strive; / Otherwise what will you do in the end, / When your neighbor puts you to shame?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Argue your case with your neighbor [i]himself,[/i] / And do [xref]b[/xref]not reveal the secret of another;</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 5:25; 18:15</xref>
        <xref num="b">Prov. 11:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Lest he who hears it revile you, / And the evil report of you does not go away.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>A [xref]a[/xref]word fitly spoken / Is [i]like[/i] apples of gold in settings of silver.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 15:23; Isa. 50:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>[i]Like[/i] an earring of gold and an ornament of fine gold / Is a wise reprover to a listening ear.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>[i]Like[/i] the cold of snow in the time of harvest / Is a faithful messenger to those who send him, / For he refreshes the soul of his masters.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>[i]Like[/i] clouds and wind [xref]a[/xref]without rain / Is one who boasts of [i]his[/i] gifts falsely.</text>
        <xref num="a">Jude 12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>By forbearance a ruler may be persuaded, / And a soft tongue can break the bone.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Have you found honey? Eat [i]only[/i] what you need, / Lest you become filled up with it and vomit it.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Let your foot be seldom in your neighbor's house, / Otherwise he will become weary of you and hate you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>A man who bears false witness against his neighbor / Is [i]like[/i] a club and a sword and a sharp arrow.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Confidence in a treacherous man in time of trouble / Is [i]like[/i] a bad tooth and a foot out of joint.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>He who sings songs to a troubled heart / Is [i]like[/i] one who takes off a garment on a cold day, / Or [i]like[/i] vinegar on soda.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]If your enemy is hungry, give him bread to eat; / And if he is thirsty, give him water to drink;</text>
        <xref num="a">vv. 21-22: Exo. 23:4; 2 Kings 6:22; Matt. 5:44; Luke 6:27; Rom. 12:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>For you will heap coals of fire upon his head, / And Jehovah will reward you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>The north wind brings forth rain; / And a backbiting tongue, an angry countenance.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]It is better to dwell in a corner of the housetop / Than in a house shared with a contentious woman.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 21:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>[i]Like[/i] cold water to a thirsty soul, / So is good news from a far country.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>[i]Like[/i] a muddied fountain and a polluted spring / Is a righteous man who gives way before the wicked man.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>It is not good to eat much honey, / Nor is it glory [i]for men[/i] to search out their own glory.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>[i]Like[/i] a city that is broken down, without walls, / Is a man whose [xref]a[/xref]spirit is without restraint.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 16:32</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="26">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Like snow in summer and like rain in harvest, / So honor is not fitting for a fool.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Like the sparrow in [i]its[/i] fluttering, like the swallow in [i]its[/i] flying, / So a curse without cause does not alight.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>A whip for the horse! A [xref]a[/xref]bridle for the donkey! / And a rod for the back of fools!</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 32:9; James 3:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Do not answer a fool according to his folly, / Lest you also be like him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Answer a fool according to his folly, / Lest he be wise in his own eyes.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>He who sends a message by the hand of a fool / Cuts off [i]his own[/i] feet [i]and[/i] drinks violence.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>[i]Like[/i] the legs of the lame which hang down, / So is a proverb in the mouth of fools.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Like one who binds a stone in a sling, / So is he who gives honor to a fool.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>[i]Like[/i] a thorn that goes up into the hand of a drunkard, / So is a proverb in the mouth of fools.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>[i]Like[/i] an archer who wounds everyone, / So is he who hires a fool or who hires those who pass by.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Like a [xref]a[/xref]dog that returns to its vomit / Is a fool who repeats his folly.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Pet. 2:22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Do you see a man who is wise in his own eyes? / There is more hope for a fool than for him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]The sluggard says, There is a roaring lion on the way; / A lion is in the streets!</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 22:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>[i]As[/i] the door turns upon its hinges, / So does the sluggard upon his bed.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]The sluggard buries his hand in the dish; / He gets weary by bringing it to his mouth again.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 22:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>The sluggard is wiser in his own eyes / Than seven men who can answer discreetly.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>He who passes by [i]and[/i] meddles with strife that does not belong to him, / Is [i]like[/i] one who takes a dog by the ears.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Like a madman who shoots firebrands, arrows, and death,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>So is the man who deceives his neighbor, / And says, Was I not joking?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>For lack of wood the fire goes out, / And where there is no whisperer, contention quiets down.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>[i]As[/i] charcoal to hot embers and wood to fire, / So is a contentious man to kindle strife.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]The words of a whisperer are like dainty morsels, / And they go down into the innermost parts of one's being.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 18:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Burning lips and a wicked heart / Are [i]like[/i] an earthen vessel overlaid with silver dross.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>He who hates disguises [i]it[/i] with his lips, / But he lays up deceit within him;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>When he speaks graciously, do not believe him; / For there are seven abominations in his heart;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>Though [i]his[/i] hatred covers itself with guile, / His wickedness will be revealed before the assembly.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>Whoever digs a pit will fall into it, / And he who rolls a stone, it will come back on him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>A lying tongue hates those it crushes, / And a flattering mouth works ruin.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="27">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Do not boast about [xref]a[/xref]tomorrow, / For you do not know what a day may bring forth.</text>
        <xref num="a">James 4:14; cf. Luke 12:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Let another praise you, and not your own mouth; / A foreigner, and not your own lips.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>A stone is heavy, and the sand weighty, / But a fool's vexation is heavier than both of them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Wrath is cruel, and anger is overwhelming, / But who can stand before jealousy?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Open [xref]a[/xref]rebuke is better / Than love that is hidden.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 28:23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Faithful are the wounds of a friend, / But the [xref]a[/xref]kisses of an enemy are profuse.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Matt. 26:49</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>The full soul loathes a honeycomb, / But to the hungry soul every bitter thing is sweet.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Like a bird that wanders from her nest, / So is a man who wanders from his place.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Oil and perfume rejoice the heart; / So a man's counsel is sweet to his friend.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Do not forsake your own friend or your father's friend / To go to your brother's house in the day of your calamity: / Better is a neighbor who is near than a brother far away.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>My son, be wise, and make my heart glad, / That I may answer him who reproaches me.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]A prudent man sees evil [i]and[/i] hides himself; / [i]But[/i] the simple pass on [i]and[/i] suffer punishment [i]for it.[/i]</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 22:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Take the garment of him who is surety for a stranger, / And hold one in pledge [i]who is surety[/i] for a foreign woman.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 20:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>He who blesses his friend with a loud voice, / Arousing [i]him[/i] early in the morning, / It will be reckoned as a curse to him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>A continual [xref]a[/xref]dripping on a very rainy day / And a contentious woman are alike;</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 19:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>He who would restrain her restrains the wind, / And grasps oil with his right hand.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Iron sharpens iron; / So a man sharpens the countenance of his friend.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Whoever tends a fig tree will [xref]a[/xref]eat its fruit, / And he who takes care of his master will be honored.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Cor. 9:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>As in water face [i]reflects[/i] face, / So the heart of man [i]reflects[/i] man.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Sheol and [note]1[/note]Abaddon are never satisfied, / And the [xref]b[/xref]eyes of man are never satisfied.</text>
        <note num="1">Meaning [i]destruction.[/i]</note>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 30:16; Hab. 2:5; Rev. 20:13</xref>
        <xref num="b">Eccl. 1:8; 1 John 2:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]The refining pot is for silver and the furnace for gold, / And a man [i]is tried[/i] by the praise [i]given[/i] him.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Prov. 17:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Though you pound a fool in a mortar with a pestle along with crushed grain, / His folly will not depart from him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Know well the condition of your flocks, / [i]And[/i] pay attention to your herds &amp;#8212;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>For riches are not forever, / Nor does a crown [i]endure[/i] from generation to generation &amp;#8212;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>[i]Then[/i] when the grass has disappeared, and the tender grass is seen, / And the herbs of the mountains have been gathered in,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>The lambs will be for your clothing, / And the goats [i]will bring[/i] the price of a field;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>And there will be goats' milk enough for your food, / For the food of your household, / And [i]for[/i] the sustenance for your maidens.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="28">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>The wicked [xref]a[/xref]flee when no man pursues, / But the righteous are as bold as a lion.</text>
        <xref num="a">Lev. 26:17, 36</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>When a land revolts, it has many rulers; / But by him who has understanding [i]and[/i] knowledge it endures.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>A destitute man who oppresses the poor / Is [i]like[/i] a driving rain which leaves no food.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Those who forsake the law praise the wicked, / But those who keep the law contend with them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Evil men do not understand justice, / But those who [xref]a[/xref]seek Jehovah understand all things.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 55:6; James 1:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Better is a poor man who walks in his integrity / Than he who is perverse in [i]his[/i] ways though he is rich.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 19:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Whoever keeps the law is an understanding son, / But he who is a companion of gluttons shames his father.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>He who increases his substance by interest and usury / Gathers it for him who is gracious to the poor.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>He who turns away his ear from hearing the law, / Even his prayer is an abomination.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Whoever causes the upright to go astray in an evil way / Will himself fall into his own pit, / But the perfect will inherit good.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>The rich man is wise in his own conceit, / But the poor man who has understanding searches him out.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>When the righteous triumph, there is great glory; / But when the wicked rise, men hide themselves.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>He who covers his transgressions will not prosper, / But whoever [xref]a[/xref]confesses and forsakes [i]them[/i] will obtain mercy.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 32:5; 1 John 1:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Blessed is the man who always fears, / But he who hardens his heart will fall into calamity.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, Happy.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>[i]Like[/i] a roaring lion and a roving bear / Is a wicked ruler over a poor people.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>The ruler who lacks understanding is also a great oppressor, / [i]But[/i] he who hates unjust gain will prolong [i]his[/i] days.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>A man who is burdened with a person's blood / [note]1[/note]Will be a fugitive until death; / Let no man support him.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., Will flee to the pit.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Whoever walks uprightly will be delivered, / But he who is perverse in [i]his[/i] ways will fall all at once.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]He who tills his land will have plenty of bread, / But he who pursues worthless [i]things[/i] will have plenty of poverty.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 12:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>A faithful man will abound with blessings, / But he who makes haste to be [xref]a[/xref]rich will not go unpunished.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 28:22; 1 Tim. 6:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>To have respect of persons is not good, / Because for a piece of bread a man will transgress.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>A man who is envious hastens after wealth, / And does not know that want will come upon him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>He who rebukes a man will afterward find [i]more[/i] favor / Than he who flatters with the tongue.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>Whoever robs his father or his mother and says, / It is no transgression, / Is the companion of a man who destroys.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>A greedy person stirs up contention, / But he who trusts in Jehovah will prosper.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>He who trusts in his own heart is a fool, / But he who walks wisely will be delivered.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>He who [xref]a[/xref]gives to the poor man will not lack, / But he who shuts his eyes will have many curses.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 15:7; Prov. 19:17; 2 Cor. 9:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>When the wicked rise, men hide themselves; / But when they perish, the righteous increase.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="29">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>He who hardens [i]his[/i] neck after being often reproved / Will suddenly be broken beyond remedy.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>When the righteous increase, the people rejoice; / But when a wicked man rules, the people groan.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Whoever loves wisdom makes his father glad, / But he who keeps company with [xref]a[/xref]harlots wastes [i]his[/i] substance.</text>
        <xref num="a">Luke 15:30</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>The king by justice establishes the land, / But a man who takes bribes overthrows it.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>A man who flatters his neighbor / Spreads a net for his steps.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>In the transgression of an evil man there is a snare, / But the righteous man sings and rejoices.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>The righteous man knows the rights of the poor; / The wicked man has no understanding of [i]such[/i] knowledge.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Scorners set a city aflame, / But wise men turn away wrath.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>If a wise man [i]has[/i] a controversy with a foolish man, / [i]The fool[/i] is either angry or laughs, and there is no rest.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>The bloodthirsty hate one who is perfect, / And they seek the life of the upright.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>A fool utters all his anger, / But a wise man holds it back.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>If a ruler pays attention to a false word, / All his servants are wicked.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>The poor man and the oppressor have this in common: / Jehovah gives light to the eyes of them both.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>If a king judges the poor in truth, / His throne will be established forever.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>The rod and reproof give wisdom, / But a child left [i]to himself[/i] brings shame to his mother.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>When the wicked increase, transgression increases; / But the righteous will see their fall.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Correct your son, and he will give you rest; / He will also give delight to your soul.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Where there is no [xref]a[/xref]vision, the people cast off restraint; / But happy is he who keeps the law.</text>
        <xref num="a">1 Sam. 3:1; Amos 8:11-12; cf. Acts 26:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>A servant will not be corrected by words [i]alone;[/i] / For though he understands, there will be no response.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Do you see a man who is hasty in his words? / There is more hope for a fool than for him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>He who delicately brings up his servant from a child / Will have him as a son in the end.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>An angry man stirs up contention, / And a furious man abounds in transgression.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>A man's pride will bring him low, / But he who is of a [xref]a[/xref]lowly spirit will obtain honor.</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 5:3; 23:12; Luke 14:11; James 4:6; 1 Pet. 5:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>Whoever is partner with a thief hates his own soul; / He hears the adjuration and utters nothing.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>The fear of man brings a snare, / But whoever puts his [xref]a[/xref]trust in Jehovah will be [note]1[/note]exalted.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, protected.</note>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 32:10; Prov. 28:25</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>Many seek the ruler's favor, / But [xref]a[/xref]justice for man [i]comes[/i] from Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 49:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>An unjust man is an abomination to the righteous, / And he who is upright in the way is an abomination to the wicked man.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="30">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>The words of Agur the son of Jakeh. The oracle. / The man declares to Ithiel, to Ithiel and Ucal:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Surely I am more [xref]a[/xref]stupid than any man, / And do not have a man's understanding;</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 73:22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And I have not learned wisdom, / Nor do I have the knowledge of the Holy One.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Who has [xref]a[/xref]ascended into heaven and descended? / Who has gathered the wind in His fists? / Who has wrapped up the waters in His garment? / Who has [xref]b[/xref]established all the ends of the earth? / What is His name, and what is His Son's name, if you know?</text>
        <xref num="a">John 3:13; Rom. 10:6-7</xref>
        <xref num="b">Job 38:4; Psa. 104:3; Isa. 40:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Every word of God is tried; / He is a shield to those who [xref]b[/xref]take refuge in Him.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Sam. 22:31; Psa. 12:6; 18:30</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 2:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Do [xref]a[/xref]not add to His words, / Lest He reprove you and you be found a liar.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 4:2; Rev. 22:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Two things I have asked of You; / Do not refuse me before I die:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Remove far from me falsehood and lies. / Give me neither poverty nor riches; / Feed me with the [xref]a[/xref]food that is my portion,</text>
        <xref num="a">Luke 11:3; 1 Tim. 6:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Lest I become full and deny [i]You[/i] and say, Who is Jehovah? / Or lest I become poor and steal and profane the name of my God.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Do not slander a servant to his master, / Lest he curse you, and you be held guilty.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>There is a generation that curse their father, / And do not bless their mother.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>There is a generation that are [xref]a[/xref]pure in their own eyes, / And yet are not [xref]b[/xref]washed from their filthiness.</text>
        <xref num="a">Luke 18:11; cf. Prov. 21:2</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 51:2; Isa. 1:16; cf. Zech. 13:1; Titus 3:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>There is a generation &amp;#8212; oh how lofty are their eyes, / And their eyelids are raised [i]arrogantly.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>There is a generation whose teeth are [i]like[/i] swords, / And their jaw teeth [i]like[/i] knives, / To devour the afflicted from off the earth, / And the needy from among men.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>The leech has two daughters, [i]crying,[/i] Give, give. / There are three things that are never satisfied, / [i]Indeed,[/i] four that do not say, Enough:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Sheol and the barren womb, / The earth that is not satisfied with water, / And the fire that does not say, Enough.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>The eye that mocks his father / And despises to obey his mother, / The ravens of the valley will pick it out, / And the young eagles will eat it.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>There are three things which are too wonderful for me, / Indeed four which I do not know:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>The way of an [xref]a[/xref]eagle in the sky, / The way of a serpent upon a rock, / The way of a ship in the midst of the sea, / And the way of a man with a maiden.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 40:13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>This is the way of an adulterous woman: / She eats and wipes her mouth / And says, I have done no wickedness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Under three things the earth quakes, / And under four, it cannot bear up:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Under a servant when he is king, / And a fool when he is filled with food;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Under a hated woman when she gets married, / And a servant girl who is heir to her mistress.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>Four things are small on the earth, / But they are exceedingly wise:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>The [xref]a[/xref]ants are a clan without strength, / Yet they prepare their food in the summer;</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 6:6-8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>The rock badgers are a clan without might, / Yet they make their houses in the rocks;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>The swarming locusts have no king, / Yet all of them go out in ranks;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>The lizard can be grasped with the hands, / Yet she is in kings' palaces.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>There are three things which are stately in [i]their[/i] step, / Indeed four which are stately in walking:</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>The lion, which is mightiest among beasts, / And does not turn back before any;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>The strutting cock girded in the loins, or a male goat, / And a king [i]who has[/i] a band of soldiers with him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
        <text>If you have been foolish in exalting yourself, / Or if you have thought an evil scheme, / [i]Put your[/i] hand upon your mouth.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
        <text>For the churning of milk produces butter, / And the wringing of the nose brings forth blood, / So the pressing of wrath brings forth strife.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="31">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>The words of King Lemuel. The oracle which his mother taught him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>What, my son? and what, O son of my womb? / And what, O son of my vows?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Do not give your strength to women, / Nor your ways to that which destroys kings.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>It is not for kings, O Lemuel, it is not for kings to drink wine; / Nor for princes [i]to say,[/i] Where is strong drink?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Lest they drink and forget what is decreed, / And pervert the rights of all the afflicted.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Give strong drink [i]rather[/i] to one who is perishing, / And wine to the bitter in soul;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Let him drink and forget his poverty, / And remember his misery no more.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Open your mouth for the dumb, / [i]And[/i] for the rights of all those who are passing away.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Open your mouth; judge righteously, / And minister justice to the poor and needy.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Who can find a [xref]a[/xref]worthy woman? / For her price is far above corals.</text>
        <xref num="a">Prov. 12:4; 19:14; Ruth 3:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>The heart of her husband trusts in her, / And he will have no lack of gain.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>She does him good and not evil / All the days of her life.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>She seeks wool and flax, / And delights to work with her hands.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>She is like the merchant ships; / She brings her food from afar.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>She rises also while it is still night / And gives food to her household, / And [i]their[/i] task to her [i]serving[/i] girls.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>She considers a field and buys it; / With the fruit of her hands she plants a vineyard.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>She girds her loins with strength / And makes strong her arms.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>She samples her merchandise [i]to be sure[/i] it is good; / Her lamp does not go out by night.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>She lays her hands to the distaff, / And her hands hold on to the spindle.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>She [xref]a[/xref]stretches out her hand to the afflicted, / And she reaches out her hands to the needy.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Psa. 138:7; Acts 4:30</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>She does not fear for her household when it snows, / For all her household are clothed with [xref]a[/xref]scarlet.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 25:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>She makes coverings for herself; / Her clothing is fine linen and [xref]a[/xref]purple.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 25:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Her husband is known in the gates, / When he sits among the [xref]a[/xref]elders of the land.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ruth 4:1-2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
        <text>She makes linen garments and sells them / And delivers girdles to the merchant.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
        <text>Strength and dignity are her clothing, / And she happily looks forward to the time to come.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
        <text>She opens her mouth with wisdom, / And the [note]1[/note]law of kindness is on her tongue.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, teaching.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
        <text>She watches closely over the ways of her household / And does not eat the bread of idleness.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
        <text>Her children rise up and call her blessed; / Her husband [i]also,[/i] and he praises her, [i]saying:[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
        <text>Many daughters have done worthily, / But you surpass them all.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
        <text>Grace is deceitful, and beauty is vain; / [i]But[/i] a woman who fears Jehovah, she will be praised.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
        <text>Give her of the fruit of her hands, / And let her works praise her in the gates.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    </chapters>
</book>
