<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="yes"?>
<book name="Zechariah">
    <info title="Author">Zechariah ([link]1:1[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Time of His Ministry">From about 520 B.C., the second year of Darius Hystaspes ([link]1:1[/link]; [link]Ezra 4-6[/link]; different from both the Darius in [link]Dan. 9:1[/link]; [link]11:1[/link] and the one in [link]Neh. 12:22[/link]), to about 518 B.C., the fourth year of Darius ([link]7:1[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Place of His Ministry">Jerusalem ([link]7:2-4[/link]).</info>
    <info title="Object of His Ministry">The captives returning to Jerusalem.</info>
    <subject>Jehovah's Hearty Consolation and Promise to His Chastised Chosen People through the Redemption of Christ, Who in His Humiliation Became Their Suffering Companion in Their Captivity</subject>
    <outlines>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="1" ref="1:1-6">The introductory word</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="2" ref="1:7-6:15">The visions of consolation and promise</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="1:7-17">The vision of a man as the Angel of Jehovah riding on a red horse and standing among the myrtle trees</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="1:18-21">The vision of the four horns and the four craftsmen</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="2:1-13">The vision of a man with a measuring line in His hand</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="4" ref="3:1-10">The vision of Joshua the high priest perfected, established, and strengthened by the Angel of Jehovah with Zerubbabel the governor of Judah</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="5" ref="4:1-14">The vision of the lampstand of gold and two olive trees</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="6" ref="5:1-4">The vision of the flying scroll</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="7" ref="5:5-11">The vision of the ephah vessel</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="8" ref="6:1-8">The vision of the four chariots</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="9" ref="6:9-15">The concluding word to confirm the eight visions by the crowning of Joshua as a type of Christ</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="3" ref="7:1-8:23">The advice to Israel to turn from the vanity of their ritualistic religion to the reality of a godly life, and the desire of Jehovah to restore Israel</outline>
    <outline type="upper-roman" num="4" ref="9:1-14:21">The prophecies of encouragement centered on Christ</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="1" ref="9:1-17">The prophecy concerning the nations around Judah in relation to Israel</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="1" ref="vv. 1-7">Concerning the destruction carried out on the nations around Judah by Alexander the Great, the king of the Grecian empire (336-323 B.C., with the influence of his four successors extending to 44 B.C.)</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="2" ref="v. 8">The Lord protecting Jerusalem with its temple as His house</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="3" ref="vv. 9-10">Christ temporarily welcomed as the King into Jerusalem in a lowly form</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="4" ref="vv. 11-17">Concerning the victory of the Jewish Maccabean heroes over Antiochus Epiphanes the king of Syria (175-164 B.C.)</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="2" ref="10:1-12">The prophecy concerning the Lord's loving visitation to Israel</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="3" ref="11:1-17">The prophecy concerning the living of Israel under the oppression of the Roman Empire</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="1" ref="vv. 1-3">The destruction carried out in the neighborhood of Israel by the Roman Empire</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="2" ref="vv. 4-6">The children of Israel falling into their neighbor's hand and into the hand of their neighbor's king &amp;#8212; living under the tyranny of the Roman Empire</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="3" ref="vv. 7-11, 14">Jehovah (as Jesus) shepherding the afflicted of the flock of Israel</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="4" ref="vv. 12-13">The Messiah, as the proper Shepherd of Israel, detested, attacked, rejected, and sold for the price of a slave</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="5" ref="vv. 15-17">The children of Israel left to the foolish and worthless shepherds</outline>
        <outline type="upper-alpha" num="4" ref="12:1-14:21">The prophecy concerning Israel's destiny in the great war of Armageddon, in their household salvation, and in the millennium</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="1" ref="12:1-14">In the great war of Armageddon</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="2" ref="13:1-9">The divine provision and the sovereign preparation for the household salvation of Israel</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="1" ref="vv. 1-7a">The divine provision of a Redeemer with His redemption</outline>
            <outline type="lower-alpha" num="2" ref="vv. 7b-9">The sovereign preparation of a people to receive the Redeemer with His redemption</outline>
        <outline type="decimal" num="3" ref="14:1-21">In the millennium</outline>
    </outlines>
    <chapters>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>In the eighth month, in the [xref]a[/xref]second year of [note]1[/note]Darius, the word of Jehovah came to [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]Zechariah the prophet, the son of [note]3[/note]Berechiah, the son of [note]4[/note]Iddo, saying,</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., Darius Hystaspes, who ruled the Medo-Persian empire from 521-486 B.C. See [link]Ezra 4:5[/link], [link]24[/link]; [link]5:3-6:12[/link]. This Darius is different from both the Darius in [link]Dan. 9:1[/link] and [link]11:1[/link] and the one in [link]Neh. 12:22[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Meaning Jehovah remembers. Zechariah was born of a priestly family in captivity ([link]Neh. 12:1[/link], [link]4[/link], [link]12[/link], [link]16[/link]). He was first a priest, and then he became a prophet. He returned to Judah with Zerubbabel at the time of the prophet Haggai in about 520 B.C. ([link]Ezra 5:1[/link]). Zechariah and Haggai encouraged the building of the temple of God under the hands of Zerubbabel and Joshua. Joshua was the high priest, representing the priesthood, and Zerubbabel, a descendant of the royal family, was the governor of Judah, representing the kingship. Thus, the temple of God was built by the kingship with the priesthood. Likewise, in the building up of the church as the Body of Christ, both the priesthood and the kingship are needed ([link]1 Pet. 2:5[/link], [link]9[/link]). See note [link]1[sup]1[/sup] in Ezra 5[/link].[br/][br/]The central thought of Zechariah's prophecy is that Jehovah remembers His chastised people and sympathizes with them in their suffering of the nations' excessive action in carrying out Jehovah's punishing of Israel. God used the nations to punish Israel, but the nations went too far in carrying out God's punishing of His elect. For Israel's suffering of His punishment, God sent Christ as His Angel to be with them and go with them through their captivity ([link]vv. 7-11[/link]). He also raised up "craftsmen" to deal with the nations who had dealt with Israel excessively ([link]vv. 20-21[/link]). Through Zechariah, a prophet of restoration, God gave His chastised people a hearty word of consolation and promise, saying that He would bring the scattered Israel back to their own country with the expectation of a time of restoration and prosperity ([link]vv. 12-17[/link]; [link]2:1-4:14[/link]; [link]6:9-15[/link]; [link]8:1-23[/link]).[br/][br/]In Zechariah's prophecy Christ was sent to Israel as their King in a lowly form ([link]9:9-10[/link]) and as their Shepherd to feed them ([link]11:7[/link]), but He was detested ([link]11:8[/link]), sold ([link]11:2-13[/link]), attacked ([link]13:7[/link]), and pierced ([link]12:10[/link]) and thereby accomplished redemption for them ([link]13:1a[/link]; [link]1:8[/link]; [link]3:9[/link]). Eventually, Christ will fight for Israel to deliver them out of the hand of Antichrist for their household salvation ([link]12:1-14:21[/link]). In the restoration Christ will be King over all the earth ([link]14:8-11[/link], [link]16[/link], [link]20-21[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">Meaning [i]Jehovah blesses[/i].</note>
        <note num="4">Meaning [i]at an appointed time[/i]. The total significance of the three names Zechariah, Berechiah, and Iddo is that at an appointed time Jehovah will bless and Jehovah will remember.</note>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 4:24; Hag. 1:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">Ezra 5:1; Matt. 23:35</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Jehovah was extremely angry with your fathers;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Therefore say to them, Thus says Jehovah [note]1[/note]of hosts, [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]Return to Me, declares Jehovah of hosts, and I will return to you, says Jehovah of hosts.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, Sabaoth. So throughout the book.</note>
        <note num="2">The exhortation to the children of Israel in [link]vv. 2-6[/link] to return to Jehovah with the promise that Jehovah will return to them indicates that although the children of Israel had returned from Babylon to Jerusalem, most of them probably had not returned to the Lord. This establishes the principle that we must return to the Lord first, and then the Lord will return to us.</note>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 1:9; Jer. 24:7; 25:5; 35:15; Mal. 3:7; Luke 15:20</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Do not be like your fathers, to whom the former prophets [xref]a[/xref]cried, saying, Thus says Jehovah of hosts, Turn from your evil ways and from your evil deeds; but they did not hear nor hearken to Me, declares Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Chron. 36:15-16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Your fathers, where are they? And the prophets, do they live forever?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>But My words and My statutes, which I commanded My servants the prophets, did they not overtake your fathers, so that they returned and said, As Jehovah of hosts has [xref]a[/xref]thought to do with us, according to our ways and according to our deeds, so has He done with us?</text>
        <xref num="a">Lam. 2:17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>On the twenty-fourth day of the eleventh month, which is the month Shebat, in the second year of Darius, the word of Jehovah came to Zechariah the prophet, the son of Berechiah, the son of Iddo, saying,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>I saw during the night, and behold, a [note]1[/note]man was riding upon a [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]red horse; and He was standing among the [note]3[/note]myrtle trees that were in the bottoms; and behind Him there were [note]4[/note]red, reddish-brown, and white horses.</text>
        <note num="1">This man is the Angel of Jehovah ([link]v. 11[/link]), Christ in His humanity. The Angel of Jehovah is Jehovah Himself as the Triune God ([link]Exo. 3:2a[/link], [link]4-6[/link], [link]13-15[/link]). He is also Christ as the embodiment of the Triune God ([link]Col. 2:9[/link]) and as the sent One of God ([link]John 5:36-38[/link]; [link]6:38-39[/link]). The Angel of Jehovah is also the Angel of God who escorted and protected Israel on their way from Egypt to the promised land ([link]Exo. 23:20[/link]; [link]32:34[/link]; [link]Judg. 6:19-24[/link]; [link]Isa. 63:9[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">Here the red horse signifies Christ's swift move in His redemption, accomplished through the shedding of His blood ([link]Eph. 1:7[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 1:18-19[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">These myrtle trees signify the humiliated yet precious people of Israel in their captivity. The redeeming Christ, as a man and as the Angel of Jehovah, the embodiment of the Triune God, was sent by God to be with the humiliated people of Israel in their captivity. Christ's standing among the myrtle trees that were in the bottoms means that He remained strongly among the captured Israel in the lowest part of the valley in their humiliation. As the One on the red horse, Christ, the redeeming One, was Israel's patron, ready to do anything for them swiftly in order to care for them in their captivity. Christ maintained Israel in their captivity that He might eventually be born into humanity through Israel to accomplish God's eternal economy.</note>
        <note num="4">The horses of three different colors indicate that Christ's redemption (the red horse) leads the repentant Israel (the reddish-brown horses) to be justified and accepted by God swiftly (the white horses). This vision of the horses portrays the situation of Israel in their captivity. In the eyes of God, Christ the Redeemer was with them taking the lead, and they, God's redeemed people, were following Him. Because they were God's redeemed people, they appear at first sight as red horses. But because they were not pure, they are signified also by the reddish-brown horses (the color reddish-brown indicating a mixture). They need to contact God and to be dealt with by Him in order to gain God and be justified by Him and thus become those signified by the white horses. Once they repent, they will swiftly be accepted by God and justified by Him.</note>
        <xref num="a">Zech. 6:2-7; Rev. 6:2, 4-5, 8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Then I said, What are these, sir? And the angel who spoke with me said to me, I will show you what these are.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And the man who stood among the myrtle trees answered and said, These are those whom Jehovah has [note]1[/note]sent to go to and fro on the earth.</text>
        <note num="1">The red, reddish-brown, and white horses had been sent by Jehovah to go to and fro on the earth to observe the situation of the nations. As indicated by the movement of the horses, God's captured people were unsettled and were without peace, rest, and the enjoyment of life. The nations, on the contrary, were sitting still and were quiet ([link]v. 11[/link]). This indicates that, in the eyes of God, all the nations around Israel at that time were sitting and enjoying their life in peace and quietness while God's elect were suffering.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And they answered the Angel of Jehovah, who was standing among the myrtle trees, and they said, We have gone to and fro on the earth, and indeed all the earth sits [xref]a[/xref]still and is quiet.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 46:10; Hab. 2:20; Rev. 8:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Then the Angel of Jehovah answered and said, O Jehovah of hosts, how long will You not have compassion on Jerusalem and on the cities of Judah, with which You have been indignant for these [xref]a[/xref]seventy years?</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 25:11-12; Dan. 9:2; Zech. 7:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And Jehovah answered the angel who spoke with me with good words, with comforting words.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>So the angel who spoke to me said to me, Cry out, saying, Thus says Jehovah of hosts: I am greatly [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]jealous for Jerusalem and for Zion;</text>
        <note num="1">Because the nations were sitting peacefully while Jerusalem was troubled, Jehovah was very jealous for Jerusalem. He was extremely angry with the nations, who were at ease, sitting still and quiet ([link]vv. 15a[/link], [link]11[/link]). God was only a little angry with Israel, but the nations, in their carrying out of God's punishment on Israel, dealt with Israel excessively ([link]v. 15b[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Joel 2:18; Zech. 8:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And I am extremely angry with the nations, who are at ease; for I was only a little [xref]a[/xref]angry, but their help increased the affliction.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 47:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>Therefore thus says Jehovah, I return to Jerusalem with [xref]a[/xref]compassions; My [xref]b[/xref]house will be built in it, declares Jehovah of hosts, and a [note]1[/note][xref]c[/xref]measuring line will be stretched over Jerusalem.</text>
        <note num="1">Measuring for the purpose of possessing. For seventy years Jerusalem was given up by God ([link]v. 12[/link]; [link]Jer. 25:11[/link]). Now He was coming back to repossess the city; thus, He caused a measuring line to be stretched over it ([link]2:1[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 12:1; 54:8; Zech. 2:10; 8:3</xref>
        <xref num="b">Isa. 44:26-28; Hag. 1:14</xref>
        <xref num="c">Zech. 2:1-2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Cry out again, saying, Thus says Jehovah of hosts, My cities will again overflow with good, and Jehovah will again [xref]a[/xref]comfort Zion and will again choose Jerusalem.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 51:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Then I lifted up my eyes and looked, and there were [note]1[/note]four horns.</text>
        <note num="1">The vision of the four horns and the four craftsmen ([link]vv. 18-21[/link]) was a comforting and encouraging word of promise to Israel as God's answer to Christ's intercession for Zion and Jerusalem in [link]v. 12[/link]. The four horns are the four kingdoms with their kings &amp;#8212; Babylon, Medo-Persia, Greece, and the Roman Empire &amp;#8212; also signified by the great human image in [link]Dan. 2:31-33[/link] and by the four beasts in [link]Dan. 7:3-8[/link], that damaged and destroyed the chosen people of God. The four craftsmen ([link]v. 20[/link]) are the skills used by God to destroy these four kingdoms with their kings. Each of the first three kingdoms &amp;#8212; Babylon, Medo-Persia, and Greece &amp;#8212; was taken over in a skillful way by the kingdom that followed it (cf. [link]Dan. 5[/link]; [link]8:3-7[/link]). The fourth Craftsman will be Christ as the stone cut out without hands, who will crush the restored Roman Empire and thereby crush the great human image as the totality of human government at His coming back ([link]Dan. 2:31-35[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>And I said to the angel who spoke with me, What are these? And he said to me, These are the [xref]a[/xref]horns that have scattered Judah, Israel, and Jerusalem.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. Dan. 2:37-40; 7:3-8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Then Jehovah showed me [note]1[/note]four craftsmen.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]18[sup]1[/sup][/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And I said, What do these come to do? And he spoke, saying, These are the horns that have so [xref]a[/xref]scattered Judah that no man lifts up his head, but these have come to terrify them, to cast down the horns of the nations who have lifted up the horn against the land of Judah to scatter it.</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 50:17-18</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Then I lifted up my eyes and I looked, and there was a [note]1[/note]man, and in His hand was a [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]measuring line.</text>
        <note num="1">This man is Christ in His humanity as the Angel of Jehovah, the One speaking with Zechariah ([link]vv. 1a[/link], [link]2[/link]; cf. [link]Ezek. 40:3[/link]).</note>
        <note num="2">See note [link]16[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 1[/link]. The man with the measuring line intended to measure Jerusalem so that Jehovah might repossess it after the seventy years of Israel's captivity ([link]vv. 2[/link], [link]4b[/link]). This measuring was not only to know the size but also to know the condition and the situation. The measuring was done by a man, not by an angel. An angel is unqualified to measure anything human, because he does not have the human nature. Only Jesus, who has both the divine nature and the human nature, is qualified to measure Jerusalem.</note>
        <xref num="a">Ezek. 40:3; Rev. 21:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And I said, Where are you going? And He said to me, To [xref]a[/xref]measure [note]1[/note]Jerusalem; to see how great its breadth is and how great its length is.</text>
        <note num="1">Whereas the temple is the sign of God's house, the city of Jerusalem is a sign of God's kingdom for His administration. The city of Jerusalem was measured and was found to be an open region ([link]v. 4[/link]), i.e., without limit. This indicates that God's kingdom is unlimited, the size of God Himself, and that God Himself is the size of His kingdom.</note>
        <xref num="a">Zech. 1:16; Rev. 11:1; 21:15-17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Then at that point the angel who spoke with me went forth and another angel came forth to meet him.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And he said to him, Run, speak to this young man, saying, Jerusalem will lie as an open region due to the multitude of men and cattle within it,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>For I will be her [note]1[/note]wall of fire round about, declares Jehovah, and I will be the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]glory within her.</text>
        <note num="1">That the wall of the city of Jerusalem and the glory within her will be Jehovah Himself indicates that Jehovah as Christ will be the protection of Jerusalem at her circumference and her glory at her center. This shows the centrality and universality of Christ in God's economy. Today Christ is the glory in the center of the church, and He is also the fire burning around the circumference of the church for her protection. In the New Jerusalem the Triune God in Christ will be the glory at its center ([link]Rev. 21:23[/link]; [link]22:1[/link], [link]5[/link]), and this glory will shine through the transparent wall of the city ([link]Rev. 21:11[/link], [link]18a[/link], [link]24[/link]) to be its protection of fire.</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 60:19; Rev. 21:23[br/]See note 5[sup]1[/sup].</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Ho! Ho! [xref]a[/xref]Flee from the land of the north, declares Jehovah, for I have [note]1[/note]spread you out like the [xref]b[/xref]four winds of the heavens, declares Jehovah.</text>
        <note num="1">The word [i]spread[/i] indicates that God's scattering the people of Israel when they were taken into captivity was His spreading them for the spreading of His testimony. When the children of Israel were scattered to Babylon, four young people became witnesses of God and a testimony for Him ([link]Dan. 1:6[/link]). In this way God's testimony was spread to Babylon. God is great and sovereign, and He has a broad heart. Therefore, He wanted His testimony to be spread to faraway places. Cf. [link]Acts 1:8[/link]; [link]8:1[/link], [link]4[/link]; [link]11:19[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 48:20; 52:12; Jer. 1:14; 50:8; 51:6, 45; Rev. 18:4</xref>
        <xref num="b">Matt. 24:31</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Ho, Zion! Escape, you who dwell with the daughter of Babylon.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>For thus says Jehovah of hosts, [note]1[/note]After the glory [note]2[/note]He has sent [note]2[/note]Me against the nations who plunder you; for he who touches you touches the [note]3[/note][xref]a[/xref]pupil of His eye.</text>
        <note num="1">The expression [i]after the glory[/i] means after the return of the captives. In the seventy years of Israel's captivity, the glory was absent from the center of Jerusalem ([link]Ezek. 11:23[/link] and note 1). But when the children of Israel returned to Jerusalem, the glory also returned. In the sight of God the return of the captives was a glory.</note>
        <note num="2">Both [i]He[/i] and [i]Me[/i] refer to Jehovah of hosts. This means that Jehovah of hosts is the Sender ([link]vv. 9[/link], [link]11[/link]) and the sent One. Jehovah is the Triune God ([link]Exo. 3:15[/link] and note). In this verse One of the three in the Godhead, referred to as He, sent another of the three, referred to as Me. The Sender is surely the Father, and the sent One is the Son ([link]John 5:36b[/link]; [link]6:57a[/link]; [link]8:16[/link]). After the glory the Triune God decided that the Father would send the Son against the nations who plundered Israel. Both the Father and the Son are Jehovah.</note>
        <note num="3">Christ as the One sent by Jehovah of hosts and as the Sender, Jehovah of hosts, will be against the nations who plunder the people of Zion and touch them as the pupil of His eye. God's people are very dear to Him, and whoever touches them touches the pupil of His eye. This was a word of comfort, encouragement, and consolation to Zerubbabel, Joshua, and all the other returned ones.</note>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 32:10; Psa. 17:8; Prov. 7:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>For I am now waving My hand over them, and they will be plunder for those who served them; and you will [xref]a[/xref]know that Jehovah of hosts has sent Me.</text>
        <xref num="a">Zech. 2:11; 4:9; 6:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Give a [xref]a[/xref]ringing shout and rejoice, O daughter of Zion, for now [note]1[/note]I am coming, and I will dwell in your [xref]b[/xref]midst, declares Jehovah.</text>
        <note num="1">The [i]I[/i] in this verse and the [i]I[/i] and [i]Me[/i] in [link]v. 11[/link] refer to Jehovah, the same One as the He and Me in [link]vv. 8-9[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 12:6; 54:1; Zeph. 3:14</xref>
        <xref num="b">Lev. 26:12; Ezek. 37:27; Zech. 8:3; John 1:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And many [xref]a[/xref]nations will join themselves to Jehovah in that day and will become My people; and I will dwell in your midst, and you will know that Jehovah of hosts has sent Me to you.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 2:2-3; 49:22; 60:3; Zech. 8:22-23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And Jehovah will inherit Judah as His [xref]a[/xref]portion upon the holy land, and He will again choose Jerusalem.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 32:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>[note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Hush, all flesh, before Jehovah! For He is roused up from His [xref]b[/xref]holy habitation.</text>
        <note num="1">Before the glory returned to Jerusalem, Jehovah was silent, but after the glory He was roused up from His holy habitation. All flesh &amp;#8212; including the flesh of the Babylonians, Persians, Greeks, and Romans &amp;#8212; must be silent. Only Jehovah has the right to speak, and only He is the deciding factor.</note>
        <xref num="a">Hag. 2:20; Zeph. 1:7; Rev. 8:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 11:4; 68:5; Isa. 57:15; 63:15; Jer. 25:30</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Then He showed me [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Joshua the high priest standing before the Angel of Jehovah and [note]2[/note]Satan standing at his [xref]b[/xref]right hand to be his adversary.</text>
        <note num="1">Joshua the high priest typifies Christ as the High Priest sent by God to His people ([link]Heb. 3:1[/link]; [link]4:14-15[/link]; [link]7:26[/link]). Joshua also represents and signifies Israel as a nation of priests ([link]Exo. 19:6[/link]; [link]Zech. 8:20-23[/link]; [link]Isa. 2:2-4a[/link]).[br/][br/]Joshua was standing before the Angel of Jehovah to be perfected, established, and strengthened in the priesthood ([link]vv. 1-10[/link]). The Angel of Jehovah would do this by measuring Joshua. Christ's care for Joshua in this chapter is a continuation of His measuring in [link]2:1-2[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">Or, the accuser, the adversary. See notes [link]10[sup]1[/sup] in Matt. 4[/link] and [link]10[sup]2[/sup] in Rev. 12[/link]. As the adversary, Satan's intention was to belittle Joshua in front of his fellows ([link]v. 8[/link]) and to frustrate the rebuilding of God's temple.[br/][br/]In [link]vv. 1-2[/link] there are three parties: Joshua, the Angel of Jehovah, and Satan. This is a repetition of the scene in the garden of Eden, where God put the man He had created in front of the tree of life, denoting God, and the tree of knowledge, denoting Satan ([link]Gen. 2:8-9[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Hag. 1:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 109:6; Rev. 12:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And Jehovah said to Satan, Jehovah [xref]a[/xref]rebuke you, Satan! Indeed, Jehovah, who has chosen Jerusalem, rebuke you! Is this not a brand plucked from the [xref]b[/xref]fire?</text>
        <xref num="a">Jude 9; cf. Luke 9:42</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 66:12; Amos 4:11; Jude 23; cf. 1 Cor. 3:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Now Joshua was clothed with [note]1[/note]filthy [xref]a[/xref]garments and was standing before the Angel.</text>
        <note num="1">In type, garments signify one's conduct as one's expression ([link]Isa. 64:6[/link]; [link]Rev. 19:8[/link]). That Joshua the high priest was clothed with filthy garments indicates that our conduct may still be unclean because we still live in the flesh, which is altogether filthy ([link]Rom. 7:18[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 7:1[/link]). Joshua's filthy garments were the basis of Satan's accusation.</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 64:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And He answered and spoke to those standing before Him, saying, [note]1[/note]Remove the filthy garments from him. Then He said to him, See, I [i]hereby[/i] make your iniquity pass from you and [xref]a[/xref]clothe you with stately robes.</text>
        <note num="1">The perfection of Christ as the Angel of Jehovah was extended to Joshua by the removing of the filthy garments from him, thus making his iniquity pass from him. Joshua was also clothed with stately robes, with garments befitting his office and status as high priest. These garments signify the expression of Christ in His divine glory and His human beauty ([link]Exo. 28:2[/link] and notes).</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 61:10; Luke 15:22; Rev. 3:4; 19:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And [note]1[/note]He said, Let them put a [note]2[/note]clean [xref]a[/xref]turban upon his head. And they put the clean turban upon his head and clothed him with garments while the Angel of Jehovah stood by.</text>
        <note num="1">Following some ancient versions; the Hebrew text reads, I.</note>
        <note num="2">The clean turban signifies that Joshua had been fully cleansed and was now clean in the presence of Christ as the Angel of Jehovah.</note>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 29:6; Zech. 6:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And the Angel of Jehovah testified to Joshua, saying,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Thus says Jehovah of hosts, If you will walk in My ways and if you will keep My charge, then you will both judge My house and keep My courts, and I will grant you to walk among these standing [i]here.[/i]</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Hear then, Joshua the high priest, you and your fellows who sit before you &amp;#8212; for they are men of symbol &amp;#8212; for I am about to bring forth My [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]servant, the [xref]b[/xref]shoot.</text>
        <note num="1">This refers to Zerubbabel, who is a type of Christ as the Servant of Jehovah, the Shoot of David ([link]Jer. 23:5[/link]), in His humanity and royal faithfulness ([link]6:12[/link]). Although he was not a king but was a governor in the position of a king ([link]Hag. 1:1[/link]), Zerubbabel was nevertheless a descendant, a shoot, of the royal family of David. As such, he typifies Christ.</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 42:1; 52:13; Ezek. 34:23-24</xref>
        <xref num="b">Isa. 4:2; Zech. 6:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>For here is the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]stone that I have set before Joshua &amp;#8212; upon one stone are [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]seven eyes. I will [note]3[/note]engrave its engraving, declares Jehovah of hosts, and I will [note]4[/note]remove the iniquity of that land in one day.</text>
        <note num="1">This stone (Zerubbabel) set before Joshua also typifies Christ as the stone for God's building ([link]Psa. 118:22[/link]; [link]Isa. 28:16[/link]; [link]Matt. 21:42[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 2:4[/link]). Zerubbabel was a stone set before Joshua to carry out God's economy.</note>
        <note num="2">The seven eyes of the stone (Christ) are the seven eyes of Jehovah and the seven eyes of the Lamb, Christ, which are the seven Spirits of God, the sevenfold intensified Spirit ([link]4:10[/link]; [link]Rev. 5:6[/link]). See note [link]10[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 4[/link].</note>
        <note num="3">Jehovah's engraving of the stone indicates that God will work on Christ as the stone for the accomplishing of God's redemption, salvation, and building. To engrave is to cut. When Christ was dying on the cross, He was engraved, cut, by God.</note>
        <note num="4">This indicates that the Christ on whom God has worked will remove the sin of the land of Israel in one day, the day of His crucifixion ([link]1 Pet. 2:24[/link]). Through His death on the cross, Christ, the Lamb of God, took away the sin of the world ([link]John 1:29[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 118:22; Isa. 28:16</xref>
        <xref num="b">Zech. 4:10; Rev. 5:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>In that day, declares Jehovah of hosts, each of you will invite his neighbor to [i]come[/i] under the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]vine and under the fig tree.</text>
        <note num="1">After our sin has been taken away ([link]v. 9[/link]) and our situation with God has been appeased, there is peace between us and God, and we can come together to enjoy Christ as the vine ([link]John 15:1[/link], [link]5[/link]), the tree of life (see note [link]9[sup]2[/sup] in Gen. 2[/link] and notes [link book="Rev." chapter="22"]2[sup]1[/sup][/link] and [link]2[sup]2[/sup] in Rev. 22[/link]), and as the fig tree, full of the fruit of life ([link]Judg. 9:10-11[/link]). Christ came to accomplish redemption, bearing the Spirit and being cut by God on the cross (see notes [link]9[sup]2[/sup][/link] and [link]9[sup]3[/sup][/link]). This issued in our enjoyment of Him as the vine and as the fig tree. The measuring carried out by Christ as the Angel of Jehovah results in such a wonderful situation.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 4:25; Isa. 36:16; Micah 4:4</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Then the angel who spoke with me returned and roused me as a man is roused from his sleep.</text>
        <note num="1">The visions in [link]chs. 3[/link] and [link book="Zech."]4[/link] are concerned, respectively, with the priesthood and the kingship, which are both related to the rebuilding of the temple (see note [link]1[sup]1[/sup] in Ezra 5[/link]). The vision in [link]ch. 3[/link] concerning Joshua was to strengthen Joshua the high priest in the priesthood, whereas the vision of the golden lampstand and the two olive trees in this chapter was to strengthen Zerubbabel the governor of Judah in the kingship. In [link]ch. 3[/link] Joshua was measured (see note [link chapter="3"]1[sup]1[/sup][/link], par. 2, there), resulting in his being strengthened and established through the cleansing. In [link]ch. 4[/link] Zerubbabel was measured so that he might be strengthened and established to continue and complete the rebuilding of the temple.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And he said to me, What do you see? And I said, I see that there is a [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]lampstand all of gold, with its bowl on top of it and its [xref]b[/xref]seven lamps upon it, with [note]2[/note]seven pipes for each of the lamps on top of it;</text>
        <note num="1">The priesthood of Joshua signifies the priesthood of the nation of Israel toward the nations for God. The lampstand of gold signifies the shining testimony of the nation of Israel toward the nations for God. God had chosen Israel to be a nation of priests ([link]Exo. 19:6[/link]). His intention was to use the nation of Israel as a priesthood to bring the nations to God that they might enter into God's presence to be enlightened, exposed, dealt with, and transfused by God with the divine riches. Furthermore, the priests were to teach the nations how to worship God and serve God (cf. [link]8:20-23[/link]). In addition to being a nation of priests, Israel was to be a testimony standing for God.[br/][br/]Intrinsically, the lampstand signifies the Triune God embodied and expressed. In [link]Exo. 25[/link] the lampstand signifies Christ as the embodiment and expression of the Triune God. Here the lampstand signifies the nation of Israel as the collective testimony of God, shining out all His virtues. For the details concerning the lampstand, see notes in [link]Exo. 25:31-40[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">The supply of the lampstand is the seven pipes for each of the seven lamps, which signify the sevenfold intensified Spirit of God as the bountiful supply ([link]Phil. 1:19b[/link]). See notes [link]5[sup]1[/sup] in Rev. 4[/link] and [link]4[sup]5[/sup], par. 1, in Rev. 1[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 25:31; Rev. 1:12</xref>
        <xref num="b">Exo. 25:37; Rev. 4:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And [i]there are[/i] [note]1[/note]two [xref]a[/xref]olive trees beside it, one to the right of the bowl and one to the left.</text>
        <note num="1">See note [link]20[sup]1[/sup] in Exo. 27[/link]. The two olive trees here signify Joshua the high priest and Zerubbabel the governor at the time, who were the two sons of oil, filled with the Spirit of Jehovah for the rebuilding of God's temple ([link]vv. 3-6[/link], [link]12-14[/link]; cf. [link]Exo. 31:3[/link] and note). The two sons of oil also typify the two witnesses, Moses and Elijah, in the last three and a half years of the present age, who will be witnesses of God in the great tribulation for the strengthening of God's peoples &amp;#8212; the Israelites and the believers in Christ ([link]Rev. 11:3-12[/link]; [link]12:17[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Zech. 4:11-12; Rev. 11:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And I answered and spoke to the angel who spoke with me, saying, What are these, sir?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And the angel who spoke with me answered and said to me, Do you not know what these are? And I said, No, sir.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And he answered and spoke to me, saying, [note]1[/note]This is the word of Jehovah to Zerubbabel, saying, Not by [xref]a[/xref]might nor by power, but by My [note]2[/note]Spirit, says Jehovah of hosts.</text>
        <note num="1">The word in [link]vv. 5-7[/link] and [link]9a[/link] indicates that Zerubbabel, the governor of Judah, who laid the foundation for the rebuilding of the temple, would bring forth the topstone, which means that he would finish the rebuilding of God's temple by the Spirit of Jehovah, not by might nor by power. The prophet Zechariah spoke this word to Zerubbabel in order to support, encourage, strengthen, and establish the hand of Zerubbabel that he might continue the building of the temple unto its consummation.</note>
        <note num="2">Whereas [link]ch. 3[/link] refers to Christ's death, which is for redemption ([link]3:9[/link]), [link]ch. 4[/link] speaks of the Spirit, who is for the carrying out of God's economy. According to the New Testament, Christ is the One who was crucified for our redemption, who was raised from among the dead, and who in resurrection has become the life-giving Spirit ([link]1 Cor. 15:3-4[/link], [link]45b[/link]). As the result of Christ's redemption, God's people may now enjoy Christ as the Spirit ([link]Gal. 3:13-14[/link]), even as the sevenfold intensified Spirit ([link]Rev. 1:4[/link]; [link]4:5[/link]; [link]5:6[/link]). After we believe in the crucified Christ, God supplies to us the all-inclusive Spirit for the accomplishing of His building ([link]Gal. 3:1-2[/link], [link]5[/link]). By this Spirit the building of the church will be consummated.</note>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 1:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Who are you, O great [xref]a[/xref]mountain? Before Zerubbabel [i]you will become[/i] a plain, and he will [note]1[/note]bring forth the [xref]b[/xref]topstone with [xref]c[/xref]shouts of Grace, grace to it.</text>
        <note num="1">To bring forth the topstone is to complete the building. The shouts of "Grace, grace to it!" indicate that the topstone itself is grace. The topstone typifies Christ, who is the grace from God to us to be the covering of God's building (see note [link]10[sup]1[/sup] in 1 Cor. 15[/link]). Christ is the foundation stone to uphold God's building ([link]Isa. 28:16[/link]; [link]1 Cor. 3:11[/link]), the cornerstone to join together the Gentile and Jewish members of His Body ([link]Eph. 2:20[/link]; [link]1 Pet. 2:6[/link]), and the topstone to consummate God's building.</note>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 51:25; Matt. 21:21</xref>
        <xref num="b">Psa. 118:22</xref>
        <xref num="c">Ezra 3:11, 13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Moreover the word of Jehovah came to me, saying,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>The hands of Zerubbabel have laid the [xref]a[/xref]foundation of this house, and his hands will [xref]b[/xref]finish [i]it;[/i] and you will [xref]c[/xref]know that Jehovah of hosts has sent Me to you.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 3:10</xref>
        <xref num="b">Ezra 6:15</xref>
        <xref num="c">Zech. 2:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>For who has despised the day of [xref]a[/xref]small things? For these [note]1[/note]seven rejoice when they see the plummet in the hand of Zerubbabel; they are the [xref]b[/xref]eyes of Jehovah running to and fro on the whole earth.</text>
        <note num="1">"These seven," which are the eyes of Jehovah, are the seven eyes on the stone in [link]3:9[/link]. The seven eyes of the stone are the seven eyes of Jehovah and also the seven eyes of the Lamb, Christ ([link]Rev. 5:6[/link]). Thus, the stone, Jehovah, and the Lamb are one. Christ is the redeeming Lamb and the building stone, and He is also Jehovah. The seven eyes of Christ are the seven Spirits of God (see notes [link]6[sup]5[/sup] in Rev. 5[/link] and [link]4[sup]5[/sup] in Rev. 1[/link]), indicating that Christ and the Holy Spirit, although distinct, are not separate. Just as a person's eyes are essentially one with the person, so the Holy Spirit is essentially one with Christ ([link]Rom. 8:9-10[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 3:17[/link]). The function of Christ's seven eyes is to observe and search in order to execute God's judgment on the universe and to transfuse and infuse all that God is into His chosen people. In His resurrection Christ, as the last Adam, became the life-giving Spirit ([link]1 Cor. 15:45b[/link]; [link]John 6:63a[/link]; [link]2 Cor. 3:6b[/link]), who is also the sevenfold intensified Spirit. This Spirit is the Spirit of life ([link]Rom. 8:2[/link]). Hence, the function of the seven Spirits is to impart the divine life into God's people for the building up of God's eternal habitation, the New Jerusalem.</note>
        <xref num="a">Hag. 2:3</xref>
        <xref num="b">2 Chron. 16:9; Prov. 15:3; Zech. 3:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Then I answered and said to him, What are these two [xref]a[/xref]olive trees on the right of the lampstand and on its left?</text>
        <xref num="a">Zech. 4:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And I answered a second time and said to him, What are the two olive [note]1[/note]branches that are by the side of the two golden spouts, [note]2[/note]which empty the [note]3[/note]gold from themselves?</text>
        <note num="1">In [link]chs. 3[/link] and [link book="Zech."]4[/link] the same person, Zerubbabel, is signified by a shoot ([link]3:8[/link]), a tree ([link]vv. 3[/link], [link]11[/link]), and a branch ([link]v. 12[/link]). This indicates that Zerubbabel himself is not the source. He is not a tree complete in himself; rather, he is a tree that is actually a branch of another tree, and that tree is the source. Moreover, Zerubbabel is also a shoot from the other tree, which tree is Christ. Christ is the unique olive tree ([link]Rom. 11:17[/link] and note 2), and Zerubbabel and all Christ's believers are branches, shoots, of Christ ([link]John 15:5a[/link]). Thus, all the believers are the many olive trees, not in the sense of being separate trees but in the sense of being branches of Christ, the unique olive tree.</note>
        <note num="2">[i]Which[/i] here refers not to the spouts but to the branches. For the shining of the lampstand, oil is needed. The two olive trees supply the olive oil by flowing the oil out through the branches into the spouts, which in turn direct the oil into the bowl, which supplies the lampstand through the pipes ([link]v. 2[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">Referring to the oil. The oil denotes the Spirit, and the Spirit is God, who in typology is signified by gold. Thus, to supply the oil for the shining of the lampstand is to flow out God to supply others with the sevenfold Spirit that they may be enlivened for God's testimony through the church.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And he spoke to me, saying, Do you not know what these are? And I said, No, sir.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And he said, These are the two [xref]a[/xref]sons of oil, who stand by the [xref]b[/xref]Lord of the whole earth.</text>
        <xref num="a">Rev. 11:4</xref>
        <xref num="b">Micah 4:13; Zech. 6:5</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="5">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Then I lifted up my eyes again and I saw, and there was a [note]2[/note]flying [xref]a[/xref]scroll.</text>
        <note num="1">The first five visions in this book ([link]1:7-4:14[/link]) are positive, as a comforting, consoling, and encouraging word from God to Joshua, Zerubbabel, and the people. In contrast, the last three visions ([link]5:1-6:8[/link]) are negative, concerning God's universal judgment on the evil people and the evil on earth.</note>
        <note num="2">The flying scroll signifies God's righteous law and its justice (just judgment). This scroll will be the base of God's thorough judgment over all the sin on earth (cf. [link]Rom. 3:19[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Ezek. 2:9</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And he said to me, What do you see? And I said, I see a flying scroll, its [note]1[/note]length twenty cubits and its breadth ten cubits.</text>
        <note num="1">The length of the flying scroll being twenty cubits and the breadth being ten cubits signifies the testimony of the law by two squares of ten cubits by ten cubits. The number two is the number for testimony ([link]Deut. 17:6[/link]), and the number ten signifies completion in fullness ([link]Rev. 2:10[/link] and note 2). Therefore, the law of God is a testimony to the whole world, and the two squares of ten cubits by ten cubits point to the completion in fullness of the law.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Then he said to me, This is the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]curse that goes forth over the face of all the land; for everyone who [note]2[/note]steals will be purged according to what is on one side, and everyone who [note]2[/note]swears will be purged according to what is on the other side.</text>
        <note num="1">The curse signifies God's punishment in judging sins according to His righteous law ([link]Gal. 3:13a[/link]). The fact that God's judgment is a curse indicates that it is a very serious matter.</note>
        <note num="2">Stealing signifies sins toward man, which are the issue of greed and covetousness, whereas swearing falsely by Jehovah's name signifies sins toward God, which are the issue of a wrong relationship with God. The law of God given to Moses is of two sections, the first concerning the relationship between man and God, and the second concerning the relationships among men (see note [link]2[sup]1[/sup] in Exo. 20[/link]). To be right with God and with man is to be righteous. Those who are not right with both God and man will suffer God's judgment.</note>
        <xref num="a">Mal. 4:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>I will cause [note]1[/note]it to go forth, declares Jehovah of hosts; and it will enter the house of him who steals and the house of him who swears falsely by My name; and it will lodge overnight within his house and [xref]a[/xref]consume it, both with its timbers and its stones.</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to God's judgment. The description in this verse indicates that the exercise of God's judgment of sins will be most serious and also very thorough.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. Lev. 14:45</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Then the angel who spoke with me went forth and said to me, Lift up now your eyes and see what this is that goes forth.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And I said, What is it? And he said, This is [note]1[/note]the ephah vessel that goes forth; and he said, This is their [note]2[/note]appearance in all the land;</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., it. An ephah vessel is a measuring vessel, a container able to hold one ephah, used for purchasing and selling in business. The vision of the ephah vessel signifies the wickedness of business, or commerce, on the earth.</note>
        <note num="2">Commerce seems to have a proper appearance; actually, it is evil, full of wickedness ([link]vv. 7-8[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>(Then a lead cover was lifted up) and this is a [note]1[/note]woman sitting within the ephah vessel.</text>
        <note num="1">The woman sitting within the ephah vessel signifies the wickedness contained in commerce ([link]v. 8a[/link]), such as covetousness, deceit, and the love of money. The vision here corresponds to that of Babylon the Great in [link]Rev. 18[/link]. The two visions show that in the sight of God the wickedness contained in commerce is a form of idolatry and fornication. Business is an adulterous woman desirous of making money.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Then he said, This is Wickedness. And he threw her down into the midst of the ephah vessel and threw the [note]1[/note]lead weight over its opening.</text>
        <note num="1">A lead cover ([link]v. 7[/link]), a lead weight, being thrown over the opening of the ephah vessel signifies the restriction of the wickedness in commerce by God's sovereignty.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Then I lifted up my eyes and I looked, and there were [note]1[/note]two women going forth, and the wind was in their wings; and they had wings like the wings of a stork. And they lifted up the ephah vessel between the earth and the heavens.</text>
        <note num="1">The one woman ([link]v. 7[/link]) becoming two women signifies a double effect of commerce once it becomes free of the restriction. The vision in this verse of the two women going forth signifies the rapid spreading of wicked commerce.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And I said to the angel who spoke with me, Where are they taking the ephah vessel?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And he said to me, [note]1[/note]To build a house for her in the land of [xref]a[/xref]Shinar; and when it is prepared, she will be set there in her own place.</text>
        <note num="1">This signifies that God's sovereignty will cause the wickedness in business, which the people of Israel learned from the Babylonians in their captivity, to go back to Babylon (the land of Shinar &amp;#8212; [link]Gen. 11:2[/link], [link]9[/link]; [link]2 Chron. 36:7[/link]; cf. [link]Dan. 1:2[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Gen. 10:10</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="6">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Then I lifted up my eyes again and I looked, and there were [note]1[/note]four chariots coming forth from between the [note]2[/note]two mountains; and the mountains were mountains of [note]3[/note]bronze.</text>
        <note num="1">The four chariots signify the four winds ([link]vv. 4-8[/link]) from the four corners of the earth ([link]Rev. 7:1-3[/link]) for God's judging of sins upon the earth. These four winds are used by God to carry out His administration in the entire universe. In particular, they are used by God to carry out His judgment, not mainly on individual persons but on nations, governments, and kingdoms. God's sovereign "blowing of the wind" brings in the different craftsmen to judge the nations that damage and destroy Israel ([link]1:20-21[/link]). See note [link]18[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 1[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">The two mountains signify a testimony of God's judgments on the earth. From between the two mountains the four winds come forth to testify to the whole earth that God is on the throne and that the earth is under His administration ([link]Dan. 7:9-10[/link]; [link]Rev. 4:2[/link] and note 2).</note>
        <note num="3">Bronze signifies God's judgment ([link]Num. 21:8-9[/link]). Thus, the two mountains of bronze signify mountains of judgment. Although the two mountains of bronze do not signify Christ, they are nevertheless closely related to Christ, for He has been appointed by God to carry out the judgment on the living and the dead ([link]John 5:22[/link]; [link]Acts 10:42[/link]; [link]17:31[/link]; [link]2 Tim. 4:1[/link]). On the one hand, Christ is the Redeemer and the Savior; on the other hand, He is the Judge. As the Judge, He will carry out God's judgment. God's judgment is for the carrying out of His testimony.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>With the first chariot were [xref]a[/xref]red [note]1[/note]horses, and with the second chariot were black horses,</text>
        <note num="1">That each chariot was equipped with horses signifies the quick movement of God's judgment. The horses of different colors, red, black, white, and speckled, signify the different manners of God's judgment.</note>
        <xref num="a">Zech. 1:8; Rev. 6:2-5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And with the third chariot were white horses, and with the fourth chariot were strong, speckled horses.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And I answered and said to the angel who spoke with me, What are these, sir?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And the angel answered and said to me, These are the [xref]a[/xref]four winds of heaven who go forth from presenting themselves to the Lord of the whole earth.</text>
        <xref num="a">Dan. 7:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>With [note]1[/note]one of the winds the black horses went forth to the land of the [xref]a[/xref]north, and the white [i]horses[/i] went forth after them, and the speckled [i]horses[/i] went forth to the land of the south.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., it.</note>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 1:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And the strong [i]horses[/i] went forth and sought to proceed to go to and fro on the earth. And He said, Proceed to [xref]a[/xref]go to and fro on the earth; and they went to and fro on the earth.</text>
        <xref num="a">Zech. 1:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Then He called out to me and spoke to me, saying, See, these who are going forth to the land of the north have given My Spirit [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]rest in the land of the north.</text>
        <note num="1">This signifies that the judgments on the countries of the north, Assyria and Babylon ([link]Jer. 1:13-15[/link]), have given rest to God's Spirit. The judgment on these countries was a comfort to God.</note>
        <xref num="a">Ezek. 5:13; 16:42</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And the word of Jehovah came to me, saying,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>Take from them of the captivity, from Heldai, Tobijah, and Jedaiah, and go the same day and enter the house of Josiah the son of Zephaniah, where they have come from Babylon.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>Indeed, take the silver and gold, and make a [note]1[/note]splendid [xref]a[/xref]crown and put it upon the head of Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest,</text>
        <note num="1">The previous eight visions of comfort, consolation, and encouragement are confirmed by the crowning of Joshua the high priest &amp;#8212; typifying Christ in His priesthood &amp;#8212; linked with Zerubbabel the governor of Judah ([link]vv. 12-13[/link]), typifying Christ as the Shoot of David in His kingship (see notes [link chapter="3"]1[sup]1[/sup][/link] and [link]8[sup]1[/sup] in ch. 3[/link]). Christ, typified in [link]vv. 11-13[/link] by two persons, Joshua and Zerubbabel, is the unique One to hold the two offices of the priesthood and the kingship. In all history He is the only person qualified to bear the responsibilities of these two offices in God's administration. Thus, in [link]Hebrews 7[/link] Christ is both the High Priest and the King, as typified by Melchizedek (cf. [link]Gen. 14:18[/link]). Because Melchizedek bore the two offices of the priesthood and the kingship, he was a type of Christ as the One who would bear both the priesthood and the kingship in God's administration.</note>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 28:37; 29:6; Lev. 8:9; Zech. 3:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And speak to him, saying, Thus speaks Jehovah of hosts, saying, Here is a man, whose name is the [xref]a[/xref]Shoot; and he will shoot forth from his place and will [note]1[/note]build the [xref]b[/xref]temple of Jehovah.</text>
        <note num="1">This indicates that the concluding word in this chapter, concerning the crowning of Joshua, was an assurance to the people that God would do something to complete the rebuilding of the temple ([link]v. 15[/link]; [link]Ezra 5:1-6:15[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Zech. 3:8</xref>
        <xref num="b">Zech. 4:9; Matt. 16:18; Eph. 2:20-22; Heb. 3:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>Indeed, it is he who will build the temple of Jehovah; and he will bear majesty and will sit and rule on his throne; and he will be a [xref]a[/xref]priest on his throne; and the counsel of peace will be [note]1[/note]between the two of them.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Between the two means[/i] between the priesthood and the kingship. In the Old Testament no king could be a priest, but in the millennium both Christ and the overcomers will be kings to reign and priests to serve God. These two responsibilities will be reconciled in both Christ and the overcomers. In the millennium the overcomers will be priests, drawing near to God and Christ, and they will also be kings, reigning over the nations with Christ ([link]Rev. 2:26-27[/link]; [link]20:4[/link], [link]6[/link]). This will be a reward to the overcomers. The believers who are defeated in this age will forfeit this reward. However, after being dealt with in the millennium, these defeated ones will participate in the blessing of this reward in that they will serve God in the priesthood and represent God in the kingship in the new heaven and new earth for eternity ([link]Rev. 22:3[/link], [link]5[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 110:4; Heb. 3:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And the splendid crown will be as a [note]1[/note]reminder in the temple of Jehovah to Helem, Tobijah, Jedaiah, and Hen the son of Zephaniah.</text>
        <note num="1">The crown with which Joshua was crowned was removed from his head and put in the temple. It was to be a reminder to the children of Israel to remember the coming Messiah, the One who would come to be the King and the Priest to execute God's administration for the fulfillment of God's economy.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And those who are [xref]a[/xref]far off will come and build the temple of Jehovah, and you will [xref]b[/xref]know that Jehovah of hosts has sent Me to you. And it will happen, if you fully obey the voice of Jehovah your God.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 60:10</xref>
        <xref num="b">Zech. 2:9</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="7">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>And in the fourth year of Darius the king the word of Jehovah came to [xref]a[/xref]Zechariah on the fourth [i]day[/i] of the ninth month, [i]the month[/i] Chislev.</text>
        <xref num="a">Ezra 5:1; 6:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Now [i]the people of[/i] Bethel had sent Sharezer and Regemmelech and their men to entreat the favor of Jehovah</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>By speaking to the priests who belong to the house of Jehovah of hosts and to the prophets, saying, Shall I [note]1[/note]weep in the fifth month and separate myself, as I have done these many years?</text>
        <note num="1">According to [link]vv. 3-6[/link] and [link]8:19a[/link], in their ritualistic religion the people of Israel wept, fasted, and separated themselves in the tenth month to express their grieving for the attacking and besieging of Jerusalem by the Babylonians ([link]Jer. 52:4[/link]), in the fourth month to express their grieving for the breaking down of the city of Jerusalem ([link]2 Kings 25:3-4[/link]), in the fifth month to express their grieving for the burning of the temple of God and the city of Jerusalem ([link]Jer. 52:12-13[/link]), and in the seventh month to express their grieving for the murder of Gedaliah ([link]2 Kings 25:22-26[/link]). In [link]vv. 7-14[/link] and in [link]8:16-17[/link], [link]19b[/link], Jehovah advised Israel to turn from the vanity of their ritualistic religion to Jehovah and to the reality of a godly life, a life full of righteousness, lovingkindness, compassion, truth, and peace. This would bring in the times of restoration mentioned in [link]8:2-23[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Then the word of Jehovah of hosts came to me, saying,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Speak to all the people of the land and to the priests, saying, When you [xref]a[/xref]fasted and mourned in the fifth and seventh [i]months,[/i] even for these [xref]b[/xref]seventy years, was it at all for Me that you fasted?</text>
        <xref num="a">Zech. 8:19</xref>
        <xref num="b">Zech. 1:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And when you eat and when you drink, are you not the ones eating and are you not the ones drinking?</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Are not [i]these[/i] the words which Jehovah proclaimed by the former prophets when Jerusalem was inhabited and prosperous and [i]had[/i] cities round about her, when the [note]1[/note]Negev and the lowlands were inhabited?</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., the dry southern desert of Canaan.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And the word of Jehovah came to Zechariah, saying,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Thus speaks Jehovah of hosts, saying, Judge with judgment of truth, and show lovingkindness and compassion each to his brother;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And do not oppress the widow and the orphan, the stranger and the poor; and let none of you think evil in your hearts about his brother.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>But they refused to listen, and they turned a stubborn shoulder and closed their ears from hearing;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And they set their hearts like adamant so as not to hear the instruction and the words which Jehovah of hosts sent by His Spirit through the former prophets; therefore great wrath came from Jehovah of hosts.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And as He called and they would not hear, so they called and I would not hear, says Jehovah of hosts;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>But with a storm I [xref]a[/xref]scattered them away upon all the nations, whom they did not know. Thus the land is desolate behind them, so that no one passes through [i]it[/i] and no one returns [i]to it;[/i] for they have made the [xref]b[/xref]desirable land desolate.</text>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 4:27; 28:64; Ezek. 36:19; Zech. 2:6</xref>
        <xref num="b">Dan. 8:9</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="8">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[note]1[/note]And the word of Jehovah of hosts came, saying,</text>
        <note num="1">This chapter reveals the desire of Jehovah to restore Israel. This restoration will take place in the millennium ([link]Matt. 19:28[/link]; [link]Acts 3:21[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Thus says Jehovah of hosts, I am [xref]a[/xref]jealous for Zion with great jealousy; indeed, I am jealous for her with great wrath.</text>
        <xref num="a">Joel 2:18; Zech. 1:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Thus says Jehovah, I [xref]a[/xref]return to Zion, and I will dwell [xref]b[/xref]within Jerusalem; and Jerusalem will be called the [xref]c[/xref]City of Truth, and the [xref]d[/xref]mountain of Jehovah of hosts, the Holy Mountain.</text>
        <xref num="a">Zech. 1:16</xref>
        <xref num="b">Zech. 2:10</xref>
        <xref num="c">Isa. 1:21, 26</xref>
        <xref num="d">Isa. 2:2-3; 11:9; 66:20; Jer. 31:23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Thus says Jehovah of hosts, Yet again old men and old women will dwell in the streets of Jerusalem, each with his staff in his hand due to the multitude of [i]his[/i] days.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And the streets of the city will be full of boys and girls playing in its streets.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>Thus says Jehovah of hosts, If it seems too [note]1[/note]wonderful in the sight of the remnant of this people in those days, will it also be too wonderful in My sight? declares Jehovah of hosts.</text>
        <note num="1">The situation of Jerusalem in the restoration will be so pleasant that it will be wonderful both in the sight of the remnant of Israel and in the sight of Jehovah.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Thus says Jehovah of hosts, I am about to [xref]a[/xref]save My people from the land of the east and from the land of the going down of the sun.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 11:11-12; 43:5-6; Ezek. 37:21; Amos 9:14-15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And I will bring them, and they will dwell within Jerusalem; and they will be My [xref]a[/xref]people and I will be their God in [xref]b[/xref]truth and in righteousness.</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 30:22; 31:1, 33; Zech. 13:9</xref>
        <xref num="b">Jer. 4:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Thus says Jehovah of hosts, [note]1[/note]Let your hands be strong, you who in these days hear these words from the mouth of the prophets who were [i]there[/i] in the [xref]a[/xref]day when the foundation of the house of Jehovah of hosts, [i]that is,[/i] the temple, was laid so that it might be built.</text>
        <note num="1">This is a word encouraging the children of Israel to be strong and bold and to finish the work of rebuilding God's house. God wanted His people to see that His interest, desire, and burden were to finish the building of the temple as the center of His interests on earth. Likewise, God's burden in this age is to gain a people to know His heart, to realize His desire, and to be one with Him to build up the Body of Christ.</note>
        <xref num="a">Hag. 2:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>For before those days a man's [xref]a[/xref]wages amounted to nothing, and an animal's wages were nothing; and for him who went out or came in there was no peace, because of the adversary; for I set all men each against his neighbor.</text>
        <xref num="a">Hag. 1:6, 9-10; 2:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>But now I will not be to the remnant of this people as I was in the former days, declares Jehovah of hosts;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>For [i]there will be[/i] peace for the seed: The vine will give forth its [xref]a[/xref]fruit, and the land will give forth its produce, and the heavens will give their dew. And I will cause the remnant of this people to inherit all these things.</text>
        <xref num="a">Joel 2:22; Hag. 2:19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And just as you were a curse among the nations, O house of Judah and house of Israel, so will I save you, and you will be a blessing. Do not fear; let your hands be strong.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>For thus says Jehovah of hosts, Just as I intended to do harm to you when your fathers provoked Me to anger, says Jehovah of hosts, and I did not repent,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>So again I intend in these days to do good to Jerusalem and to the house of Judah; do not fear.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>These are the things which you shall do: Each man speak [xref]a[/xref]truth to his neighbor; judge with truth and the judgment of peace in your gates;</text>
        <xref num="a">Zech. 7:9; 8:19; Eph. 4:25</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And let none of you think evil in your hearts about his neighbor; and do not love a false oath; for all these are the things I hate, declares Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>Then the word of Jehovah of hosts came to me, saying,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>Thus says Jehovah of hosts, The fast of the fourth [i]month[/i] and the fast of the [xref]a[/xref]fifth [i]month[/i] and the fast of the [xref]b[/xref]seventh [i]month[/i] and the fast of the tenth [i]month[/i] will become joy and rejoicing and cheerful feasts to the house of Judah; therefore love truth and peace.</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 52:12-13</xref>
        <xref num="b">2 Kings 25:25; Jer. 41:1; Zech. 7:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>Thus says Jehovah of hosts, [note]1[/note]Peoples will again come, even the inhabitants of many cities;</text>
        <note num="1">In the restoration the Gentiles will come to Israel to entreat the favor, the grace, of Jehovah, and the children of Israel will be priests to them ([link]vv. 20-23[/link]; [link]Isa. 2:2-3[/link]; [link]61:6[/link]). After the Jews are saved at the Lord's coming back ([link]12:10[/link]; [link]Rom. 11:26-27[/link]), they will become the priests to teach all the repentant nations. By that time the entire nation of Israel will be a priesthood, thus fulfilling God's original intention expressed in [link]Exo. 19:6[/link]. They will teach the Gentiles, the nations, to know God's way and God's person, and they will teach them to worship and serve God. As priests, they will bring the nations into the presence of God that they may be enlightened, corrected, and favored with all the riches of God. The prophecy in [link]vv. 20-23[/link] was an encouraging word spoken to the children of Israel. See note [link]3[sup]2[/sup] in Isa. 2[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>And the inhabitants of one will go to another, saying, Let us go at once to entreat the favor of Jehovah and to seek Jehovah of hosts; [i]and the other:[/i] I will go too.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
        <text>Indeed, many peoples and strong nations will come to [xref]a[/xref]seek Jehovah of hosts in Jerusalem and to entreat the favor of Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 2:3; Micah 4:1-2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
        <text>Thus says Jehovah of hosts, In those days, from all the [note]1[/note]languages of the [xref]a[/xref]nations, ten men will take hold, indeed, they will take hold of the skirt of a Jewish man, saying, Let us go with you, for we have heard that God is with you.</text>
        <note num="1">In the millennium God will reverse the judgment on Babel ([link]Gen. 11:7-9[/link]) and deal with the problem caused by the different languages among the nations. What happened at Pentecost ([link]Acts 2:4-11[/link]) is a prefigure of what will take place during the age of the millennial kingdom.</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 60:3; 66:23; Zech. 2:11</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="9">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[note]1[/note]The burden of the word of Jehovah against the [note]2[/note]land of Hadrach, / And [xref]a[/xref]Damascus will be its resting place / (For Jehovah has an eye on man, / Especially on the tribes of Israel),</text>
        <note num="1">The visions in [link]chs. 1-6[/link] are mainly for consolation to the children of Israel, whereas the prophecies in [link]chs. 9-14[/link] are mainly for their encouragement. Both the consolation and the encouragement are Christ ([link]Luke 2:25[/link] and note 2). [link]Chapters 9-11[/link] speak of Christ's lowly first coming, whereas [link]chs. 12-14[/link] speak of Christ's victorious second coming.</note>
        <note num="2">The prophecy in [link]vv. 1-7[/link] concerns the destruction carried out on the nations around Judah by Alexander the Great, king of the Grecian Empire (336-323 B.C., with the influence of his four successors up to 44 B.C.), prophesied by Daniel as the abdomen and the thighs of the great human image in [link]Dan. 2:32[/link], as the third beast in [link]Dan. 7:6[/link], as the male goat in [link]Dan. 8:5[/link], and as a mighty king in [link]Dan. 11:3[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 17:1-14; Jer. 49:23-27; Amos 1:3-5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And Hamath also, [i]which[/i] borders on it; / Tyre and Sidon, because they are very wise.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>For [xref]a[/xref]Tyre built herself a stronghold / And heaped up silver like dust / And gold like the mire of the streets.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 23:1-18; Ezek. 26:1-28:19; Amos 1:9-10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>The Lord is about to take possession of her, / And He will strike her might in the sea, / And she will be consumed with fire.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>[xref]a[/xref]Ashkelon will see it and be afraid; / Gaza also, and it will writhe much in anguish; / And Ekron, for her expectation will have been confounded. / And the king will perish from Gaza, / And Ashkelon will not be inhabited.</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 47:5-7; Zeph. 2:4-7; Amos 1:7-8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And a mixed race will dwell in Ashdod, / And I will cut off the pride of the Philistines.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And I will remove his blood from his mouth / And his detestable things from between his teeth; / And he also will remain unto our God; / And he will be like a leader in Judah, / And Ekron will be like a Jebusite.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And I will [xref]a[/xref]encamp around My [note]1[/note]house because of an army, / Because of him who passes by and returns; / And no oppressor will pass over them any more; / For now I see with My eyes.</text>
        <note num="1">This verse reveals that during the attack of Alexander the Great, the Lord protected Jerusalem with the temple, which was His house. Although Alexander, a mighty king, caused damage to many nations around Judah, he did not cause much damage to Judah and Jerusalem, and he did not damage the temple at all. This was a sign of the restoration that would be brought in by the coming of Christ in [link]vv. 9-10[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 34:7; Zech. 2:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>[note]1[/note]Exult greatly, O [xref]a[/xref]daughter of Zion; / Shout, O [xref]b[/xref]daughter of Jerusalem! / Now your [xref]c[/xref]King comes to you. / He is righteous and bears salvation, / Lowly and riding upon a donkey, / Even upon a [xref]d[/xref]colt, the foal of a donkey,</text>
        <note num="1">The prophecy in [link]vv. 9-10[/link] is an insertion; [link]v. 11[/link] is the continuation of [link]v. 8[/link]. The prophecy in [link]v. 9[/link] reveals that Christ would come in a righteous way with salvation for God's people and that He would come as a King, but as a lowly King, a humiliated King, riding not on a majestic horse but on a donkey, even a colt of a donkey. This was fulfilled when Jesus Christ came into Jerusalem the last time ([link]Matt. 21:1-11[/link]). At that time Christ was temporarily welcomed by the people of Israel.[br/][br/]The prophecy concerning the coming of Christ in this verse and the prophecy concerning the millennial kingdom in [link]v. 10[/link] are inserted between the first part of the chapter, concerned with Alexander the Great, and the last part, concerned with Antiochus Epiphanes. This entire book indicates that the all-inclusive Christ, who is the center and the circumference, the centrality and the universality, of God's move to fulfill His economy on the earth, is intimately involved with human history and with the great human empires, especially the empires of Persia ([link]chs. 1-6[/link]), and Greece and Rome ([link]chs. 7-14[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 62:11; Zech. 2:10; Matt. 21:5; John 12:15</xref>
        <xref num="b">2 Kings 19:21; Isa. 37:22; Lam. 2:13; Micah 4:8; Zeph. 3:14; cf. S.S. 1:5; Luke 23:28</xref>
        <xref num="c">Jer. 23:5; 30:9; Matt. 2:2</xref>
        <xref num="d">Mark 11:7; Luke 19:33</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>[note]1[/note]And I will cut off the chariot from Ephraim / And the horse from Jerusalem, / And the battle bow will be cut off; / And He will speak peace unto the nations, / And His [xref]a[/xref]dominion will be from sea to sea / And from the [note]2[/note]River unto the ends of the earth.</text>
        <note num="1">The prophecy in this verse refers to the millennial kingdom, which will be the time of restoration ([link]Matt. 19:28[/link]; [link]Acts 3:21[/link]). In the millennium God will cause all warfare to cease ([link]Isa. 2:4[/link]) and will bring in peace and His eternal kingdom ([link]Rev. 11:15[/link]). This verse, coming immediately after the prophecy concerning Christ's coming in [link]v. 9[/link], indicates that if the people of Israel had welcomed Christ in His first coming, the kingdom of the heavens would have been set up on earth, and the age of restoration would have come at that time. However, when Christ came the first time, He was welcomed only temporarily and was ultimately rejected, detested to the uttermost, and put to death by being crucified. As a result, the restoration was suspended, and a time of judgment over the children of Israel entered in ([link]Matt. 23:37-24:2[/link]), a time that has lasted nearly twenty centuries. Therefore, Christ needs to come a second time, this time not riding a donkey but like lightning ([link]Matt. 24:27[/link]). Then peace and the eternal kingdom, as God's dominion, will be on the earth from sea to sea. This is the sequence according to the spiritual significance.</note>
        <note num="2">I.e., the Euphrates.</note>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 72:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>[note]1[/note]As for you also, because of the [xref]a[/xref]blood of your covenant, / I have [xref]b[/xref]released your captives from the pit, where there is no water.</text>
        <note num="1">The prophecy in [link]vv. 11-17[/link] concerns the victory of the Jewish Maccabean heroes over Antiochus Epiphanes, the king of Syria (175-164 B.C.), the kingdom of the north, prophesied by Daniel in [link]Dan. 8:9-14[/link], [link]23-25[/link] and [link]11:21-35[/link] (see notes there). Antiochus Epiphanes was a type of the coming Antichrist.</note>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 26:28; Mark 14:24; Luke 22:20</xref>
        <xref num="b">Isa. 42:7; 51:14; 61:1; Luke 4:18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>Turn to the stronghold, O prisoners with hope. / This very day I am declaring that I will restore [xref]a[/xref]double to you.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 61:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>For I will bend Judah for Myself, / And I will fill a bow with Ephraim; / And I will stir up your [xref]a[/xref]sons, O Zion, / Against your sons, O [note]1[/note]Javan; / And I will make you like a warrior's sword.</text>
        <note num="1">I.e., Greece. This is the key to understanding [link]vv. 11-17[/link]. The sons of Greece (Javan) are Antiochus and those with him, and the sons of Zion are the Maccabees. Thus, [link]v. 13[/link] prophecies that at the time of Antiochus Epiphanes, God would stir up His sons, the sons of Zion, against the sons of Greece.</note>
        <xref num="a">Dan. 11:32-34</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And Jehovah will appear above [note]1[/note]them, / And His arrow will go forth like lightning; / And the Lord Jehovah will blow the [xref]a[/xref]trumpet, / And He will go in the whirlwinds of the south.</text>
        <note num="1">In [link]vv. 14-15[/link] them and they refer to the Maccabees, who were to be defended by God.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. Isa. 27:13; 1 Cor. 15:52</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>Jehovah of hosts will [xref]a[/xref]defend them; / And they will devour and trample the sling stones. / And they will drink; they will be noisy as if with wine; / And they will be filled like a [i]sacrificial[/i] basin, / Like the corners of the altar.</text>
        <xref num="a">Zech. 12:8</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And Jehovah their God will save them in [note]1[/note]that day as the flock of His people, / For [i]they will be like[/i] the stones of a crown, sparkling in His land.</text>
        <note num="1">Referring to December 25, 165 B.C., the day when the Maccabees cleansed the temple after defeating Antiochus Epiphanes.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>For how [note]1[/note]great is their goodness, and how great their beauty! / Grain will make the young men flourish, / And new wine, the virgins.</text>
        <note num="1">This word was spoken in congratulations to the Maccabees for their victory.</note>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="10">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Ask [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]rain of Jehovah / At the time of spring rain, / [i]Of[/i] Jehovah who makes the lightning, / And He will give them showers of rain, / To everyone herbage in the field.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Rain[/i] here signifies blessing. Here the Lord encourages His people to ask Him for His abundant blessing at the time when He is favorable toward them.</note>
        <xref num="a">Deut. 11:14; James 5:7</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>For the [note]1[/note]teraphim have spoken [note]2[/note]vanity, / And the diviners have seen a lie / And have spoken false dreams; / They comforted in vain. / Therefore [i]the people[/i] have wandered like sheep; / They are afflicted because there is [xref]a[/xref]no shepherd.</text>
        <note num="1">Images or false gods kept in the people's homes.</note>
        <note num="2">Or, iniquity.</note>
        <xref num="a">1 Kings 22:17; Ezek. 34:5; Matt. 9:36</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>My anger is kindled against the shepherds, / And I will punish the [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]male goats; / For Jehovah of hosts has [note]2[/note]visited His flock, the house of Judah, / And will make them like His [note]3[/note]horse of majesty in battle.</text>
        <note num="1">The male goats are the improper shepherds. The proper shepherds are the prophets, the proper ones who speak for God.</note>
        <note num="2">Jehovah's visiting His people was His coming to them in the man Jesus ([link]Matt. 1:23[/link]) to be the real Shepherd of His flock ([link]Matt. 2:6[/link]; [link]9:36[/link]; [link]John 10:2-4[/link], [link]11[/link], [link]14[/link]).</note>
        <note num="3">After being visited by the Lord as the Shepherd, every weak sheep among God's people becomes a horse of majesty. The situation of God's people in [link]vv. 3-12[/link] is the result of Jehovah's loving visitation.</note>
        <xref num="a">Ezek. 34:17; Matt. 25:33</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>From [note]1[/note]him will come forth the cornerstone, from him the [xref]a[/xref]peg, / From him the battle bow, / From him every ruler together.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]Him[/i] (four times) refers to Judah in [link]v. 3[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 22:23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And they will be as mighty men trampling [i]their enemies[/i] / In the mire of the streets in the battle; / And they will fight, for Jehovah is with them; / And the riders of horses will be put to shame.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And I will strengthen the house of Judah, / And I will save the house of Joseph; / And I will [xref]a[/xref]bring them back, for I have had compassion on them; / And they will be as though I had not rejected them; / For I am Jehovah their God, and I will answer them.</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 3:18; Ezek. 37:21; 39:25</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And [i]they of[/i] Ephraim will be like a mighty man, / And their hearts will rejoice as if with wine; / Indeed, their children will see [i]it[/i] and rejoice; / Their heart will exult in Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>I will whistle for them and gather them, for I have redeemed them; / And they will [xref]a[/xref]multiply as they have multiplied.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 49:19; Ezek. 36:37</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And I will [xref]a[/xref]sow them among the peoples; and in distant lands they will / [xref]b[/xref]remember Me; / And they will live with their children and return.</text>
        <xref num="a">Hosea 2:23</xref>
        <xref num="b">Deut. 30:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>I will also bring them back from the land of [xref]a[/xref]Egypt / And gather them out of Assyria; / And to the land of Gilead and Lebanon I will bring them; / And there will not be [i]enough room[/i] found for them.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 11:11, 16; Hosea 11:11</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And He will pass through the sea [i]of[/i] distress / And strike the waves in the sea, / And all the depths of the Nile will [xref]a[/xref]dry up; / And the pride of Assyria will be brought down, / And the scepter of Egypt will depart.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 11:15-16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And [note]1[/note]I will strengthen them in Jehovah, / And they will [xref]a[/xref]walk about in His name, / Declares Jehovah.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]I[/i] here refers to Jehovah, indicating that Jehovah will strengthen His people in Himself. They will then walk about in His name, i.e., in His person as the reality of His name ([link]Matt. 28:19[/link] and note 5). To be in God's name is to be one with God in our daily walk by our living, walking, and having our being in God's name (cf. [link]Col. 3:17[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Micah 4:5</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="11">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Open your doors, O Lebanon, / That the [note]1[/note]fire may devour your cedars.</text>
        <note num="1">[link]Verses 1-3[/link] reveal the destruction carried out in the neighborhood of Israel by the Roman Empire. The fire here refers to the coming of the Romans to devastate Lebanon and Jordan.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>Howl, O fir tree, for the cedar has fallen, / Because the majestic [i]trees[/i] are devastated. / Howl, O oaks of Bashan, / For the impenetrable forest is brought down.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>The sound of the howling of shepherds! / For their majesty is devastated. / The sound of the roaring of young lions! / For the pride of Jordan is devastated.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>Thus says Jehovah my God, Shepherd the flock of slaughter,</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Whose owners slaughter them and are not punished; and they who sell them say, Blessed be Jehovah, for I am rich; and their own shepherds do not spare them.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>For I will no longer spare the inhabitants of the land, declares Jehovah; but I am about to cause each man to fall into his [note]1[/note]neighbor's hand and into the hand of his king; and they will strike the land, and I will not deliver them from their hand.</text>
        <note num="1">The neighbor here refers to the subordinate kings and governors of the Roman Empire, such as Herod and Pilate, in the region of Palestine, and the king is Caesar.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>So [note]1[/note]I shepherded the flock of slaughter, and thereby the afflicted of the flock. And I took to myself two staffs; one I called [note]2[/note]Favor, and the other I called Bonds; and I shepherded the flock.</text>
        <note num="1">[i]I[/i] here refers to Jehovah, as indicated by the previous verse. Jehovah as Jesus came to feed His people, who were about to be slaughtered, the afflicted of the flock.</note>
        <note num="2">Jehovah as Jesus brought two staffs &amp;#8212; Favor and Bonds. Favor refers to grace, and Bonds refers to being bound into oneness. Jesus came as the Shepherd to feed God's flock with grace so that they might have oneness.</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>Then I destroyed the [note]1[/note]three shepherds in one month; for my soul was impatient with them, and their soul also detested me.</text>
        <note num="1">The three shepherds here are the priests, the elders, and the scribes ([link]Matt. 16:21[/link]). Jehovah as Jesus set aside the three shepherds and destroyed them, and their souls detested Him. The Lord Jesus as the proper Shepherd was rejected, leaving the children of Israel as a flock without any shepherd (cf. [link]Matt. 9:36[/link]). See note [link]15[sup]1[/sup][/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>Then I said, I will not shepherd you. What is to die will die, and what is to be destroyed will be destroyed, and those who are left will each eat one another's flesh.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And I took my staff, Favor, and I [note]1[/note]broke it in pieces so as to break my covenant which I had made with all the peoples.</text>
        <note num="1">This indicates that the Lord annulled the covenant which God made through Moses, leaving the people without a covenant to cover them. He thus took away the grace (favor).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And it was broken in that day; and thus the afflicted of the flock, who watched me, knew that it was the word of Jehovah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And I said to them, If it is good in your sight, give me my wages; but if not, [note]1[/note]do not bother. So they weighed out my wages, [note]2[/note][xref]a[/xref]thirty [i]pieces[/i] of silver.</text>
        <note num="1">Lit., cease.</note>
        <note num="2">[link]Verses 12-13[/link] reveal that the Messiah, as the proper Shepherd of Israel, was detested, attacked, rejected, and sold for thirty pieces of silver, the price of a slave ([link]Exo. 21:32[/link]). What is prophesied here was fulfilled in the Gospels ([link]Matt. 26:14-15[/link]; [link]27:3-10[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 26:15; cf. Exo. 21:32</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And Jehovah said to me, Throw it to the [xref]a[/xref]potter, that magnificent price that I am priced with by them. So I took the thirty [i]pieces[/i] of silver and threw them to the potter, into the house of Jehovah.</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 27:9-10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>Then I [note]1[/note]broke my second staff, Bonds, in pieces, so as to break the brotherhood [xref]a[/xref]between Judah and Israel.</text>
        <note num="1">This indicates that the binding love among the people of Israel also was taken away (see note [link]10[sup]1[/sup][/link]). As a result, the nation was divided and full of inner fighting ([link]v. 9[/link]). From the day of Christ's crucifixion there has not been any oneness among the Jews. Although those in the northern kingdom, Israel, and the southern kingdom, Judah, were brothers, the brotherhood among them has been broken because the binding love has been broken. This took place while they were living under the oppression of the Roman Empire.</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 9:21; cf. Ezek. 37:16-19</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And Jehovah said to me, Again, take the equipment of a [note]1[/note]foolish shepherd.</text>
        <note num="1">The priests, the elders, and the scribes as the evil shepherds were annulled ([link]v. 8a[/link]), and Jesus as the proper Shepherd was crucified, rejected to the uttermost ([link]vv. 8b[/link], [link]12-13[/link]). Therefore, the children of Israel were left to the foolish and worthless shepherds, who would not take care of them ([link]vv. 15-17[/link]). After the crucifixion of Christ, there was no proper leadership among the people of Israel, and they were all scattered ([link]Matt. 26:31[/link]). They fought with one another, devouring one another. The foolish, worthless shepherds who rose up among them caused them further suffering. This kind of situation allowed Titus, the Roman prince, to devastate the entire country of Judah in A.D. 70 ([link]Matt. 21:33-41[/link] and note 41[sup]1[/sup]).[br/][br/]The center of the prophecies in [link]chs. 9-11[/link] is Christ as the rejected Messiah. As the coming Savior and Redeemer, Christ came and entered into Jerusalem as the King in a lowly form ([link]9:9-10[/link]). At first, He was welcomed by the people, but later, under the influence of the elders, priests, and scribes, they changed their mind and detested Him ([link]v. 8b[/link]). The Lord Jesus was sold, judged, sentenced, and put on the cross to die ([link]vv. 12-13[/link]). Thus, the Messiah, who was welcomed temporarily, was utterly rejected. As a result, the people of Israel were divided, persecuted by the Roman Empire, and scattered throughout the earth ([link]vv. 14-17[/link]).</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>For I am about to raise up a shepherd in the land who will not visit those who are perishing, nor seek the scattered, nor heal what is broken, nor sustain what stands, but will devour the flesh of the fat [i]ones[/i] and tear off their hooves.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>Woe to the worthless [xref]a[/xref]shepherd, / Who abandons the flock! / The sword [i]will fall[/i] on his arm / And on his right eye. / His arm will be utterly withered, / And his right eye will be totally darkened.</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 23:1; Ezek. 34:2; John 10:12-13</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="12">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>[note]1[/note]The burden of the word of Jehovah concerning Israel. [i]Thus[/i] declares Jehovah, who [xref]a[/xref]stretches forth the heavens and lays the foundations of the earth and forms the [note]2[/note][xref]b[/xref]spirit of man within him,</text>
        <note num="1">[link]Chapters 12-14[/link] of this book unveil Christ as the Messiah returning to be enthroned as the King not only over Israel but also over the whole world. His first coming, described in [link]chs. 9-11[/link], was humble and intimate; His coming back, described in [link]chs. 12-14[/link], will be with power and authority.</note>
        <note num="2">In His creation God made three crucial, equally important items &amp;#8212; the heavens, the earth, and the spirit of man. The heavens are for the earth, the earth is for man, and man was created by God with a spirit that he may contact God, receive God, worship God, live God, fulfill God's purpose for God, and be one with God. In His economy God planned to have Christ as the centrality and universality of His move on earth. For His chosen people, who would care for Him as the Creator and as the Redeemer, there was the need for Him to create a receiving organ so that they would have the capacity to receive all that God had planned for Christ to be. Hence, this book charges us to pay full attention to our human spirit, that we may receive the Christ revealed in this book and may understand all that is revealed therein concerning Him ([link]Eph. 1:17-18a[/link]; [link]3:5[/link]). See notes [link]7[sup]5[/sup] in Gen. 2[/link], [link]5[sup]1[/sup] in Isa. 42[/link], [link]24[sup]4[/sup] in John 4[/link], and [link]23[sup]2[/sup] in Phil. 4[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Job 9:8; Psa. 104:2; Isa. 40:22; 42:5; 44:24; 45:12, 18; 48:13; 51:13</xref>
        <xref num="b">Gen. 2:7; Num. 16:22; Eccl. 12:7; 1 Cor. 2:11; 1 Thes. 5:23; Heb. 4:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>I am about to make Jerusalem a [xref]a[/xref]cup of reeling to all the surrounding peoples; and when [i]what happens[/i] in [note]1[/note]siege is upon Jerusalem, it will be upon Judah as well.</text>
        <note num="1">Chapters 12-14 prophesy concerning Israel's destiny in the great war of Armageddon, in their household salvation, and in the millennium. The war of Armageddon will be the greatest war among mankind. This war will take place at the end of the three and a half years of the great tribulation ([link]Matt. 24:21[/link]; [link]Dan. 7:25[/link]; [link]12:7[/link]; [link]Rev. 11:2[/link]; [link]13:5[/link]). Although this war will be motivated by Antichrist with the intention of destroying Israel, it will be waged by Satan through his human followers as his earthly army, against God with His saints as His heavenly army ([link]14:2-5[/link]; [link]Joel 3:11[/link]; [link]Rev. 16:13-14[/link]; [link]17:14[/link]; [link]19:14[/link]). Antichrist, the embodiment of Satan, will be the commander of Satan's army, and Christ, the embodiment of God, will be the Commander of God's army. In this divine war Christ will destroy Antichrist by the breath of His mouth and bring him to nothing by the manifestation of His coming ([link]2 Thes. 2:8[/link]). This war will be the great winepress of the fury of God trodden by Christ at His coming back to judge the world ([link]Isa. 63:1-6[/link]; [link]Rev. 14:17-20[/link]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 51:17, 22-23</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And in that [xref]a[/xref]day I will make Jerusalem a burdensome stone to all the peoples; all who burden themselves with her will be cut up. Indeed all the nations of the earth will be [xref]b[/xref]gathered against her.</text>
        <xref num="a">Zech. 12:4, 6, 8-9, 11; 13:1; 14:4, 6, 8-9, 13</xref>
        <xref num="b">Joel 3:2, 9-12; Zech. 14:2-3; Rev. 16:14; Micah 4:11-13</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>In that day, declares Jehovah, I will strike every horse with bewilderment and its [xref]a[/xref]rider with madness; and I will open My eyes upon the house of Judah and will strike every horse of the peoples with blindness.</text>
        <xref num="a">Psa. 76:6; Ezek. 38:4; Zech. 10:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>Then the leaders of Judah will say in their heart, The inhabitants of Jerusalem, by Jehovah of hosts their God, are my strength.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>In that day I will make the leaders of Judah like a [xref]a[/xref]fire pot on wood and like a torch of fire among sheaves, and they will consume all the surrounding peoples on the right and on the left. And Jerusalem will dwell again in her own place, in Jerusalem.</text>
        <xref num="a">Obad. 18</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>And Jehovah will save the tents of Judah first, so that the beauty of the house of David and the beauty of the inhabitants of Jerusalem may not be magnified above Judah.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>In that day Jehovah will [xref]a[/xref]defend the inhabitants of Jerusalem; and he who is feeble among them in that day will be like David, and the house of David will be like God, like the [note]1[/note]Angel of Jehovah before them.</text>
        <note num="1">Here [i]Angel of Jehovah[/i] is in apposition to [i]God[/i] earlier in the verse (cf. [link]Exo. 3:2-6[/link] and note 2[sup]1[/sup]).</note>
        <xref num="a">Zech. 2:5; 9:8, 15-16; Joel 3:16-17</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And in that day I will seek to destroy all the nations that [xref]a[/xref]come against Jerusalem.</text>
        <xref num="a">Zech. 12:2; Rev. 16:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>And I will [xref]a[/xref]pour out on the house of David and on the inhabitants of Jerusalem the [note]1[/note][xref]b[/xref]Spirit of grace and of supplications; and they will [note]2[/note]look upon Me, whom [note]3[/note]they have [note]4[/note][xref]c[/xref]pierced; and they will wail over Him with wailing as for an [note]5[/note]only [xref]d[/xref]son and cry bitterly over Him with bitter crying as for a [note]5[/note]firstborn son.</text>
        <note num="1">In Acts 2 God poured out His Spirit upon all flesh, and three thousand were saved ([link]Acts 2:17[/link], [link]41[/link]). But when God pours out the Spirit of grace upon the inhabitants of Jerusalem, many thousands of Israel, even the entire race of Israel alive at that time, will be saved ([link]Rom. 11:26-27[/link]). The Spirit of grace here is in contrast to the Spirit of power in [link]Acts 1:8[/link] and [link]2:1-4[/link]. The Spirit of power is to strengthen us, but the Spirit of grace is to bring us into the enjoyment of the Triune God. In Acts 2, at the beginning of the age of grace, the church age, the Spirit was mainly the Spirit of power, but in this verse, at the end, the consummation, of the age of grace, the Spirit will be mainly the Spirit of grace for the enjoyment of the Triune God. The Jews on the day of Pentecost were stubborn and hard; hence, the Spirit of power was poured out to inspire them to repent. But the half of the inhabitants of Jerusalem that survive the attack of Antichrist and his armies ([link]14:2[/link]) will have lost their taste for everything other than God and will have already repented. Therefore, the Spirit of grace will be poured out upon them so that they can receive the Triune God as their enjoyment.</note>
        <note num="2">At the end of the war of Armageddon, Christ will come to earth, and the remnant of Israel will look on Him whom they have pierced ([link]John 19:34[/link], [link]37[/link]; [link]Rev. 1:7[/link]), will repent and wail, and will believe in Christ and receive Him. In this way all Israel will be saved ([link]Rom. 11:26-27[/link]). This will be the household salvation rendered to Israel by God.</note>
        <note num="3">Although it was their forefathers who pierced the Lord Jesus, God counts that as something done by these repentant ones.</note>
        <note num="4">The piercing of Christ is the foundation of redemption ([link]John 19:34[/link]). Apart from Christ's being pierced, there is no base for our redemption.</note>
        <note num="5">Repentant Israel will wail over Christ as the only Son of God ([link]John 1:18[/link]; [link]3:16[/link]) and will cry bitterly over Him as the firstborn Son of God ([link]Rom. 8:29[/link]; [link]Heb. 1:6a[/link]). Christ's being the only begotten Son is for us to be redeemed and to receive eternal life ([link]John 3:14-16[/link]). Christ's becoming the firstborn Son through His death and resurrection ([link]Rom. 1:3-4[/link]) is for us to become sons of God as heirs to inherit all the riches of what God is, that is, to receive, participate in, and enjoy all the riches of the Triune God ([link]Rom. 8:14-17[/link]; [link]Gal. 3:26[/link], [link]29[/link]). In their repentance Israel will realize that as the only begotten Son Christ has redeemed them and has brought them eternal life and that as the firstborn Son He has made them heirs to inherit the riches of the Triune God as their enjoyment.</note>
        <xref num="a">Ezek. 39:29; Joel 2:28</xref>
        <xref num="b">Heb. 10:29</xref>
        <xref num="c">Psa. 22:16; John 19:34, 37; Rev. 1:7</xref>
        <xref num="d">Jer. 6:26; Amos 8:10</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>In that day there will be great [xref]a[/xref]wailing in Jerusalem, like the wailing of Hadad-rimmon in the valley of [xref]b[/xref]Megiddon.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Chron. 35:24</xref>
        <xref num="b">2 Kings 23:29</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And the land will [xref]a[/xref]wail, every family by itself: the [note]1[/note]family of the house of David by itself, and their wives by themselves; the family of the house of [xref]b[/xref]Nathan by itself, and their wives by themselves;</text>
        <note num="1">Zechariah uses three kinds of families &amp;#8212; the royal family of David (David and Nathan), the family of the priesthood (Levi), and the family of an evil man (Shimei, who cursed David &amp;#8212; [link]2 Sam. 16:5-8[/link]) &amp;#8212; as illustrations. All those who look upon Christ, the pierced One, with a repentant spirit, will wail over Him.</note>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 24:30; Rev. 1:7</xref>
        <xref num="b">2 Sam. 5:14; Luke 3:31</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>The family of the house of Levi by itself, and their wives by themselves; the family of the Shimeites by itself, and their wives by themselves;</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>All the families that remain, every family by itself, and their wives by themselves.</text>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="13">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>In that day there will be an [note]1[/note]opened [xref]a[/xref]fountain for the house of David and for the inhabitants of Jerusalem, [xref]b[/xref]for sin and for impurity.</text>
        <note num="1">This opened fountain is Christ's pierced side ([link]John 19:34[/link], [link]37[/link]), which was opened for the accomplishing of redemption.</note>
        <xref num="a">John 19:34</xref>
        <xref num="b">Ezek. 36:25; Heb. 9:14; 1 Pet. 1:19; Rev. 1:5</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>And in that day, declares Jehovah of hosts, I will cut off the names of the idols from the land, and they will no longer be remembered; and I will also cause the prophets and the unclean spirit to pass from the land.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>And if anyone still prophesies, his father and mother, who begot him, will say to him, You shall not live, for you have spoken falsely in the name of Jehovah; and his father and mother, who begot him, will pierce him through when he prophesies.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And in that day the prophets will each be ashamed of his vision when he prophesies; and they will not wear a [xref]a[/xref]hairy garment in order to deceive.</text>
        <xref num="a">2 Kings 1:8; Matt. 3:4</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>But He will say, I am [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]no prophet; I am a tiller of the ground; for a man sold Me in My youth.</text>
        <note num="1">[link]Verses 2-4[/link] speak of God's causing the false prophets to pass from the land. This cleared the way for Christ to come in as the real Prophet. However, Christ said that He was not a prophet but a tiller of the ground. This means that He was not the kind of prophet, a false prophet, mentioned in the preceding verses. Christ came to be the real Prophet ([link]Matt. 13:57[/link]; [link]Deut. 18:15-19[/link], cf. [link]Acts 3:22[/link]) but was rejected and wounded in His side in the house of Israel, His relatives in the flesh ([link]vv. 5-6[/link]; [link]12:10[/link]). That wound became the base of their redemption, which Christ accomplished for them in His death.</note>
        <xref num="a">Amos 7:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And [i]someone[/i] will say to Him, What are these [xref]a[/xref]wounds between Your arms? And He will say, Those with which I was wounded in the house of those who [note]1[/note]love Me.</text>
        <note num="1">The children of Israel killed Christ, but in this sweet word Christ counts their action as wounds from those who love Him.</note>
        <xref num="a">John 19:34, 37; cf. Psa. 22:16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>Awake, O sword, against My Shepherd, / And against the man [i]who is[/i] My [note]1[/note]Fellow, / Declares Jehovah of hosts.[separator][xref]a[/xref]Strike the Shepherd, / That the sheep may be [xref]b[/xref]scattered; / And I will turn My hand upon the [note]2[/note]little ones.</text>
        <note num="1">Christ, the Fellow of Jehovah, came as the God-sent Shepherd to the children of Israel ([link]11:7[/link]; [link]Matt. 9:36[/link]; [link]John 10:11[/link]) but was attacked unto death by them ([link]v. 7a[/link]; [link]Matt. 26:31[/link]; [link]Acts 2:23[/link]). As a man Christ was both a relative of the children of Israel and a Fellow of Jehovah. As He was hanging on the cross, His relatives wounded Him ([link]v. 6[/link]), and God called in the sword to strike Him.</note>
        <note num="2">[i]Little ones[/i] here refers to the people of Israel. This indicates that God reacted to the rejection of Christ by the children of Israel and turned His hand upon them as the little ones by punishing them through Titus the Roman prince and his army in A.D. 70 and scattering them into the nations to be despised, humiliated, persecuted, and destroyed throughout the age of grace until today ([link]Matt. 21:41a[/link]; [link]23:38[/link]; [link]24:2[/link]). This is God's sovereign preparation of a people to receive the Redeemer with His redemption and His salvation. See notes [link chapter="12"]10[sup]1[/sup][/link] and [link]10[sup]2[/sup] in ch. 12[/link].</note>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 26:31; Mark 14:27</xref>
        <xref num="b">John 16:32</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And in all the land, declares Jehovah, / [note]1[/note]Two parts in it will be cut off [i]and[/i] will die, / But the third part will be left in it.</text>
        <note num="1">In the great tribulation at the consummation of the present age, in all the land of Israel two-thirds of the people will be cut off, slaughtered, by Antichrist in his persecution of the Jews ([link]Rev. 11:2[/link]; [link]13:7[/link]). One-third of the remnant will be left in the land and will be brought through fire and refined like silver and tried like gold by the persecution of Antichrist ([link]vv. 8b-9a[/link]). These will be those who are written in the book as the secret record ([link]Dan. 12:1b[/link]). They will call on the Lord's name, and the Lord will answer them. The Lord will say that they are His people, and they will say that the Lord is their God ([link]v. 9b[/link]). They will be saved into the enjoyment of the riches of the Triune God, first in the millennium to be the priests to teach the nations ([link]8:20-23[/link]; [link]Isa. 2:3[/link]) and then in the New Jerusalem to participate in all the blessings God has ordained in eternity and for eternity (see [link]Rev. 21:12b[/link] and note 4, par. 2). This is the household salvation to Israel ([link]Rom. 11:26-27[/link]). See note [link]1[sup]3[/sup] in Dan. 12[/link].</note>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And I will bring the third part through [xref]a[/xref]fire / And [xref]b[/xref]refine them as silver is refined / And try them as gold is tried. / They will call on My name, / And I will answer them; / I will say, They are My [xref]c[/xref]people, / And they will say, Jehovah is my God.</text>
        <xref num="a">cf. 1 Cor. 3:13</xref>
        <xref num="b">Isa. 48:10; Mal. 3:2-3</xref>
        <xref num="c">Psa. 144:15; Jer. 30:22; Ezek. 11:20; Hosea 2:23</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="14">
        <verse num="1">
        <text>Indeed a day is coming for Jehovah when the spoil [i]taken[/i] from you will be divided among you.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
        <text>For I will [xref]a[/xref]gather all the nations against Jerusalem to battle; and the city will be captured, and the houses plundered, and the women ravished; and [note]1[/note]half of the city will go forth into captivity, but the rest of the people will not be cut off from the city.</text>
        <note num="1">In the great tribulation Antichrist and his armies will slaughter two-thirds of the Jews ([link]13:8[/link] and note). Of the one-third remaining in the land, most will probably be in the area of Jerusalem. Out of this one-third, half the city will be captured by Antichrist. In His mercy God will preserve the remaining half. Antichrist will attempt to destroy them also; however, as revealed in [link]vv. 3-7[/link], Jehovah as Christ will come with His saints ([link]vv. 3[/link], [link]5[/link]) and go forth to fight against and defeat Antichrist and his followers, the nations ([link]Joel 3:11[/link]; [link]Rev. 17:14[/link]; [link]19:11-21[/link]). This will result in Israel's household salvation ([link]Rom. 11:26-27[/link]). See [link]12:8-10[/link] and notes.</note>
        <xref num="a">Joel 3:2; Rev. 16:14</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
        <text>Then Jehovah will go forth and [xref]a[/xref]fight against those nations, as when He fights in a day of battle.</text>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 14:14; Deut. 1:30; cf. Joel 3:16; Hag. 2:21-22</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
        <text>And His [note]1[/note]feet will stand in that day on the [xref]a[/xref]Mount of Olives, which is before Jerusalem on the east; and the Mount of Olives will be split at its middle toward the east and toward the west into a very great valley, so that half of the mountain will remove to the north and half of it to the south.</text>
        <note num="1">In fulfillment of [link]Acts 1:11[/link] the feet of Jehovah as Christ will stand in that day on the Mount of Olives.</note>
        <xref num="a">Ezek. 11:23; Acts 1:11-12; Matt. 21:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
        <text>And you will flee into the valley of My mountains, for the valley of the mountains will reach unto Azel; yes, you will flee, just as you fled before the [xref]a[/xref]earthquake in the days of Uzziah the king of Judah. And Jehovah my God will [xref]b[/xref]come, [i]and[/i] all the saints with [note]1[/note]Him.</text>
        <note num="1">Some MSS read, You.</note>
        <xref num="a">Amos 1:1</xref>
        <xref num="b">Matt. 16:27; 24:30-31; 25:31; Mark 8:38; Jude 14; Rev. 19:11-16</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
        <text>And in that day there will be [xref]a[/xref]no light; [note]1[/note]the shining ones will withdraw.</text>
        <note num="1">The shining ones here are the sun, the moon, and the stars. The things that take place in [link]vv. 6-7[/link] indicate that God will change a number of things in the universe in order to judge the evil human beings and to save His elect.</note>
        <xref num="a">Joel 3:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
        <text>For it will be a [i]kind of[/i] day [xref]a[/xref]known only to Jehovah, neither day nor night; but at evening time there will be light.</text>
        <xref num="a">Matt. 24:36; Mark 13:32</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
        <text>And in that day [note]1[/note]living [xref]a[/xref]waters will go forth from Jerusalem; half of them toward the [note]2[/note]eastern sea and half of them toward the [note]3[/note]western sea; it will be there in summer and in winter.</text>
        <note num="1">In the millennium there will be no thirst, for living waters will go forth from Jerusalem. This is similar to the record in [link]Ezek. 47:1-2[/link].</note>
        <note num="2">I.e., the Dead Sea.</note>
        <note num="3">I.e., the Mediterranean Sea.</note>
        <xref num="a">Ezek. 47:1; Joel 3:18; Rev. 22:1</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
        <text>And Jehovah will be [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]King over all the earth; and in that day Jehovah will be the one [i]God[/i] and His name the one [i]name.[/i]</text>
        <note num="1">In the millennium Jehovah as Christ will be King over all the earth ([link]9:10b[/link]; [link]Psa. 72:8[/link]), and He will be the one God and His name the one name.</note>
        <xref num="a">Dan. 2:44; Rev. 11:15</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
        <text>All the land will be changed into a plain from Geba to Rimmon south of Jerusalem; and [i]Jerusalem[/i] will be raised and will dwell in her place, from Benjamin's Gate to the place of the First Gate to the Corner Gate, and [i]from[/i] the Tower of [xref]a[/xref]Hananel to the king's winepresses.</text>
        <xref num="a">Neh. 3:1; 12:39; Jer. 31:38</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
        <text>And [i]people[/i] will dwell in her, and there will be [xref]a[/xref]no more curse, for Jerusalem will [xref]b[/xref]dwell securely.</text>
        <xref num="a">Jer. 31:40; Rev. 22:3</xref>
        <xref num="b">Jer. 23:6</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
        <text>And this will be the plague with which Jehovah will strike all the peoples who have fought against Jerusalem: Their flesh will rot while they are standing on their feet, and their eyes will rot in their sockets, and their tongue will rot in their mouth.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
        <text>And in that day a great panic from Jehovah will be among them; and each will seize his neighbor's hand, and his hand will rise up against his neighbor's hand.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
        <text>And Judah will also fight at Jerusalem; and the wealth of all the surrounding nations will be gathered together, gold and silver and garments, in great abundance.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
        <text>And as this plague is, so will the plague be on the horse, the mule, the camel, the donkey, and all the cattle that are in those camps.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
        <text>And everyone left from all the nations that went forth against Jerusalem will go up from year to year to [xref]a[/xref]worship the King, Jehovah of hosts, and to keep the [xref]b[/xref]Feast of Tabernacles.</text>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 60:6-7, 9; 66:23</xref>
        <xref num="b">Lev. 23:34, 43; Neh. 8:14; Hosea 12:9; John 7:2</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
        <text>And whichever of the families of the earth does [xref]a[/xref]not go up to Jerusalem to worship the King, Jehovah of hosts, upon them there will be [note]1[/note]no rain.</text>
        <note num="1">Because the present age is the age of grace, God sends rain on the just and the unjust alike ([link]Matt. 5:45[/link]). However, the coming age will be the age of righteousness. Those who do not go up to Jerusalem to worship the King and to keep the Feast of Tabernacles will not receive rain.</note>
        <xref num="a">Isa. 60:12</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
        <text>And if the family of Egypt does not go up and enter, there will be no [i]rain[/i] upon them; there will be the plague with which Jehovah strikes the nations that do not go up to keep the Feast of Tabernacles.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
        <text>This will be the sin of Egypt and the sin of all the nations that do not go up to keep the Feast of Tabernacles.</text>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
        <text>In that day on the horses' bells will be, [xref]a[/xref]Holiness to Jehovah; and the [note]1[/note]pots in the house of Jehovah will be like the basins before the altar.</text>
        <note num="1">Pots are small, whereas the basins are large; but in the millennium the pots in the house of God will be as large as the basins before the altar.</note>
        <xref num="a">Exo. 28:36; Isa. 23:18; Jer. 2:3</xref>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
        <text>Indeed every pot in Jerusalem and in Judah will be holiness to Jehovah of hosts; and all those who sacrifice will come and take of them and boil in them; and there will never again be a [note]1[/note][xref]a[/xref]Canaanite in the house of Jehovah of hosts in that day.</text>
        <note num="1">Or, merchant.</note>
        <xref num="a">cf. Isa. 35:8; Joel 3:17; Rev. 21:27; 22:15</xref>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    </chapters>
</book>
