<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>As a lily growing out of a bramble bush</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Praise of the Lord&amp;mdash;His Incarnation</category>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="1937-1998" biolink="">Howard Higashi</author>
    <composer biodate="1937-1998" biolink="">Howard Higashi</composer>
  </creators>
  <hymncode>5611123332165</hymncode>
  <key>F Major</key>
  <time>3/4</time>
  <tempo>130</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - | C - - | C - - | F - - | C - - | C - - | Am - - | Dm - - | G - - | C - - | C7 - - | F - - | Dm - - | C/G - - | G - - | F - - | C - - | C - - | C - - | C - - | F - - | C - - | C - - | Am - - | Dm - - | G - - | C - - | C7 - - | F - - | Dm - - | C/G - - | G - - | F - - | C - - | C - - | C - - | C - - | F - - | C - - | C - - | Am - - | Dm - - | G - - | C - - | C7 - - | F - - | Dm - - | C/G - - | G - - | F - - | C - F/C | C - - |</chords>
  <melody>| 0 - 5_./ 6_./ | 1 1 1/ 2/ | 3 - 3/ 3/ | 2( 1) 6_. | 5_. - 3/ 4/ | 5 5 5/ 5/ | 5 4 3 | 2 - 1 (break) | 7_. - 5_./ 6_./ | 1 1 1/ 2/ | 3 - 2/ 1/ | 6( - 5) | 4 - 3/ 2/ | 3 - 4/( 3/) | 2 - 5_./ 5_./ | 6_. 1 2 | 1( - - (break) | 1) - (Verse_2) 5_./ 6_./ | 1/ 1/ 1 1 | 3 - 3/ 3/ | 2 1 6_. | 5_. - | 3/ 4/ 5 5 5 | 5 4 3 | 2 2 1 (break) | 7_. - 5_./ 6_./ | 1 1 1 | 3 - 2/ 1/ | 6 6 5 | 4 - 3/ 2/ | 3 3 4 | 2 5_. 5_. | 6_. 1 2 | 1( - - | 1) - 0 (break) | (Chorus) 5 - 6 | 5 3 2 | 1 - 6_. | 5_. - - | 1 - 1 | 3 5 6/ 5/ | 2 - 3 | 2 - - (break) | 5 - 6 | 5 3 2 | 1. 7_./ 1 | 4 - 1/ 2/ | 3 3 4/ 3/ | 2 - 5_./ 5_./ | 6_.( 1) 2 | 1( - - | 1) - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>As a li -- ly grow -- ing out of a bram -- ble bush; As a bright star shin -- ing forth in the dark -- est night; Is a sto -- ry ex -- cel -- lent, bright and fra -- grant Of Bo -- az and Ruth in a di -- vine ro -- mance. Ruth the Mo -- ab -- it -- ess joined to God's ho -- ly e -- lect; Bo -- az took care of her and re -- deemed all her debt. First she gleaned from his land, Then got mar -- ried to him. This is how she was joined to God's e -- ter -- nal plan. Lord, I love You and trea -- sure You. Lord, I choose You and res -- pond to You. You're my ev -- ery -- thing, You're a -- bove all, You're my Hus -- band, and my rest, And my all in all.</singingstanza>
    <globalstaffsize>14</globalstaffsize>
    <topmargin>0.25</topmargin>
    <bottommargin>0.25</bottommargin>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="ref">Ruth</link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midi location="lb" length="71">lb74.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">As a lily growing out of a bramble bush;
As a bright star shining forth in the darkest night;
Is a story excellent, bright and fragrant
Of Boaz and Ruth in a divine romance.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Ruth the Moabitess joined to God's holy elect;
Boaz took care of her and redeemed all her debt.
First she gleaned from his land,
Then got married to him.
This is how she was joined to God's eternal plan.</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">Lord, I love You and treasure You.
Lord, I choose You and respond to You.
You're my everything, You're above all,
You're my Husband, and my rest,
And my all in all.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">The eternal God entered and stepped into time;
For this He needed persons to carry the line &amp;mdash;
Those who fulfilled His plan, to bring God into man
Bringing divinity into humanity.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">In the universe this is the greatest event,
That is Christ's incarnation &amp;mdash; in His first advent.
Ruth became an ancestor in this mystery &amp;mdash;
God and man to be mingled as one entity.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">God had promised the seed of a woman for man
That would crush Satan's head and redeem fallen man;
To make God and man one, what a glory to Him!
We are qualified now to partake of Him.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">We are Moabites too, constituted with sin;
We are under God's wrath and His condemnation.
But through Christ's redemption, He's our portion we claim;
In this organic union, we're married to Him.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
