<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>When upon life's billows you are tempest tossed</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Comfort in Trials&amp;mdash;By the Lord's Blessings</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="494"/><english num="707"/><french num="133"/><korean num="494"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="1856-1926" biolink="">Johnson Oatman Jr.</author>
    <composer biodate="1851-1921" biolink="">Edwin Othello Excell</composer>
  </creators>
  <meter>11.11.11.11. with chorus.</meter>
  <hymncode>33345553434</hymncode>
  <key>D Major</key>
  <time>2/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - | C/E - | Dm - | - - | G/B - | G7 - | C - | G7 - | C - | C/E - | Dm - | - - | Dm/F - | Dm Dm/F | C/G G7 | C - | C - | C/E - | Dm - | Dm/F - | G7 - | G7/B - | C - | G7 - | C/E - | F - | G - | C G/D | C/E C | F Dm | C/G G7 | C - |</chords>
  <melody>| 3/ 3/ 3/ 4/ | 5/ 5/ 5/ 3/ | 4 3 | 4 - | 2/ 3/ 4/ 5/ | 7/ 6/ 5/ 4/ | 3 4 | 5 - (break) | 3/ 3/ 3/ 4/ | 5/ 5/ 5/ 3/ | 4 3 | 4 - | 2/ 3/ 4/ 5/ | 7/ 6/ 5/ 4/ | 3 2 | 1 - (break) | (Chorus) 5. 5/ | ._1/ 5/ 5/ 3/ | 4 4 | 4 - | 4. 4/ | 7/ 6/ 5/ 4/ | 3 4 | 5 - (break) | ._1. ._1/ | 7/ 6. | 7/ 7/ 6/ 6/ | (.5 - | ._1/ ._1/ 7/ ._1/ | 7/ 6/ 5/ 4/ | 3 2 | 1 - |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>When up -- on life's bil -- lows you are tem -- pest tossed, When you are dis -- cou -- raged, think -- ing all is lost, Count your ma -- ny bless -- ings name them one by one, And it will sur -- prise you what the Lord hath done. Count your bless -- ings, name them one by one; Count your bless -- ings, see what God hath done; Count your bless -- ings, name them one by one, And it will sur -- prise you what the Lord hath done.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midi location="h" length="48">e0707_i.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">When upon life's billows you are tempest tossed,
When you are discouraged, thinking all is lost,
Count your many blessings name them one by one,
And it will surprise you what the Lord hath done.</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">Count your blessings, name them one by one;
Count your blessings, see what God hath done;
Count your blessings, name them one by one,
    And it will surprise you what the Lord hath done.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Are you ever burdened with a load of care?
Does the cross seem heavy you are called to bear?
Count your many blessings, every doubt will fly,
And you will be singing as the days go by.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">When you look at others with their lands and gold,
Think that Christ has promised you His wealth untold.
Count your many blessings, money cannot buy
Your reward in heaven, nor your Lord on high.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">So amid the conflict, whether great or small,
Do not be discouraged, God is over all;
Count your many blessings, angels will attend,
Help and comfort give you to your journey's end.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
