<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Soon our Lord will come, the day is drawing nigh</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Hope of Glory&amp;mdash;Waiting and Watching</category>
  <numbers><cebuano num="956"/><chinese num="755"/><english num="956"/><german num="956"/><korean num="755"/><portuguese num="481"/><russian num="232"/><spanish num="436"/></numbers>
  <creators>
	<author biodate="1905-1997" biolink="www.witnesslee.org">Witness Lee</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 5./ 5// 6./ 5// ._3 ._1 | ._2./ ._1// 6./ 7// ._1 - | 7./ ._1// ._2./ ._1// ._3./ ._2// ._4./ 7// | ._1 - - 0 (break) | 5./ 5// 6./ 5// ._3 ._1 | ._2./ ._1// 6./ 7// ._1 - | 7./ ._1// ._2./ ._1// ._3./ ._2// ._4./ 7// | ._1 - - 0 (break) | (Chorus) ._3 ._3 ._5./ ._4// ._2./ 7// | ._1 ._1 ._3 - | 6 6 ._2./ ._3// ._2./ ._1// | 7 6 5 0 (break) | 5./ 5// 6./ 5// ._3 ._1 | ._2./ ._1// 6./ 7// ._1 - | 7./ ._1// ._2./ ._1// ._3./ ._2// ._4./ 7// | ._1 - - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
	<singingstanza>Soon our Lord will come, the day is draw -- ing nigh, Sound of His ap -- proach -- ing we can hear. Watch -- ful we must be and al -- ways on a -- lert That the Lord our hearts with rap -- ture cheer. Glo -- ry! glo -- ry! Christ will come a -- gain! Glo -- ry! glo -- ry! We with Him shall reign! With a glo -- rious bod -- y, ev -- er with the Lord, Sing -- ing all His praise with glad ac -- cord.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <links>
	<link type="group">hymnal-subj119.xml</link>
	<link type="lyrics" url="www.witness-lee-hymns.org/hymns/H0956.html">View Lyrics</link>
  </links>
  <music>
	<midiref type="h" num="948"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
	<stanza type="verse" number="1">Soon our Lord will come, the day is drawing nigh,
  Sound of His approaching we can hear.
Watchful we must be and always on alert
  That the Lord our hearts with rapture cheer.</stanza>
	<stanza type="chorus" number="">Glory! glory! Christ will come again!
Glory! glory! We with Him shall reign!
With a glorious body, ever with the Lord,
  Singing all His praise with glad accord.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="2">Soon our Lord will come, the Morning Star appear;
  Night is deep, and soon will dawn the day.
Never with the current of the age we go,
  That from trials we'll be kept away.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="3">Soon our Lord will come His servants to reward;
  Those who love Him then the crown will share.
Watchful we must be and treasure not the world,
  Love and serve the Lord, His burden bear.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="4">Soon our Lord will come and in His kingdom reign;
  Satan will be bound, the world subdued.
We must fight the battle, overcome the foe,
  On His throne He then will us include.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
