<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>It was a garden in the primal age</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Ultimate Manifestation&amp;mdash;The Holy City</category>
  <numbers><cebuano num="975"/><chinese num="774"/><english num="975"/><french num="191"/><korean num="774"/><portuguese num="497"/><russian num="437"/><spanish num="454"/><tagalog num="975"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="1905-1997" biolink="www.witnesslee.org">Witness Lee</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 1 - 2 3 | 4 - 3 - | 2 1 1 7_. | 1 - - - (break) | 3 - 4 5 | 6 - 5 - | 4 3 2 1 | 2 - - - (break) | 5 - 5 4 | 3 - 2 - | 3 5 5 4# | 5 - - - (break) | 3 - 2 1 | 7_. 1 2 4 | 3 - 2 - | 1 - - - |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>It was a gar -- den in the prim -- al age, But at the end it is a ci -- ty square; Cre -- a -- tion's cen -- ter in the gar -- den was, God's build -- ing is -- sues in the ci -- ty fair.</singingstanza>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="group">hymnal-subj224.xml</link>
    <link type="lyrics" url="www.witness-lee-hymns.org/hymns/H0975.html">View Lyrics</link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midiref type="h" num="454"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">It was a garden in the primal age,
But at the end it is a city square;
Creation's center in the garden was,
God's building issues in the city fair.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Both in the garden and the city fair
A river and the tree of life are seen,
Christ typifying as the life supply,
The Spirit showing as the living stream.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">Both in the garden and the city bright
Three kinds of precious substances are found;
There are the gold, the pearls, and precious stones
Which for the building work of God abound.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">But in the garden all these precious things
Are just materials lying in the earth,
Yet in the city all are builded up
And form that dwelling of transcendent worth.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">Man in the garden of the clay was formed,
In nature as the Lord created him;
The tree of life was then without the man,
Not having yet become his life within.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">But in the city glorious the tree
Within the corporate "man" doth grow, thereby
Revealing Christ Himself as life divine
Being to man his inward life supply.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="7">'Tis for the city man is wrought upon,
Therefore regenerated and transformed
To purest gold, to pearls and precious stones,
As Christ's own Body, to Himself conformed.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="8">Within the garden also was a bride,
Who was to Adam as his counterpart;
Lastly, the city is itself the bride
As Christ's own fulness, precious to His heart.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="9">The city is God's building work replete,
A composition of the justified;
A habitation it affords to God
And is to Christ His own beloved bride.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="10">'Tis God's expression, ultimate and full,
Corporate and universal, marvelous;
God's glory it completely manifests,
And is Christ's counterpart most glorious.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
