<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>How true it is no heart may comprehend</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Ultimate Manifestation&amp;mdash;God in Christ as All in All</category>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="">Moravian Brethren</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 0 - - 3 | 3. 1/ 1 2 | 3. 3/ 3 4 | 5 - - 3 | 2 3 4. 4/ | 4 3 5 3 (break) | 2 - - 3 | 3. 1/ 1 2 | 3. 3/ 3 4 | 5 - - 3 | 6 5 4#. 4#/ | 5 6 7 6 (break) | 5 - - 5 | ._1 5 4 3 | 6. 6/ ._1 6 | 5 - - 5 | 4 3 2 1 | 6. 4/ 3 2 | 1 - - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>How true it is no heart may com -- pre -- hend The glo -- ry God pre -- par -- eth for His own, And what will hap -- pen when this age shall end; But yet in vi -- sion Je -- sus hath made known How fair and ho -- ly shall the Church des -- cend, Lit up with light of pre -- cious jas -- per stone.</singingstanza>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midiref type="h" num="44"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">How true it is no heart may comprehend
The glory God prepareth for His own,
And what will happen when this age shall end;
But yet in vision Jesus hath made known
How fair and holy shall the Church descend,
Lit up with light of precious jasper stone.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">And He shall make His Church all heavenly fair,
With gold and pearls, and every radiant stone,
And reign in holiness and glory there,
And shine as suns and stars have never shone;
And He shall lead His Bride, His joy and care,
With blissful singing to His Father's throne.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">And then the blest communion shall have come,
Of God's dear children meeting from afar;
Within His burning love they blend as one,
Yet each, according as His counsels are,
Shall have peculiar glory of his own,
As one star differeth from another star.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">And God is all in all in that great day,
And He is their exceeding great Reward;
Their stream of life, their beautiful array,
Their food, their joy, their radiance, Christ the Lord;
The music of their wondrous song shall say,
How great the joy that passeth thought or word.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">And this is that eternal life of heaven,
Laid up with Christ in God, the mystery
Of resurrection life which He hath given:
A fount of living waters full and free;
A life by which the gates of death are riven,
A life which on the throne of Christ shall be.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">And here in this waste wilderness begun,
So soon as we believe in Christ aright,
And quickened by the Spirit of the Son,
Receive Him as our only life and light,
As all the branches in the vine are one,
So we are one forever in His sight.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="7">Now come, Lord Jesus, quickly from above,
Do Thou sustain us on the desert road,
And draw us after Thee by might of love,
Our Fatherland art Thou, O love of God;
Once safe in Thee, no more shall we remove,
O Thou our everlasting sure abode.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
