<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>God's intention in this universe is with humanity</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Experience of God&amp;mdash;His Dispensation</category>
  <numbers><cebuano num="1199"/><chinese num="ts:448"/><dutch num="91"/><english num="1199"/><german num="1199"/><lsmyp num="209"/><russian num="222"/><tagalog num="1199"/></numbers>
  <creators>
	<author biodate="1972" biolink="" fullname="Ned Nossaman">N. N.</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 0 - - 5./ 5// | 5/ 5/ 5./ 4// 3./ 5// ._1./ ._2// | ._3./ ._3// ._3./ ._2// ._1 ._1./ 7// | 6./ 6// 6./ 7// ._1./ 7// ._1./ 6// (break) | 5./ 6// 5./ 3// 5 5./ 5// | 5./ 5// 5./ 4// 3./ 5// ._1./ ._2// | ._3./ ._3// ._3./ ._2// ._1 ._1 | ._2 ._2 ._1 7 | ._1 - - 0 (break) | (Chorus) 5. 4/ 3./ 5// ._1./ ._2// | ._3 - ._1 0 | 6. 7/ ._1./ 7// ._1./ 6// | 5 - 3 - (break) | 5. 4/ 3./ 5// ._1./ ._2// | ._3 - ._1 ._1 | ._2 ._2 ._1 7 | ._1 - - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
	<singingstanza>God's in -- ten -- tion in this u -- ni -- verse is with hu -- man -- i -- ty, So the Lord be -- came the Spir -- it just with man to min -- gled be. We re -- joice that we can all par -- take of His e -- con -- o -- my. Yes, min -- gling is the way. Min -- gle, min -- gle, hal -- le -- lu -- jah, Min -- gle, min -- gle, hal -- le -- lu -- jah, Min -- gle, min -- gle, hal -- le -- lu -- jah, Yes, min -- gling is the way!</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <links>
	<link type="group">hymnal-subj083.xml</link>
  </links>
  <music>
	<midiref type="h" num="1017"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
	<stanza type="verse" number="1">God's intention in this universe is with humanity,
So the Lord became the Spirit just with man to mingled be.
We rejoice that we can all partake of His economy.
  Yes, mingling is the way.</stanza>
	<stanza type="chorus" number="">Mingle, mingle, hallelujah,
Mingle, mingle, hallelujah,
Mingle, mingle, hallelujah,
  Yes, mingling is the way!</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="2">In the center of our being, past our mind, emotion, will,
Is a certain spot created to contain the Lord until
By His flowing and His flooding He will all our being fill;
  Yes, mingling is the way.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="3">Now within the Lord's recov'ry, we're so glad to find the way
To experience the Triune God and live by Him today&amp;mdash;
Get into the mingled spirit, and within the spirit stay;
  Yes, mingling is the way.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="4">In the midst of seven lampstands, now the Son of Man we see;
Eyes ablaze and feet a'burning, He's for God's recovery.
God's intention He's accomplishing&amp;mdash;a corporate entity;
  Yes, mingling is the way.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="5">In our daily life and all we are and do and think and say,
How we need a deeper mingling just to gain the Lord each day;
Lord, we give ourselves completely just to take the mingled way.
  Yes, mingling is the way.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="6">From the fruit of daily living, New Jerusalem we'll see,
It's the ultimate in mingling&amp;mdash;it's divine humanity.
And what joy that we can share it all, and share it corporately.
  Yes, mingling is the way.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
