<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>This is the time for building the temple of the Lord</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>The Church&amp;mdash;The Lord's Recovery</category>
  <numbers><cebuano num="1254"/><chinese num="ts:606"/><english num="1254"/><german num="1254"/><korean num="830"/><russian num="489"/><spanish num="384"/></numbers>
  <creators>
	<author biodate="" biolink="">Adapted</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 0. 0 5/ | 5 6/ 6 ._1/ | ._1. 6 3/ | 5 5/ 6 6/ | 3.( 3) 5/ | ._3 ._3/ ._3 ._2/ | ._1. 6 7/ | ._1 ._1/ ._2 ._3/ (break) | ._2.( ._2) 5/ | 5 6/ 6 ._1/ | ._1. 6 3/ | 5 5/ 6 6/ | 3.( 3) 3/ | 2 3/ 4# 5/ | 6/ ._2( ._2) ._1/ | 7. 6. (break) | 5.( 5) (Chorus) 5/ | ._3.( ._3) 5/ | ._3.( ._3) ._2/ | ._1 ._1/ ._2/( ._1/) 6/ (break) | 5.( 5) 5/ | 5 4/ 4 6/ | 6 5/ 5 ._1/ | ._1 ._1/ 6/( 7/) ._1/ (break) | ._2.( ._2) 5/ | ._3.( ._3) 5/ | ._3.( ._3) ._2/ | ._1 ._1/ ._2 ._2#/ (break) | ._3.( ._3) ._3/ | ._3 ._3/ ._4 ._3/ | ._3 ._2/ (.6 ._1/ | (.._5 ._3/ ._2 ._1/ | ._1.( ._1) 0/ |</melody>
  <layout>
	<singingstanza>This is the time for build -- ing the tem -- ple of the Lord That all the lo -- cal church -- es may ful -- ly be re -- stored. 'Tis not the time for our house while God's house li -- eth waste&amp;mdash; O broth -- ers, for God's build -- ing, rise up, make haste! Be strong, be strong, God's dwell -- ing place to build! The Lord of hosts is with us, with His glo -- ry 'twill be filled! Be strong, be strong, and work in one ac -- cord, That all the na -- tions may be -- hold the tem -- ple of the Lord.</singingstanza>
	<globalstaffsize>16</globalstaffsize>
	<topmargin>0.25</topmargin>
	<bottommargin>0.25</bottommargin>
	<columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <links>
	<link type="group">hymnal-subj211.xml</link>
	<link type="ref">Haggai 1</link>
  </links>
  <music>
	<midiref type="h" num="503"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
	<stanza type="verse" number="1">This is the time for building the temple of the Lord
That all the local churches may fully be restored.
'Tis not the time for our house while God's house lieth waste&amp;mdash;
O brothers, for God's building, rise up, make haste!</stanza>
	<stanza type="chorus" number="">Be strong, be strong, God's dwelling place to build!
The Lord of hosts is with us, with His glory 'twill be filled!
Be strong, be strong, and work in one accord,
  That all the nations may behold the temple of the Lord.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="2">O hear, the Lord is speaking: Consider now your ways,
Ye sow and bring in little, for lacking is My praise.
Go up into the mountain, material to provide,
And build My house that I may be glorified.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="3">Ye who are priests, ye remnant of Christians now obey&amp;mdash;
The Lord Himself is with us, whatever men may say,
With spirits stirred and burning, now let us come to work;
May none his part with others in building shirk.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="4">I'll fill this house with glory, the Lord of hosts has said,
And the desire of nations will be exhibited.
Its glory will be greater than all that's gone before,
And we will share this glory forevermore.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
