<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>There in old Chaldea, product of man's fall</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>The Church&amp;mdash;As the Called Race</category>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="">Adapted</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 5 5 5 5 | 5.( 6/) 5 - | 2 2 1 2 | 3 - - - (break) | 1 3 5 ._1 | ._1 - 7 - | 6 6 3 4# | 5 - - - (break) | 2 2 5 2 | 3.( 4/) 3 - | 5 5 ._1 5 | 6 - - - (break) | 6 5 4 5 | 6( 5) 4( 5) | 6 5 4 3 | 2 - - - (break) | (Chorus) 1 1 1 1 | 1( 7_./)( 6_./) 7_.( 1) | 2 2 2 1/( 2/) | 3 - - - (break) | 5 5 ._1 7 | ._1 - 5 - | 4 3 2. 1/ | (.1 - - - |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>There in old Chal -- de -- a, pro -- duct of man's fall, God ap -- peared to A -- bram&amp;mdash; called him from it all. "Get thee from thy coun -- try, from thy fath -- er's clan, Get thee from thy kin -- dred to an -- oth -- er land." Our Lord God Je -- ho -- vah called a cor -- porate man, One that would ex -- press Him and ful -- fill His plan.</singingstanza>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midiref type="h" num="871"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">There in old Chaldea, product of man's fall,
God appeared to Abram&amp;mdash;called him from it all.
"Get thee from thy country, from thy father's clan,
Get thee from thy kindred to another land."</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">Our Lord God Jehovah called a corporate man,
  One that would express Him and fulfill His plan.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Through the Lord's infusion, Abraham became
Father of the faithful&amp;mdash;life had changed his name.
Though the Lord's appearing, brought him to the land,
Still he needed Isaac to fulfill God's plan.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">Isaac from his father did inherit all:
Sonship's full enjoyment, blessing of God's call.
Though all things receiving, incomplete was he;
Lacking transformation and maturity.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">In his father's footsteps, Jacob then became
Prince of God, a wrestler, Israel his name;
By the Spirit's dealing, fully grown, he reigned;
O'er the earth, through Joseph, ruling pow'r obtained.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">Thus do Jacob, Isaac, Abraham portray
Path that we, God's called ones, must walk in today:
Members of the Body, as a corporate man,
We complete His calling and fulfill His plan.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
