<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>The day approaches; Jesus soon is coming</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Hope of Glory&amp;mdash;Preparing for Christ's Return</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="ts:930"/><dutch num="92"/><english num="1307"/><lsmyp num="273"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="">Adapted</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 0 - 0/ 3/ 3/ 2/ | 1. 2/ 3/ 5/ 6/ 3/ | 5 4. 4/ 4/ 3/ | 2. 3/ 4/ 5/ 2/ 4/ (break) | 3 - 0/ 1/ 1/ 1/ | 3b. 3b/ 3b/ 3b/ 2/ 1/ | 3 3 0/ 5/ ._1/ 3/ | 5. 3/ 4/ 4/ 3/ 2/ (break) | 1( - 1/) (Chorus) 5/ 6/ 3/ | 4. 5/ 7/ 6/ 5/ 4/ | 3 5 0/ 5/ 6/ 3/ | 4. 5/ 7/ 6/ 5/ 6/ (break) | 3( - 3/) 1/ 3/ 5/ | ._1. 3/ 3/ 3/ 4/ 5/ | 7 6. 6/ ._1/ 2/ | 5. 3/ 4/ 4/ 3/ 2/ | 1( - 1/) 0. |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>The day ap -- proach -- es; Je -- sus soon is com -- ing. Re -- deem the time; it must not slip a -- way. Lord, make us rea -- dy for the cry: "Be -- hold Him!" By us -- ing ev -- ery mo -- ment of each day. When Je -- sus comes, will we go in to meet Him? When Je -- sus comes, will we from self have ceased? He's com -- ing soon to take the wise ones with Him. Oh, let us not be left out -- side the feast.</singingstanza>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="group">hymnal-subj114.xml</link>
    <link type="relevant" category="nt" num="1307"></link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midiref type="h" num="1078"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">The day approaches; Jesus soon is coming.
Redeem the time; it must not slip away.
Lord, make us ready for the cry: "Behold Him!"
By using every moment of each day.</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">When Jesus comes, will we go in to meet Him?
When Jesus comes, will we from self have ceased?
He's coming soon to take the wise ones with Him.
  Oh, let us not be left outside the feast.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Lord, help us to redeem these golden moments;
Our vessels fill with ointment from above;
Help us amen each trial and tribulation;
Increase in us; make us abound in love.</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">He's coming soon&amp;mdash;these moments are so precious.
The oil is here&amp;mdash;Oh, let us buy the more.
Amen the trials and welcome tribulations&amp;mdash;
  The kingdom's ours through these afflictions sore.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">Lord, ever turn us from our soulish pleasures
To gaze upon Thy tender, loving face.
Oh, keep us running forth to meet the Bridegroom
And patiently attending to the race.</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">When Jesus comes, will we be in His presence?
When Jesus comes, will we His face behold?
Oh, let us not return to sloth and folly,
  But jealously His loving presence hold.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">As His dear Bride, let us go forth to meet Him,
Our lamps well-trimmed, our fires burning bright,
Our vessels filled, our eyes set on His glory,
To be with Him completely satisfied.</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">Yes, satisfied&amp;mdash;Christ and His Bride together.
Yes, satisfied&amp;mdash;throughout eternity.
Oh, what a rest, what joy, what love, what favor
  To be His Bride when He comes to His feast!</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
