<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>When the Lord descends from heaven</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Hope of Glory&amp;mdash;Waiting and Watching</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="754"/><english num="1354"/><french num="182"/><portuguese num="482"/><russian num="339"/><spanish num="437"/><tagalog num="1354"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="">Adapted</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 0 - - 1./ 2// | 3./ 3// 3./ 3// 3./ 2// 1./ 1// | 2./ 1// 1./ 6_.// 5_. 1./ 2// | 3./ 3// 3./ 3// 3./ 3// 2./ 1// (break) | 2 - - 1./ 2// | 3./ 3// 3./ 3// 3./ 2// 1./ 1// | 2./ 1// 1./ 6_.// 5_. 1./ 2// (break) | 3./ 3// 3./ 1// 2./ 2// 2./ 7_.// | 1 - - (Chorus) 3./ 4// (break) | 5( - 5./) 4// 3./ 4// | 5 - 3 3./ 3// | 4( - 4./) 3// 2./ 3// (break) | 4 - 2 3./ 4// | 5( - 5./) 3// 2./ 1// | 1 - 4 4./ 2// | 3./ 3// 3./ 1// 2./ 2// 2./ 7_.// | 1 - - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>When the Lord de -- scends from heav -- en, and God's trum -- pet sound we hear, Those who sleep will rise, and death will swal -- lowed be. When the Lord de -- scends from heav -- en, rap -- tured we will be who live, And our bod -- ies be trans -- formed in lib -- er -- ty. When the Lord will come in glo -- ry We will see His glo -- rious bod -- y; When the Lord will come in glo -- ry, To trans -- fig -- ure all His sons, we'll have a share.</singingstanza>
    <globalstaffsize>16</globalstaffsize>
    <topmargin>0.25</topmargin>
    <bottommargin>0.25</bottommargin>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midiref type="h" num="1226"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">When the Lord descends from heaven, and God's trumpet sound we hear,
Those who sleep will rise, and death will swallowed be.
When the Lord descends from heaven, raptured we will be who live,
And our bodies be transformed in liberty.</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">When the Lord will come in glory
We will see His glorious body;
When the Lord will come in glory,
To transfigure all His sons, we'll have a share.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">When the Lord descends from heaven, then the morning bright will dawn,
This dark night will pass, and weeping will be o'er.
When the Lord descends from heaven, days of glory will begin;
Sighing and corruption gone forevermore.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">E'er the Lord will come from heaven, the bright morning star will shine,
Those who watch escape the trial, gain the prize.
Then the Lord will come and as the Sun of righteousness will reign;
Earth will be restored, God's mercy realize.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">Soon the Lord will come from heaven; may we watch and wait with prayer,
Loins be girt about, and lamps be burning bright.
Soon the Lord will come from heaven, may we serve Him faithfully,
Thus the ministry fulfill, our gifts incite.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
