<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>I'm so full of joy, I want to tell you, friend</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Gospel&amp;mdash;Persuasion</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="ts:838"/><english num="6838"/></numbers>
  <meter>Peculiar Meter.</meter>
  <hymncode>55123215616</hymncode>
  <key>F Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - - | C - - - | F - - - | Dm - - - | G - - - | C - C/E - | F - Dm7 - | C/G - G7 - | C - - - | F - - - | C - - - | Am - D7 - | G - - C/E | F - G7/F - | Em - Am - | Dm - D7/F# - | G - - C/E | F - G7/F - | Em - Am - | Dm - G7 - | C F/C C - ||</chords>
  <melody>| 0 - - 5_./ 5_./ | 1. 2/ 3/ 2/ 1/ 5_./ | 6_.. 1/ 6_.. 5_./ | 4. 4/ 4/ 3/ 2/ 6_./ (break) | 7_. - - 5_. | 5. 5/ 5/ 3/ 2/ 1/ | 6_.. 7_./ 1 6_. | 5_.. 7_./ 2 3./ 2// (break) | 1 - - 1/ 1/ | 6_.. 6_./ 6_./ 1/ 2/ 1/ | 5_. - 5_. 5_./ 5_./ | 3. 3/ 3/ 3/ 3//( 2//) 1/ (break) | 2 - - 1/ 1/ | 6. 6/ 6/ 5/ 4/ 6/ | 5.( 3//)( 2//) 1. 1/ | 2. 2/ 2/ 2/ 3/ 2/ (break) | 5 - - 1/ 1/ | 6. 6/ 6/ 5/ 4/ 6/ | 5. 3//( 2//) 1. 1/ | 2. 2/ 2/ 2/ 3/ 2/ | 1 - - 0 ||</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>I'm so full of joy, I want to tell you, friend, At last I'm gen -- u -- ine -- ly free! My sad -- ness, suf -- f'rings, sor -- rows all have fled Since on the Lord I've be -- lieved! He is not some creed I have to fol -- low, Nor some law that lays de -- mands on me; He's God's Son, He's Je -- sus, our sal -- va -- tion, Flows love and life a -- bun -- dant -- ly. He's un -- locked the pri -- son, set the cap -- tives free, From death to life de -- liv -- ered me.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midi location="h" length="48">e6838_i.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">I'm so full of joy, I want to tell you, friend,
At last I'm genuinely free!
My sadness, suff'rings, sorrows all have fled
Since on the Lord I've believed!
He is not some creed I have to follow,
Nor some law that lays demands on me;
He's God's Son, He's Jesus, our salvation,
Flows love and life abundantly.
He's unlocked the prison, set the captives free,
From death to life delivered me.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Now I soar the heavens as on eagles' wings,
For Jesus is my freedom true.
So vast this joy! Each day my heart must sing:
"I have enough; I have You!"
Friend, where can you find another like Him?
In His love He's waited for so long!
While His loving heart is open, wouldn't you
Come forward, trust Him with your all?
In the freedom of the glory of God's sons
Your heart will sing a glad new song!</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
