<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Abba, we come, and low we bow before Thee</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Worship of the Father&amp;mdash;His Redemption</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="39"/><english num="8039"/></numbers>
  <meter>11.11.11.10.</meter>
  <hymncode>53215645665</hymncode>
  <key>D Major</key>
  <time>3/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - | C/E - - | F - - | C - - | C - - | Am - - | Dm - - | G - - | C - - | C/E - - | F - - | G7/F - - | C/E - - | F - F/A | C/G - G7 | C - - ||</chords>
  <melody>| 5 3 2 | 1 - 5 | 6. 4/ 5/ 6/ | 6 5 - | 1 1 1 | 1 2 3/( 5/) | 5 4 3 | 3 (.2 2/( 5/) | 5 3 2 | 5 - 5 | 6 - 7/ ._1/ | ._1 7 6 | 5 4 3 | ._1 6 4 | 3 - 2 | 1 - - ||</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>Ab -- ba, we come, and low we bow be -- fore Thee, Kneel -- ing, we wor -- ship, with whole heart a -- dore Thee, Nor cat -- tle nor sheep, Thy req -- ui -- site of -- fering; In spir -- it, re -- al -- i -- ty&amp;mdash; Christ&amp;mdash; we bring.</singingstanza>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midi location="h" length="">e8039_i.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Abba, we come, and low we bow before Thee,
Kneeling, we worship, with whole heart adore Thee,
Nor cattle nor sheep, Thy requisite offering;
In spirit, "reality"&amp;mdash;Christ&amp;mdash;we bring.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Abba, "I AM," eternal, self-existing,
Ancient of Days who forever shall be,
Thy throne in the heav'ns established aboundeth
In holiness, glory, authority.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">Hopeless and helpless, blackened by offenses,
How could we dare to entreat for forgiveness?
We only had seen Thine impartial righteousness,
Never Thine heart full of love for us.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">Yet from Thy bosom, Thy dear Son Thou sendedst,
To reveal fully Thy wondrous self to us;
Each day sinners waited yet for redemption,
Enthroned, Thou could'st no satisfaction find.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">Thine only Son Thou briefly didst abandon
Just to gain us who were lost in transgression;
Allow'dst Him to die in anguish, forsaken,
To open our way to draw nigh to Thee.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">Thy Son beloved didst die for us, O Father;
Now we're Thy sons, into Thy name we gather;
Thou once didst inspire great fear in our hearts
But "Abba," dear Father today Thou art.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="7">Thy love so deep, Thy grace so all-surpassing
Abba, Thy sons ne'er could pay back such blessing;
We can but o'erflow with gratitude ever,
And worship and praise Thee forevermore.</stanza>
    <stanza type="note" number="">"Reality" in verse 1 refers to Christ.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
