1:1|ASV|Paul, called  to be an apostle of Jesus Christ through the will of God, and Sosthenes our brother,
1:1|Darby|Paul, [a] called apostle of Jesus Christ, by God's will, and  Sosthenes the brother,
1:1|KJV|Paul called to be an apostle of Jesus Christ through the will of God, and Sosthenes our brother,
1:1|WYC|Paul, called apostle of Jesus Christ, by the will of God, and Sosthenes, brother,
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|憑神旨意，蒙召作基督耶穌使徒的保羅，和弟兄所提尼，
1:2|ASV|unto the church of God which is at Corinth, even them that are sanctified in Christ Jesus, called to be saints, with all that call upon the name of our Lord Jesus Christ in every place, their Lord and ours:
1:2|Darby|to the assembly of God which is in Corinth, to [those]  sanctified in Christ Jesus, called saints, with all that in  every place call on the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, both  theirs and ours:
1:2|KJV|Unto the church of God which is at Corinth, to them that are sanctified in Christ Jesus, called to be saints, with all that in every place call upon the name of Jesus Christ our Lord, both their's and our's:
1:2|WYC|to the church of God that is at Corinth, to them that be hallowed in Christ Jesus, and called saints, with all that inwardly call the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, in each place of them and of ours,
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|寫信給在哥林多神的召會，就是給在基督耶穌裡被聖別，蒙召的聖徒，同著所有在各處呼求我們主耶穌基督之名的人；祂是他們的，也是我們的；
1:3|ASV|Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.
1:3|Darby|Grace to you and peace from God our Father, and [the] Lord  Jesus Christ.
1:3|KJV|Grace be unto you, and peace, from God our Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ.
1:3|WYC|grace to you and peace of God, our Father, and of the Lord Jesus Christ.
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願恩典與平安，從神我們的父，並主耶穌基督歸與你們。
1:4|ASV|I thank my God always concerning you, for the grace of God which was given you in Christ Jesus;
1:4|Darby|I thank my God always about you, in respect of the grace of  God given to you in Christ Jesus;
1:4|KJV|I thank my God always on your behalf, for the grace of God which is given you by Jesus Christ;
1:4|WYC|I do thankings to my God evermore for you, in the grace of God that is given to you in Christ Jesus.
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我因神在基督耶穌裡所賜給你們的恩典，常常為你們感謝我的神，
1:5|ASV|that in everything ye were enriched in him, in all utterance and all knowledge;
1:5|Darby|that in everything ye have been enriched in him, in all word  [of doctrine], and all knowledge,
1:5|KJV|That in every thing ye are enriched by him, in all utterance, and in all knowledge;
1:5<version name="WYC">For in all things ye be made rich in him, in each word, and in each knowing [and in each knowing, <i>or science</i>],</version>
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為你們在基督裡，在一切的發表和知識上，樣樣都得以富足，
1:6|ASV|even as the testimony of Christ was confirmed in you:
1:6|Darby|(according as the testimony of the Christ has been confirmed  in you,)
1:6|KJV|Even as the testimony of Christ was confirmed in you:
1:6|WYC|as the witnessing of Christ is confirmed in you;
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|正如我們為基督所作的見證，在你們裡面得以堅固，
1:7|ASV|so that ye come behind in no gift; waiting for the revelation of our Lord Jesus Christ;
1:7|Darby|so that ye come short in no gift, awaiting the revelation of  our Lord Jesus Christ;
1:7|KJV|So that ye come behind in no gift; waiting for the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ:
1:7<version name="WYC">so that nothing fail to you in any grace, that abide the showing of our Lord Jesus Christ [abiding the revelation, <i>or showing</i>, of our Lord Jesus Christ];</version>
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以致你們在恩賜上一無所缺，熱切等待我們主耶穌基督的顯現；
1:8|ASV|who shall also confirm you unto the end, that ye be unreproveable in the day of our Lord Jesus Christ.
1:8|Darby|who shall also confirm you to [the] end, unimpeachable in  the day of our Lord Jesus Christ.
1:8|KJV|Who shall also confirm you unto the end, that ye may be blameless in the day of our Lord Jesus Christ.
1:8<version name="WYC">which also shall confirm you into the end without crime [which also shall confirm you till into the end without crime, <i>or great sin</i>], in the day of the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ.</version>
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂也必堅固你們到底，使你們在我們主耶穌基督的日子無可指責。
1:9|ASV|God is faithful, through whom ye were called into the fellowship of his Son Jesus Christ our Lord.
1:9|Darby|God [is] faithful, by whom ye have been called into [the]  fellowship of his Son Jesus Christ our Lord.
1:9|KJV|God is faithful, by whom ye were called unto the fellowship of his Son Jesus Christ our Lord.
1:9|WYC|A true God [Forsooth God is true], by whom ye be called into the fellowship of his Son Jesus Christ our Lord.
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神是信實的，你們乃是為祂所召，進入了祂兒子我們主耶穌基督的交通。
1:10|ASV|Now I beseech you, brethren, through the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that ye all speak the same thing and that there be no divisions among you; but that ye be perfected together in the same mind and in the same judgment.
1:10|Darby|Now I exhort you, brethren, by the name of our Lord Jesus  Christ, that ye all say the same thing, and that there be not  among you divisions; but that ye be perfectly united in the  same mind and in the same opinion.
1:10|KJV|Now I beseech you, brethren, by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that ye all speak the same thing, and that there be no divisions among you; but that ye be perfectly joined together in the same mind and in the same judgment.
1:10<version name="WYC">But, brethren, I beseech you, by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that ye all say the same thing, and that dissensions be not among you [and that schisms, <i>or divisions</i>, <i>dissensions</i>, <i>or discords</i>, be not among you]; but be ye perfect in the same wit, and in the same knowing.</version>
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，我藉我們主耶穌基督的名，懇求你們都說一樣的話，你們中間也不可有分裂，只要在一樣的心思和一樣的意見裡，彼此和諧。
1:11|ASV|For it hath been signified unto me concerning you, my brethren, by them that are of the household of Chloe, that there are contentions among you.
1:11|Darby|For it has been shewn to me concerning you, my brethren, by  those of [the house of] Chloe, that there are strifes among  you.
1:11|KJV|For it hath been declared unto me of you, my brethren, by them which are of the house of Chloe, that there are contentions among you.
1:11|WYC|For, my brethren, it is told to me of them that be at Chloe's, that strives be among you.
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為，我的弟兄們，革來氏家裡的人曾對我題到你們的事，說你們中間有爭競。
1:12|ASV|Now this I mean, that each one of you saith, I am of Paul; and I of Apollos: and I of Cephas; and I of Christ.
1:12|Darby|But I speak of this, that each of you says, *I* am of Paul,  and *I* of Apollos, and *I* of Cephas, and *I* of Christ.
1:12|KJV|Now this I say, that every one of you saith, I am of Paul; and I of Apollos; and I of Cephas; and I of Christ.
1:12<version name="WYC">And I say that, that each of you saith, For I am of Paul, and I <i>am</i> of Apollos, and I <i>am</i> of Cephas, but I <i>am </i>of Christ. [Forsooth I say this thing, that each of you saith, Forsooth I am of Paul, forsooth I of Apollos, truly I of Cephas, <i>that is, Peter</i>, forsooth I of Christ.]</version>
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我是說，你們各人說，我是屬保羅的，我是屬亞波羅的，我是屬磯法的，我是屬基督的。
1:13|ASV|Is Christ divided? was Paul crucified for you? or were ye baptized into the name of Paul?
1:13|Darby|Is the Christ divided? has Paul been crucified for you? or  have ye been baptised unto the name of Paul?
1:13|KJV|Is Christ divided? was Paul crucified for you? or were ye baptized in the name of Paul?
1:13|WYC|Whether Christ is parted? whether Paul was crucified for you, either ye be baptized in the name of Paul [or be ye baptized in the name of Paul]?
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|基督是分開的麼？保羅為你們釘了十字架麼？或者你們是浸入保羅的名裡麼？
1:14|ASV|I thank God that I baptized none of you, save Crispus and Gaius;
1:14|Darby|I thank God that I have baptised none of you, unless  Crispus and Gaius,
1:14|KJV|I thank God that I baptized none of you, but Crispus and Gaius;
1:14|WYC|I do thankings to my God [I do  thankings to God], that I baptized none of you, but Crispus and Gaius;
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我感謝神，除了基利司布並該猶以外，我沒有浸過你們一個人，
1:15|ASV|lest any man should say that ye were baptized into my name.
1:15|Darby|that no one may say that I have baptised unto my own name.
1:15|KJV|Lest any should say that I had baptized in mine own name.
1:15|WYC|lest any man say, that ye be baptized in my name.
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|免得有人說，你們是浸入我的名裡。
1:16|ASV|And I baptized also the household of Stephanas: besides, I know not whether I baptized any other.
1:16|Darby|Yes, I baptised also the house of Stephanas; for the rest I  know not if I have baptised any other.
1:16|KJV|And I baptized also the household of Stephanas: besides, I know not whether I baptized any other.
1:16|WYC|And I baptized also the house of Stephanas, but I know not, that I baptized any other [if I baptized any other].
1:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我也浸過司提反家；此外浸過別人沒有，我就記不得了。
1:17|ASV|For Christ sent me not to baptize, but to preach the gospel: not in wisdom of words, lest the cross of Christ should be made void.
1:17|Darby|For Christ has not sent me to baptise, but to preach glad  tidings; not in wisdom of word, that the cross of the Christ  may not be made vain.
1:17|KJV|For Christ sent me not to baptize, but to preach the gospel: not with wisdom of words, lest the cross of Christ should be made of none effect.
1:17|WYC|For Christ sent me not to baptize, but to preach the gospel; not in wisdom of word, that the cross of Christ be not voided away.
1:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|基督差遣我，原不是為施浸，乃是為傳福音；並不用言論的智慧，免得基督的十字架落了空。
1:18|ASV|For the word of the cross is to them that perish foolishness; but unto us who are saved it is the power of God.
1:18|Darby|For the word of the cross is to them that perish  foolishness, but to us that are saved it is God's power.
1:18|KJV|For the preaching of the cross is to them that perish foolishness; but unto us which are saved it is the power of God.
1:18|WYC|For the word of the cross is folly to them that perish; but to them that be made safe, that is to say, to us, it is the virtue of God.
1:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為十字架的話，對那正在滅亡的人為愚拙，對我們正在得救的人卻為神的大能。
1:19|ASV|For it is written, I will destroy the wisdom of the wise, And the discernment of the discerning will I bring to nought.
1:19|Darby|For it is written, I will destroy the wisdom of the wise,  and set aside the understanding of the understanding ones.
1:19|KJV|For it is written, I will destroy the wisdom of the wise, and will bring to nothing the understanding of the prudent.
1:19|WYC|For it is written, I shall destroy the wisdom of wise men [I shall lose the wisdom of wise men], and I shall reprove the prudence of prudent men.
1:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為經上記著：“我要滅絕智慧人的智慧，廢棄通達人的通達。”
1:20|ASV|Where is the wise? where is the scribe? where is the disputer of this world? hath not God made foolish the wisdom of the world?
1:20|Darby|Where [is the] wise? where scribe? where disputer of this  world? has not God made foolish the wisdom of the world?
1:20|KJV|Where is the wise? where is the scribe? where is the disputer of this world? hath not God made foolish the wisdom of this world?
1:20<version name="WYC">Where is the wise man? where is the wise lawyer [where is the writer, <i>or man of law</i>]? where is the purchaser of this world?  Whether God hath not made the wisdom of this world fond [Whether God hath not made the wisdom of this world foolish]?</version>
1:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|智慧人在那裡？經學家在那裡？這世代的辯士在那裡？神豈不是使世上的智慧成為愚拙麼？
1:21|ASV|For seeing that in the wisdom of God the world through its wisdom knew not God, it was God's good pleasure through the foolishness of the preaching to save them that believe.
1:21|Darby|For since, in the wisdom of God, the world by wisdom has  not known God, God has been pleased by the foolishness of the  preaching to save those that believe.
1:21|KJV|For after that in the wisdom of God the world by wisdom knew not God, it pleased God by the foolishness of preaching to save them that believe.
1:21|WYC|For the world in wisdom of God knew not God by wisdom [For why for in the wisdom of God the world knew not God by wisdom], it pleased to God, by [the] folly of preaching, to make them safe that believed.
1:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|既然照著神的智慧，世人憑自己的智慧，未曾認識神，神就樂意藉著所傳之事的愚拙，拯救那些信的人。
1:22|ASV|Seeing that Jews ask for signs, and Greeks seek after wisdom:
1:22|Darby|Since Jews indeed ask for signs, and Greeks seek wisdom;
1:22|KJV|For the Jews require a sign, and the Greeks seek after wisdom:
1:22|WYC|For Jews seek signs, and Greeks seek wisdom;
1:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|猶太人是求神蹟，希利尼人是尋求智慧，
1:23|ASV|but we preach Christ crucified, unto Jews a stumblingblock, and unto Gentiles foolishness;
1:23|Darby|but *we* preach Christ crucified, to Jews an offence, and  to nations foolishness;
1:23|KJV|But we preach Christ crucified, unto the Jews a stumblingblock, and unto the Greeks foolishness;
1:23|WYC|but we preach Christ crucified, to Jews cause of stumbling [to Jews soothly offence], and to heathen men folly;
1:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們卻是傳揚釘十字架的基督，對猶太人為絆腳石，對外邦人為愚拙；
1:24|ASV|but unto them that are called, both Jews and Greeks, Christ the power of God, and the wisdom of God.
1:24|Darby|but to those that [are] called, both Jews and Greeks,  Christ God's power and God's wisdom.
1:24|KJV|But unto them which are called, both Jews and Greeks, Christ the power of God, and the wisdom of God.
1:24<version name="WYC">but to those Jews and Greeks that be called, <i>we preach </i>Christ the virtue of God and the wisdom of God. [forsooth to them called, Jews and Greeks, Christ the virtue of God, and the wisdom of God.]</version>
1:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但對那蒙召的，無論是猶太人、或希利尼人，基督總是神的能力，神的智慧。
1:25|ASV|Because the foolishness of God is wiser than men; and the weakness of God is stronger than men.
1:25|Darby|Because the foolishness of God is wiser than men, and the  weakness of God is stronger than men.
1:25|KJV|Because the foolishness of God is wiser than men; and the weakness of God is stronger than men.
1:25<version name="WYC">For that that is folly thing of God, is wiser than men; and that that is the feeble thing of God [and that that is the sick thing, <i>or frail</i>, of God], is stronger than men.</version>
1:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因神的愚拙總比人智慧，神的軟弱總比人強壯。
1:26|ASV|For behold your calling, brethren, that not many wise after the flesh, not many mighty, not many noble, are called:
1:26|Darby|For consider your calling, brethren, that [there are] not  many wise according to flesh, not many powerful, not many  high-born.
1:26|KJV|For ye see your calling, brethren, how that not many wise men after the flesh, not many mighty, not many noble, are called:
1:26|WYC|But, brethren, see ye your calling [Forsooth, see ye your calling, brethren]; for not many wise men after the flesh, not many mighty, not many noble.
1:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，你們看你們蒙召的，按著肉體有智慧的不多，有能力的不多，出身尊高的也不多；
1:27|ASV|but God chose the foolish things of the world, that he might put to shame them that are wise; and God chose the weak things of the world, that he might put to shame the things that are strong;
1:27|Darby|But God has chosen the foolish things of the world, that he  may put to shame the wise; and God has chosen the weak things  of the world, that he may put to shame the strong things;
1:27|KJV|But God hath chosen the foolish things of the world to confound the wise; and God hath chosen the weak things of the world to confound the things which are mighty;
1:27<version name="WYC">But God chose those things that be fond of the world, to confound wise men; and God chose the feeble things of the world, to confound the strong things; [But God chose those things that be foolish of the world, that he confound wise men; and God chose the sick things, <i>or frail</i>, of the world, that he confound the strong things;]</version>
1:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神卻揀選了世上愚拙的，叫那有智慧的羞愧；神又揀選了世上軟弱的，叫那強壯的羞愧；
1:28|ASV|and the base things of the world, and the things that are despised, did God choose, yea and the things that are not, that he might bring to nought the things that are:
1:28|Darby|and the ignoble things of the world, and the despised, has  God chosen, [and] things that are not, that he may annul the  things that are;
1:28|KJV|And base things of the world, and things which are despised, hath God chosen, yea, and things which are not, to bring to nought things that are:
1:28|WYC|and God chose the unnoble things and despisable things of the world, and those things that be not, to destroy those things that be;
1:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神也揀選了世上出身卑下的，以及被人藐視的，就是那些無有的，為要廢掉那些有的，
1:29|ASV|that no flesh should glory before God.
1:29|Darby|so that no flesh should boast before God.
1:29|KJV|That no flesh should glory in his presence.
1:29<version name="WYC">that each man have not glory in his sight. [that each flesh, <i>or man</i>, glory not in his sight.]</version>
1:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|使一切屬肉體的人，在神面前都不能誇口。
1:30|ASV|But of him are ye in Christ Jesus, who was made unto us wisdom from God, and righteousness and sanctification, and redemption:
1:30|Darby|But of him are *ye* in Christ Jesus, who has been made to  us wisdom from God, and righteousness, and holiness, and  redemption;
1:30|KJV|But of him are ye in Christ Jesus, who of God is made unto us wisdom, and righteousness, and sanctification, and redemption:
1:30|WYC|But of him ye be in Christ Jesus, which is made of God to us wisdom, and rightwiseness, and holiness, and again-buying;
1:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但你們得在基督耶穌裡，是出於神，這基督成了從神給我們的智慧：公義、聖別和救贖，
1:31<version name="ASV">that, according as it is written, He that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:31<version name="Darby">that according as it is written, He that boasts, let him  boast in [the] Lord. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:31<version name="KJV">That, according as it is written, He that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:31|WYC|that, as it is written, He that glorieth, have glory in the Lord [He that glorieth, glory in the Lord].
1:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|為使，如經上所記：“誇口的當在主裡誇口。”
2:1|ASV|And I, brethren, when I came unto you, came not with excellency of speech or of wisdom, proclaiming to you the testimony of God.
2:1|Darby|And *I*, when I came to you, brethren, came not in  excellency of word, or wisdom, announcing to you the testimony  of God.
2:1|KJV|And I, brethren, when I came to you, came not with excellency of speech or of wisdom, declaring unto you the testimony of God.
2:1|WYC|And I, brethren, when I came to you, came not in the highness of word, either of wisdom [or of wisdom], telling to you the witnessing of Christ.
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，從前我到你們那裡去，並沒有照著高超的言論或智慧，對你們宣傳神的奧祕。
2:2|ASV|For I determined not to know anything among you, save Jesus Christ, and him crucified.
2:2|Darby|For I did not judge [it well] to know anything among you  save Jesus Christ, and *him* crucified.
2:2|KJV|For I determined not to know any thing among you, save Jesus Christ, and him crucified.
2:2|WYC|For I deemed not [in] me to know any thing among you, but Christ Jesus, and him crucified.
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我曾定了主意，在你們中間不知道別的，只知道耶穌基督，並這位釘十字架的。
2:3|ASV|And I was with you in weakness, and in fear, and in much trembling.
2:3|Darby|And *I* was with you in weakness and in fear and in much  trembling;
2:3|KJV|And I was with you in weakness, and in fear, and in much trembling.
2:3|WYC|And I in frailty, and dread, and in much trembling, was among you; [And I in sickness, and dread, and much trembling, was with you;]
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在你們那裡，又軟弱，又懼怕，又甚戰兢。
2:4|ASV|And my speech and my preaching were not in persuasive words of wisdom, but in demonstration of the Spirit and of power:
2:4|Darby|and my word and my preaching, not in persuasive words of  wisdom, but in demonstration of [the] Spirit and of power;
2:4|KJV|And my speech and my preaching was not with enticing words of man's wisdom, but in demonstration of the Spirit and of power:
2:4|WYC|and my word and my preaching was not in subtly stirring words of man's wisdom, but in showing of Spirit and of virtue;
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我說的話，講的道，不是用智慧動聽的言語，乃是用那靈和能力的明證，
2:5|ASV|that your faith should not stand in the wisdom of men, but in the power of God.
2:5|Darby|that your faith might not stand in men's wisdom, but in  God's power.
2:5|KJV|That your faith should not stand in the wisdom of men, but in the power of God.
2:5|WYC|that your faith be not in the wisdom of men, but in the virtue of God.
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|叫你們的信不在於人的智慧，乃在於神的能力。
2:6|ASV|We speak wisdom, however, among them that are fullgrown: yet a wisdom not of this world, nor of the rulers of this world, who are coming to nought:
2:6|Darby|But we speak wisdom among the perfect; but wisdom not of  this world, nor of the rulers of this world, who come to  nought.
2:6|KJV|Howbeit we speak wisdom among them that are perfect: yet not the wisdom of this world, nor of the princes of this world, that come to nought:
2:6|WYC|For we speak wisdom among perfect men, but not wisdom of this world, neither of princes of this world, that be destroyed;
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而在長成的人中，我們也講智慧，但不是這世代的智慧，也不是這世代有權有位正被廢掉之人的智慧。
2:7|ASV|but we speak God's wisdom in a mystery, even the wisdom that hath been hidden, which God foreordained before the worlds unto our glory:
2:7|Darby|But we speak God's wisdom in [a] mystery, that hidden  [wisdom] which God had predetermined before the ages for our  glory:
2:7|KJV|But we speak the wisdom of God in a mystery, even the hidden wisdom, which God ordained before the world unto our glory:
2:7<version name="WYC">but we speak the wisdom of God in mystery, which wisdom is hid; which <i>wisdom</i> God before-ordained before worlds into our glory [the which God before-ordained before worlds into our glory],</version>
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們講的，乃是從前所隱藏，神奧祕中的智慧，就是神在萬世以前，為使我們得榮耀所豫定的；
2:8|ASV|which none of the rulers of this world hath known: for had they known it, they would not have crucified the Lord of glory:
2:8|Darby|which none of the princes of this age knew, (for had they  known, they would not have crucified the Lord of glory;)
2:8|KJV|Which none of the princes of this world knew: for had they known it, they would not have crucified the Lord of glory.
2:8|WYC|which none of the princes of this world knew; for if they had known, they should never have crucified the Lord of glory.
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這智慧，這世代有權有位的人，並沒有一個知道，因為他們若知道，就不會把榮耀的主釘十字架了。
2:9|ASV|but as it is written, Things which eye saw not, and ear heard not, And which entered not into the heart of man, Whatsoever things God prepared for them that love him.
2:9|Darby|but according as it is written, Things which eye has not  seen, and ear not heard, and which have not come into man's  heart, which God has prepared for them that love him,
2:9|KJV|But as it is written, Eye hath not seen, nor ear heard, neither have entered into the heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him.
2:9|WYC|But as it is written, That eye saw not, nor ear heard, neither it ascended into the heart of man, what things God arrayed to them that love him [what things God made ready before to them that love him];
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只是如經上所記：“神為愛祂的人所豫備的，是眼睛未曾看見，耳朵未曾聽見，人心也未曾想到的。”
2:10|ASV|But unto us God revealed  them through the Spirit: for the Spirit searcheth all things, yea, the deep things of God.
2:10|Darby|but God has revealed to us by [his] Spirit; for the Spirit  searches all things, even the depths of God.
2:10|KJV|But God hath revealed them unto us by his Spirit: for the Spirit searcheth all things, yea, the deep things of God.
2:10|WYC|but God showed to us by his Spirit.  For why the Spirit searcheth all things, yea, the deep things of God.
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但神藉著那靈向我們啟示了，因為那靈參透萬事，甚至神的深奧也參透了。
2:11|ASV|For who among men knoweth the things of a man, save the spirit of the man, which is in him? even so the things of God none knoweth, save the Spirit of God.
2:11|Darby|For who of men hath known the things of a man except the  spirit of the man which is in him? thus also the things of God  knows no one except the Spirit of God.
2:11|KJV|For what man knoweth the things of a man, save the spirit of man which is in him? even so the things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God.
2:11|WYC|And who of men knoweth, what things be of man, but the spirit of man that is in him?  So [and] what things be of God, no man knoweth, but the Spirit of God.
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為除了在人裡面人的靈，在人中間有誰知道人的事？照樣，除了神的靈，也沒有人知道神的事。
2:12|ASV|But we received, not the spirit of the world, but the spirit which is from God; that we might know the things that were freely given to us of God.
2:12|Darby|But *we* have received, not the spirit of the world, but  the Spirit which [is] of God, that we may know the things which  have been freely given to us of God:
2:12|KJV|Now we have received, not the spirit of the world, but the spirit which is of God; that we might know the things that are freely given to us of God.
2:12|WYC|And we have not received the spirit of this world, but the Spirit that is of God, that we know what things be given to us of God.
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們所領受的，並不是世上的靈，乃是那出於神的靈，使我們能知道神白白恩賜我們的事；
2:13|ASV|Which things also we speak, not in words which man's wisdom teacheth, but which the Spirit teacheth; combining spiritual things with spiritual words.
2:13|Darby|which also we speak, not in words taught by human wisdom,  but in those taught by the Spirit, communicating spiritual  [things] by spiritual [means].
2:13|KJV|Which things also we speak, not in the words which man's wisdom teacheth, but which the Holy Ghost teacheth; comparing spiritual things with spiritual.
2:13|WYC|Which things we speak also, not in wise words of man's wisdom, but in the doctrine of the Spirit, and make a likeness of spiritual things to ghostly men. [The which things we speak, not in taught words of man's wisdom, but in doctrine of the Spirit, comparisoning spiritual things to ghostly men.]
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些事我們也講說，不是用人智慧所教導的言語，乃是用那靈所教導的言語，用屬靈的話，解釋屬靈的事。
2:14|ASV|Now the natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God: for they are foolishness unto him; and he cannot know them, because they are spiritually judged.
2:14|Darby|But [the] natural man does not receive the things of the  Spirit of God, for they are folly to him; and he cannot know  [them] because they are spiritually discerned;
2:14|KJV|But the natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God: for they are foolishness unto him: neither can he know them, because they are spiritually discerned.
2:14<version name="WYC">For a beastly man perceiveth not those things that be of the Spirit of God; for it is folly to him, and he may not understand, for it is examined ghostly [for it is examined, <i>or assayed</i>, ghostly].</version>
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而屬魂的人不領受神的靈的事，因他以這些事為愚拙，並且他不能明白，因為這些事是憑靈看透的。
2:15|ASV|But he that is spiritual judgeth all things, and he himself is judged of no man.
2:15|Darby|but the spiritual discerns all things, and *he* is  discerned of no one.
2:15|KJV|But he that is spiritual judgeth all things, yet he himself is judged of no man.
2:15|WYC|But a spiritual man deemeth all things, and he is deemed of no man.
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|惟有屬靈的人看透萬事，卻沒有一人看透他。
2:16<version name="ASV">For who hath known the mind of the Lord, that he should instruct him? But we have the mind of Christ. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:16<version name="Darby">For who has known the mind of [the] Lord, who shall  instruct him? But *we* have the mind of Christ. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:16<version name="KJV">For who hath known the mind of the Lord, that he may instruct him? but we have the mind of Christ.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:16|WYC|As it is written, And who knew the wit of the Lord, or who taught him?  And we have the wit of Christ.
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|誰曾知道主的心思能教導祂？但我們是有基督的心思了。
3:1|ASV|And I, brethren, could not speak unto you as unto spiritual, but as unto carnal, as unto babes in Christ.
3:1|Darby|And *I*, brethren, have not been able to speak to you as to  spiritual, but as to fleshly; as to babes in Christ.
3:1|KJV|And I, brethren, could not speak unto you as unto spiritual, but as unto carnal, even as unto babes in Christ.
3:1<version name="WYC">And I, brethren, might not speak to you as to spiritual men, but as to fleshly <i>men </i>[but as to fleshly]; as to little children in Christ,</version>
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，我從前對你們說話，不能把你們當作屬靈的，只能當作屬肉的，當作在基督裡的嬰孩。
3:2|ASV|I fed you with milk, not with meat; for ye were not yet able to bear it: nay, not even now are ye able;
3:2|Darby|I have given you milk to drink, not meat, for ye have not  yet been able, nor indeed are ye yet able;
3:2|KJV|I have fed you with milk, and not with meat: for hitherto ye were not able to bear it, neither yet now are ye able.
3:2<version name="WYC">I gave to you milk to drink, not meat; for ye might not yet <i>understand</i>, neither ye be able to now [but neither now soothly ye be able],</version>
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我給你們奶喝，沒有給你們乾糧，因為那時你們不能喫，就是如今還是不能，
3:3|ASV|for ye are yet carnal: for whereas there is among you jealousy and strife, are ye not carnal, and do ye not walk after the manner of men?
3:3|Darby|for ye are yet carnal. For whereas [there are] among you  emulation and strife, are ye not carnal, and walk according to  man?
3:3|KJV|For ye are yet carnal: for whereas there is among you envying, and strife, and divisions, are ye not carnal, and walk as men?
3:3|WYC|for yet ye be fleshly.  For while envy and strife is among you, whether ye be not fleshly, and ye go after man?
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因你們仍是屬肉體的。因為在你們中間有嫉妒、爭競，你們豈不是屬肉體，照著人的樣子而行麼？
3:4|ASV|For when one saith, I am of Paul; and another, I am of Apollos; are ye not men?
3:4|Darby|For when one says, *I* am of Paul, and another, *I* of  Apollos, are ye not men?
3:4|KJV|For while one saith, I am of Paul; and another, I am of Apollos; are ye not carnal?
3:4<version name="WYC">For when some saith, I am of Paul, and another, But I am of Apollos [another forsooth, I am of Apollos], whether ye be not [<i>fleshly</i>] men?</version>
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有的說，我是屬保羅的，另有的說，我是屬亞波羅的；你們豈不是屬肉體的人麼？
3:5|ASV|What then is Apollos? and what is Paul? Ministers through whom ye believed; and each as the Lord gave to him.
3:5|Darby|Who then is Apollos, and who Paul? Ministering servants,  through whom ye have believed, and as the Lord has given to  each.
3:5|KJV|Who then is Paul, and who is Apollos, but ministers by whom ye believed, even as the Lord gave to every man?
3:5|WYC|What therefore is Apollos, and what Paul?  They be ministers of him, to whom ye have believed; and to each man as God hath given.
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞波羅算甚麼？保羅算甚麼？照著主所賜給他們各人的，不過是執事，藉著他們，你們信了。
3:6|ASV|I planted, Apollos watered; but God gave the increase.
3:6|Darby|*I* have planted; Apollos watered; but God has given the  increase.
3:6|KJV|I have planted, Apollos watered; but God gave the increase.
3:6<version name="WYC">I planted, Apollos moisted [Apollos watered, <i>or moisted</i>], but God gave increasing.</version>
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我栽種了，亞波羅澆灌了，惟有神叫他生長。
3:7|ASV|So then neither is he that planteth anything, neither he that watereth; but God that giveth the increase.
3:7|Darby|So that neither the planter is anything, nor the waterer;  but God the giver of the increase.
3:7|KJV|So then neither is he that planteth any thing, neither he that watereth; but God that giveth the increase.
3:7|WYC|Therefore [And so] neither he that planteth is any thing, neither he that moisteth, but God that giveth increasing.
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|可見栽種的算不得甚麼，澆灌的也算不得甚麼，只在那叫他生長的神。
3:8|ASV|Now he that planteth and he that watereth are one: but each shall receive his own reward according to his own labor.
3:8|Darby|But the planter and the waterer are one; but each shall  receive his own reward according to his own labour.
3:8|KJV|Now he that planteth and he that watereth are one: and every man shall receive his own reward according to his own labour.
3:8|WYC|And he that planteth, and he that moisteth, be one; and each shall take his own meed, after his travail.
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|栽種的和澆灌的都是一樣，但將來各人要照自己的勞苦，得自己的賞賜。
3:9|ASV|For we are God's fellow-workers: ye are God's husbandry, God's building.
3:9|Darby|For we are God's fellow-workmen; ye are God's husbandry,  God's building.
3:9|KJV|For we are labourers together with God: ye are God's husbandry, ye are God's building.
3:9|WYC|For we be the helpers of God; ye be the earth-tilling of God, ye be the building of God.
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們是神的同工，你們是神的耕地，神的建築。
3:10|ASV|According to the grace of God which was given unto me, as a wise masterbuilder I laid a foundation; and another buildeth thereon. But let each man take heed how he buildeth thereon.
3:10|Darby|According to the grace of God which has been given to me,  as a wise architect, I have laid the foundation, but another  builds upon it. But let each see how he builds upon it.
3:10|KJV|According to the grace of God which is given unto me, as a wise masterbuilder, I have laid the foundation, and another buildeth thereon. But let every man take heed how he buildeth thereupon.
3:10|WYC|After the grace of God that is given to me, as a wise master carpenter I setted the foundament [I set the foundament]; and another buildeth above.  But each man see, how he buildeth above [how and what things he buildeth upon].
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我照神所給我的恩典，好像一個智慧的工頭，立好了根基，有別人在上面建造，只是各人要謹慎怎樣在上面建造。
3:11|ASV|For other foundation can no man lay than that which is laid, which is Jesus Christ.
3:11|Darby|For other foundation can no man lay besides that which [is]  laid, which is Jesus Christ.
3:11|KJV|For other foundation can no man lay than that is laid, which is Jesus Christ.
3:11|WYC|For no man may set another foundament, except that that is set [besides that that is set], which is Christ Jesus.
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為除了那已經立好的根基，就是耶穌基督以外，沒有人能立別的根基。
3:12|ASV|But if any man buildeth on the foundation gold, silver, costly stones, wood, hay, stubble;
3:12|Darby|Now if any one build upon [this] foundation, gold, silver,  precious stones, wood, grass, straw,
3:12|KJV|Now if any man build upon this foundation gold, silver, precious stones, wood, hay, stubble;
3:12|WYC|For if any man buildeth over this foundament, gold, silver, precious stones, sticks, hay, or stubble, [Forsooth if any man build upon this foundament, gold, silver, precious stones, sticks, hay, stubble,]
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而，若有人用金、銀、寶石，木、草、禾秸，在這根基上建造，
3:13|ASV|each man's work shall be made manifest: for the day shall declare it, because it is revealed in fire; and the fire itself shall prove each man's work of what sort it is.
3:13|Darby|the work of each shall be made manifest; for the day shall  declare [it], because it is revealed in fire; and the fire  shall try the work of each what it is.
3:13|KJV|Every man's work shall be made manifest: for the day shall declare it, because it shall be revealed by fire; and the fire shall try every man's work of what sort it is.
3:13|WYC|every man's work shall be open; for the day of the Lord shall declare, for it shall be showed in fire; the fire shall prove the work of each man, what manner work it is [what manner it is].
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|各人的工程必然顯露，因為那日子要將牠指明出來；牠要在火中被揭露，這火要試驗各人的工程是那一種的。
3:14|ASV|If any man's work shall abide which he built thereon, he shall receive a reward.
3:14|Darby|If the work of any one which he has built upon [the  foundation] shall abide, he shall receive a reward.
3:14|KJV|If any man's work abide which he hath built thereupon, he shall receive a reward.
3:14|WYC|If the work of any man dwell still, which he builded above [which he builded upon], he shall receive meed.
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人在那根基上所建造的工程若存得住，他就要得賞賜。
3:15|ASV|If any man's work shall be burned, he shall suffer loss: but he himself shall be saved; yet so as through fire.
3:15|Darby|If the work of any one shall be consumed, he shall suffer  loss, but *he* shall be saved, but so as through [the] fire.
3:15|KJV|If any man's work shall be burned, he shall suffer loss: but he himself shall be saved; yet so as by fire.
3:15|WYC|If any man's work burn, he shall suffer harm [If any man's work shall burn, he shall suffer impairing]; but he shall be safe, so nevertheless as by fire.
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人的工程若被燒燬，他就要受虧損，自己卻要得救；只是這樣得救，要像從火裡經過的一樣。
3:16|ASV|Know ye not that ye are a temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you?
3:16|Darby|Do ye not know that ye are [the] temple of God, and [that]  the Spirit of God dwells in you?
3:16|KJV|Know ye not that ye are the temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you?
3:16|WYC|Know ye not, that ye be the temple of God, and the Spirit of God dwelleth in you?
3:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|豈不知你們是神的殿，神的靈住在你們裡面麼？
3:17|ASV|If any man destroyeth the temple of God, him shall God destroy; for the temple of God is holy, and such are ye.
3:17|Darby|If any one corrupt the temple of God, *him* shall God  destroy; for the temple of God is holy, and such are *ye*.
3:17|KJV|If any man defile the temple of God, him shall God destroy; for the temple of God is holy, which temple ye are.
3:17|WYC|And if any [man] defouleth the temple of God, God shall destroy him [God shall lose him]; for the temple of God is holy, which ye be.
3:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若有人毀壞神的那殿，神必要毀壞這人，因為神的那殿是聖的，你們就是這殿。
3:18|ASV|Let no man deceive himself. If any man thinketh that he is wise among you in this world, let him become a fool, that he may become wise.
3:18|Darby|Let no one deceive himself: if any one thinks himself to be  wise among you in this world, let him become foolish, that he  may be wise.
3:18|KJV|Let no man deceive himself. If any man among you seemeth to be wise in this world, let him become a fool, that he may be wise.
3:18|WYC|No man deceive himself.  If any man among you is seen to be wise in this world, be he made a fool, that he be wise.
3:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人不可自欺；你們中間若有人自以為在這世代中有智慧，他就該變作愚拙，好成為有智慧的。
3:19|ASV|For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God. For it is written, He that taketh the wise in their craftiness:
3:19|Darby|For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God; for  it is written, He who takes the wise in their craftiness.
3:19|KJV|For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God. For it is written, He taketh the wise in their own craftiness.
3:19<version name="WYC">For the wisdom of this world is folly with God; for it is written, I shall catch wise men in their fell wisdom [I shall catch wise men in their fell wisdom, <i>or</i> <i>subtle guile</i>];</version>
3:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因這世界的智慧，在神看是愚拙，如經上記著：“主叫智慧的人中了自己的詭計。”
3:20|ASV|and again, The Lord knoweth the reasonings of the wise that they are vain.
3:20|Darby|And again, [The] Lord knows the reasonings of the wise that  they are vain.
3:20|KJV|And again, The Lord knoweth the thoughts of the wise, that they are vain.
3:20|WYC|and again, The Lord knoweth the thoughts of wise men, for those be vain [for they be vain].
3:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又說，“主知道智慧人的意念是虛空的。”
3:21|ASV|Wherefore let no one glory in men. For all things are yours;
3:21|Darby|So that let no one boast in men; for all things are yours.
3:21|KJV|Therefore let no man glory in men. For all things are your's;
3:21|WYC|Therefore no man have glory in men [And so no man glory in men].  For all things be yours,
3:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以誰都不可拿人誇口，因為萬有全是你們的，
3:22|ASV|whether Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death, or things present, or things to come; all are yours;
3:22|Darby|Whether Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas, or [the] world, or  life, or death, or things present, or things coming, all are  yours;
3:22|KJV|Whether Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death, or things present, or things to come; all are your's;
3:22|WYC|either Paul, either Apollos, either Cephas, either the world, either life, either death, either things present, either things to coming [either things to come]; for all things be yours,
3:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|或保羅、或亞波羅、或磯法、或世界、或生命、或死亡、或現今的事、或要來的事，全是你們的，
3:23<version name="ASV">and ye are Christ's; and Christ is God's. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:23<version name="Darby">and *ye* [are] Christ's, and Christ [is] God's. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:23<version name="KJV">And ye are Christ's; and Christ is God's.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:23<version name="WYC">and ye <i>be</i> of Christ, and Christ <i>is</i> of God.</version>
3:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但你們是基督的，基督又是神的。
4:1|ASV|Let a man so account of us, as of ministers of Christ, and stewards of the mysteries of God.
4:1|Darby|Let a man so account of us as servants of Christ, and  stewards of [the] mysteries of God.
4:1|KJV|Let a man so account of us, as of the ministers of Christ, and stewards of the mysteries of God.
4:1<version name="WYC">So a man guess us [So a man guess, <i>or</i> <i>deem</i>, us], as ministers of Christ, and dispensers of the mysteries of God.</version>
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，人應當把我們看作基督的執事，和神的奧祕的管家。
4:2|ASV|Here, moreover, it is required in stewards, that a man be found faithful.
4:2|Darby|Here, further, it is sought in stewards, that a man be found  faithful.
4:2|KJV|Moreover it is required in stewards, that a man be found faithful.
4:2|WYC|Now it is sought here among the dispensers, that a man be found true.
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|還有，在此所求於管家的，是要他顯為忠信。
4:3|ASV|But with me it is a very small thing that I should be judged of you, or of man's judgment: yea, I judge not mine own self.
4:3|Darby|But for me it is the very smallest matter that I be examined  of you or of man's day. Nor do I even examine myself.
4:3|KJV|But with me it is a very small thing that I should be judged of you, or of man's judgment: yea, I judge not mine own self.
4:3|WYC|And to me it is for the least thing, that I be deemed of you, or of man's day; but neither I deem myself.
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於我被你們察驗，或被人審判的日子察驗，對我都是極小的事，連我也不察驗自己。
4:4|ASV|For I know nothing against myself; yet am I not hereby justified: but he that judgeth me is the Lord.
4:4|Darby|For I am conscious of nothing in myself; but I am not  justified by this: but he that examines me is the Lord.
4:4|KJV|For I know nothing by myself; yet am I not hereby justified: but he that judgeth me is the Lord.
4:4|WYC|For I am nothing over-trusting to myself, but not in this thing I am justified [Soothly I am nothing guilty to myself, but not in this thing am I justified]; for he that deemeth me, is the Lord.
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我雖不覺得自己有錯，卻也不能因此得稱義，但察驗我的乃是主。
4:5|ASV|Wherefore judge nothing before the time, until the Lord come, who will both bring to light the hidden things of darkness, and make manifest the counsels of the hearts; and then shall each man have his praise from God.
4:5|Darby|So that do not judge anything before [the] time, until the  Lord shall come, who shall also both bring to light the hidden  things of darkness, and shall make manifest the counsels of  hearts; and then shall each have [his] praise from God.
4:5|KJV|Therefore judge nothing before the time, until the Lord come, who both will bring to light the hidden things of darkness, and will make manifest the counsels of the hearts: and then shall every man have praise of God.
4:5|WYC|Therefore do not ye deem before the time, till that the Lord come, which shall lighten [alighten] the hid things of darknesses, and shall show the counsels of hearts; and then praising shall be to each man of God.
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以在那時以前，甚麼都不要論斷，直等主來，祂要照出暗中的隱情，也要顯明人心的意圖，那時各人要從神那裡得著稱讚。
4:6|ASV|Now these things, brethren, I have in a figure transferred to myself and Apollos for your sakes; that in us ye might learn not to go beyond the things which are written; that no one of you be puffed up for the one against the other.
4:6|Darby|Now these things, brethren, I have transferred, in their  application, to myself and Apollos, for your sakes, that ye may  learn in us the [lesson of] not [letting your thoughts go]  above what is written, that ye may not be puffed up one for  [such a] one against another.
4:6|KJV|And these things, brethren, I have in a figure transferred to myself and to Apollos for your sakes; that ye might learn in us not to think of men above that which is written, that no one of you be puffed up for one against another.
4:6<version name="WYC">And, brethren, I have transfigured these things into me and into Apollos, for you; that in us ye learn, lest over that it is written, one against another be blown with pride for another. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21457a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，我為你們的緣故，將這些事轉比到自己和亞波羅身上，叫你們從我們學習不越過所寫的，免得你們自高自大，高看這個，鄙視那個。
4:7|ASV|For who maketh thee to differ? and what hast thou that thou didst not receive? but if thou didst receive it, why dost thou glory as if thou hadst not received it?
4:7|Darby|For who makes thee to differ? and what hast thou which thou  hast not received? but if also thou hast received, why boastest  thou as not receiving?
4:7|KJV|For who maketh thee to differ from another? and what hast thou that thou didst not receive? now if thou didst receive it, why dost thou glory, as if thou hadst not received it?
4:7|WYC|Who deemeth thee?  And what hast thou, that thou hast not received?  And if thou hast received, what gloriest thou, as thou haddest not received?
4:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|使你與人不同的是誰？你有甚麼不是領受的？若真是領受的，你為甚麼誇口，彷彿不是領受的？
4:8|ASV|Already are ye filled, already ye are become rich, ye have come to reign without us: yea and I would that ye did reign, that we also might reign with you.
4:8|Darby|Already ye are filled; already ye have been enriched; ye  have reigned without us; and I would that ye reigned, that *we*  also might reign with you.
4:8|KJV|Now ye are full, now ye are rich, ye have reigned as kings without us: and I would to God ye did reign, that we also might reign with you.
4:8|WYC|Now ye be filled [Now ye be full-filled], now ye be made rich; ye reign without us; and I would that ye reign, that also we reign with you.
4:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們已經飽足了，已經豐富了，不用我們，自己就作王了。我巴不得你們果真作王，叫我們也得與你們一同作王。
4:9|ASV|For, I think, God hath set forth us the apostles last of all, as men doomed to death: for we are made a spectacle unto the world, both to angels and men.
4:9|Darby|For I think that God has set us the apostles for the last,  as appointed to death. For we have become a spectacle to the  world, both to angels and men.
4:9|KJV|For I think that God hath set forth us the apostles last, as it were appointed to death: for we are made a spectacle unto the world, and to angels, and to men.
4:9|WYC|And I guess, that God showed us the last apostles, as those that be sent to the death [Soothly I ween, that God showed us the last apostles, as made ready to death]; for we be made a spectacle to the world, and to angels, and to men.
4:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我想神把我們使徒顯列在末後，好像定了死罪的人，因為我們對世界，就是對天使和世人，成了一臺戲。
4:10|ASV|We are fools for Christ's sake, but ye are wise in Christ; we are weak, but ye are strong; ye have glory, but we have dishonor.
4:10|Darby|*We* [are] fools for Christ's sake, but *ye* prudent in  Christ: *we* weak, but *ye* strong: *ye* glorious, but *we* in  dishonour.
4:10|KJV|We are fools for Christ's sake, but ye are wise in Christ; we are weak, but ye are strong; ye are honourable, but we are despised.
4:10|WYC|We fools for Christ, but ye prudent in Christ; we frail [we sick], but ye strong; ye noble, but we unnoble.
4:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們為基督的緣故是愚拙的，你們在基督裡倒是精明的；我們軟弱，你們倒強壯；你們有榮耀，我們倒被輕視。
4:11|ASV|Even unto this present hour we both hunger, and thirst, and are naked, and are buffeted, and have no certain dwelling-place;
4:11|Darby|To the present hour we both hunger and thirst, and are in  nakedness, and buffeted, and wander without a home,
4:11|KJV|Even unto this present hour we both hunger, and thirst, and are naked, and are buffeted, and have no certain dwellingplace;
4:11<version name="WYC">Till into this hour we hunger, and thirst, and be naked, and be smitten with buffets, and we be unstable [and we be unstable, <i>moving from place to place</i>],</version>
4:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|直到今時，我們還是又飢，又渴，又赤身露體，又挨拳打，又居無定所；
4:12|ASV|and we toil, working with our own hands: being reviled, we bless; being persecuted, we endure;
4:12|Darby|and labour, working with our own hands. Railed at, we  bless; persecuted, we suffer [it];
4:12|KJV|And labour, working with our own hands: being reviled, we bless; being persecuted, we suffer it:
4:12<version name="WYC">and we travail working with our hands; we be cursed, and we bless; we suffer persecution, and we abide long [and we sustain, <i>or abide long</i>];</version>
4:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且勞苦，親手作工；被人咒罵，我們就祝福；被人逼迫，我們就忍受；
4:13|ASV|being defamed, we entreat: we are made as the filth of the world, the offscouring of all things, even until now.
4:13|Darby|insulted, we entreat: we are become as [the] offscouring of  the world, [the] refuse of all, until now.
4:13|KJV|Being defamed, we intreat: we are made as the filth of the world, and are the offscouring of all things unto this day.
4:13<version name="WYC">we be blasphemed, and we beseech; as cleansings of this world we be made the out-casting [we be made the parings, <i>or</i> <i>out-castings</i>,] of all things till yet.</version>
4:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|被人毀謗，我們就善勸；我們成了世界上的污穢，萬物中的渣滓，直到如今。
4:14|ASV|I write not these things to shame you, but to admonish you as my beloved children.
4:14|Darby|Not [as] chiding do I write these things to you, but as my  beloved children I admonish [you].
4:14|KJV|I write not these things to shame you, but as my beloved sons I warn you.
4:14|WYC|I write not these things, that I confound you, but I warn you as my most dear-worthy sons.
4:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我寫這些話，不是羞辱你們，乃像勸戒我親愛的兒女一樣。
4:15|ASV|For though ye have ten thousand tutors in Christ, yet have ye not many fathers; for in Christ Jesus I begat you through the gospel.
4:15|Darby|For if ye should have ten thousand instructors in Christ,  yet not many fathers; for in Christ Jesus *I* have begotten you  through the glad tidings.
4:15|KJV|For though ye have ten thousand instructers in Christ, yet have ye not many fathers: for in Christ Jesus I have begotten you through the gospel.
4:15|WYC|For why if ye have ten thousand of under-masters in Christ, but not many fathers; for in Christ Jesus I have engendered you by the gospel [for why in Christ Jesus I have gendered you by the gospel].
4:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們在基督裡，縱有上萬的導師，父親卻不多，因為是我在基督耶穌裡藉著福音生了你們。
4:16|ASV|I beseech you therefore, be ye imitators of me.
4:16|Darby|I entreat you therefore, be my imitators.
4:16|KJV|Wherefore I beseech you, be ye followers of me.
4:16|WYC|Therefore, brethren, I pray you [Therefore I pray you], be ye followers of me, as I of Christ.
4:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我懇求你們要效法我。
4:17|ASV|For this cause have I sent unto you Timothy, who is my beloved and faithful child in the Lord, who shall put you in remembrance of my ways which are in Christ, even as I teach everywhere in every church.
4:17|Darby|For this reason I have sent to you Timotheus, who is my  beloved and faithful child in [the] Lord, who shall put you in  mind of my ways [as] they [are] in Christ, according as I teach  everywhere in every assembly.
4:17|KJV|For this cause have I sent unto you Timotheus, who is my beloved son, and faithful in the Lord, who shall bring you into remembrance of my ways which be in Christ, as I teach every where in every church.
4:17<version name="WYC">Therefore I sent to you Timothy, which is my most dear-worthy son, and faithful in the Lord, which shall teach you my ways [which shall admonish you, <i>or teach</i>, my ways], that be in Christ Jesus; as I teach every where in each church.</version>
4:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此我已打發提摩太到你們那裡去；他在主裡是我所親愛、忠信的孩子；他必題醒你們，我在基督耶穌裡怎樣行事，正如我在各處各召會中所教導的。
4:18|ASV|Now some are puffed up, as though I were not coming to you.
4:18|Darby|But some have been puffed up, as if I were not coming to  you;
4:18|KJV|Now some are puffed up, as though I would not come to you.
4:18<version name="WYC">As though I should not come to you, so some be blown with pride [so some be in-blown <i>with pride</i>];</version>
4:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有些人以為我不到你們那裡去，就自高自大，
4:19|ASV|But I will come to you shortly, if the Lord will; and I will know, not the word of them that are puffed up, but the power.
4:19|Darby|but I will come quickly to you, if the Lord will; and I  will know, not the word of those that are puffed up, but the  power.
4:19|KJV|But I will come to you shortly, if the Lord will, and will know, not the speech of them which are puffed up, but the power.
4:19<version name="WYC">but I shall come to you soon, if God will; and I shall know not the word of them that be blown with pride [that be in-blown <i>with pride</i>], but the virtue.</version>
4:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而主若願意，我必快到你們那裡去；並且我所要知道的，不是那些自高自大之人的言語，乃是他們的能力。
4:20|ASV|For the kingdom of God is not in word, but in power.
4:20|Darby|For the kingdom of God [is] not in word, but in power.
4:20|KJV|For the kingdom of God is not in word, but in power.
4:20|WYC|For the realm of God is not in word, but in virtue.
4:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神的國不在於言語，乃在於能力。
4:21<version name="ASV">What will ye? shall I come unto you with a rod, or in love and a spirit of gentleness? </p><p /><br /></version>
4:21<version name="Darby">What will ye? that I come to you with a rod; or in love,  and [in] a spirit of meekness? </p><p /><br /></version>
4:21<version name="KJV">What will ye? shall I come unto you with a rod, or in love, and in the spirit of meekness?</p><p /><br /></version>
4:21|WYC|What will ye?  Shall I come to you in a rod, or in charity, and in a spirit of mildness?
4:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們願意怎麼樣？是要我帶著刑杖，還是要我在愛和溫柔的靈裡，到你們那裡去？
5:1|ASV|It is actually reported that there is fornication among you, and such fornication as is not even among the Gentiles, that one of you hath his father's wife.
5:1|Darby|It is universally reported [that there is] fornication among  you, and such fornication as [is] not even among the nations,  so that one should have his father's wife.
5:1|KJV|It is reported commonly that there is fornication among you, and such fornication as is not so much as named among the Gentiles, that one should have his father's wife.
5:1|WYC|Yet all manner of fornication is heard among you, and such fornication, which is not among heathen men, so that some man have the wife of his father [so that one man have the wife of his father].
5:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|確實聽說在你們中間有淫亂的事，這樣的淫亂，連外邦人中也沒有，就是有人收了他的繼母。
5:2|ASV|And ye are puffed up, and did not rather mourn, that he that had done this deed might be taken away from among you.
5:2|Darby|And *ye* are puffed up, and ye have not rather mourned, in  order that he that has done this deed might be taken away out  of the midst of you.
5:2|KJV|And ye are puffed up, and have not rather mourned, that he that hath done this deed might be taken away from among you.
5:2<version name="WYC">And ye be swollen with pride [And ye be blown <i>with pride</i>], and not more had wailing, that he that did this work, be taken away from the middle of you.</version>
5:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們還是自高自大！豈不應當哀慟，把行這事的人從你們中間挪開？
5:3|ASV|For I verily, being absent in body but present in spirit, have already as though I were present judged him that hath so wrought this thing,
5:3|Darby|For *I*, [as] absent in body but present in spirit, have  already judged as present,
5:3|KJV|For I verily, as absent in body, but present in spirit, have judged already, as though I were present, concerning him that hath so done this deed,
5:3|WYC|And I absent in body [Soothly I absent in body], but present in spirit, now have deemed as present him that hath thus wrought,
5:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我身體雖不在你們那裡，靈卻與你們同在，我已經審判了行這樣事的人，好像與你們同在一樣，
5:4|ASV|in the name of our Lord Jesus, ye being gathered together, and my spirit, with the power of our Lord Jesus,
5:4|Darby|[to deliver,] in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ (ye and  my spirit being gathered together, with the power of our Lord  Jesus Christ), him that has so wrought this:
5:4|KJV|In the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, when ye are gathered together, and my spirit, with the power of our Lord Jesus Christ,
5:4|WYC|when ye be gathered together in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, and my spirit, with the virtue of the Lord Jesus,
5:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就是當你們和我的靈聚集的時候，在我們主耶穌的名裡，帶同我們主耶穌的能力，
5:5|ASV|to deliver such a one unto Satan for the destruction of the flesh, that the spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord Jesus.
5:5|Darby|to deliver him, [I say,] [being] such, to Satan for  destruction of the flesh, that the spirit may be saved in the  day of the Lord Jesus.
5:5|KJV|To deliver such an one unto Satan for the destruction of the flesh, that the spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord Jesus.
5:5|WYC|to betake such a man to Satan, into the perishing of flesh, that the spirit be safe in the day of our Lord Jesus Christ.
5:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|把這樣的人交給撒但，使他的肉體受敗壞，好叫他的靈在主的日子可以得救。
5:6|ASV|Your glorying is not good. Know ye not that a little leaven leaveneth the whole lump?
5:6|Darby|Your boasting [is] not good. Do ye not know that a little  leaven leavens the whole lump?
5:6|KJV|Your glorying is not good. Know ye not that a little leaven leaveneth the whole lump?
5:6|WYC|Your glorying is not good.  Know ye not, that a little sourdough impaireth all the gobbet [that a little sourdough corrupteth all the gobbet]?
5:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們誇口是不好的。豈不知一點麵酵能使全團發起來麼？
5:7|ASV|Purge out the old leaven, that ye may be a new lump, even as ye are unleavened. For our passover also hath been sacrificed, even Christ:
5:7|Darby|Purge out the old leaven, that ye may be a new lump,  according as ye are unleavened. For also our passover, Christ,  has been sacrificed;
5:7|KJV|Purge out therefore the old leaven, that ye may be a new lump, as ye are unleavened. For even Christ our passover is sacrificed for us:
5:7<version name="WYC">Cleanse ye out the old sourdough, that ye be new sprinkling together, as ye be therf.  For Christ offered is our pask. [Cleanse ye out old sourdough, that ye be new sprinkling together, as ye be therf, <i>or without souring</i>.  Forsooth Christ is offered our pask.]</version>
5:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要把舊酵除淨，好使你們成為新團，正如你們是無酵的一樣，因為我們的逾越節基督，已經被殺獻祭了。
5:8|ASV|wherefore let us keep the feast, not with old leaven, neither with the leaven of malice and wickedness, but with the unleavened bread of sincerity and truth.
5:8|Darby|so that let us celebrate the feast, not with old leaven, nor  with leaven of malice and wickedness, but with unleavened  [bread] of sincerity and truth.
5:8|KJV|Therefore let us keep the feast, not with old leaven, neither with the leaven of malice and wickedness; but with the unleavened bread of sincerity and truth.
5:8|WYC|Therefore eat we, not in old sourdough, neither in sourdough of malice and waywardness, but in therf things of clearness and of truth [of clearness and truth].
5:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我們守這節，不可用舊酵，也不可用惡毒邪惡的酵，只用純誠真實的無酵餅。
5:9|ASV|I wrote unto you in my epistle to have no company with fornicators;
5:9|Darby|I have written to you in the epistle not to mix with  fornicators;
5:9|KJV|I wrote unto you in an epistle not to company with fornicators:
5:9<version name="WYC">I wrote to you in an epistle, that ye be not mixed with lechers, [I wrote to you in an epistle, that ye be not mingled,<i> or commune not</i>, with lechers,]</version>
5:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我曾寫信給你們說，不可與淫亂的人交往，
5:10|ASV|not at all meaning with the fornicators of this world, or with the covetous and extortioners, or with idolaters; for then must ye needs go out of the world:
5:10|Darby|not altogether with the fornicators of this world, or with  the avaricious and rapacious, or idolaters, since [then] ye  should go out of the world.
5:10|KJV|Yet not altogether with the fornicators of this world, or with the covetous, or extortioners, or with idolaters; for then must ye needs go out of the world.
5:10<version name="WYC">not with lechers of this world, nor <i>with</i> covetous men, nor raveners, nor with men serving to maumets <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21482a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>, else ye should have gone out of this world.</version>
5:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並不是指這世上所有行淫亂的、或貪婪的、或勒索的、或拜偶像的，若是那樣，你們就需要離開世界。
5:11|ASV|but as it is, I wrote unto you not to keep company, if any man that is named a brother be a fornicator, or covetous, or an idolater, or a reviler, or a drunkard, or an extortioner; with such a one no, not to eat.
5:11|Darby|But now I have written to you, if any one called brother be  fornicator, or avaricious, or idolater, or abusive, or a  drunkard, or rapacious, not to mix with [him]; with such a one  not even to eat.
5:11|KJV|But now I have written unto you not to keep company, if any man that is called a brother be a fornicator, or covetous, or an idolator, or a railer, or a drunkard, or an extortioner; with such an one no not to eat.
5:11<version name="WYC">But now I have written to you, that ye be not mixed [Now soothly I wrote to you, to be not mingled,<i> or commune not with such</i>].  If he that is named a brother among you, and is a lecher, or covetous, or serving to idols, or a curser, or full of drunkenness, or a ravener, to take no meat with such [with such neither to take meat].</version>
5:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但如今我寫給你們說，若有人稱為弟兄，是行淫亂的、或貪婪的、或拜偶像的、或辱罵的、或醉酒的、或勒索的，這樣的人不可與他交往，甚至與他一同喫飯都不可。
5:12|ASV|For what have I to do with judging them that are without? Do not ye judge them that are within?
5:12|Darby|For what have *I* [to do] with judging those outside also?  *ye*, do not ye judge them that are within?
5:12|KJV|For what have I to do to judge them also that are without? do not ye judge them that are within?
5:12<version name="WYC">For what <i>is</i> it to me to deem of them that be withoutforth?  Whether ye deem not of things that be withinforth? [Forsooth what to me to deem of them that be withoutforth.  Whether ye deem not of them that be withinforth?]</version>
5:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為審判召會外的人與我何干？召會裡的人豈不是你們審判的麼？
5:13<version name="ASV">But them that are without God judgeth. Put away the wicked man from among yourselves. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:13<version name="Darby">But those without God judges. Remove the wicked person from  amongst yourselves. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:13<version name="KJV">But them that are without God judgeth. Therefore put away from among yourselves that wicked person.</p><p /><br /></version>
5:13|WYC|For God shall deem them that be withoutforth.  Do ye away evil from yourselves.
5:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於召會外的人，有神審判他們。你們要把那惡人從你們中間挪開。
6:1|ASV|Dare any of you, having a matter against his neighbor, go to law before the unrighteous, and not before the saints?
6:1|Darby|Dare any one of you, having a matter against another,  prosecute his suit before the unjust, and not before the  saints?
6:1|KJV|Dare any of you, having a matter against another, go to law before the unjust, and not before the saints?
6:1<version name="WYC">Dare any of you that hath a cause against another, be deemed at wicked men, and not at holy men? [Dare any of you, having a cause against another, be deemed at wicked men, and not at saints, <i>or holy men</i>?]</version>
6:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們中間有人與別人起了相爭的事，怎敢在不義的人面前，而不在聖徒面前求審？
6:2|ASV|Or know ye not that the saints shall judge the world? and if the world is judged by you, are ye unworthy to judge the smallest matters?
6:2|Darby|Do ye not then know that the saints shall judge the world?  and if the world is judged by you, are ye unworthy of [the]  smallest judgments?
6:2|KJV|Do ye not know that the saints shall judge the world? and if the world shall be judged by you, are ye unworthy to judge the smallest matters?
6:2|WYC|Whether ye know not, that saints shall deem this world?  And if the world shall be deemed by you, be ye unworthy to deem the least things?
6:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|豈不知聖徒要審判世界麼？若世界為你們所審判，難道你們不配審判這最小的事麼？
6:3|ASV|Know ye not that we shall judge angels? how much more, things that pertain to this life?
6:3|Darby|Do ye not know that we shall judge angels? and not then  matters of this life?
6:3|KJV|Know ye not that we shall judge angels? how much more things that pertain to this life?
6:3|WYC|Know ye not, that we shall deem angels? how much more worldly things?
6:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|豈不知我們要審判天使麼？何況今生的事？
6:4|ASV|If then ye have to judge things pertaining to this life, do ye set them to judge who are of no account in the church?
6:4|Darby|If then ye have judgments as to things of this life, set  those [to judge] who are little esteemed in the assembly.
6:4|KJV|If then ye have judgments of things pertaining to this life, set them to judge who are least esteemed in the church.
6:4<version name="WYC">Therefore if ye have worldly dooms, ordain ye those contemptible men [ordain ye those contemptible men, <i>or of little reputation</i>], that be in the church, to deem.</version>
6:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|既是這樣，你們若有今生的事當上法庭，是派召會所不看為甚麼的人審判麼？
6:5|ASV|I say this to move you to shame. What, cannot there be found among you one wise man who shall be able to decide between his brethren,
6:5|Darby|I speak to you [to put you] to shame. Thus there is not a  wise person among you, not even one, who shall be able to  decide between his brethren!
6:5|KJV|I speak to your shame. Is it so, that there is not a wise man among you? no, not one that shall be able to judge between his brethren?
6:5|WYC|I say to make you ashamed.  So there is not any wise man, that may deem betwixt a brother and his brother; [I say to your shame.  So there is not any wise man, that may deem between a brother and his brother;]
6:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我說這話，是要叫你們羞愧。難道你們中間竟沒有一個智慧人，能在他弟兄中間審斷麼？
6:6|ASV|but brother goeth to law with brother, and that before unbelievers?
6:6|Darby|But brother prosecutes his suit with brother, and that  before unbelievers.
6:6|KJV|But brother goeth to law with brother, and that before the unbelievers.
6:6|WYC|but brother with brother striveth in doom, and that among unfaithful men.
6:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們竟是弟兄與弟兄告狀，而且告在不信的人面前。
6:7|ASV|Nay, already it is altogether a defect in you, that ye have lawsuits one with another. Why not rather take wrong? why not rather be defrauded?
6:7|Darby|Already indeed then it is altogether a fault in you that ye  have suits between yourselves. Why do ye not rather suffer  wrong? why are ye not rather defrauded?
6:7|KJV|Now therefore there is utterly a fault among you, because ye go to law one with another. Why do ye not rather take wrong? why do ye not rather suffer yourselves to be defrauded?
6:7<version name="WYC">And now trespass is always among you [Now forsooth trespass is all-gates in you], for ye have dooms among you.  Why rather take ye not wrong? why rather suffer ye not deceit [why not more suffer ye fraud, <i>or deceit</i>]?</version>
6:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們彼此爭訟，這已全然是你們的失敗了。為甚麼不寧願受冤枉？為甚麼不寧願被虧負？
6:8|ASV|Nay, but ye yourselves do wrong, and defraud, and that your brethren.
6:8|Darby|But *ye* do wrong, and defraud, and this [your] brethren.
6:8|KJV|Nay, ye do wrong, and defraud, and that your brethren.
6:8|WYC|But also ye do wrong, and do fraud [and defraud], and that to brethren.
6:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們倒是冤枉人，虧負人，況且這又是對弟兄。
6:9|ASV|Or know ye not that the unrighteous shall not inherit the kingdom of God? Be not deceived: neither fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor effeminate, nor abusers of themselves with men,
6:9|Darby|Do ye not know that unrighteous [persons] shall not inherit  [the] kingdom of God? Do not err: neither fornicators, nor  idolaters, nor adulterers, nor those who make women of  themselves, nor who abuse themselves with men,
6:9|KJV|Know ye not that the unrighteous shall not inherit the kingdom of God? Be not deceived: neither fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor effeminate, nor abusers of themselves with mankind,
6:9|WYC|Whether ye know not, that wicked men shall not wield the kingdom of God?  Do not ye err; neither lechers, neither men that serve maumets [neither men serving to idols], neither adulterers, neither lechers against kind, neither they that do lechery with men,
6:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們豈不知，不義的不能承受神的國麼？不要受迷惑，無論是淫亂的、拜偶像的、姦淫的、作孌童的、同性戀的、
6:10|ASV|nor thieves, nor covetous, nor drunkards, nor revilers, nor extortioners, shall inherit the kingdom of God.
6:10|Darby|nor thieves, nor covetous, nor drunkards, nor abusive  persons, nor [the] rapacious, shall inherit [the] kingdom of  God.
6:10|KJV|Nor thieves, nor covetous, nor drunkards, nor revilers, nor extortioners, shall inherit the kingdom of God.
6:10<version name="WYC">neither thieves, neither avaricious men [neither covetous men, <i>or niggards</i>], neither <i>men</i> full of drunkenness, neither cursers, neither raveners, shall wield the kingdom of God.</version>
6:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|偷竊的、貪婪的、醉酒的、辱罵的、勒索的，都不能承受神的國。
6:11|ASV|And such were some of you: but ye were washed, but ye were sanctified, but ye were justified in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ, and in the Spirit of our God.
6:11|Darby|And these things were some of you; but ye have been washed,  but ye have been sanctified, but ye have been justified in the  name of the Lord Jesus, and by the Spirit of our God.
6:11|KJV|And such were some of you: but ye are washed, but ye are sanctified, but ye are justified in the name of the Lord Jesus, and by the Spirit of our God.
6:11|WYC|And ye were sometime these things [And these things ye were sometime]; but ye be washed, but ye be hallowed, but ye be justified in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, and in the Spirit of our God.
6:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們中間有人從前也是這樣，但在主耶穌基督的名裡，並在我們神的靈裡，你們已經洗淨了自己，已經聖別了，已經稱義了。
6:12|ASV|All things are lawful for me; but not all things are expedient. All things are lawful for me; but I will not be brought under the power of any.
6:12|Darby|All things are lawful to me, but all things do not profit;  all things are lawful to me, but *I* will not be brought under  the power of any.
6:12|KJV|All things are lawful unto me, but all things are not expedient: all things are lawful for me, but I will not be brought under the power of any.
6:12|WYC|All things be leaveful to me, but not all things be speedful.  All things be leaveful to me, but I shall not be brought down under any man's power.
6:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡事我都可行，但不都有益處；凡事我都可行，但無論那一件，我總不受牠的轄制。
6:13|ASV|Meats for the belly, and the belly for meats: but God shall bring to nought both it and them. But the body is not for fornication, but for the Lord; and the Lord for the body:
6:13|Darby|Meats for the belly, and the belly for meats; but God will  bring to nothing both it and them: but the body [is] not for  fornication, but for the Lord, and the Lord for the body.
6:13|KJV|Meats for the belly, and the belly for meats: but God shall destroy both it and them. Now the body is not for fornication, but for the Lord; and the Lord for the body.
6:13|WYC|Meat to the womb, and the womb to meats; and God shall destroy both this and that.  And the body not to fornication, but to the Lord, and the Lord to the body.
6:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|食物是為肚腹，肚腹是為食物；但這兩樣，神都要廢掉。可是身體不是為淫亂，乃是為主，主也是為身體。
6:14|ASV|and God both raised the Lord, and will raise up as through his power.
6:14|Darby|And God has both raised up the Lord, and will raise us up  from among [the dead] by his power.
6:14|KJV|And God hath both raised up the Lord, and will also raise up us by his own power.
6:14|WYC|For God raised the Lord, and shall raise us by his virtue.
6:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且神已經使主復活，也必藉著祂的能力，使我們復活起來。
6:15|ASV|Know ye not that your bodies are members of Christ? shall I then take away the members of Christ, and make them members of a harlot? God forbid.
6:15|Darby|Do ye not know that your bodies are members of Christ?  Shall I then, taking the members of the Christ, make [them]  members of a harlot? Far be the thought.
6:15|KJV|Know ye not that your bodies are the members of Christ? shall I then take the members of Christ, and make them the members of an harlot? God forbid.
6:15<version name="WYC">Know ye not, that your bodies be members of Christ?  Shall I then take the members of Christ, and shall I make <i>them</i> the members of a whore?  God forbid [Far be it].</version>
6:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|豈不知你們的身體是基督的肢體麼？我可以把基督的肢體作成娼妓的肢體麼？絕對不可！
6:16|ASV|Or know ye not that he that is joined to a harlot is one body? for, The twain, saith he, shall become one flesh.
6:16|Darby|Do ye not know that he [that is] joined to the harlot is  one body? for the two, he says, shall be one flesh.
6:16|KJV|What? know ye not that he which is joined to an harlot is one body? for two, saith he, shall be one flesh.
6:16|WYC|Whether ye know not, that he that cleaveth to a whore, is made one body?  For he saith, There shall be twain in one flesh [There shall be two in one flesh].
6:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|豈不知與娼妓聯合的，便是與她成為一體麼？因為主說，“二人要成為一體。”
6:17|ASV|But he that is joined unto the Lord is one spirit.
6:17|Darby|But he that [is] joined to the Lord is one Spirit.
6:17|KJV|But he that is joined unto the Lord is one spirit.
6:17|WYC|And he that cleaveth to the Lord, is one spirit.
6:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但與主聯合的，便是與主成為一靈。
6:18|ASV|Flee fornication. Every sin that a man doeth is without the body; but he that committeth fornication sinneth against his own body.
6:18|Darby|Flee fornication. Every sin which a man may practise is  without the body, but he that commits fornication sins against  his own body.
6:18|KJV|Flee fornication. Every sin that a man doeth is without the body; but he that committeth fornication sinneth against his own body.
6:18|WYC|Flee ye fornication; all sin whatever sin a man doeth [all sin whatever a man shall do], is without the body; but he that doeth fornication, sinneth against his body.
6:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要逃避淫亂。人所犯的，無論甚麼罪，都在身體以外，惟有行淫的，是得罪自己的身體。
6:19|ASV|Or know ye not that your body is a temple of the Holy Spirit which is in you, which ye have from God? and ye are not your own;
6:19|Darby|Do ye not know that your body is [the] temple of the Holy  Spirit which [is] in you, which ye have of God; and ye are not  your own?
6:19|KJV|What? know ye not that your body is the temple of the Holy Ghost which is in you, which ye have of God, and ye are not your own?
6:19|WYC|Whether ye know not, that your members be the temple of the Holy Ghost, that is in you, whom ye have of God, and ye be not your own?
6:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|豈不知你們的身體，就是在你們裡面之聖靈的殿麼？這聖靈是你們從神而得的，並且你們不是屬自己的，
6:20<version name="ASV">for ye were bought with a price: glorify God therefore in your body. </p><p /><br /></version>
6:20<version name="Darby">for ye have been bought with a price: glorify now then God  in your body. </p><p /><br /></version>
6:20<version name="KJV">For ye are bought with a price: therefore glorify God in your body, and in your spirit, which are God's.</p><p /><br /></version>
6:20|WYC|For ye be bought with great price.  Glorify ye, and bear ye God in your body.
6:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為你們是重價買來的。這樣，就要在你們的身體上榮耀神。
7:1|ASV|Now concerning the things whereof ye wrote: It is good for a man not to touch a woman.
7:1|Darby|But concerning the things of which ye have written [to me]:  [It is] good for a man not to touch a woman;
7:1|KJV|Now concerning the things whereof ye wrote unto me: It is good for a man not to touch a woman.
7:1|WYC|But of those things that ye have written to me, it is good to a man to touch not a woman [it is good to a man for to not touch a woman].
7:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|關於你們所寫的，我認為男不近女倒好，
7:2|ASV|But, because of fornications, let each man have his own wife, and let each woman have her own husband.
7:2|Darby|but on account of fornications, let each have his own wife,  and each [woman] have her own husband.
7:2|KJV|Nevertheless, to avoid fornication, let every man have his own wife, and let every woman have her own husband.
7:2|WYC|But for fornication each man have his own wife, and each woman have her own husband.
7:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但為避免淫亂，男人當各有自己的妻子，女人也當各有自己的丈夫。
7:3|ASV|Let the husband render unto the wife her due: and likewise also the wife unto the husband.
7:3|Darby|Let the husband render her due to the wife, and in like  manner the wife to the husband.
7:3|KJV|Let the husband render unto the wife due benevolence: and likewise also the wife unto the husband.
7:3|WYC|The husband yield debt to the wife, and also the wife to the husband.
7:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|丈夫對妻子當盡應盡之分，妻子對丈夫也要如此。
7:4|ASV|The wife hath not power over her own body, but the husband: and likewise also the husband hath not power over his own body, but the wife.
7:4|Darby|The wife has not authority over her own body, but the  husband: in like manner also the husband has not authority over  his own body, but the wife.
7:4|KJV|The wife hath not power of her own body, but the husband: and likewise also the husband hath not power of his own body, but the wife.
7:4|WYC|The woman hath not power of her body, but the husband; [also forsooth] and the husband hath not power of his body, but the woman [but the wife].
7:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|妻子對自己的身體沒有主權，丈夫纔有；照樣，丈夫對自己的身體也沒有主權，妻子纔有。
7:5|ASV|Defraud ye not one the other, except it be by consent for a season, that ye may give yourselves unto prayer, and may be together again, that Satan tempt you not because of your incontinency.
7:5|Darby|Defraud not one another, unless, it may be, by consent for a  time, that ye may devote yourselves to prayer, and again be  together, that Satan tempt you not because of your  incontinency.
7:5|KJV|Defraud ye not one the other, except it be with consent for a time, that ye may give yourselves to fasting and prayer; and come together again, that Satan tempt you not for your incontinency.
7:5|WYC|Do not ye defraud each to other [Do not defraud together], but peradventure of consent for a time, that ye give attention to prayer; and again turn again to the same thing, lest Satan tempt you for your uncontinence.
7:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們不可彼此虧負，除非出於同意，暫時分房，為要專心禱告，以後仍要同房，免得撒但因你們不能自制，試誘你們。
7:6|ASV|But this I say by way of concession, not of commandment.
7:6|Darby|But this I say, as consenting [to], not as commanding [it].
7:6|KJV|But I speak this by permission, and not of commandment.
7:6<version name="WYC">But I say this thing as giving leave, not by commandment. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21511a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
7:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我說這話，是容許你們，並不是命令。
7:7|ASV|Yet I would that all men were even as I myself. Howbeit each man hath his own gift from God, one after this manner, and another after that.
7:7|Darby|Now I wish all men to be even as myself: but every one has  his own gift of God: one man thus, and another thus.
7:7|KJV|For I would that all men were even as I myself. But every man hath his proper gift of God, one after this manner, and another after that.
7:7|WYC|For I will, that all men be as myself.  But each man hath his proper gift of God; one thus, and another thus.
7:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我願意眾人都像我一樣；只是各人都有自己從神得來的恩賜，有人是這樣，有人是那樣。
7:8|ASV|But I say to the unmarried and to widows, It is good for them if they abide even as I.
7:8|Darby|But I say to the unmarried and to the widows, It is good for  them that they remain even as I.
7:8|KJV|I say therefore to the unmarried and widows, it is good for them if they abide even as I.
7:8|WYC|But I say to them, that be not wedded, and to widows [and widows], it is good to them, if they dwell so as I.
7:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我對未婚的和寡婦說，若他們常像我就好。
7:9|ASV|But if they have not continency, let them marry: for it is better to marry than to burn.
7:9|Darby|But if they have not control over themselves, let them  marry; for it is better to marry than to burn.
7:9|KJV|But if they cannot contain, let them marry: for it is better to marry than to burn.
7:9|WYC|And if they contain not themselves, be they wedded; for it is better to be wedded, than to be burnt.
7:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但他們若不能自制，就可以嫁娶，與其慾火中燒，倒不如嫁娶為妙。
7:10|ASV|But unto the married I give charge, yea not I, but the Lord, That the wife depart not from her husband
7:10|Darby|But to the married I enjoin, not *I*, but the Lord, Let not  wife be separated from husband;
7:10|KJV|And unto the married I command, yet not I, but the Lord, Let not the wife depart from her husband:
7:10|WYC|But to them that be joined in matrimony, I command, not I, but the Lord, that the wife depart not from the husband;
7:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於那已婚的，我吩咐他們，其實不是我吩咐，乃是主吩咐，說，妻子不可離開丈夫。
7:11|ASV|(but should she depart, let her remain unmarried, or else be reconciled to her husband); and that the husband leave not his wife.
7:11|Darby|(but if also she shall have been separated, let her remain  unmarried, or be reconciled to her husband;) and let not  husband leave wife.
7:11|KJV|But and if she depart, let her remain unmarried or be reconciled to her husband: and let not the husband put away his wife.
7:11|WYC|and that if she departeth, that she dwell unwedded, or be reconciled to her husband; and the husband forsake not the wife.
7:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|（若真是離開了，她就不可再嫁，不然，仍要同丈夫和好。）丈夫也不可離棄妻子。
7:12|ASV|But to the rest say I, not the Lord: If any brother hath an unbelieving wife, and she is content to dwell with him, let him not leave her.
7:12|Darby|But as to the rest, *I* say, not the Lord, If any brother  have an unbelieving wife, and *she* consent to dwell with him,  let him not leave her.
7:12|KJV|But to the rest speak I, not the Lord: If any brother hath a wife that believeth not, and she be pleased to dwell with him, let him not put her away.
7:12<version name="WYC">But to others I say, not the Lord.  If any brother hath an unfaithful wife, and she consenteth to dwell with him, leave he her not [If any brother have an unfaithful, <i>or</i> <i>heathen</i>, wife, and she consent for to dwell with him, leave he, <i>or forsake</i>, her not].</version>
7:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我對其餘的人說，不是主說，倘若某弟兄有不信的妻子，妻子也情願和他同住，他就不要離棄妻子；
7:13|ASV|And the woman that hath an unbelieving husband, and he is content to dwell with her, let her not leave her husband.
7:13|Darby|And a woman who has an unbelieving husband, and he consents  to dwell with her, let her not leave [her] husband.
7:13|KJV|And the woman which hath an husband that believeth not, and if he be pleased to dwell with her, let her not leave him.
7:13|WYC|And if any woman hath an unfaithful husband [And if the woman hath an husband unfaithful], and this consenteth to dwell with her, leave she not the husband.
7:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|妻子有不信的丈夫，丈夫也情願和她同住，她就不要離棄丈夫。
7:14|ASV|For the unbelieving husband is sanctified in the wife, and the unbelieving wife is sanctified in the brother: else were your children unclean; but now are they holy.
7:14|Darby|For the unbelieving husband is sanctified in the wife, and  the unbelieving wife is sanctified in the brother; since  [otherwise] indeed your children are unclean, but now they are  holy.
7:14|KJV|For the unbelieving husband is sanctified by the wife, and the unbelieving wife is sanctified by the husband: else were your children unclean; but now are they holy.
7:14|WYC|For the unfaithful husband is hallowed by the faithful woman, and the unfaithful woman is hallowed by the faithful husband.  Else your children were unclean, but now they be holy.
7:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為不信的丈夫，就因著妻子被聖別，並且不信的妻子，也因著弟兄被聖別；不然，你們的兒女就不潔淨，但如今他們是聖別的了。
7:15|ASV|Yet if the unbelieving departeth, let him depart: the brother or the sister is not under bondage in such cases: but God hath called us in peace.
7:15|Darby|But if the unbeliever go away, let them go away; a brother  or a sister is not bound in such [cases], but God has called us  in peace.
7:15|KJV|But if the unbelieving depart, let him depart. A brother or a sister is not under bondage in such cases: but God hath called us to peace.
7:15|WYC|That if the unfaithful departeth, depart he.  For why the brother or sister is not subject to servage in such; for God hath called us in peace.
7:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|倘若那不信的人離去，就由他離去罷；無論是弟兄、是姊妹，在這種情形之下，都不必受束縛，然而神已經在平安裡召了我們。
7:16|ASV|For how knowest thou, O wife, whether thou shalt save thy husband? Or how knowest thou, O husband, whether thou shalt save thy wife?
7:16|Darby|For what knowest thou, O wife, if thou shalt save thy  husband? or what knowest thou, O husband, if thou shalt save  thy wife?
7:16|KJV|For what knowest thou, O wife, whether thou shalt save thy husband? or how knowest thou, O man, whether thou shalt save thy wife?
7:16|WYC|And whereof knowest thou, woman, if thou shalt make the man safe; or whereof knowest thou, man, if thou shalt make the woman safe?
7:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|況且你這作妻子的，怎麼知道能不能救你的丈夫？你這作丈夫的，怎麼知道能不能救你的妻子？
7:17|ASV|Only, as the Lord hath distributed to each man, as God hath called each, so let him walk. And so ordain I in all the churches.
7:17|Darby|However, as the Lord has divided to each, as God has called  each, so let him walk; and thus I ordain in all the assemblies.
7:17|KJV|But as God hath distributed to every man, as the Lord hath called every one, so let him walk. And so ordain I in all churches.
7:17<version name="WYC">But as the Lord hath parted to each, and as God hath called each man, so go he, as I teach in all churches. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21522b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
7:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只要照主所分給各人的，和神所召各人的而行。我在眾召會中都是這樣吩咐。
7:18|ASV|Was any man called being circumcised? Let him not become uncircumcised. Hath any been called in uncircumcision? Let him not be circumcised.
7:18|Darby|Has any one been called circumcised? let him not become  uncircumcised: has any one been called in uncircumcision? let  him not be circumcised.
7:18|KJV|Is any man called being circumcised? let him not become uncircumcised. Is any called in uncircumcision? let him not be circumcised.
7:18|WYC|A man circumcised is called, bring he not to prepuce.  A man is called in prepuce, be he not circumcised.
7:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有人蒙召時已受割禮，就不要回復原狀；有人蒙召時未受割禮，就不要受割禮。
7:19|ASV|Circumcision is nothing, and uncircumcision is nothing; but the keeping of the commandments of God.
7:19|Darby|Circumcision is nothing, and uncircumcision is nothing; but  keeping God's commandments.
7:19|KJV|Circumcision is nothing, and uncircumcision is nothing, but the keeping of the commandments of God.
7:19|WYC|Circumcision is nought, and prepuce is nought, but the keeping of the commandments of God.
7:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|受割禮算不得甚麼，不受割禮也算不得甚麼，只有遵守神的誡命纔算得數。
7:20|ASV|Let each man abide in that calling wherein he was called.
7:20|Darby|Let each abide in that calling in which he has been called.
7:20|KJV|Let every man abide in the same calling wherein he was called.
7:20|WYC|Each man in what calling he is called, in that dwell he.
7:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|各人在甚麼身分裡蒙召，仍要留於這身分。
7:21|ASV|Wast thou called being a bondservant? Care not for it: nay, even if thou canst become free, use it rather.
7:21|Darby|Hast thou been called [being] a bondman, let it not concern  thee; but and if thou canst become free, use [it] rather.
7:21|KJV|Art thou called being a servant? care not for it: but if thou mayest be made free, use it rather.
7:21|WYC|Thou servant art called, be it no charge to thee [Thou a servant art called, be it not charge to thee]; but if thou mayest be made free, use it rather.
7:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你是一個奴僕蒙召麼？不要在意；但即使你能自由，也寧可仍用奴僕的身分。
7:22|ASV|For he that was called in the Lord being a bondservant, is the Lord's freedman: likewise he that was called being free, is Christ's bondservant.
7:22|Darby|For the bondman that is called in [the] Lord is the Lord's  freedman; in like manner [also] the freeman being called is  Christ's bondman.
7:22|KJV|For he that is called in the Lord, being a servant, is the Lord's freeman: likewise also he that is called, being free, is Christ's servant.
7:22|WYC|He that is a servant, and is called in the Lord, is a free man of the Lord.  Also [and] he that is a free man, and is called, is the servant of Christ.
7:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為一個奴僕在主裡蒙召，就是屬於主得自由的人；照樣，一個自由的人蒙召，就是基督的奴僕。
7:23|ASV|Ye were bought with a price; become not bondservants of men.
7:23|Darby|Ye have been bought with a price; do not be the bondmen of  men.
7:23|KJV|Ye are bought with a price; be not ye the servants of men.
7:23|WYC|With price ye be bought; do not ye be made servants of men.
7:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們是重價買來的，不要作人的奴僕。
7:24|ASV|Brethren, let each man, wherein he was called, therein abide with God.
7:24|Darby|Let each, wherein he is called, brethren, therein abide  with God.
7:24|KJV|Brethren, let every man, wherein he is called, therein abide with God.
7:24|WYC|Therefore each man in what thing he is called a brother, dwell he in this with God. [Each man therefore in what calling he is called, in that dwell he with God.]
7:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，你們各人是在甚麼身分裡蒙召，仍要與神一同留在這身分裡。
7:25|ASV|Now concerning virgins I have no commandment of the Lord: but I give my judgment, as one that hath obtained mercy of the Lord to be trustworthy.
7:25|Darby|But concerning virgins, I have no commandment of [the]  Lord; but I give my opinion, as having received mercy of [the]  Lord to be faithful.
7:25|KJV|Now concerning virgins I have no commandment of the Lord: yet I give my judgment, as one that hath obtained mercy of the Lord to be faithful.
7:25|WYC|But of virgins I have no commandment of God; but I give counsel, as he that hath gotten mercy of the Lord, that I be true.
7:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|關於童身的人，我沒有主的命令，但我既蒙主憐憫成為忠信的，就題出我的意見。
7:26|ASV|I think therefore that this is good by reason of the distress that is upon us, namely, that it is good for a man to be as he is.
7:26|Darby|I think then that this is good, on account of the present  necessity, that [it is] good for a man to remain so as he is.
7:26|KJV|I suppose therefore that this is good for the present distress, I say, that it is good for a man so to be.
7:26|WYC|Therefore I guess, that this thing is good for the present need; for it is good to a man to be so [for it is good for a man to be so].
7:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因現今的艱難，我以為人最好保持現狀。
7:27|ASV|Art thou bound unto a wife? Seek not to be loosed. Art thou loosed from a wife? Seek not a wife.
7:27|Darby|Art thou bound to a wife? seek not to be loosed; art thou  free from a wife? do not seek a wife.
7:27|KJV|Art thou bound unto a wife? seek not to be loosed. Art thou loosed from a wife? seek not a wife.
7:27|WYC|Thou art bound to a wife, do not thou seek unbinding; thou art unbound from a wife, do not thou seek a wife.
7:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你有妻子束縛著麼？就不要尋求脫離。你沒有妻子束縛著麼？就不要尋求妻子。
7:28|ASV|But shouldest thou marry, thou hast not sinned; and if a virgin marry, she hath not sinned. Yet such shall have tribulation in the flesh: and I would spare you.
7:28|Darby|But if thou shouldest also marry, thou hast not sinned; and  if the virgin marry, they have not sinned: but such shall have  tribulation in the flesh; but I spare you.
7:28|KJV|But and if thou marry, thou hast not sinned; and if a virgin marry, she hath not sinned. Nevertheless such shall have trouble in the flesh: but I spare you.
7:28|WYC|But if thou hast taken a wife, thou hast not sinned; and if a maiden is wedded, she sinned not; nevertheless such shall have tribulation of flesh.  But I spare you.
7:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但你若娶妻，也不是犯罪；處女若出嫁，也不是犯罪；然而這等人肉身必受苦難，我卻願意你們免受這苦難。
7:29|ASV|But this I say, brethren, the time is shortened, that henceforth both those that have wives may be as though they had none;
7:29|Darby|But this I say, brethren, the time is straitened. For the  rest, that they who have wives, be as not having [any]:
7:29|KJV|But this I say, brethren, the time is short: it remaineth, that both they that have wives be as though they had none;
7:29|WYC|Therefore, brethren [And so, brethren], I say this thing, The time is short.  Another is this, that they that have wives, be as though they had none;
7:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只是弟兄們，我對你們說，時候縮短了。從此以後，那有妻子的，要像沒有妻子；
7:30|ASV|and those that weep, as though they wept not; and those that rejoice, as though they rejoiced not; and those that buy, as though they possessed not;
7:30|Darby|and they that weep, as not weeping; and they that rejoice,  as not rejoicing; and they that buy, as not possessing;
7:30|KJV|And they that weep, as though they wept not; and they that rejoice, as though they rejoiced not; and they that buy, as though they possessed not;
7:30|WYC|and they that weep, as they wept not; and they that joy, as they joyed not; and they that buy, as they had not;
7:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哀哭的，要像不哀哭；喜樂的，要像不喜樂；置買的，要像無所擁有；
7:31|ASV|and those that use the world, as not using it to the full: for the fashion of this world passeth away.
7:31|Darby|and they that use the world, as not disposing of it as  their own; for the fashion of this world passes.
7:31|KJV|And they that use this world, as not abusing it: for the fashion of this world passeth away.
7:31<version name="WYC">and they that use this world, as they that use [it] not.  For why the figure of this world passeth. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21536c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup></version>
7:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|使用世物的，要像不浪費使用；因這世界的樣子正在逝去。
7:32|ASV|But I would have you to be free from cares. He that is unmarried is careful for the things of the Lord, how he may please the Lord:
7:32|Darby|But I wish you to be without care. The unmarried cares for  the things of the Lord, how he shall please the Lord;
7:32|KJV|But I would have you without carefulness. He that is unmarried careth for the things that belong to the Lord, how he may please the Lord:
7:32|WYC|But I will, that ye be without busyness [Forsooth I will you to be without busyness], for he that is without wife, is busy what things be of the Lord, how he shall please God.
7:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我願你們無所罣慮。沒有娶妻的，是為主的事罣慮，想怎樣討主喜悅；
7:33|ASV|but he that is married is careful for the things of the world, how he may please his wife,
7:33|Darby|but he that has married cares for the things of the world,  how he shall please his wife.
7:33|KJV|But he that is married careth for the things that are of the world, how he may please his wife.
7:33|WYC|But he that is with a wife, is busy what things be of the world, how he shall please the wife [how he shall please his wife], and he is parted.
7:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|娶了妻的，是為世上的事罣慮，想怎樣討妻子喜悅，就分心了。
7:34|ASV|and is divided. So also the woman that is unmarried and the virgin is careful for the things of the Lord, that she may be holy both in body and in spirit: but she that is married is careful for the things of the world, how she may please her husband.
7:34|Darby|There is a difference between the wife and the virgin. The  unmarried cares for the things of the Lord, that she may be  holy both in body and spirit; but she that has married cares  for the things of the world, how she shall please her husband.
7:34|KJV|There is difference also between a wife and a virgin. The unmarried woman careth for the things of the Lord, that she may be holy both in body and in spirit: but she that is married careth for the things of the world, how she may please her husband.
7:34|WYC|And a woman unwedded and [a] maiden thinketh what things be of the Lord, that she be holy in body and spirit.  But she that is wedded, thinketh what things be of the world, how she shall please the husband [how she shall please her husband].
7:34|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|未結婚的婦女和守童身的女子，是為著主的事罣慮，要在身體和靈上都聖別；已經出嫁的，是為世上的事罣慮，想怎樣討丈夫喜悅。
7:35|ASV|And this I say for your own profit; not that I may cast a snare upon you, but for that which is seemly, and that ye may attend upon the Lord without distraction.
7:35|Darby|But I say this for your own profit; not that I may set a  snare before you, but for what [is] seemly, and waiting on the  Lord without distraction.
7:35|KJV|And this I speak for your own profit; not that I may cast a snare upon you, but for that which is comely, and that ye may attend upon the Lord without distraction.
7:35<version name="WYC">And I say these things to your profit, not that I cast to you a snare, but to that that is seemly, and that giveth easiness, without hindering to make prayers to the Lord. [Soothly I say these things to your profit, not that I cast to you a snare, but to that that is honest, and that giveth facility, <i>or easiness</i>, without letting to beseech to the Lord.]</version>
7:35|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我說這話，是為你們自己的益處；不是要牢籠你們，乃是要叫你們行合宜的事，得以殷勤服事主，沒有分心的事。
7:36|ASV|But if any man thinketh that he behaveth himself unseemly toward his virgin daughter, if she be past the flower of her age, and if need so requireth, let him do what he will; he sinneth not; let them marry.
7:36|Darby|But if any one think that he behaves unseemly to his  virginity, if he be beyond the flower of his age, and so it  must be, let him do what he will, he does not sin: let them  marry.
7:36|KJV|But if any man think that he behaveth himself uncomely toward his virgin, if she pass the flower of her age, and need so require, let him do what he will, he sinneth not: let them marry.
7:36<version name="WYC">And if any man guesseth himself to be seen foul on his virgin, that she is full waxen [that she is well old], and so it behooveth to be done, do she that that she will <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21541d" title="See footnote d">d</a>]</sup>; she sinneth not, if she be wedded <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21541e" title="See footnote e">e</a>]</sup>.</version>
7:36|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若有人以為待他的童身女兒不合宜，她也過了華齡，事又當行，他就可隨願辦理，不是犯罪，讓他們結婚。
7:37|ASV|But he that standeth stedfast in his heart, having no necessity, but hath power as touching in his own heart, to keep his own virgin daughter, shall do well.
7:37|Darby|But he who stands firm in his heart, having no need, but  has authority over his own will, and has judged this in his  heart to keep his own virginity, he does well.
7:37|KJV|Nevertheless he that standeth stedfast in his heart, having no necessity, but hath power over his own will, and hath so decreed in his heart that he will keep his virgin, doeth well.
7:37<version name="WYC">For he that ordained stably in his heart [For why he that ordained stably, <i>or steadfast</i>, in his heart], not having need, but having power of his will, and hath deemed in his heart this thing, to keep his virgin [for to keep his virginity], doeth well.</version>
7:37|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但他若心裡堅定，沒有不得已的事，對自己的意思又有主權，心裡也決定了留下自己的童身女兒，如此行也好。
7:38|ASV|So then both he that giveth his own virgin daughter in marriage doeth well; and he that giveth her not in marriage shall do better.
7:38|Darby|So that he that marries himself does well; and he that does  not marry does better.
7:38|KJV|So then he that giveth her in marriage doeth well; but he that giveth her not in marriage doeth better.
7:38|WYC|Therefore he that joineth his virgin in matrimony, doeth well; and he that joineth not, doeth better.
7:38|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣看來，叫自己的童身女兒出嫁是好，不叫她出嫁更是好。
7:39|ASV|A wife is bound for so long time as her husband liveth; but if the husband be dead, she is free to be married to whom she will; only in the Lord.
7:39|Darby|A wife is bound for whatever time her husband lives; but if  the husband be fallen asleep, she is free to be married to whom  she will, only in [the] Lord.
7:39|KJV|The wife is bound by the law as long as her husband liveth; but if her husband be dead, she is at liberty to be married to whom she will; only in the Lord.
7:39|WYC|The woman is bound to the law, as long time as her husband liveth; and if her husband is dead, she is delivered from the law of the husband [she is delivered from the law], be she wedded to whom she will, only in the Lord.
7:39|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|丈夫活著的時候，妻子是被束縛的；丈夫若睡了，妻子就可以自由，隨願嫁人，只是要嫁在主裡的人。
7:40<version name="ASV">But she is happier if she abide as she is, after my judgment: and I think that I also have the Spirit of God. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:40<version name="Darby">But she is happier if she so remain, according to my  judgment; but I think that *I* also have God's Spirit. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:40<version name="KJV">But she is happier if she so abide, after my judgment: and I think also that I have the Spirit of God.</p><p /><br /></version>
7:40|WYC|But she shall be more blessed, if she dwelleth thus [if she shall thus dwell], after my counsel; and I ween, that I have the Spirit of God.
7:40|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而，按我的意見，她若守節更是有福；但我想我也有神的靈了。
8:1|ASV|Now concerning things sacrificed to idols: We know that we all have knowledge. Knowledge puffeth up, but love edifieth.
8:1|Darby|But concerning things sacrificed to idols, we know, (for we  all have knowledge: knowledge puffs up, but love edifies.
8:1|KJV|Now as touching things offered unto idols, we know that we all have knowledge. Knowledge puffeth up, but charity edifieth.
8:1<version name="WYC">But of these things that be sacrificed to idols, we know, for all we have knowing.  But knowing bloweth, charity edifieth [Soothly science, <i>or knowing</i>, in-bloweth <i>with pride</i>, charity edifieth].</version>
8:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|關於祭偶像之物，我們曉得我們都有知識。知識是叫人自高自大，惟有愛建造人。
8:2|ASV|If any man thinketh that he knoweth anything, he knoweth not yet as he ought to know;
8:2|Darby|If any one think he knows anything, he knows nothing yet as  he ought to know [it].
8:2|KJV|And if any man think that he knoweth any thing, he knoweth nothing yet as he ought to know.
8:2<version name="WYC">But if any man guesseth [Forsooth if any man guess, <i>or deem</i>], that he knoweth any thing, he hath not yet known how it behooveth him to know.</version>
8:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若有人自以為知道甚麼，按他所當知道的，他仍是不知道；
8:3|ASV|but if any man loveth God, the same is known by him.
8:3|Darby|But if any one love God, *he* is known of him):
8:3|KJV|But if any man love God, the same is known of him.
8:3|WYC|And if any man loveth God, this is known of him.
8:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但若有人愛神，這人乃是神所知道的。
8:4|ASV|Concerning therefore the eating of things sacrificed to idols, we know that no idol is anything in the world, and that there is no God but one.
8:4|Darby|-- concerning then the eating of things sacrificed to idols,  we know that an idol [is] nothing in [the] world, and that  there [is] no other God save one.
8:4|KJV|As concerning therefore the eating of those things that are offered in sacrifice unto idols, we know that an idol is nothing in the world, and that there is none other God but one.
8:4|WYC|But of meats that be offered to idols, we know, that an idol is nothing in the world, and that there is no God but one.
8:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|關於喫祭偶像之物，我們曉得偶像在世上算不得甚麼，也曉得神只有一位，再沒有別的神。
8:5|ASV|For though there be that are called gods, whether in heaven or on earth; as there are gods many, and lords many;
8:5|Darby|For and if indeed there are [those] called gods, whether in  heaven or on earth, (as there are gods many, and lords many,)
8:5|KJV|For though there be that are called gods, whether in heaven or in earth, (as there be gods many, and lords many,)
8:5|WYC|For though there be some that be said gods [For why though there be that be said gods], either in heaven, either in earth, as there be many gods, and many lords;
8:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|縱然有稱為神的，或在天，或在地，就如那許多的神，許多的主，
8:6|ASV|yet to us there is one God, the Father, of whom are all things, and we unto him; and one Lord, Jesus Christ, through whom are all things, and we through him.
8:6|Darby|yet to us [there is] one God, the Father, of whom all  things, and *we* for him; and one Lord, Jesus Christ, by whom  [are] all things, and *we* by him.
8:6|KJV|But to us there is but one God, the Father, of whom are all things, and we in him; and one Lord Jesus Christ, by whom are all things, and we by him.
8:6<version name="WYC">nevertheless to us is one God, the Father, of whom <i>be</i> all things, and we in him; and one Lord Jesus Christ, by whom <i>be </i>all things, and we by him.</version>
8:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在我們卻只有一位神，就是父，萬物都本於祂，我們也歸於祂；並有一位主，就是耶穌基督，萬物都是藉著祂有的，我們也是藉著祂有的。
8:7|ASV|Howbeit there is not in all men that knowledge: but some, being used until now to the idol, eat as of a thing sacrificed to an idol; and their conscience being weak is defiled.
8:7|Darby|But knowledge [is] not in all: but some, with conscience of  the idol, until now eat as of a thing sacrificed to idols; and  their conscience, being weak, is defiled.
8:7|KJV|Howbeit there is not in every man that knowledge: for some with conscience of the idol unto this hour eat it as a thing offered unto an idol; and their conscience being weak is defiled.
8:7|WYC|But not in all men is knowing.  For some men with conscience of idol till now eat as thing offered to idols; and their conscience is defouled, for it is frail [when it is sick].
8:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而人不都有這等知識；有人直到如今還帶著拜偶像的習慣感，就以為所喫的是祭偶像之物；他們的良心既然軟弱，就受了玷污。
8:8|ASV|But food will not commend us to God: neither, if we eat not, are we the worse; nor, if we eat, are we the better.
8:8|Darby|But meat does not commend us to God; neither if we should  not eat do we come short; nor if we should eat have we an  advantage.
8:8|KJV|But meat commendeth us not to God: for neither, if we eat, are we the better; neither, if we eat not, are we the worse.
8:8<version name="WYC">[Forsooth] Meat commendeth us not to God; for neither we shall fail, if we eat not, neither if we eat, we shall have plenty [we shall abound, <i>or have plenty</i>].</version>
8:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其實食物不能將我們薦與神，因為我們不喫也無虧缺，喫也無盈超。
8:9|ASV|But take heed lest by any means this liberty of yours become a stumblingblock to the weak.
8:9|Darby|But see lest anywise this your right [to eat] itself be a  stumbling-block to the weak.
8:9|KJV|But take heed lest by any means this liberty of yours become a stumblingblock to them that are weak.
8:9<version name="WYC">But see ye, lest peradventure this your leave be made hurting to frail men. [See ye forsooth, lest peradventure this your license, <i>or leave</i>, be made hurting, <i>or offence,</i> to sick men, <i>or frail</i>.]</version>
8:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只是你們要謹慎，恐怕你們這權利，竟成了那軟弱人的絆腳石。
8:10|ASV|For if a man see thee who hast knowledge sitting at meat in an idol's temple, will not his conscience, if he is weak, be emboldened to eat things sacrificed to idols?
8:10|Darby|For if any one see thee, who hast knowledge, sitting at  table in an idol-house, shall not his conscience, he being  weak, be emboldened to eat the things sacrificed to the idol?
8:10|KJV|For if any man see thee which hast knowledge sit at meat in the idol's temple, shall not the conscience of him which is weak be emboldened to eat those things which are offered to idols;
8:10|WYC|For if any man shall see him, that hath knowing, eating in a place where idols be worshipped, whether his conscience, since it is frail [since it is sick], shall not be edified to eat things offered to idols?
8:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若有人見你這有知識的，在偶像的廟裡坐席，這人既是軟弱的，他的良心豈不放膽去喫那祭偶像之物麼？
8:11|ASV|For through thy knowledge he that is weak perisheth, the brother for whose sake Christ died.
8:11|Darby|and the weak [one], the brother for whose sake Christ died,  will perish through thy knowledge.
8:11|KJV|And through thy knowledge shall the weak brother perish, for whom Christ died?
8:11|WYC|And the frail brother [And the sick brother], for whom Christ died, shall perish in thy knowing.
8:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此，基督為他死的那軟弱弟兄，也就被你的知識敗壞了。
8:12|ASV|And thus, sinning against the brethren, and wounding their conscience when it is weak, ye sin against Christ.
8:12|Darby|Now, thus sinning against the brethren, and wounding their  weak conscience, ye sin against Christ.
8:12|KJV|But when ye sin so against the brethren, and wound their weak conscience, ye sin against Christ.
8:12|WYC|For thus ye sinning against brethren, and smiting their frail conscience [and smiting their sick conscience], sin against Christ.
8:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們這樣得罪弟兄們，傷了他們軟弱的良心，就是得罪基督。
8:13<version name="ASV">Wherefore, if meat causeth my brother to stumble, I will eat no flesh for evermore, that I cause not my brother to stumble. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:13<version name="Darby">Wherefore if meat be a fall-trap to my brother, I will eat  no flesh for ever, that I may not be a fall-trap to my brother. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:13<version name="KJV">Wherefore, if meat make my brother to offend, I will eat no flesh while the world standeth, lest I make my brother to offend.</p><p /><br /></version>
8:13|WYC|Wherefore if meat causeth my brother to stumble, I shall never eat flesh, lest I cause my brother to stumble. [Wherefore if meat causeth my brother to offend, I shall not eat flesh into without end, lest I cause my brother to offend.]
8:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以食物若真絆跌我的弟兄，我就絕不喫肉直到永遠，免得絆跌我的弟兄。
9:1|ASV|Am I not free? Am I not an apostle? Have I not seen Jesus our Lord? Are not ye my work in the Lord?
9:1|Darby|Am I not free? am I not an apostle? have I not seen Jesus  our Lord? are not *ye* my work in [the] Lord?
9:1|KJV|Am I am not an apostle? am I not free? have I not seen Jesus Christ our Lord? are not ye my work in the Lord?
9:1|WYC|Whether I am not free?  Am I not apostle?  Whether I saw not Jesus Christ, our Lord?  Whether ye be not my work in the Lord?
9:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我不是自由的麼？我不是使徒麼？我不是見過我們的主耶穌麼？你們不是我在主裡所作之工麼？
9:2|ASV|If to others I am not an apostle, yet at least I am to you; for the seal of mine apostleship are ye in the Lord.
9:2|Darby|If I am not an apostle to others, yet at any rate I am to  you: for the seal of mine apostleship are *ye* in [the] Lord.
9:2|KJV|If I be not an apostle unto others, yet doubtless I am to you: for the seal of mine apostleship are ye in the Lord.
9:2<version name="WYC">And though to others I am not apostle, but nevertheless to you I am; for ye be the little sign of mine apostlehood [for why ye be the signal, <i>or little sign</i>, of mine apostlehood] in the Lord.</version>
9:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若是對別人我不是使徒，對你們我總是使徒，因為你們在主裡正是我使徒職分的印記。
9:3|ASV|My defence to them that examine me is this.
9:3|Darby|My defence to those who examine me is this:
9:3|KJV|Mine answer to them that do examine me is this,
9:3|WYC|My defence to them that ask me, that is. [My defence to them that ask me, is this].
9:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我對那查問我的人，就是這樣分訴。
9:4|ASV|Have we no right to eat and to drink?
9:4|Darby|Have we not a right to eat and to drink?
9:4|KJV|Have we not power to eat and to drink?
9:4|WYC|Whether we have not power to eat and drink?
9:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|難道我們沒有權利喫喝麼？
9:5|ASV|Have we no right to lead about a wife that is a believer, even as the rest of the apostles, and the brethren of the Lord, and Cephas?
9:5|Darby|have we not a right to take round a sister [as] wife, as  also the other apostles, and the brethren of the Lord, and  Cephas?
9:5|KJV|Have we not power to lead about a sister, a wife, as well as other apostles, and as the brethren of the Lord, and Cephas?
9:5|WYC|Whether we have not power to lead about a woman, a sister, as also other apostles, and brethren of the Lord, and Cephas?
9:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|難道我們沒有權利帶著為妻子的姊妹往來，彷彿其餘的使徒，和主的兄弟，並磯法一樣麼？
9:6|ASV|Or I only and Barnabas, have we not a right to forbear working?
9:6|Darby|Or *I* alone and Barnabas, have we not a right not to work?
9:6|KJV|Or I only and Barnabas, have not we power to forbear working?
9:6|WYC|Or I alone and Barnabas have not power to work these things?
9:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|獨有我與巴拿巴沒有權利不作工麼？
9:7|ASV|What soldier ever serveth at his own charges? who planteth a vineyard, and eateth not the fruit thereof? Or who feedeth a flock, and eateth not of the milk of the flock?
9:7|Darby|Who ever carries on war at his own charges? who plants a  vineyard and does not eat of its fruit? or who herds a flock  and does not eat of the milk of the flock?
9:7|KJV|Who goeth a warfare any time at his own charges? who planteth a vineyard, and eateth not of the fruit thereof? or who feedeth a flock, and eateth not of the milk of the flock?
9:7<version name="WYC">Who travaileth any time with his own wages?  Who planteth a vineyard, and eateth not of his fruit?  Who keepeth a flock, and eateth not of the milk of the flock? <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21565a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
9:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有誰當兵，曾自備糧餉？有誰栽種葡萄園，不喫園中的果子？有誰牧養羊群，不喫羊群的奶？
9:8|ASV|Do I speak these things after the manner of men? or saith not the law also the same?
9:8|Darby|Do I speak these things as a man, or does not the law also  say these things?
9:8|KJV|Say I these things as a man? or saith not the law the same also?
9:8|WYC|Whether after man I say these things? whether also the law saith not these things?
9:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我說這話，豈是照著人的看法麼？律法不也是這樣說麼？
9:9|ASV|For it is written in the law of Moses, Thou shalt not muzzle the ox when he treadeth out the corn. Is it for the oxen that God careth,
9:9|Darby|For in the law of Moses it is written, Thou shalt not muzzle  the ox that is treading out corn. Is God occupied about the  oxen,
9:9|KJV|For it is written in the law of Moses, thou shalt not muzzle the mouth of the ox that treadeth out the corn. Doth God take care for oxen?
9:9|WYC|For it is written in the law of Moses, Thou shalt not bind [up] the mouth of the ox that thresheth.  Whether of oxen is charge to God?
9:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在摩西的律法上記著：“牛踹穀的時候，不可籠住牠的嘴。”難道神所關心的是牛麼？
9:10|ASV|or saith he it assuredly for our sake? Yea, for our sake it was written: because he that ploweth ought to plow in hope, and he that thresheth, to thresh in hope of partaking.
9:10|Darby|or does he say [it] altogether for our sakes? For for our  sakes it has been written, that the plougher should plough in  hope, and he that treads out corn, in hope of partaking of  [it].
9:10|KJV|Or saith he it altogether for our sakes? For our sakes, no doubt, this is written: that he that ploweth should plow in hope; and that he that thresheth in hope should be partaker of his hope.
9:10|WYC|Whether for us he saith these things?  For why those be written for us [For why for us they be written]; for he that ploweth, oweth to plow in hope, and he that thresheth, in hope to take fruits.
9:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|還是全為我們說的？的確是為我們寫的，因為耕種的當存著指望去耕種，打場的也當存著分享的指望去打場。
9:11|ASV|If we sowed unto you spiritual things, is it a great matter if we shall reap your carnal things?
9:11|Darby|If we have sown to you spiritual things, [is it a] great  [thing] if *we* shall reap your carnal things?
9:11|KJV|If we have sown unto you spiritual things, is it a great thing if we shall reap your carnal things?
9:11|WYC|If we sow spiritual things to you, is it great, if we reap your fleshly things?
9:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們若把屬靈之物撒給你們，就是從你們收割肉身之物，這還算大事麼？
9:12|ASV|If others partake of this right over you, do not we yet more? Nevertheless we did not use this right; but we bear all things, that we may cause no hindrance to the gospel of Christ.
9:12|Darby|If others partake of this right over you, should not rather  *we*? But we have not used this right, but we bear all things,  that we may put no hindrance in the way of the glad tidings of  the Christ.
9:12|KJV|If others be partakers of this power over you, are not we rather? Nevertheless we have not used this power; but suffer all things, lest we should hinder the gospel of Christ.
9:12|WYC|If others be partners of your power, why not rather we?  But we use not this power, but we suffer all things, that we give no hindering [that we give no letting] to the evangel of Christ.
9:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若別人在你們身上分享這權利，何況我們？然而我們沒有用過這權利，倒凡事忍受，免得基督的福音受到任何攔阻。
9:13|ASV|Know ye not that they that minister about sacred things eat of the things of the temple, and they that wait upon the altar have their portion with the altar?
9:13|Darby|Do ye not know that they who labour [at] sacred things eat  of the [offerings offered in the] temple; they that attend at  the altar partake with the altar?
9:13|KJV|Do ye not know that they which minister about holy things live of the things of the temple? and they which wait at the altar are partakers with the altar?
9:13|WYC|Know ye not, that they that work in the temple, eat those things that be of the temple [Know ye not, that they that work in the sanctuary, eat those things that be of the sanctuary], and they that serve to the altar, be partners of the altar?
9:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們豈不知為聖事勞碌的，就喫殿中之物麼？伺候祭壇的，就同祭壇分領壇上的祭物麼？
9:14|ASV|Even so did the Lord ordain that they that proclaim the gospel should live of the gospel.
9:14|Darby|So also the Lord has ordained to those that announce the  glad tidings to live of the glad tidings.
9:14|KJV|Even so hath the Lord ordained that they which preach the gospel should live of the gospel.
9:14|WYC|So [and] the Lord ordained to them that tell the gospel, to live of the gospel.
9:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主也是這樣命定，叫宣傳福音的靠福音養生。
9:15|ASV|But I have used none of these things: and I write not these things that it may be so done in my case; for  it were good for me rather to die, than that any man should make my glorifying void.
9:15|Darby|But *I* have used none of these things. Now I have not  written these things that it should be thus in my case; for [it  were] good for me rather to die than that any one should make  vain my boast.
9:15|KJV|But I have used none of these things: neither have I written these things, that it should be so done unto me: for it were better for me to die, than that any man should make my glorying void.
9:15|WYC|But I used none of these things; and I wrote not these things, that they be done so in me; for it is good rather for me to die, than that any man should make my rejoicing void [than that any man void my glory].
9:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但這些權利我全沒有用過；我寫這些話，並非要你們這樣待我，因為我寧可死，也不─沒有人能使我所誇的落了空。
9:16|ASV|For if I preach the gospel, I have nothing to glory of; for necessity is laid upon me; for woe is unto me, if I preach not the gospel.
9:16|Darby|For if I announce the glad tidings, I have nothing to boast  of; for a necessity is laid upon me; for it is woe to me if I  should not announce the glad tidings.
9:16|KJV|For though I preach the gospel, I have nothing to glory of: for necessity is laid upon me; yea, woe is unto me, if I preach not the gospel!
9:16<version name="WYC">For if I preach the gospel, glory is not to me, for need-like I must do it <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21574b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup>; for woe to me, if I preach not the gospel.</version>
9:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我若傳福音，於我原沒有可誇的，因為我是不得已的。若不傳福音，我便有禍了。
9:17|ASV|For if I do this of mine own will, I have a reward: but if not of mine own will, I have a stewardship intrusted to me.
9:17|Darby|For if I do this voluntarily, I have a reward; but if not  of my own will, I am entrusted with an administration.
9:17|KJV|For if I do this thing willingly, I have a reward: but if against my will, a dispensation of the gospel is committed unto me.
9:17|WYC|But if I do this thing willfully, I have meed; but if against my will, dispensing is betaken to me. [Forsooth if I willing do this thing, I have meed; soothly if against my will, dispensation is betaken to me.]
9:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我若甘心作這事，就有賞賜；若不甘心，管家的職分卻已經託付我了。
9:18|ASV|What then is my reward? That, when I preach the gospel, I may make the gospel without charge, so as not to use to the full my right in the gospel.
9:18|Darby|What is the reward then that I have? That in announcing the  glad tidings I make the glad tidings costless [to others], so  as not to have made use, as belonging to me, of my right in  [announcing] the glad tidings.
9:18|KJV|What is my reward then? Verily that, when I preach the gospel, I may make the gospel of Christ without charge, that I abuse not my power in the gospel.
9:18<version name="WYC">What then is my meed?  That I preaching the gospel, put the gospel without others' cost, that I use not my power in the gospel. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21576c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup></version>
9:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我的賞賜是甚麼？就是在傳福音上，我免費供應福音，免得用盡我在福音上的權利。
9:19|ASV|For though I was free from all men, I brought myself under bondage to all, that I might gain the more.
9:19|Darby|For being free from all, I have made myself bondman to all,  that I might gain the most [possible].
9:19|KJV|For though I be free from all men, yet have I made myself servant unto all, that I might gain the more.
9:19|WYC|For why when I was free of all men, I made me servant of all men, to win the more men [that I should win more men].
9:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我雖從眾人得了自由，卻自願奴役於眾人，為要多得人。
9:20|ASV|And to the Jews I became as a Jew, that I might gain Jews; to them that are under the law, as under the law, not being myself under the law, that I might gain them that are under the law;
9:20|Darby|And I became to the Jews as a Jew, in order that I might  gain the Jews: to those under law, as under law, not being  myself under law, in order that I might gain those under law:
9:20|KJV|And unto the Jews I became as a Jew, that I might gain the Jews; to them that are under the law, as under the law, that I might gain them that are under the law;
9:20|WYC|And to Jews I am made as a Jew, to win the Jews [that I should win Jews]; to them that be under the law, as I were under the law, when I was not under the law, to win them that were under the law [that I should win them that were under the law];
9:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|向猶太人，我就作猶太人，為要得猶太人；向律法之下的人，我就作律法之下的人，（雖然我自己不在律法之下，）為要得律法之下的人；
9:21|ASV|to them that are without law, as without law, not being without law to God, but under law to Christ, that I might gain them that are without law.
9:21|Darby|to those without law, as without law, (not as without law  to God, but as legitimately subject to Christ,) in order that I  might gain [those] without law.
9:21|KJV|To them that are without law, as without law, (being not without law to God, but under the law to Christ,) that I might gain them that are without law.
9:21|WYC|to them that were without law, as I were without law, when I was not without [the] law of God, but I was in the law of Christ, to win them that were without law [that I should win them that were without law].
9:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|向律法之外的人，我就作律法之外的人，（對神，我不是在律法之外，反而對基督，我是在律法之內，）為要得律法之外的人。
9:22|ASV|To the weak I became weak, that I might gain the weak: I am become all things to all men, that I may by all means save some.
9:22|Darby|I became to the weak, [as] weak, in order that I might gain  the weak. To all I have become all things, in order that at all  events I might save some.
9:22|KJV|To the weak became I as weak, that I might gain the weak: I am made all things to all men, that I might by all means save some.
9:22|WYC|I am made frail to frail men, to win frail men; to all men I am made all things, to make all men safe. [I am made sick to sick men, that I should win sick men; to all men I am made all things, that I should make all men safe.]
9:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|向軟弱的人，我就成為軟弱的，為要得軟弱的人。向眾人，我成了眾人所是的；無論如何，總要救些人。
9:23|ASV|And I do all things for the gospel's sake, that I may be a joint partaker thereof.
9:23|Darby|And I do all things for the sake of the glad tidings, that  I may be fellow-partaker with them.
9:23|KJV|And this I do for the gospel's sake, that I might be partaker thereof with you.
9:23|WYC|But I do all things for the gospel, that I [should] be made partner of it.
9:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡我所行的，都是為福音的緣故，為要與人同享這福音。
9:24|ASV|Know ye not that they that run in a race run all, but one receiveth the prize? Even so run; that ye may attain.
9:24|Darby|Know ye not that they who run in [the] race-course run all,  but one receives the prize? Thus run in order that ye may  obtain.
9:24|KJV|Know ye not that they which run in a race run all, but one receiveth the prize? So run, that ye may obtain.
9:24|WYC|Know ye not, that they that run in a furlong, all run, but one taketh the prize?  So run ye, that ye catch.
9:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|豈不知在場上賽跑的都跑，但得獎賞的只有一人？你們應當這樣跑，好叫你們得著獎賞。
9:25|ASV|And every man that striveth in the games exerciseth self-control in all things. Now they do it to receive a corruptible crown; but we an incorruptible.
9:25|Darby|But every one that contends [for a prize] is temperate in  all things: *they* then indeed that they may receive a  corruptible crown, but *we* an incorruptible.
9:25|KJV|And every man that striveth for the mastery is temperate in all things. Now they do it to obtain a corruptible crown; but we an incorruptible.
9:25|WYC|Each man that striveth in fight, abstaineth him from all things; and they [forsooth], that they take a corruptible crown, but we an uncorrupt.
9:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡較力爭勝的，諸事都有節制；他們不過是要得能壞的華冠，我們卻是要得不能壞的華冠。
9:26|ASV|I therefore so run, as not uncertainly; so fight I, as not beating the air:
9:26|Darby|*I* therefore thus run, as not uncertainly; so I combat, as  not beating the air.
9:26|KJV|I therefore so run, not as uncertainly; so fight I, not as one that beateth the air:
9:26|WYC|Therefore I run so, not as to an uncertain thing; thus I fight, not as beating the air;
9:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我這樣奔跑，不像無定向的；我這樣鬥拳，不像打空氣的；
9:27<version name="ASV">but I buffet my body, and bring it into bondage: lest by any means, after that I have preached to others, I myself should be rejected. </p><p /><br /></version>
9:27<version name="Darby">But I buffet my body, and lead it captive, lest [after]  having preached to others I should be myself rejected. </p><p /><br /></version>
9:27<version name="KJV">But I keep under my body, and bring it into subjection: lest that by any means, when I have preached to others, I myself should be a castaway.</p><p /><br /></version>
9:27<version name="WYC">but I chastise my body, and bring <i>it</i> into servage; lest peradventure when I preach to others [lest peradventure when I have preached to others], I myself be made reprovable.</version>
9:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我乃是痛擊己身，叫身為奴，免得我傳給別人，自己反不蒙稱許。
10:1|ASV|For I would not, brethren, have you ignorant, that our fathers were all under the cloud, and all passed through the sea;
10:1|Darby|For I would not have you ignorant, brethren, that all our  fathers were under the cloud, and all passed through the sea;
10:1|KJV|Moreover, brethren, I would not that ye should be ignorant, how that all our fathers were under the cloud, and all passed through the sea;
10:1|WYC|Brethren, I will not, that ye not know [Soothly, brethren, I will not you to unknow], that all our fathers were under [a] cloud, and all passed the sea;
10:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為弟兄們，我不願意你們不知道，我們的祖宗從前都在雲下，都從海中經過；
10:2|ASV|and were all baptized unto Moses in the cloud and in the sea;
10:2|Darby|and all were baptised unto Moses in the cloud and in the  sea;
10:2|KJV|And were all baptized unto Moses in the cloud and in the sea;
10:2|WYC|and all were baptized in Moses, in the cloud and in the sea;
10:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|都在雲裡，也在海裡，受浸歸了摩西；
10:3|ASV|and did all eat the same spiritual food;
10:3|Darby|and all ate the same spiritual food,
10:3|KJV|And did all eat the same spiritual meat;
10:3|WYC|and all ate the same spiritual meat,
10:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且都喫了一樣的靈食，
10:4|ASV|and did all drink the same spiritual drink: for they drank of a spiritual rock that followed them: and the rock was Christ.
10:4|Darby|and all drank the same spiritual drink, for they drank of a  spiritual rock which followed [them]: (now the rock was the  Christ;)
10:4|KJV|And did all drink the same spiritual drink: for they drank of that spiritual Rock that followed them: and that Rock was Christ.
10:4|WYC|and all drank the same spiritual drink; and they drank of the spiritual stone following them [forsooth they drank of the spiritual stone following them]; and the stone was Christ.
10:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|也都喝了一樣的靈水；所喝的是出於隨行的靈磐石，那磐石就是基督。
10:5|ASV|Howbeit with most of them God was not well pleased: for they were overthrown in the wilderness.
10:5|Darby|yet God was not pleased with the most of them, for they  were strewed in the desert.
10:5|KJV|But with many of them God was not well pleased: for they were overthrown in the wilderness.
10:5|WYC|But not in full many of them it was well pleasant to God; for why they were cast down in [the] desert.
10:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但他們大多數的人，神並不喜悅，因此他們倒斃在曠野。
10:6|ASV|Now these things were our examples, to the intent we should not lust after evil things, as they also lusted.
10:6|Darby|But these things happened [as] types of us, that we should  not be lusters after evil things, as they also lusted.
10:6|KJV|Now these things were our examples, to the intent we should not lust after evil things, as they also lusted.
10:6|WYC|But these things were done in figure of us, that we be not coveters of evil things, as [and] they coveted.
10:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些事都是我們的鑑戒，叫我們不作貪戀惡事的人，像他們那樣貪戀。
10:7|ASV|Neither be ye idolaters, as were some of them; as it is written, The people sat down to eat and drink, and rose up to play.
10:7|Darby|Neither be ye idolaters, as some of them; as it is written,  The people sat down to eat and to drink, and rose up to play.
10:7|KJV|Neither be ye idolaters, as were some of them; as it is written, The people sat down to eat and drink, and rose up to play.
10:7|WYC|Neither be ye made idolaters, as some of them; as it is written, The people sat to eat and drink, and they rose up to play [and they have risen up to play].
10:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|也不要作拜偶像的人，像他們有些人那樣；如經上所記：“百姓坐下喫喝，起來玩耍。”
10:8|ASV|Neither let us commit fornication, as some of them committed, and fell in one day three and twenty thousand.
10:8|Darby|Neither let us commit fornication, as some of them  committed fornication, and fell in one day three and twenty  thousand.
10:8|KJV|Neither let us commit fornication, as some of them committed, and fell in one day three and twenty thousand.
10:8<version name="WYC">Neither do we fornication, as some of them did fornication, and three and twenty thousand were dead in one day [and three and twenty thousand fell, <i>or died</i>, in one day].</version>
10:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們也不要行淫，像他們有些人行的，一天就倒斃了二萬三千人。
10:9|ASV|Neither let us make trial of the Lord, as some of them made trial, and perished by the serpents.
10:9|Darby|Neither let us tempt the Christ, as some of them tempted,  and perished by serpents.
10:9|KJV|Neither let us tempt Christ, as some of them also tempted, and were destroyed of serpents.
10:9|WYC|Neither tempt we Christ, as some of them tempted, and perished of serpents.
10:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們也不要試探基督，像他們有些人試探的，就被蛇所滅。
10:10|ASV|Neither murmur ye, as some of them murmured, and perished by the destroyer.
10:10|Darby|Neither murmur ye, as some of them murmured, and perished  by the destroyer.
10:10|KJV|Neither murmur ye, as some of them also murmured, and were destroyed of the destroyer.
10:10<version name="WYC">Neither grumble ye, as some of them grumbled, and they perished of a destroyer. [Neither grutch ye, as some of them grutched, and they perished of the waster, <i>or destroyer</i>.]</version>
10:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們也不要發怨言，像他們有些人發的，就被滅命的所滅。
10:11|ASV|Now these things happened unto them by way of example; and they were written for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the ages are come.
10:11|Darby|Now all these things happened to them [as] types, and have  been written for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the ages  are come.
10:11|KJV|Now all these things happened unto them for examples: and they are written for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the world are come.
10:11<version name="WYC">And all these things fell to them in figure; but they be written to our amending, into whom the ends of the worlds be come [soothly they be written to our correction, <i>or amending</i>, into whom the ends of the world have come].</version>
10:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些發生在他們身上的事，都是鑑戒，並且寫在經上，正是為警戒我們這生在諸世代終局的人。
10:12|ASV|Wherefore let him that thinketh he standeth take heed lest he fall.
10:12|Darby|So that let him that thinks that he stands take heed lest  he fall.
10:12|KJV|Wherefore let him that thinketh he standeth take heed lest he fall.
10:12|WYC|Therefore he that guesseth him(self), that he standeth, see he, that he fall not. [And so he that guesseth him to stand, see, that he fall not.]
10:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以自以為站得穩的，要謹慎，免得跌倒。
10:13|ASV|There hath no temptation taken you but such as man can bear: but God is faithful, who will not suffer you to be tempted above that ye are able; but will with the temptation make also the way of escape, that ye may be able to endure it.
10:13|Darby|No temptation has taken you but such as is according to  man's nature; and God is faithful, who will not suffer you to  be tempted above what ye are able [to bear], but will with the  temptation make the issue also, so that [ye] should be able to  bear [it].
10:13|KJV|There hath no temptation taken you but such as is common to man: but God is faithful, who will not suffer you to be tempted above that ye are able; but will with the temptation also make a way to escape, that ye may be able to bear it.
10:13<version name="WYC">Temptation take not you, but man's <i>temptation</i>; for God is true, which shall not suffer you to be tempted above that that ye be able; but he shall make with temptation also purveyance, that ye be able to suffer [that ye may sustain].</version>
10:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那臨到你們的試誘，無非是人所能受的；神是信實的，必不容你們受試誘過於所能受的，祂也必隨著試誘開一條出路，叫你們能忍受得住。
10:14|ASV|Wherefore, my beloved, flee from idolatry.
10:14|Darby|Wherefore, my beloved, flee from idolatry.
10:14|KJV|Wherefore, my dearly beloved, flee from idolatry.
10:14|WYC|Wherefore, ye most dear-worthy to me, flee ye from the worshipping of maumets [flee from worshipping of idols].
10:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，我所親愛的，你們要逃避拜偶像的事。
10:15|ASV|I speak as to wise men; judge ye what I say.
10:15|Darby|I speak as to intelligent [persons]: do *ye* judge what I  say.
10:15|KJV|I speak as to wise men; judge ye what I say.
10:15|WYC|As to prudent men I speak, deem ye yourselves that thing that I say.
10:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我好像對精明人說的，你們要審斷我所說的。
10:16|ASV|The cup of blessing which we bless, is it not a communion of the blood of Christ? The bread which we break, is it not a communion of the body of Christ?
10:16|Darby|The cup of blessing which we bless, is it not [the]  communion of the blood of the Christ? The bread which we break,  is it not [the] communion of the body of the Christ?
10:16|KJV|The cup of blessing which we bless, is it not the communion of the blood of Christ? The bread which we break, is it not the communion of the body of Christ?
10:16<version name="WYC">Whether the cup of blessing which we bless, is not the communing of Christ's blood? and whether the bread which we break, is not the <i>part</i> taking of the body of the Lord? [The cup of blessing which we bless, whether it is not the communing of Christ's blood? and the bread which we break, whether it is not the dealing, <i>or part taking</i>, of the body of the Lord?]</version>
10:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們所祝福的福杯，豈不是基督之血的交通麼？我們所擘開的餅，豈不是基督身體的交通麼？
10:17|ASV|seeing that we, who are many, are one bread, one body: for we are all partake of the one bread.
10:17|Darby|Because we, [being] many, are one loaf, one body; for we  all partake of that one loaf.
10:17|KJV|For we being many are one bread, and one body: for we are all partakers of that one bread.
10:17|WYC|For we many be one bread and one body, all we that take part of one bread and of one cup.
10:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因著只有一個餅，我們雖多，還是一個身體，因我們都分受這一個餅。
10:18|ASV|Behold Israel after the flesh: have not they that eat the sacrifices communion with the altar?
10:18|Darby|See Israel according to flesh: are not they who eat the  sacrifices in communion with the altar?
10:18|KJV|Behold Israel after the flesh: are not they which eat of the sacrifices partakers of the altar?
10:18|WYC|See ye Israel after the flesh, whether they that eat sacrifices, be not partners of the altar?
10:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們看那按著肉體是以色列人的，那些喫祭物的，豈不是與祭壇交通的人麼？
10:19|ASV|What say I then? that a thing sacrificed to idols is anything, or that an idol is anything?
10:19|Darby|What then do I say? that what is sacrificed to an idol is  anything, or that an idol is anything?
10:19|KJV|What say I then? that the idol is any thing, or that which is offered in sacrifice to idols is any thing?
10:19|WYC|What therefore say I, that a thing that is offered to idols is any thing, or that the idol is any thing?
10:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我是怎麼說的？豈是說祭偶像之物算得甚麼？或是說偶像算得甚麼？
10:20|ASV|But I say, that the things which the Gentiles sacrifice, they sacrifice to demons, and not to God: and I would not that ye should have communion with demons.
10:20|Darby|But that what [the nations] sacrifice they sacrifice to  demons, and not to God. Now I do not wish you to be in  communion with demons.
10:20|KJV|But I say, that the things which the Gentiles sacrifice, they sacrifice to devils, and not to God: and I would not that ye should have fellowship with devils.
10:20|WYC|But those things that heathen men offer, they offer to devils, and not to God.  But I will not, that ye be made fellows of fiends;
10:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我乃是說，外邦人所獻的祭，是祭鬼，不是祭神；我不願意你們成為與鬼交通的人。
10:21|ASV|Ye cannot drink the cup of the Lord, and the cup of demons: ye cannot partake of the table of the Lord, and of the table of demons.
10:21|Darby|Ye cannot drink [the] Lord's cup, and [the] cup of demons:  ye cannot partake of [the] Lord's table, and of [the] table of  demons.
10:21|KJV|Ye cannot drink the cup of the Lord, and the cup of devils: ye cannot be partakers of the Lord's table, and of the table of devils.
10:21|WYC|for ye be not able to drink the cup of the Lord [for ye may not drink the cup of the Lord], and the cup of fiends; ye be not able to be partners of the board of the Lord [ye may not be partners of the board of the Lord], and of the board of fiends.
10:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們不能喝主的杯，又喝鬼的杯；不能有分於主的筵席，又有分於鬼的筵席。
10:22|ASV|Or do we provoke the Lord to jealousy? are we stronger than he?
10:22|Darby|Do we provoke the Lord to jealousy? are we stronger than  he?
10:22|KJV|Do we provoke the Lord to jealousy? are we stronger than he?
10:22|WYC|Whether we have envy to the Lord? whether we be stronger than he?
10:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們可惹主的妒忌麼？難道我們比祂還強麼？
10:23|ASV|All things are lawful; but not all things are expedient. All things are lawful; but not all things edify.
10:23|Darby|All things are lawful, but all are not profitable; all  things are lawful, but all do not edify.
10:23|KJV|All things are lawful for me, but all things are not expedient: all things are lawful for me, but all things edify not.
10:23|WYC|All things be leaveful to me, but not all things be speedful.  All things be leaveful to me, but not all things edify.
10:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡事都可行，但不都有益處；凡事都可行，但不都建造人。
10:24|ASV|Let no man seek his own, but  each his neighbor's good.
10:24|Darby|Let no one seek his own [advantage], but that of the  other.
10:24|KJV|Let no man seek his own, but every man another's wealth.
10:24|WYC|No man seek that thing that is his own, but that thing that is of another.
10:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|無論何人，不要尋求自己的益處，乃要尋求別人的益處。
10:25|ASV|Whatsoever is sold in the shambles, eat, asking no question for conscience' sake,
10:25|Darby|Everything sold in the shambles eat, making no inquiry for  conscience sake.
10:25|KJV|Whatsoever is sold in the shambles, that eat, asking no question for conscience sake:
10:25|WYC|All thing that is sold in the butchery, eat ye, asking nothing for conscience.
10:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡肉市上所賣的，你們只管喫，不要為良心的緣故查問甚麼，
10:26|ASV|for the earth is the Lord's, and the fulness thereof.
10:26|Darby|For the earth [is] the Lord's and its fulness.
10:26|KJV|For the earth is the Lord's, and the fulness thereof.
10:26|WYC|The earth and the plenty of it, is the Lord's.
10:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為地和地的豐滿，都屬於主。
10:27|ASV|If one of them that believe not biddeth you to a feast, and ye are disposed to go; whatsoever is set before you, eat, asking no question for conscience' sake.
10:27|Darby|But if any one of the unbelievers invite you, and ye are  minded to go, all that is set before you eat, making no inquiry  for conscience sake.
10:27|KJV|If any of them that believe not bid you to a feast, and ye be disposed to go; whatsoever is set before you, eat, asking no question for conscience sake.
10:27<version name="WYC">If any of heathen men call you to supper [Forsooth if any of unfaithful, <i>or heathen men</i>, calleth you to supper], and ye will go, all thing that is set to you, eat ye, asking nothing for conscience.</version>
10:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若有不信的人請你們，你們也願意去，凡擺在你們面前的，只管喫，不要為良心的緣故查問甚麼。
10:28|ASV|But if any man say unto you, This hath been offered in sacrifice, eat not, for his sake that showed it, and for conscience sake:
10:28|Darby|But if any one say to you, This is offered to holy  purposes, do not eat, for his sake that pointed it out, and  conscience sake;
10:28|KJV|But if any man say unto you, this is offered in sacrifice unto idols, eat not for his sake that shewed it, and for conscience sake: for the earth is the Lord's, and the fulness thereof:
10:28<version name="WYC">But if any man saith [If any man soothly say to you], This thing is offered to idols, do not ye eat, for him that showed [<i>this thing</i>], and for conscience;</version>
10:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但若有人對你們說，這是獻過祭的物，就要為那指出的人，並為良心的緣故，不喫；
10:29|ASV|conscience, I say, not thine own, but the other's; for why is my liberty judged by another conscience?
10:29|Darby|but conscience, I mean, not thine own, but that of the  other: for why is my liberty judged by another conscience?
10:29|KJV|Conscience, I say, not thine own, but of the other: for why is my liberty judged of another man's conscience?
10:29<version name="WYC">and I say not, thy conscience, but of another [<i>man's</i>].  But whereto is my freedom deemed of another man's conscience [Soothly whereto is my liberty, <i>or</i> <i>freedom</i>, deemed of another man's conscience]?</version>
10:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我說的良心，不是你自己的，乃是別人的。我這自由為甚麼被別人的良心審判？
10:30|ASV|If I partake with thankfulness, why am I evil spoken of for that for which I give thanks?
10:30|Darby|If *I* partake with thanksgiving, why am I spoken evil of  for what *I* give thanks for?
10:30|KJV|For if I by grace be a partaker, why am I evil spoken of for that for which I give thanks?
10:30<version name="WYC">Therefore if I take part with grace, what am I blasphemed, for that that I do thankings [for that that I do graces, <i>or thankings</i>]?</version>
10:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我若感恩著分受，為甚麼在我所感謝的物上被人毀謗？
10:31|ASV|Whether therefore ye eat, or drink, or whatsoever ye do, do all to the glory of God.
10:31|Darby|Whether therefore ye eat, or drink, or whatever ye do, do  all things to God's glory.
10:31|KJV|Whether therefore ye eat, or drink, or whatsoever ye do, do all to the glory of God.
10:31|WYC|Therefore whether ye eat, or drink, or do any other thing, do ye all things to the glory of God.
10:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以你們或喫、或喝、或作甚麼事，一切都要為榮耀神而行。
10:32|ASV|Give no occasions of stumbling, either to Jews, or to Greeks, or to the church of God:
10:32|Darby|Give no occasion to stumbling, whether to Jews, or Greeks,  or the assembly of God.
10:32|KJV|Give none offence, neither to the Jews, nor to the Gentiles, nor to the church of God:
10:32|WYC|Be ye without offence to Jews, and to heathen men, and to the church of God;
10:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不拘對猶太人，對希利尼人，對神的召會，你們都不要成為絆腳石；
10:33<version name="ASV">even as I also please all men in all things, not seeking mine own profit, but the profit of the many, that they may be saved. </p><p /><br /></version>
10:33<version name="Darby">Even as *I* also please all in all things; not seeking my  own profit, but that of the many, that they may be saved. </p><p /><br /></version>
10:33<version name="KJV">Even as I please all men in all things, not seeking mine own profit, but the profit of many, that they may be saved.</p><p /><br /></version>
10:33<version name="WYC">as [and] I by all things please to all men, not seeking that that is profitable to me [not seeking what is profitable to me], but that that <i>is profitable </i>to many men, that they be made safe.</version>
10:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就好像我也凡事叫眾人喜悅，不尋求自己的益處，只尋求多人的益處，叫他們可以得救。
11:1|ASV|Be ye imitators of me, even as I also am of Christ.
11:1|Darby|Be my imitators, even as *I* also [am] of Christ.
11:1|KJV|Be ye followers of me, even as I also am of Christ.
11:1<version name="WYC">Be ye my followers, as [and] I <i>am</i> of Christ. [Be ye followers of me, as and I of Christ.]</version>
11:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要效法我，像我效法基督一樣。
11:2|ASV|Now I praise you that ye remember me in all things, and hold fast the traditions, even as I delivered them to you.
11:2|Darby|Now I praise you, that in all things ye are mindful of me;  and that as I have directed you, ye keep the directions.
11:2|KJV|Now I praise you, brethren, that ye remember me in all things, and keep the ordinances, as I delivered them to you.
11:2|WYC|And, brethren, I praise you, that by all things ye be mindful of me; and as I betook to you my commandments, ye hold [and as I betook to you my commandments, ye keep].
11:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但我稱讚你們，因你們凡事記念我，又照著所交付給你們的，堅守我所傳授的。
11:3|ASV|But I would have you know, that the head of every man is Christ; and the head of the woman is the man; and the head of Christ is God.
11:3|Darby|But I wish you to know that the Christ is the head of every  man, but woman's head [is] the man, and the Christ's head God.
11:3|KJV|But I would have you know, that the head of every man is Christ; and the head of the woman is the man; and the head of Christ is God.
11:3<version name="WYC">But I will that ye know, that Christ is [the] head of each man; but the head of the woman is the man; and the head of Christ <i>is</i> God.</version>
11:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我且願意你們知道，基督是各人的頭，男人是女人的頭，神是基督的頭。
11:4|ASV|Every man praying or prophesying, having his head covered, dishonoreth his head.
11:4|Darby|Every man praying or prophesying, having [anything] on his  head, puts his head to shame.
11:4|KJV|Every man praying or prophesying, having his head covered, dishonoureth his head.
11:4|WYC|Each man praying, or prophesying, when his head is covered, defouleth his head.
11:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡男人禱告，或是申言，若蒙著頭，就羞辱自己的頭。
11:5|ASV|But every woman praying or prophesying with her head unveiled dishonoreth her head; for it is one and the same thing as if she were shaven.
11:5|Darby|But every woman praying or prophesying with her head  uncovered puts her own head to shame; for it is one and the  same as a shaved [woman].
11:5|KJV|But every woman that prayeth or prophesieth with her head uncovered dishonoureth her head: for that is even all one as if she were shaven.
11:5<version name="WYC">But each woman praying, or prophesying, when her head is not covered, defouleth her head; for it is one, as if she were polled [as if she be made bald, <i>polled</i>,<i> or clipped</i>].</version>
11:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但凡女人禱告，或是申言，若不蒙著頭，就羞辱自己的頭，因為這就如同剃了頭髮一樣。
11:6|ASV|For if a woman is not veiled, let her also be shorn: but if it is a shame to a woman to be shorn or shaven, let her be veiled.
11:6|Darby|For if a woman be not covered, let her hair also be cut  off. But if [it be] shameful to a woman to have her hair cut  off or to be shaved, let her be covered.
11:6|KJV|For if the woman be not covered, let her also be shorn: but if it be a shame for a woman to be shorn or shaven, let her be covered.
11:6<version name="WYC">And if a woman be not covered [For if a woman be not veiled, <i>or</i> <i>covered</i>], be she polled; and if it is foul thing to a woman to be polled, or to be made bald, cover she her head.</version>
11:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|女人若不蒙著頭，就該剪了頭髮；女人若以剪髮或剃髮為羞愧，就該把自己蒙起來。
11:7|ASV|For a man indeed ought not to have his head veiled, forasmuch as he is the image and glory of God: but the woman is the glory of the man.
11:7|Darby|For man indeed ought not to have his head covered, being  God's image and glory; but woman is man's glory.
11:7|KJV|For a man indeed ought not to cover his head, forasmuch as he is the image and glory of God: but the woman is the glory of the man.
11:7|WYC|But a man shall not cover his head, for he is the image and glory of God; but a woman is the glory of man.
11:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|男人既是神的形像和榮耀，就不該蒙著頭，但女人是男人的榮耀。
11:8|ASV|For the man is not of the woman; but the woman of the man:
11:8|Darby|For man is not of woman, but woman of man.
11:8|KJV|For the man is not of the woman: but the woman of the man.
11:8|WYC|For a man is not of the woman, but the woman of the man.
11:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|男人原不是由女人而出，女人卻是由男人而出，
11:9|ASV|for neither was the man created for the woman; but the woman for the man:
11:9|Darby|For also man was not created for the sake of the woman, but  woman for the sake of the man.
11:9|KJV|Neither was the man created for the woman; but the woman for the man.
11:9|WYC|And the man is not made for the woman, but the woman for the man.
11:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且男人不是為著女人創造的，女人卻是為著男人創造的。
11:10|ASV|for this cause ought the woman to have a sign of authority on her head, because of the angels.
11:10|Darby|Therefore ought the woman to have authority on her head,  on account of the angels.
11:10|KJV|For this cause ought the woman to have power on her head because of the angels.
11:10|WYC|Therefore the woman shall have a covering on her head, also for angels.
11:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此，女人為著天使的緣故，應當在頭上有服權柄的表記。
11:11|ASV|Nevertheless, neither is the woman without the man, nor the man without the woman, in the Lord.
11:11|Darby|However, neither [is] woman without man, nor man without  woman, in [the] Lord.
11:11|KJV|Nevertheless neither is the man without the woman, neither the woman without the man, in the Lord.
11:11<version name="WYC">Nevertheless neither the man <i>is</i> without the woman, neither the woman <i>is</i> without [the] man, in the Lord.</version>
11:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而在主裡面，女也不是無男，男也不是無女。
11:12|ASV|For as the woman is of the man, so is the man also by the woman; but all things are of God.
11:12|Darby|For as the woman [is] of the man, so also [is] the man by  the woman, but all things of God.
11:12|KJV|For as the woman is of the man, even so is the man also by the woman; but all things of God.
11:12<version name="WYC">For why as the woman <i>is</i> of the man, so [and] the man <i>is</i> by the woman; but all things  <i>be </i>of God.</version>
11:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為女人怎樣出於男人，照樣，男人也是藉著女人，但萬有都是出於神。
11:13|ASV|Judge ye in yourselves: is it seemly that a woman pray unto God unveiled?
11:13|Darby|Judge in yourselves: is it comely that a woman should pray  to God uncovered?
11:13|KJV|Judge in yourselves: is it comely that a woman pray unto God uncovered?
11:13<version name="WYC">Deem ye yourselves; beseemeth it a woman not covered on the head to pray to God? [Ye yourselves deem; becometh, <i>or beseemeth</i>, it a woman not veiled, <i>or</i> <i>covered</i>, to pray to God?]</version>
11:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們自己裡面審斷：女人禱告神不蒙著頭，是合宜的麼？
11:14|ASV|Doth not even nature itself teach you, that, if a man have long hair, it is a dishonor to him?
11:14|Darby|Does not even nature itself teach you, that man, if he  have long hair, it is a dishonour to him?
11:14|KJV|Doth not even nature itself teach you, that, if a man have long hair, it is a shame unto him?
11:14<version name="WYC">Neither the nature itself teacheth us [<i>that</i>], for if a man nourish long hair, it is shame to him; [Neither the kind itself teacheth us that, for if a man nourish long hair, it is evil fame to him;]</version>
11:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們的本性豈不也教導你們，男人若有長頭髮，便是他的羞辱，
11:15|ASV|But if a woman have long hair, it is a glory to her: for her hair is given her for a covering.
11:15|Darby|But woman, if she have long hair, [it is] glory to her;  for the long hair is given [to her] in lieu of a veil.
11:15|KJV|But if a woman have long hair, it is a glory to her: for her hair is given her for a covering.
11:15|WYC|but if a woman nourish long hair, it is glory to her, for hairs be given to her for covering.
11:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|而女人有長頭髮，乃是她的榮耀麼？因為這長頭髮是給她作蓋頭的。
11:16|ASV|But if any man seemeth to be contentious, we have no such custom, neither the churches of God.
11:16|Darby|But if any one think to be contentious, *we* have no such  custom, nor the assemblies of God.
11:16|KJV|But if any man seem to be contentious, we have no such custom, neither the churches of God.
11:16|WYC|But if any man is seen to be full of strife, we have none such custom, neither the church of God.
11:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若有人想要強辯，我們卻沒有這樣的規矩，神的眾召會也沒有。
11:17|ASV|But in giving you this charge, I praise you not, that ye come together not for the better but for the worse.
11:17|Darby|But [in] prescribing [to you on] this [which I now enter  on], I do not praise, [namely,] that ye come together, not for  the better, but for the worse.
11:17|KJV|Now in this that I declare unto you I praise you not, that ye come together not for the better, but for the worse.
11:17|WYC|But this thing I command, not praising, that ye come together not into the better, but into the worse.
11:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而，我要吩咐一事，並不是稱讚你們，因為你們聚在一起，不是受益，乃是招損。
11:18|ASV|For first of all, when ye come together in the church, I hear that divisions exist among you; and I partly believe it.
11:18|Darby|For first, when ye come together in assembly, I hear there  exist divisions among you, and I partly give credit [to it].
11:18|KJV|For first of all, when ye come together in the church, I hear that there be divisions among you; and I partly believe it.
11:18<version name="WYC">First for when ye come together into the church, I hear that dissensions be, and in part I believe [I hear that partings, <i>or dissensions</i>, be, and of part I believe].</version>
11:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|第一，我聽說你們在召會中聚在一起的時候，你們中間有分裂，我也有幾分相信。
11:19|ASV|For there must be also factions among you, that they that are approved may be made manifest among you.
11:19|Darby|For there must also be sects among you, that the approved  may become manifest among you.
11:19|KJV|For there must be also heresies among you, that they which are approved may be made manifest among you.
11:19<version name="WYC">For it behooveth heresies to be, that they that be approved, be openly known in you. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21637a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
11:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在你們中間不免有派別，好叫那些蒙稱許的人在你們中間顯明出來。
11:20|ASV|When therefore ye assemble yourselves together, it is not possible to eat the Lord's supper:
11:20|Darby|When ye come therefore together into one place, it is not  to eat [the] Lord's supper.
11:20|KJV|When ye come together therefore into one place, this is not to eat the Lord's supper.
11:20|WYC|Therefore when ye come together into one, now it is not to eat the Lord's supper;
11:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們聚在一處的時候，並不是喫主的晚餐，
11:21|ASV|for in your eating each one taketh before other his own supper; and one is hungry, and another is drunken.
11:21|Darby|For each one in eating takes his *own* supper before  [others], and one is hungry and another drinks to excess.
11:21|KJV|For in eating every one taketh before other his own supper: and one is hungry, and another is drunken.
11:21|WYC|for why each man before taketh his supper to eat, and one is hungry, and another is drunken.
11:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為喫的時候，各人先喫自己的飯，甚至這個飢餓，那個酒醉。
11:22|ASV|What, have ye not houses to eat and to drink in? or despise ye the church of God, and put them to shame that have not? What shall I say to you? shall I praise you? In this I praise you not.
11:22|Darby|Have ye not then houses for eating and drinking? or do ye  despise the assembly of God, and put to shame them who have  not? What shall I say to you? shall I praise you? In this  [point] I do not praise.
11:22|KJV|What? have ye not houses to eat and to drink in? or despise ye the church of God, and shame them that have not? what shall I say to you? shall I praise you in this? I praise you not.
11:22<version name="WYC">Whether ye have not houses [for] to eat and drink, or ye despise the church of God, and confound them that have none?  What shall I say to you?  I praise you, but herein I praise <i>you</i> not. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21640b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
11:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要喫喝，難道沒有家麼？還是你們藐視神的召會，羞辱那無有的？我對你們可怎麼說？可稱讚你們麼？在這事上我不稱讚。
11:23|ASV|For I received of the Lord that which also I delivered unto you, that the Lord Jesus in the night in which he was betrayed took bread;
11:23|Darby|For *I* received from the Lord, that which I also  delivered to you, that the Lord Jesus, in the night in which he  was delivered up, took bread,
11:23|KJV|For I have received of the Lord that which also I delivered unto you, that the Lord Jesus the same night in which he was betrayed took bread:
11:23|WYC|For I have taken of the Lord that thing, which [and] I have betaken to you.  For the Lord Jesus, in what night he was betrayed, took bread,
11:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我從主領受又交付你們的，就是主耶穌被出賣的那一夜，拿起餅來，
11:24|ASV|and when he had given thanks, he brake it, and said, This is my body, which is for you: this do in remembrance of me.
11:24|Darby|and having given thanks broke [it], and said, This is my  body, which [is] for you: this do in remembrance of me.
11:24|KJV|And when he had given thanks, he brake it, and said, Take, eat: this is my body, which is broken for you: this do in remembrance of me.
11:24<version name="WYC">and did thankings, and brake, and said [and doing graces, <i>or thanks</i>, he brake, and said], Take ye, and eat ye; this is my body, which shall be betrayed for you; do ye this thing into my mind.</version>
11:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祝謝了，就擘開，說，這是我的身體，為你們捨的，你們要如此行，為的是記念我。
11:25|ASV|In like manner also the cup, after supper, saying, This cup is the new covenant in my blood: this do, as often as ye drink it, in remembrance of me.
11:25|Darby|In like manner also the cup, after having supped, saying,  This cup is the new covenant in my blood: this do, as often as  ye shall drink [it], in remembrance of me.
11:25|KJV|After the same manner also he took the cup, when he had supped, saying, this cup is the new testament in my blood: this do ye, as oft as ye drink it, in remembrance of me.
11:25<version name="WYC">Also the cup, after that he had supped, and said [Also and <i>he took</i> the cup, after he had supped, saying], This cup is the new testament in my blood; do ye this thing, as oft as ye shall drink [<i>it</i>], into my mind.</version>
11:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|飯後，也照樣拿起杯來，說，這杯是用我的血所立的新約，你們每逢喝的時候，要如此行，為的是記念我。
11:26|ASV|For as often as ye eat this bread, and drink the cup, ye proclaim the Lord's death till he come.
11:26|Darby|For as often as ye shall eat this bread, and drink the  cup, ye announce the death of the Lord, until he come.
11:26|KJV|For as often as ye eat this bread, and drink this cup, ye do shew the Lord's death till he come.
11:26|WYC|For as oft as ye shall eat this bread, and drink this cup, ye shall tell the death of the Lord, till that he come [ye shall show the death of the Lord, till he come].
11:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們每逢喫這餅，喝這杯，是宣告主的死，直等到祂來。
11:27|ASV|Wherefore whosoever shall eat the bread or drink the cup of the Lord in an unworthy manner, shall be guilty of the body and the blood of the Lord.
11:27|Darby|So that whosoever shall eat the bread, or drink the cup of  the Lord, unworthily, shall be guilty in respect of the body  and of the blood of the Lord.
11:27|KJV|Wherefore whosoever shall eat this bread, and drink this cup of the Lord, unworthily, shall be guilty of the body and blood of the Lord.
11:27|WYC|Therefore whoever eateth the bread, or drinketh the cup of the Lord unworthily, he shall be guilty of the body and of the blood of the Lord. [And so whoever shall eat the bread, or drink the cup of the Lord unworthily, he shall be guilty of the body and blood of the Lord.]
11:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以無論何人，不配的喫主的餅，喝主的杯，就是得罪主的身體和主的血了。
11:28|ASV|But let a man prove himself, and so let him eat of the bread, and drink of the cup.
11:28|Darby|But let a man prove himself, and thus eat of the bread,  and drink of the cup.
11:28|KJV|But let a man examine himself, and so let him eat of that bread, and drink of that cup.
11:28|WYC|But prove a man himself, and so eat he of that bread, and drink he of the cup [and drink of the cup].
11:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人應當察驗自己，然後喫這餅，喝這杯。
11:29|ASV|For he that eateth and drinketh, eateth and drinketh judgment unto himself, if he discern not the body.
11:29|Darby|For [the] eater and drinker eats and drinks judgment to  himself, not distinguishing the body.
11:29|KJV|For he that eateth and drinketh unworthily, eateth and drinketh damnation to himself, not discerning the Lord's body.
11:29<version name="WYC">For he that eateth and drinketh unworthily, eateth and drinketh doom to him[self] [eateth and drinketh doom, <i>or</i> <i>damnation</i>, to himself], not wisely deeming the body of the Lord.</version>
11:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為那喫喝的，若不分辨那身體，就是給自己喫喝審判了。
11:30|ASV|For this cause many among you are weak and sickly, and not a few sleep.
11:30|Darby|On this account many among you [are] weak and infirm, and  a good many are fallen asleep.
11:30|KJV|For this cause many are weak and sickly among you, and many sleep.
11:30<version name="WYC">Therefore among you many <i>be</i> sick and feeble, and many sleep. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21648c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup></version>
11:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此，在你們中間有好些軟弱的與患病的，睡的也不少。
11:31|ASV|But if we discerned ourselves, we should not be judged.
11:31|Darby|But if we judged ourselves, so were we not judged.
11:31|KJV|For if we would judge ourselves, we should not be judged.
11:31|WYC|And if we deemed wisely us selves [For if we deemed wisely ourselves], we should not be deemed;
11:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但我們若分辨自己，就不至於受審判。
11:32|ASV|But when we are judged, we are chastened of the Lord, that we may not be condemned with the world.
11:32|Darby|But being judged, we are disciplined of [the] Lord, that  we may not be condemned with the world.
11:32|KJV|But when we are judged, we are chastened of the Lord, that we should not be condemned with the world.
11:32|WYC|but while we be deemed of the Lord, we be chastised, that we be not condemned with this world.
11:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們受主審判，乃是受管教，免得我們和世人同被定罪。
11:33|ASV|Wherefore, my brethren, when ye come together to eat, wait one for another.
11:33|Darby|So that, my brethren, when ye come together to eat, wait  for one another.
11:33|KJV|Wherefore, my brethren, when ye come together to eat, tarry one for another.
11:33|WYC|Therefore, my brethren, when ye come together to eat, abide ye together.
11:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我弟兄們，你們聚在一起喫的時候，要彼此等待。
11:34<version name="ASV">If any man is hungry, let him eat at home; that your coming together be not unto judgment. And the rest will I set in order whensoever I come. </p><p /><br /></version>
11:34<version name="Darby">If any one be hungry, let him eat at home, that ye may not  come together for judgment. But the other things, whenever I  come, I will set in order. </p><p /><br /></version>
11:34<version name="KJV">And if any man hunger, let him eat at home; that ye come not together unto condemnation. And the rest will I set in order when I come.</p><p /><br /></version>
11:34|WYC|If any man hungereth [If any man hunger], eat he at home, that ye come not together into doom.  And I shall dispose other things, when I come.
11:34|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若有人飢餓，就當在家裡喫，免得你們聚在一起受到審判。其餘的事，我來的時候再安排。
12:1|ASV|Now concerning spiritual gifts, brethren, I would not have you ignorant.
12:1|Darby|But concerning spiritual [manifestations], brethren, I do  not wish you to be ignorant.
12:1|KJV|Now concerning spiritual gifts, brethren, I would not have you ignorant.
12:1|WYC|But of spiritual things, brethren, I will not that ye not know [I will not you to unknow].
12:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，關於屬靈的恩賜，我不願意你們不明白。
12:2|ASV|Ye know that when ye were Gentiles ye were led away unto those dumb idols, howsoever ye might led.
12:2|Darby|Ye know that when ye were [of the] nations [ye were] led  away to dumb idols, in whatever way ye might be led.
12:2|KJV|Ye know that ye were Gentiles, carried away unto these dumb idols, even as ye were led.
12:2|WYC|For ye know, that when ye were heathen men, how ye were led going to dumb maumets. [Soothly ye know, for when ye were heathen men, as ye were led going to dumb simulacra.]
12:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們作外邦人的時候，無論何時不論怎樣受到帶領，你們就被帶走，去拜那不能出聲的偶像，這是你們知道的。
12:3|ASV|Wherefore I make known unto you, that no man speaking in the Spirit of God saith, Jesus is anathema; and no man can say, Jesus is Lord, but in the Holy Spirit.
12:3|Darby|I give you therefore to know, that no one, speaking in [the  power of the] Spirit of God, says, Curse [on] Jesus; and no one  can say, Lord Jesus, unless in [the power of the] Holy Spirit.
12:3|KJV|Wherefore I give you to understand, that no man speaking by the Spirit of God calleth Jesus accursed: and that no man can say that Jesus is the Lord, but by the Holy Ghost.
12:3<version name="WYC">Therefore I make known to you, that no man speaking in the Spirit of God, saith parting from Jesus; and no man may say the Lord Jesus [<i>is</i>], but in the Holy Ghost.</version>
12:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我要你們知道，在神的靈裡說話的，沒有人說，受咒詛的，耶穌！若不是在聖靈裡，也沒有人能說，主，耶穌！
12:4|ASV|Now there are diversities of gifts, but the same Spirit.
12:4|Darby|But there are distinctions of gifts, but the same Spirit;
12:4|KJV|Now there are diversities of gifts, but the same Spirit.
12:4<version name="WYC">And diverse graces there be, but <i>it is </i>all one Spirit [but the same Spirit <i>is</i>];</version>
12:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而，恩賜雖有分別，靈卻是同一位；
12:5|ASV|And there are diversities of ministrations, and the same Lord.
12:5|Darby|and there are distinctions of services, and the same Lord;
12:5|KJV|And there are differences of administrations, but the same Lord.
12:5<version name="WYC">and diverse services <i>there be</i>, but <i>it is </i>all one Lord; [and partings of servings <i>be</i>, but the same Lord <i>is</i>;]</version>
12:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|職事也有分別，主卻是同一位；
12:6|ASV|And there are diversities of workings, but the same God, who worketh all things in all.
12:6|Darby|and there are distinctions of operations, but the same God  who operates all things in all.
12:6|KJV|And there are diversities of operations, but it is the same God which worketh all in all.
12:6<version name="WYC">and diverse workings there be, but it <i>is</i> all one God [and partings of workings be, but the same God <i>is</i>], that worketh all things in all things.</version>
12:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|功效也有分別，神卻是同一位，在眾人裡面運行一切的事。
12:7|ASV|But to each one is given the manifestation of the Spirit to profit withal.
12:7|Darby|But to each the manifestation of the Spirit is given for  profit.
12:7|KJV|But the manifestation of the Spirit is given to every man to profit withal.
12:7|WYC|And to each man the showing of Spirit is given to profit.
12:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只是那靈的表顯賜給各人，是要叫人得益處。
12:8|ASV|For to one is given through the Spirit the word of wisdom; and to another the word of knowledge, according to the same Spirit:
12:8|Darby|For to one, by the Spirit, is given [the] word of wisdom;  and to another [the] word of knowledge, according to the same  Spirit;
12:8|KJV|For to one is given by the Spirit the word of wisdom; to another the word of knowledge by the same Spirit;
12:8|WYC|And the word of wisdom is given to one by Spirit [To another forsooth by Spirit the word of wisdom is given]; to another the word of knowing, by the same Spirit;
12:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這人藉著那靈得了智慧的言語，那人也照同一位靈得了知識的言語，
12:9|ASV|to another faith, in the same Spirit; and to another gifts of healings, in the one Spirit;
12:9|Darby|and to a different one faith, in [the power of] the same  Spirit; and to another gifts of healing in [the power of] the  same Spirit;
12:9|KJV|To another faith by the same Spirit; to another the gifts of healing by the same Spirit;
12:9<version name="WYC">faith to another, in the same Spirit; to another, grace of healings <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21661a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>, in one Spirit;</version>
12:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|另有別人在同一位靈裡得了信心，還有一人在這一位靈裡得了醫病的恩賜，
12:10|ASV|and to another workings of miracles; and to another prophecy; and to another discernings of spirits; to another divers kinds of tongues; and to another the interpretation of tongues:
12:10|Darby|and to another operations of miracles; and to another  prophecy; and to another discerning of spirits; and to a  different one kinds of tongues; and to another interpretation  of tongues.
12:10|KJV|To another the working of miracles; to another prophecy; to another discerning of spirits; to another divers kinds of tongues; to another the interpretation of tongues:
12:10<version name="WYC">to another, the working of works of power; to another, prophecy; to another, very knowing of spirits; to another, kinds of languages; to another, expounding of words. [to another, the working of virtues; to another, prophecy; to another, discretion, <i>or very knowing</i>, of spirits; to another, kinds of tongues, <i>or languages</i>; to another, interpreting, <i>or expounding</i>, of words.]</version>
12:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|另有一人能行異能，另有一人能申言，另有一人能辨別諸靈，另有別人能說各種方言，另有一人能繙方言。
12:11|ASV|but all these worketh the one and the same Spirit, dividing to each one severally even as he will.
12:11|Darby|But all these things operates the one and the same Spirit,  dividing to each in particular according as he pleases.
12:11|KJV|But all these worketh that one and the selfsame Spirit, dividing to every man severally as he will.
12:11|WYC|And one and the same Spirit worketh all these things [Forsooth all these things one and the same Spirit worketh], parting to each by themselves as he will.
12:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但這一切都是這位獨一且同一的靈所運行，照著祂的定意個別分給各人的。
12:12|ASV|For as the body is one, and hath many members, and all the members of the body, being many, are one body; so also is Christ.
12:12|Darby|For even as the body is one and has many members, but all  the members of the body, being many, are one body, so also [is]  the Christ.
12:12|KJV|For as the body is one, and hath many members, and all the members of that one body, being many, are one body: so also is Christ.
12:12|WYC|For as there is one body, and hath many members, and all the members of the body when those be many [when they be many], be one body, so also Christ.
12:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就如身體是一個，卻有許多肢體，而且身體上一切的肢體雖多，仍是一個身體，基督也是這樣。
12:13|ASV|For in one Spirit were we all baptized into one body, whether Jews or Greeks, whether bond or free; and were all made to drink of one Spirit.
12:13|Darby|For also in [the power of] one Spirit *we* have all been  baptised into one body, whether Jews or Greeks, whether bondmen  or free, and have all been given to drink of one Spirit.
12:13|KJV|For by one Spirit are we all baptized into one body, whether we be Jews or Gentiles, whether we be bond or free; and have been all made to drink into one Spirit.
12:13|WYC|For in one Spirit all we be baptized into one body, either Jews, either heathen, either servants, either free; and all we be filled with drink in one Spirit. [And soothly in one Spirit all we be baptized into one body, either Jews, or heathen, or servants, or free; and all we have drunk in one Spirit.]
12:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們不拘是猶太人或希利尼人，是為奴的或自主的，都已經在一位靈裡受浸，成了一個身體，且都得以喝一位靈。
12:14|ASV|For the body is not one member, but many.
12:14|Darby|For also the body is not one member but many.
12:14|KJV|For the body is not one member, but many.
12:14|WYC|For the body is not one member, but many.
12:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|身體原不是一個肢體，乃是許多肢體。
12:15|ASV|If the foot shall say, Because I am not the hand, I am not of the body; it is not therefore not of the body.
12:15|Darby|If the foot say, Because I am not a hand I am not of the  body, is it on account of this not indeed of the body?
12:15|KJV|If the foot shall say, Because I am not the hand, I am not of the body; is it therefore not of the body?
12:15|WYC|If the foot shall say, For I am not the hand, I am not of the body; not therefore it is not of the body [not therefore is it not of the body(?)].
12:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|倘若腳說，我不是手，所以不屬於身體，牠不能因此就不屬於身體。
12:16|ASV|And if the ear shall say, Because I am not the eye, I am not of the body; it is not therefore not of the body.
12:16|Darby|And if the ear say, Because I am not an eye I am not of  the body, is it on account of this not indeed of the body?
12:16|KJV|And if the ear shall say, Because I am not the eye, I am not of the body; is it therefore not of the body?
12:16|WYC|And if the ear saith [And if the ear shall say], For I am not the eye, I am not of the body; not therefore it is not of the body [not therefore is it not of the body(?)].
12:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|倘若耳說，我不是眼，所以不屬於身體，牠也不能因此就不屬於身體。
12:17|ASV|If the whole body were an eye, where were the hearing? If the whole were hearing, where were the smelling?
12:17|Darby|If the whole body [were] an eye, where the hearing? if all  hearing, where the smelling?
12:17|KJV|If the whole body were an eye, where were the hearing? If the whole were hearing, where were the smelling?
12:17|WYC|If all the body is the eye [If all the body were the eye], where is [the] hearing? and if all the body is hearing, where is [the] smelling?
12:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若全身是眼，聽覺在那裡？若全身是聽覺，嗅覺在那裡？
12:18|ASV|But now hath God set the members each one of them in the body, even as it pleased him.
12:18|Darby|But now God has set the members, each one of them in the  body, according as it has pleased [him].
12:18|KJV|But now hath God set the members every one of them in the body, as it hath pleased him.
12:18|WYC|But now God hath set members, and each of them in the body, as he would.
12:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但如今神照著自己的意思，把肢體俱各安置在身體上了。
12:19|ASV|And if they were all one member, where were the body?
12:19|Darby|But if all were one member, where the body?
12:19|KJV|And if they were all one member, where were the body?
12:19<version name="WYC">And if all were one member, where <i>were</i> the body?</version>
12:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若都是一個肢體，身體在那裡？
12:20|ASV|But now they are many members, but one body.
12:20|Darby|But now the members [are] many, and the body one.
12:20|KJV|But now are they many members, yet but one body.
12:20|WYC|But now there be many members, but one body.
12:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但如今肢體是多的，身體卻是一個。
12:21|ASV|And the eye cannot say to the hand, I have no need of thee: or again the head to the feet, I have no need of you.
12:21|Darby|The eye cannot say to the hand, I have not need of thee;  or again, the head to the feet, I have not need of you.
12:21|KJV|And the eye cannot say unto the hand, I have no need of thee: nor again the head to the feet, I have no need of you.
12:21|WYC|And the eye may not say to the hand [Forsooth the eye shall not be able to say to the hand], I have no need to thy works; or again the head to the feet, Ye be not necessary to me.
12:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|眼不能對手說，我不需要你；頭也不能對腳說，我不需要你。
12:22|ASV|Nay, much rather, those members of the body which seem to be more feeble are necessary:
12:22|Darby|But much rather, the members of the body which seem to be  weaker are necessary;
12:22|KJV|Nay, much more those members of the body, which seem to be more feeble, are necessary:
12:22<version name="WYC">But much more those that be seen to be the lower members of the body [But much more those that be seen to be more sick, <i>or lower</i>, members of the body], be more needful;</version>
12:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不但如此，身上肢體似乎較為軟弱的，更是不可少的；
12:23|ASV|and those parts of the body, which we think to be less honorable, upon these we bestow more abundant honor; and our uncomely parts have more abundant comeliness;
12:23|Darby|and those [parts] of the body which we esteem to be the  more void of honour, these we clothe with more abundant honour;  and our uncomely [parts] have more abundant comeliness;
12:23|KJV|And those members of the body, which we think to be less honourable, upon these we bestow more abundant honour; and our uncomely parts have more abundant comeliness.
12:23<version name="WYC">and those that we guess to be the unworthier members of the body, to them we give more honour; and those members that be unseemly, have more seemliness. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21675b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
12:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|身上肢體我們以為比較不體面的，就給牠加上更豐盈的體面；我們不俊美的肢體，就得著更豐盈的俊美；
12:24|ASV|whereas our comely parts have no need: but God tempered the body together, giving more abundant honor to that part which lacked;
12:24|Darby|but our comely [parts] have not need. But God has tempered  the body together, having given more abundant honour to [the  part] that lacked;
12:24|KJV|For our comely parts have no need: but God hath tempered the body together, having given more abundant honour to that part which lacked.
12:24|WYC|For our seemly members have need of none; but God tempered the body, giving more honour to it, to whom it failed, [Forsooth our honest members of none have need; but God tempered the body, giving more worship to it, to whom it failed,]
12:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於我們俊美的肢體，就不需要了。但神將這身體調和在一起，把更豐盈的體面加給那有缺欠的肢體，
12:25|ASV|that there should be no schism in the body; but that the members should have the same care one for another.
12:25|Darby|that there might be no division in the body, but that the  members might have the same concern one for another.
12:25|KJV|That there should be no schism in the body; but that the members should have the same care one for another.
12:25|WYC|that debate be not in the body, but that the members be busy into the same thing each for other [but that the members be busy into the same thing for each other].
12:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|免得身體上有了分裂，總要肢體彼此同樣相顧。
12:26|ASV|And whether one member suffereth, all the members suffer with it; or one member is honored, all the members rejoice with it.
12:26|Darby|And if one member suffer, all the members suffer with  [it]; and if one member be glorified, all the members rejoice  with [it].
12:26|KJV|And whether one member suffer, all the members suffer with it; or one member be honoured, all the members rejoice with it.
12:26|WYC|And if one member suffereth any thing [And if one member suffer any thing], all members suffer therewith; either if one member joyeth [either if one member glorieth], all members joy together.
12:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若一個肢體受苦，所有的肢體就一同受苦；若一個肢體得榮耀，所有的肢體就一同歡樂。
12:27|ASV|Now ye are the body of Christ, and severally members thereof.
12:27|Darby|Now *ye* are Christ's body, and members in particular.
12:27|KJV|Now ye are the body of Christ, and members in particular.
12:27|WYC|And ye be the body of Christ, and members of member. [Forsooth ye be the body of Christ, and members of members.]
12:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們就是基督的身體，並且各自作肢體。
12:28|ASV|And God hath set some in the church, first apostles, secondly prophets, thirdly teachers, then miracles, then gifts of healings, helps, governments, divers kinds of tongues.
12:28|Darby|And God has set certain in the assembly: first, apostles;  secondly, prophets; thirdly, teachers; then miraculous powers;  then gifts of healings; helps; governments; kinds of tongues.
12:28|KJV|And God hath set some in the church, first apostles, secondarily prophets, thirdly teachers, after that miracles, then gifts of healings, helps, governments, diversities of tongues.
12:28|WYC|But God set some men in the church, first apostles, the second time prophets [And soothly God put some in the church, first apostles, the second prophets], the third teachers, afterward works of power, afterward graces of healings, helpings, governings, kinds of languages, interpretations of words.
12:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神在召會中所設立的，第一是使徒，第二是申言者，第三是教師；其次是行異能的，再次是得恩賜醫病的，幫助的，治理的，說各種方言的。
12:29|ASV|Are all apostles? are all prophets? are all teachers? are all workers of miracles?
12:29|Darby|[Are] all apostles? [are] all prophets? [are] all  teachers? [are] all [in possession of] miraculous powers?
12:29|KJV|Are all apostles? are all prophets? are all teachers? are all workers of miracles?
12:29<version name="WYC">Whether all [<i>be</i>] apostles? whether all [<i>be</i>] prophets? Whether all teachers? whether all works of power?</version>
12:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|豈都是使徒麼？豈都是申言者麼？豈都是教師麼？豈都是行異能的麼？
12:30|ASV|have all gifts of healings? do all speak with tongues? do all interpret?
12:30|Darby|have all gifts of healings? do all speak with tongues? do  all interpret?
12:30|KJV|Have all the gifts of healing? do all speak with tongues? do all interpret?
12:30<version name="WYC">whether all have grace of healings? whether all speak with languages? whether all expound [whether all interpret, <i>or expound</i>]?</version>
12:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|豈都有醫病的恩賜麼？豈都說方言麼？豈都繙方言麼？
12:31<version name="ASV">But desire earnestly the greater gifts. And moreover a most excellent way show I unto you. </p><p /><br /></version>
12:31<version name="Darby">But desire earnestly the greater gifts, and yet shew I  unto you a way of more surpassing excellence. </p><p /><br /></version>
12:31<version name="KJV">But covet earnestly the best gifts: and yet shew I unto you a more excellent way.</p><p /><br /></version>
12:31|WYC|But follow ye the better ghostly gifts.  And yet I show to you a more excellent way.
12:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但你們要切慕那更大的恩賜。我還要把極超越的路指示你們。
13:1|ASV|If I speak with the tongues of men and of angels, but have not love, I am become sounding brass, or a clanging cymbal.
13:1|Darby|If I speak with the tongues of men and of angels, but have  not love, I am become sounding brass or a clanging cymbal.
13:1|KJV|Though I speak with the tongues of men and of angels, and have not charity, I am become as sounding brass, or a tinkling cymbal.
13:1|WYC|If I speak with tongues of men and of angels, and I have not charity, I am made as brass sounding, or a cymbal tinkling.
13:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我若能說人和天使的方言，卻沒有愛，我就成了鳴的鑼、響的鈸。
13:2|ASV|And if I have the gift of prophecy, and know all mysteries and all knowledge; and if I have all faith, so as to remove mountains, but have not love, I am nothing.
13:2|Darby|And if I have prophecy, and know all mysteries and all  knowledge, and if I have all faith, so as to remove mountains,  but have not love, I am nothing.
13:2|KJV|And though I have the gift of prophecy, and understand all mysteries, and all knowledge; and though I have all faith, so that I could remove mountains, and have not charity, I am nothing.
13:2<version name="WYC">And if I have prophecy, and know all mysteries, and all knowing [and all knowing, <i>or</i> <i>science</i>], and if I have all faith, so that I move hills from their place [so that I bear over hills <i>from one place to another</i>], and I have not charity, I am nought.</version>
13:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我若有申言的恩賜，也明白一切的奧祕，和一切的知識，並有全備的信，以致能彀移山，卻沒有愛，我就算不得甚麼。
13:3|ASV|And if I bestow all my goods to feed the poor, and if I give my body to be burned, but have not love, it profiteth me nothing.
13:3|Darby|And if I shall dole out all my goods in food, and if I  deliver up my body that I may be burned, but have not love, I  profit nothing.
13:3|KJV|And though I bestow all my goods to feed the poor, and though I give my body to be burned, and have not charity, it profiteth me nothing.
13:3|WYC|And if I part all my goods into the meats of poor men, and if I betake my body, so that I burn, and if I have not charity, it profiteth to me nothing.
13:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我若將我一切所有的變賣為食物分給人喫，又捨己身叫我可以誇口，卻沒有愛，仍然與我無益。
13:4|ASV|Love suffereth long, and is kind; love envieth not; love vaunteth not itself, is not puffed up,
13:4|Darby|Love has long patience, is kind; love is not emulous [of  others]; love is not insolent and rash, is not puffed up,
13:4|KJV|Charity suffereth long, and is kind; charity envieth not; charity vaunteth not itself, is not puffed up,
13:4<version name="WYC">Charity is patient, it is benign; charity envieth not, it doeth not wickedly, it is not blown [it is not in-blown<i> with pride</i>],</version>
13:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|愛是恆久忍耐，又有恩慈；愛是不嫉妒；愛是不自誇，不張狂，
13:5|ASV|doth not behave itself unseemly, seeketh not its own, is not provoked, taketh not account of evil;
13:5|Darby|does not behave in an unseemly manner, does not seek what  is its own, is not quickly provoked, does not impute evil,
13:5|KJV|Doth not behave itself unseemly, seeketh not her own, is not easily provoked, thinketh no evil;
13:5<version name="WYC">it is not covetous [<i>of worships</i>], it seeketh not those things that be his own [it seeketh not those things that be her own], it is not stirred to wrath, it thinketh not evil,</version>
13:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不作不合宜的事，不求自己的益處，不輕易發怒，不計算人的惡，
13:6|ASV|rejoiceth not in unrighteousness, but rejoiceth with the truth;
13:6|Darby|does not rejoice at iniquity but rejoices with the truth,
13:6|KJV|Rejoiceth not in iniquity, but rejoiceth in the truth;
13:6|WYC|it joyeth not on wickedness, but it joyeth together to truth; [it joyeth not in wickedness, forsooth it joyeth together with truth;]
13:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不因不義而歡樂，卻與真理同歡樂；
13:7|ASV|beareth all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things.
13:7|Darby|bears all things, believes all things, hopes all things,  endures all things.
13:7|KJV|Beareth all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things.
13:7|WYC|it suffereth all things, it believeth all things, it hopeth all things, it sustaineth all things.
13:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡事包容，凡事相信，凡事盼望，凡事忍耐。
13:8|ASV|Love never faileth: but whether there be prophecies, they shall be done away; whether there be tongues, they shall cease; whether there be knowledge, it shall be done away.
13:8|Darby|Love never fails; but whether prophecies, they shall be  done away; or tongues, they shall cease; or knowledge, it shall  be done away.
13:8|KJV|Charity never faileth: but whether there be prophecies, they shall fail; whether there be tongues, they shall cease; whether there be knowledge, it shall vanish away.
13:8|WYC|Charity falleth never down, whether prophecies shall be voided, either languages shall cease, either science shall be destroyed [whether prophecies shall be voided, or languages shall cease, or science shall be destroyed].
13:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|愛是永不敗落；但申言終必歸於無用，方言終必停止，知識也終必歸於無用。
13:9|ASV|For we know in part, and we prophesy in part;
13:9|Darby|For we know in part, and we prophesy in part:
13:9|KJV|For we know in part, and we prophesy in part.
13:9|WYC|For a part we know, and a part we prophesy; [For of part we know, and of part we prophesy;]
13:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們所知道的是局部的，所申言的也是局部的；
13:10|ASV|but when that which is perfect is come, that which is in part shall be done away.
13:10|Darby|but when that which is perfect has come, that which is in  part shall be done away.
13:10|KJV|But when that which is perfect is come, then that which is in part shall be done away.
13:10|WYC|but when that shall come that is perfect, that thing that is of part shall be voided.
13:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|及至那完全的來到，這局部的就要歸於無用了。
13:11|ASV|When I was a child, I spake as a child, I felt as a child, I thought as a child: now that I am become a man, I have put away childish things.
13:11|Darby|When I was a child, I spoke as a child, I felt as a child,  I reasoned as a child; when I became a man, I had done with  what belonged to the child.
13:11|KJV|When I was a child, I spake as a child, I understood as a child, I thought as a child: but when I became a man, I put away childish things.
13:11|WYC|When I was a little child, I spake as a little child, I understood as a little child, I thought as a little child; but when I was made a man, I voided those things that were of a little child.
13:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我作孩童的時候，說話像孩童，思想像孩童，推究像孩童，既已成人，就把孩童的事廢掉了。
13:12|ASV|For now we see in a mirror, darkly; but then face to face: now I know in part; but then shall I know fully even as also I was fully known.
13:12|Darby|For we see now through a dim window obscurely, but then  face to face; now I know partially, but then I shall know  according as I also have been known.
13:12|KJV|For now we see through a glass, darkly; but then face to face: now I know in part; but then shall I know even as also I am known.
13:12|WYC|And we see now [Forsooth we see now] by a mirror in darkness, but then face to face; now I know of part, but then I shall know, as [and] I am known.
13:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們如今對著鏡子觀看，糢糊不清，到那時就要面對面了。我如今所知道的是局部的，到那時就全知道，如同我全被知道一樣。
13:13<version name="ASV">But now abideth faith, hope, love, these three; and the greatest of these is love. </p><p /><br /></version>
13:13<version name="Darby">And now abide faith, hope, love; these three things; and  the greater of these [is] love. </p><p /><br /></version>
13:13<version name="KJV">And now abideth faith, hope, charity, these three; but the greatest of these is charity.</p><p /><br /></version>
13:13|WYC|And now dwelleth faith, hope, charity, these three; but the most of these is charity.
13:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|如今常存的，有信、望、愛這三樣，其中最大的是愛。
14:1|ASV|Follow after love; yet desire earnestly spiritual gifts, but rather that ye may prophesy.
14:1|Darby|Follow after love, and be emulous of spiritual  [manifestations], but rather that ye may prophesy.
14:1|KJV|Follow after charity, and desire spiritual gifts, but rather that ye may prophesy.
14:1|WYC|Follow ye charity, love ye spiritual things, but more that ye prophesy.
14:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要追求愛，更要切慕屬靈的恩賜，尤其要切慕申言。
14:2|ASV|For he that speaketh in a tongue speaketh not unto men, but unto God; for no man understandeth; but in the spirit he speaketh mysteries.
14:2|Darby|For he that speaks with a tongue does not speak to men but  to God: for no one hears; but in spirit he speaks mysteries.
14:2|KJV|For he that speaketh in an unknown tongue speaketh not unto men, but unto God: for no man understandeth him; howbeit in the spirit he speaketh mysteries.
14:2|WYC|And he that speaketh in tongue, speaketh not to men, but to God; for no man heareth.  But the Spirit speaketh mysteries.
14:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那說方言的，原不是對人說，乃是對神說，因為沒有人聽出來，然而他在靈裡卻是講說各樣的奧祕。
14:3|ASV|But he that prophesieth speaketh unto men edification, and exhortation, and consolation.
14:3|Darby|But he that prophesies speaks to men [in] edification, and  encouragement, and consolation.
14:3|KJV|But he that prophesieth speaketh unto men to edification, and exhortation, and comfort.
14:3|WYC|For he that prophesieth, speaketh to men to edification, and admonishing, and comforting.
14:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但那申言的，是對人講說建造、勉勵和安慰。
14:4|ASV|He that speaketh in a tongue edifieth himself; but he that prophesieth edifieth the church.
14:4|Darby|He that speaks with a tongue edifies himself; but he that  prophesies edifies [the] assembly.
14:4|KJV|He that speaketh in an unknown tongue edifieth himself; but he that prophesieth edifieth the church.
14:4|WYC|He that speaketh in tongue, edifieth himself; but he that prophesieth, edifieth the church of God.
14:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那說方言的，是建造自己，但那申言的，乃是建造召會。
14:5|ASV|Now I would have you all speak with tongues, but rather that ye should prophesy: and greater is he that prophesieth than he that speaketh with tongues, except he interpret, that the church may receive edifying.
14:5|Darby|Now I desire that ye should all speak with tongues, but  rather that ye should prophesy. But greater is he that  prophesies than he that speaks with tongues, unless he  interpret, that the assembly may receive edification.
14:5|KJV|I would that ye all spake with tongues but rather that ye prophesied: for greater is he that prophesieth than he that speaketh with tongues, except he interpret, that the church may receive edifying.
14:5<version name="WYC">And I will, that all ye speak in tongues, but more that ye prophesy.  For he that prophesieth, is more than he that speaketh in languages; but peradventure he expound, that the church take edification. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21701a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
14:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我願意你們都說方言，但我更願意你們申言；說方言的，若不繙出來，使召會得建造，那申言的，就比他強了。
14:6|ASV|But now, brethren, if I come unto you speaking with tongues, what shall I profit you, unless I speak to you either by way of revelation, or of knowledge, or of prophesying, or of teaching?
14:6|Darby|And now, brethren, if I come to you speaking with tongues,  what shall I profit you, unless I shall speak to you either in  revelation, or in knowledge, or in prophecy, or in teaching?
14:6|KJV|Now, brethren, if I come unto you speaking with tongues, what shall I profit you, except I shall speak to you either by revelation, or by knowledge, or by prophesying, or by doctrine?
14:6<version name="WYC">But now, brethren, if I come to you, and speak in tongues, what shall I profit to you, but if I speak to you either in revelation, either in science, either in prophecy, either in teaching? <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21702b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
14:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，我到你們那裡去，若只說方言，與你們有甚麼益處？除非我用啟示，或知識，或豫言，或教訓，對你們講說。
14:7|ASV|Even things without life, giving a voice, whether pipe or harp, if they give not a distinction in the sounds, how shall it be known what is piped or harped?
14:7|Darby|Even lifeless things giving a sound, whether pipe or harp,  if they give not distinction to the sounds, how shall it be  known what is piped or harped?
14:7|KJV|And even things without life giving sound, whether pipe or harp, except they give a distinction in the sounds, how shall it be known what is piped or harped?
14:7<version name="WYC">For those things that be without soul, and giveth voices, either pipe, either harp, but those give distinction of soundings, how shall it be known that that is sung, either that that is trumpeted. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21703c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup></version>
14:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就是那無生命而發聲之物，或簫、或琴，若發出來的聲調沒有分別，怎能知道所吹所彈的是甚麼？
14:8|ASV|For if the trumpet give an uncertain voice, who shall prepare himself for war?
14:8|Darby|For also, if the trumpet give an uncertain sound, who shall  prepare himself for war?
14:8|KJV|For if the trumpet give an uncertain sound, who shall prepare himself to the battle?
14:8|WYC|For if a trumpet give an uncertain sound [For why if the trump give uncertain voice], who shall make himself ready to battle?
14:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若吹無定的號聲，誰能豫備打仗？
14:9|ASV|So also ye, unless ye utter by the tongue speech easy to understood, how shall it be known what is spoken? for ye will be speaking into the air.
14:9|Darby|Thus also *ye* with the tongue, unless ye give a distinct  speech, how shall it be known what is spoken? for ye will be  speaking to the air.
14:9|KJV|So likewise ye, except ye utter by the tongue words easy to be understood, how shall it be known what is spoken? for ye shall speak into the air.
14:9<version name="WYC">So [and] but ye give an open word by tongue, how shall that that is said be known?  For ye shall be speaking in vain <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21705d" title="See footnote d">d</a>]</sup>.</version>
14:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們也是如此，若不用舌頭說容易明白的話，人怎能知道你所說的是甚麼？這樣，你們就是向空氣說話了。
14:10|ASV|There are, it may be, so many kinds of voices in the world, and no kind is without signification.
14:10|Darby|There are, it may be, so many kinds of voices in the  world, and none of undistinguishable sound.
14:10|KJV|There are, it may be, so many kinds of voices in the world, and none of them is without signification.
14:10<version name="WYC">There be many kinds of languages in this world, and nothing is without voice. [as so many kinds of tongues, <i>or languages</i>, be in this world, and nothing is without voice.]</version>
14:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|世上的口音，種類或者甚多，卻沒有一樣是無音義的。
14:11|ASV|If then I know not the meaning of the voice, I shall be to him that speaketh a barbarian, and he that speaketh will be a barbarian unto me.
14:11|Darby|If therefore I do not know the power of the sound, I shall  be to him that speaks a barbarian, and he that speaks a  barbarian for me.
14:11|KJV|Therefore if I know not the meaning of the voice, I shall be unto him that speaketh a barbarian, and he that speaketh shall be a barbarian unto me.
14:11<version name="WYC">But if I know not the virtue of a voice [Therefore if I know not the virtue of voice], I shall be to him, to whom I shall speak, a barbaric; and he that speaketh to me, <i>shall be </i>a barbaric.</version>
14:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我若不明白那口音的意思，我對那說話的便是化外之人，那說話的對我也是化外之人。
14:12|ASV|So also ye, since ye are zealous of spiritual gifts, seek that ye may abound unto the edifying of the church.
14:12|Darby|Thus *ye* also, since ye are desirous of spirits, seek  that ye may abound for the edification of the assembly.
14:12|KJV|Even so ye, forasmuch as ye are zealous of spiritual gifts, seek that ye may excel to the edifying of the church.
14:12<version name="WYC">So ye, for ye be lovers of spirits, seek ye that ye be plenteous to edification of the church. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21708e" title="See footnote e">e</a>]</sup></version>
14:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們也是如此，既渴慕靈，就要為著召會的建造，尋求得以超越。
14:13|ASV|Wherefore let him that speaketh in a tongue pray that he may interpret.
14:13|Darby|Wherefore let him that speaks with a tongue pray that he  may interpret.
14:13|KJV|Wherefore let him that speaketh in an unknown tongue pray that he may interpret.
14:13<version name="WYC">And therefore he that speaketh in language, pray, that he expound. [And therefore he that speaketh in tongue, pray, that he interpret, <i>or expound</i>.]</version>
14:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以那說方言的，就當禱告，使他能繙出來。
14:14|ASV|For if I pray in a tongue, my spirit prayeth, but my understanding is unfruitful.
14:14|Darby|For if I pray with a tongue, my spirit prays, but my  understanding is unfruitful.
14:14|KJV|For if I pray in an unknown tongue, my spirit prayeth, but my understanding is unfruitful.
14:14<version name="WYC">For if I pray in tongue, my spirit prayeth; mine understanding is without fruit. [For why if I pray in tongue, my spirit prayeth; forsooth my mind, <i>or reason</i>, is without fruit.]</version>
14:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我若用方言禱告，我的靈就禱告，我的心思卻沒有作用。
14:15|ASV|What is it then? I will pray with the spirit, and I will pray with the understanding also: I will sing with the spirit, and I will sing with the understanding also.
14:15|Darby|What is it then? I will pray with the spirit, but I will  pray also with the understanding; I will sing with the spirit,  but I will sing also with the understanding.
14:15|KJV|What is it then? I will pray with the spirit, and I will pray with the understanding also: I will sing with the spirit, and I will sing with the understanding also.
14:15|WYC|What then?  I shall pray in spirit, I shall pray [and] in mind; I shall say psalm in spirit, I shall say psalm also in mind.
14:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這卻怎麼樣？我要用靈禱告，也要用心思禱告；我要用靈歌唱，也要用心思歌唱。
14:16|ASV|Else if thou bless with the spirit, how shall he that filleth the place of the unlearned say the Amen at thy giving of thanks, seeing he knoweth not what thou sayest?
14:16|Darby|Since otherwise, if thou blessest with [the] spirit, how  shall he who fills the place of the simple [Christian] say  Amen, at thy giving of thanks, since he does not know what thou  sayest?
14:16|KJV|Else when thou shalt bless with the spirit, how shall he that occupieth the room of the unlearned say Amen at thy giving of thanks, seeing he understandeth not what thou sayest?
14:16<version name="WYC">For if thou blessest in spirit, who filleth the place of an unlearned man, how shall he say Amen on thy blessing, for he knoweth not, what thou sayest? <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21712f" title="See footnote f">f</a>]</sup></version>
14:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不然，你若用靈祝福，在場那不通方言的人，既然不曉得你所說的，怎能在你感謝的時候說阿們？
14:17|ASV|For thou verily givest thanks well, but the other is not edified.
14:17|Darby|For *thou* indeed givest thanks well, but the other is not  edified.
14:17|KJV|For thou verily givest thanks well, but the other is not edified.
14:17<version name="WYC">For thou [soothly] doest well thankings, but another man is not edified. [For why thou soothly doest well graces, <i>or thankings</i>, but another is not edified.]</version>
14:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你固然感謝得好，無奈別人得不著建造。
14:18|ASV|I thank God, I speak with tongues more than you all:
14:18|Darby|I thank God I speak in a tongue more than all of you:
14:18|KJV|I thank my God, I speak with tongues more than ye all:
14:18|WYC|I thank my God, for I speak in the language of all you; [I do graces to my God, for I speak in the tongue of all you;]
14:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我感謝神，我說方言比你們眾人還多，
14:19|ASV|howbeit in the church I had rather speak five words with my understanding, that I might instruct others also, than ten thousand words in a tongue.
14:19|Darby|but in [the] assembly I desire to speak five words with my  understanding, that I may instruct others also, [rather] than  ten thousand words in a tongue.
14:19|KJV|Yet in the church I had rather speak five words with my understanding, that by my voice I might teach others also, than ten thousand words in an unknown tongue.
14:19<version name="WYC">but in the church I will speak five words in my wit, that also I teach other men, than ten thousand words in tongue [than ten thousands of words in tongue<i> not understood</i>].</version>
14:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但在召會中，我寧願用我的心思說五句話，可以教導人，強如用方言說萬句話。
14:20|ASV|Brethren, be not children in mind: yet in malice be ye babes, but in mind be men.
14:20|Darby|Brethren, be not children in [your] minds, but in malice  be babes; but in [your] minds be grown [men].
14:20|KJV|Brethren, be not children in understanding: howbeit in malice be ye children, but in understanding be men.
14:20|WYC|Brethren, do not ye be made children in wits, but in malice be ye children; but in wits be ye perfect.
14:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，在領悟上不要作小孩子，但在惡事上要作嬰孩，在領悟上卻要成熟。
14:21|ASV|In the law it is written, By men of strange tongues and by the lips of strangers will I speak unto this people; and not even thus will they hear me, saith the Lord.
14:21|Darby|It is written in the law, By people of other tongues, and  by strange lips, will I speak to this people; and neither thus  will they hear me, saith the Lord.
14:21|KJV|In the law it is written, With men of other tongues and other lips will I speak unto this people; and yet for all that will they not hear me, saith the Lord.
14:21|WYC|For in the law it is written, That in other tongues and other lips I shall speak to this people, and neither so they shall hear me, saith the Lord.
14:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|律法上記著：“主說，我要用異邦人的舌頭，和異邦人的嘴脣，向這百姓說話；雖然如此，他們還是不聽從我。”
14:22|ASV|Wherefore tongues are for a sign, not to them that believe, but to the unbelieving: but prophesying is for a sign, not to the unbelieving, but to them that believe.
14:22|Darby|So that tongues are for a sign, not to those who believe,  but to unbelievers; but prophecy, not to unbelievers, but to  those who believe.
14:22|KJV|Wherefore tongues are for a sign, not to them that believe, but to them that believe not: but prophesying serveth not for them that believe not, but for them which believe.
14:22|WYC|Therefore languages be into token, not to faithful men, but to men out of the faith; but prophecies be not to men out of the faith, but to faithful men.
14:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，方言不是給信的人作表記，乃是給不信的人；但申言不是給不信的人作表記，乃是給信的人。
14:23|ASV|If therefore the whole church be assembled together and all speak with tongues, and there come in men unlearned or unbelieving, will they not say that ye are mad?
14:23|Darby|If therefore the whole assembly come together in one  place, and all speak with tongues, and simple [persons] enter  in, or unbelievers, will not they say ye are mad?
14:23|KJV|If therefore the whole church be come together into one place, and all speak with tongues, and there come in those that are unlearned, or unbelievers, will they not say that ye are mad?
14:23|WYC|Therefore if all the church come together into one, and all men speak in tongues, if unlearned men, either men out of the faith enter, whether they shall not say [soothly if idiots enter, or men out of the faith, whether they say not], What be ye mad?
14:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以若全召會聚在一處的時候，眾人都說方言，有不通方言的，或是不信的人進來，豈不說你們癲狂了麼？
14:24|ASV|But if all prophesy, and there come in one unbelieving or unlearned, he is reproved by all, he is judged by all;
14:24|Darby|But if all prophesy, and some unbeliever or simple  [person] come in, he is convicted of all, he is judged of all;
14:24|KJV|But if all prophesy, and there come in one that believeth not, or one unlearned, he is convinced of all, he is judged of all:
14:24|WYC|But if all men prophesy, if any unfaithful man or unlearned man enter [Forsooth if all men prophecy, forsooth if any unfaithful man or idiot enter], he is convicted of all, he is wisely deemed of all.
14:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但若眾人都申言，有不信的，或是不通方言的人進來，他就被眾人勸服，被眾人審明了；
14:25|ASV|the secrets of his heart are made manifest; and so he will fall down on his face and worship God, declaring that God is among you indeed.
14:25|Darby|the secrets of his heart are manifested; and thus, falling  upon [his] face, he will do homage to God, reporting that God  is indeed amongst you.
14:25|KJV|And thus are the secrets of his heart made manifest; and so falling down on his face he will worship God, and report that God is in you of a truth.
14:25<version name="WYC">For the hid things of his heart be known, and so he shall fall down on the face, and shall worship God <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21721g" title="See footnote g">g</a>]</sup>, and show verily that God is in you.</version>
14:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他心裡的隱情顯露出來，就必面伏於地敬拜神，宣告說，神真是在你們中間了。
14:26|ASV|What is it then, brethren? When ye come together, each one hath a psalm, hath a teaching, hath a revelation, hath a tongue, hath an interpretation. Let all things be done unto edifying.
14:26|Darby|What is it then, brethren? whenever ye come together, each  [of you] has a psalm, has a teaching, has a tongue, has a  revelation, has an interpretation. Let all things be done to  edification.
14:26|KJV|How is it then, brethren? when ye come together, every one of you hath a psalm, hath a doctrine, hath a tongue, hath a revelation, hath an interpretation. Let all things be done unto edifying.
14:26<version name="WYC">What then, brethren?  When ye come together, each of you hath a psalm, he hath teaching, he hath apocalypse, he hath tongue, he hath expounding; all things be they done to edification. [Therefore, brethren, what is?  When ye come together, each of you hath a psalm, he hath teaching, he hath apocalypse, <i>or</i> <i>revelation</i>, he hath tongue, he hath interpreting, <i>or expounding</i>; be all things done to edification.]</version>
14:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，這卻怎麼樣？每逢你們聚在一起的時候，各人或有詩歌，或有教訓，或有啟示，或有方言，或有繙出來的話，凡事都當為建造。
14:27|ASV|If any man speaketh in a tongue, let it be by two, or at the most three, and that in turn; and let one interpret:
14:27|Darby|If any one speak with a tongue, [let it be] two, or at the  most three, and separately, and let one interpret;
14:27|KJV|If any man speak in an unknown tongue, let it be by two, or at the most by three, and that by course; and let one interpret.
14:27<version name="WYC">Whether a man speaketh in tongue, by two men, either three at the most <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21723h" title="See footnote h">h</a>]</sup>, and by parts, that one interpret.</version>
14:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若有人說方言，只好兩個人，至多三個人，且要輪流著說，也要有一個人繙出來；
14:28|ASV|but if there be no interpreter, let him keep silence in the church; and let him speak to himself, and to God.
14:28|Darby|but if there be no interpreter, let him be silent in [the]  assembly, and let him speak to himself and to God.
14:28|KJV|But if there be no interpreter, let him keep silence in the church; and let him speak to himself, and to God.
14:28|WYC|But if there be not an interpreter, be he still in the church, and speak he to himself and to God.
14:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若沒有繙的人，就當在召會中靜默，只對自己和神說就是了。
14:29|ASV|And let the prophets speak  by two or three, and let the others discern.
14:29|Darby|And let two or three prophets speak, and let the others  judge.
14:29|KJV|Let the prophets speak two or three, and let the other judge.
14:29|WYC|Prophets twain or three say [Soothly prophets two or three say], and others wisely deem.
14:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於申言者，可以兩個人或三個人說話，其餘的就當明辨。
14:30|ASV|But if a revelation be made to another sitting by, let the first keep silence.
14:30|Darby|But if there be a revelation to another sitting [there],  let the first be silent.
14:30|KJV|If any thing be revealed to another that sitteth by, let the first hold his peace.
14:30|WYC|But if any thing be showed to a sitter, the former be still. [That if any thing shall be showed to one sitting, be the former still.]
14:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但若在座的，另有人得了啟示，那先說話的就當靜默。
14:31|ASV|For ye all can prophesy one by one, that all may learn, and all may be exhorted;
14:31|Darby|For ye can all prophesy one by one, that all may learn and  all be encouraged.
14:31|KJV|For ye may all prophesy one by one, that all may learn, and all may be comforted.
14:31|WYC|For ye may all prophesy [For ye be able to prophesy all], each by himself, that all men learn, and all admonish.
14:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為你們都能一個一個的申言，為要使眾人有學習，使眾人得勉勵。
14:32|ASV|and the spirits of the prophets are subject to the prophets;
14:32|Darby|And spirits of prophets are subject to prophets.
14:32|KJV|And the spirits of the prophets are subject to the prophets.
14:32|WYC|And the spirits of prophets be subject to prophets;
14:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且申言者的靈，是服從申言者的，
14:33|ASV|for God is not a God of confusion, but of peace. As in all the churches of the saints,
14:33|Darby|For God is not [a God] of disorder but of peace, as in all  the assemblies of the saints.
14:33|KJV|For God is not the author of confusion, but of peace, as in all churches of the saints.
14:33|WYC|for why God is not of dissension, but of peace; as I teach in all churches of holy men.
14:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神不是混亂的，乃是和平的。
14:34|ASV|let the women keep silence in the churches: for it is not permitted unto them to speak; but let them be in subjection, as also saith the law.
14:34|Darby|Let [your] women be silent in the assemblies, for it is  not permitted to them to speak; but to be in subjection, as the  law also says.
14:34|KJV|Let your women keep silence in the churches: for it is not permitted unto them to speak; but they are commanded to be under obedience as also saith the law.
14:34|WYC|Women in churches be still; for it is not suffered to them to speak, but to be subject, as the law saith.
14:34|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|婦女在召會中要靜默，像在眾聖徒的眾召會中一樣，因為不准她們說話；她們乃要服從，正如律法所說的。
14:35|ASV|And if they would learn anything, let them ask their own husbands at home: for it is shameful for a woman to speak in the church.
14:35|Darby|But if they wish to learn anything, let them ask their own  husbands at home; for it is a shame for a woman to speak in  assembly.
14:35|KJV|And if they will learn any thing, let them ask their husbands at home: for it is a shame for women to speak in the church.
14:35|WYC|But if they will any thing learn, ask they their husbands at home; for it is foul thing to a woman to speak in the church.
14:35|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|她們若想要學甚麼，可以在家裡問自己的丈夫，因為婦女在召會中說話，是可恥的。
14:36|ASV|What? was it from you that the word of God went forth? or came it unto you alone?
14:36|Darby|Did the word of God go out from you, or did it come to you  only?
14:36|KJV|What? came the word of God out from you? or came it unto you only?
14:36|WYC|Whether the word of God came forth of you, or to you alone it came?
14:36|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神的話豈是從你們出來麼？豈是單臨到你們麼？
14:37|ASV|If any man thinketh himself to be a prophet, or spiritual, let him take knowledge of the things which I write unto you, that they are the commandment of the Lord.
14:37|Darby|If any one thinks himself to be a prophet or spiritual,  let him recognise the things that I write to you, that it is  [the] Lord's commandment.
14:37|KJV|If any man think himself to be a prophet, or spiritual, let him acknowledge that the things that I write unto you are the commandments of the Lord.
14:37|WYC|If any man is seen to be a prophet, or spiritual, know he those things that I write to you, for those be the commandments of the Lord [know he the things that I write to you, for they be the commandments of the Lord].
14:37|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若有人自以為是申言者，或是屬靈的，就該清楚知道，我所寫給你們的是主的命令。
14:38|ASV|But if any man is ignorant, let him be ignorant.
14:38|Darby|But if any be ignorant, let him be ignorant.
14:38|KJV|But if any man be ignorant, let him be ignorant.
14:38|WYC|And if any man not knoweth [Forsooth if any man unknoweth], he shall be unknowing.
14:38|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但若有人不理會，就由他不理會罷。
14:39|ASV|Wherefore, my brethren, desire earnestly to prophesy, and forbid not to speak with tongues.
14:39|Darby|So that, brethren, desire to prophesy, and do not forbid  the speaking with tongues.
14:39|KJV|Wherefore, brethren, covet to prophesy, and forbid not to speak with tongues.
14:39|WYC|Therefore, brethren, love ye to prophesy, and do not ye forbid to speak in tongues.
14:39|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我弟兄們，你們要切慕申言，也不要禁止說方言。
14:40<version name="ASV">But let all things be done decently and in order. </p><p /><br /></version>
14:40<version name="Darby">But let all things be done comelily and with order. </p><p /><br /></version>
14:40<version name="KJV">Let all things be done decently and in order.</p><p /><br /></version>
14:40|WYC|But be all things done seemly [Forsooth be all things done honestly], and by due order in you.
14:40|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡事都要端正得體的按著次序行。
15:1|ASV|Now I make known unto you brethren, the gospel which I preached unto you, which also ye received, wherein also ye stand,
15:1|Darby|But I make known to you, brethren, the glad tidings which I  announced to you, which also ye received, in which also ye  stand,
15:1|KJV|Moreover, brethren, I declare unto you the gospel which I preached unto you, which also ye have received, and wherein ye stand;
15:1|WYC|Soothly, brethren, I make the gospel known to you, which I have preached to you, which also ye have taken, in which [and] ye stand,
15:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，我要你們明白我先前所傳與你們的福音，這福音你們也領受了，又在其中站住；
15:2|ASV|by which also ye are saved, if ye hold fast the word which I preached unto you, except ye believed in vain.
15:2|Darby|by which also ye are saved, (if ye hold fast the word which  I announced to you as the glad tidings,) unless indeed ye have  believed in vain.
15:2|KJV|By which also ye are saved, if ye keep in memory what I preached unto you, unless ye have believed in vain.
15:2|WYC|by which also ye shall be saved [by which and ye be saved]; by which reason I have preached to you, if ye hold, if ye have not believed idly.
15:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們若持守我所傳與你們為福音的話，也必藉這福音逐漸得救，除非你們是徒然相信。
15:3|ASV|For I delivered unto you first of all that which also I received: that Christ died for our sins according to the scriptures;
15:3|Darby|For I delivered to you, in the first place, what also I had  received, that Christ died for our sins, according to the  scriptures;
15:3|KJV|For I delivered unto you first of all that which I also received, how that Christ died for our sins according to the scriptures;
15:3<version name="WYC">For I betook to you at the beginning that thing which also I have received; that Christ was dead for our sins, by the scriptures; <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21739a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
15:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我從前所領受又傳與你們的，第一，就是基督照聖經所說，為我們的罪死了，
15:4|ASV|and that he was buried; and that he hath been raised on the third day according to the scriptures;
15:4|Darby|and that he was buried; and that he was raised the third  day, according to the scriptures;
15:4|KJV|And that he was buried, and that he rose again the third day according to the scriptures:
15:4|WYC|and that he was buried, and that he rose again in the third day, after [the] scriptures;
15:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|而且埋葬了，又照聖經所說，第三天復活了；
15:5|ASV|and that he appeared to Cephas; then to the twelve;
15:5|Darby|and that he appeared to Cephas, then to the twelve.
15:5|KJV|And that he was seen of Cephas, then of the twelve:
15:5|WYC|and that he was seen to Cephas, and after these things to eleven;
15:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且向磯法顯現，然後向十二使徒顯現，
15:6|ASV|then he appeared to above five hundred brethren at once, of whom the greater part remain until now, but some are fallen asleep;
15:6|Darby|Then he appeared to above five hundred brethren at once, of  whom the most remain until now, but some also have fallen  asleep.
15:6|KJV|After that, he was seen of above five hundred brethren at once; of whom the greater part remain unto this present, but some are fallen asleep.
15:6<version name="WYC">afterward he was seen to more than five hundred brethren together, of which many live yet, but some be dead <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21742b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup>;</version>
15:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|後來一時向五百多弟兄顯現，其中大多數到如今還在，但也有些已經睡了；
15:7|ASV|then he appeared to James; then to all the apostles;
15:7|Darby|Then he appeared to James; then to all the apostles;
15:7|KJV|After that, he was seen of James; then of all the apostles.
15:7|WYC|afterward he was seen to James, and afterward to all the apostles.
15:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以後向雅各顯現，然後向眾使徒顯現，
15:8|ASV|and last of all, as to the  child untimely born, he appeared to me also.
15:8|Darby|and last of all, as to an abortion, he appeared to *me*  also.
15:8|KJV|And last of all he was seen of me also, as of one born out of due time.
15:8|WYC|And last of all he was seen also to me, as to a dead born child [as to a mis-born child].
15:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|末了也向我這如同未到產期而生的人顯現。
15:9|ASV|For I am the least of the apostles, that am not meet to be called an apostle, because I persecuted the church of God.
15:9|Darby|For *I* am the least of the apostles, who am not fit to be  called apostle, because I have persecuted the assembly of God.
15:9|KJV|For I am the least of the apostles, that am not meet to be called an apostle, because I persecuted the church of God.
15:9|WYC|For I am the least of the apostles, that am not worthy to be called apostle, for I pursued the church of God.
15:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我原是使徒中最小的，不適於稱為使徒，因為我逼迫過神的召會。
15:10|ASV|But by the grace of God I am what I am: and his grace which was bestowed upon me was not found vain; but I labored more abundantly than they all: yet not I, but the grace of God which was with me.
15:10|Darby|But by God's grace I am what I am; and his grace, which  [was] towards me, has not been vain; but I have laboured more  abundantly than they all, but not *I*, but the grace of God  which [was] with me.
15:10|KJV|But by the grace of God I am what I am: and his grace which was bestowed upon me was not in vain; but I laboured more abundantly than they all: yet not I, but the grace of God which was with me.
15:10<version name="WYC">But by the grace of God I am that thing that I am; and his grace was not void in me [and his grace was not void, <i>or</i> <i>idle</i>, in me].  For I travailed more plenteously than all they [But I travailed more plenteously than all they]; but not I, but the grace of God with me.</version>
15:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而因著神的恩，我成了我今天這個人，並且神的恩臨到我，不是徒然的；反而我比眾使徒格外勞苦，但這不是我，乃是神的恩與我同在。
15:11|ASV|Whether then it be I or they, so we preach, and so ye believed.
15:11|Darby|Whether, therefore, I or they, thus we preach, and thus ye  have believed.
15:11|KJV|Therefore whether it were I or they, so we preach, and so ye believed.
15:11|WYC|But whether I, or they, so we have preached, and so ye have believed.
15:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，不拘是我，是眾使徒，我們如此傳，你們也如此信了。
15:12|ASV|Now if Christ is preached that he hath been raised from the dead, how say some among you that there is no resurrection of the dead?
15:12|Darby|Now if Christ is preached that he is raised from among  [the] dead, how say some among you that there is not a  resurrection of [those that are] dead?
15:12|KJV|Now if Christ be preached that he rose from the dead, how say some among you that there is no resurrection of the dead?
15:12|WYC|And if Christ is preached, that he rose again from death [from dead], how say some men among you [how say some in you], that the again-rising of dead men is not?
15:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|既傳基督從死人中復活了，怎麼在你們中間，有人說沒有死人的復活？
15:13|ASV|But if there is no resurrection of the dead, neither hath Christ been raised:
15:13|Darby|But if there is not a resurrection of [those that are]  dead, neither is Christ raised:
15:13|KJV|But if there be no resurrection of the dead, then is Christ not risen:
15:13|WYC|And if the again-rising of dead men is not, neither Christ rose again from death [neither Christ rose again].
15:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若沒有死人的復活，基督也就沒有復活了；
15:14|ASV|and if Christ hath not been raised, then is our preaching vain, your faith also is vain.
15:14|Darby|but if Christ is not raised, then, indeed, vain also [is]  our preaching, and vain also your faith.
15:14|KJV|And if Christ be not risen, then is our preaching vain, and your faith is also vain.
15:14|WYC|And if Christ rose not, our preaching is vain, our faith is vain.
15:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若基督沒有復活，我們所傳揚的，便是徒然，你們所信的，也是徒然，
15:15|ASV|Yea, we are found false witnesses of God; because we witnessed of God that he raised up Christ: whom he raised not up, if so be that the dead are not raised.
15:15|Darby|And we are found also false witnesses of God; for we have  witnessed concerning God that he raised the Christ, whom he has  not raised if indeed [those that are] dead are not raised.
15:15|KJV|Yea, and we are found false witnesses of God; because we have testified of God that he raised up Christ: whom he raised not up, if so be that the dead rise not.
15:15|WYC|[Forsooth] And we be found false witnesses of God, for we have said witnessing against God, that he raised Christ, whom he raised not, if dead men rise not again.
15:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們也就被發現是神的假見證人，因為死人若真不復活，我們就是妄證神叫祂所沒有復活的基督復活了。
15:16|ASV|For if the dead are not raised, neither hath Christ been raised:
15:16|Darby|For if [those that are] dead are not raised, neither is  Christ raised;
15:16|KJV|For if the dead rise not, then is not Christ raised:
15:16|WYC|For why if dead men rise not again, neither Christ rose again;
15:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為死人若不復活，基督也就沒有復活了；
15:17|ASV|and if Christ hath not been raised, your faith is vain; ye are yet in your sins.
15:17|Darby|but if Christ be not raised, your faith [is] vain; ye are  yet in your sins.
15:17|KJV|And if Christ be not raised, your faith is vain; ye are yet in your sins.
15:17|WYC|and if Christ rose not again, our faith is vain; and yet ye be in your sins.
15:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|基督若沒有復活，你們所信的，便是枉然，你們就仍在你們的罪裡。
15:18|ASV|Then they also that are fallen asleep in Christ have perished.
15:18|Darby|Then indeed also those who have fallen asleep in Christ  have perished.
15:18|KJV|Then they also which are fallen asleep in Christ are perished.
15:18<version name="WYC">And then they that have died in Christ, have perished. [Therefore and they that slept, <i>or died</i>, in Christ, have perished.]</version>
15:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，在基督裡睡了的人也滅亡了。
15:19|ASV|If we have only hoped in Christ in this life, we are of all men most pitiable.
15:19|Darby|If in this life only we have hope in Christ, we are [the]  most miserable of all men.
15:19|KJV|If in this life only we have hope in Christ, we are of all men most miserable.
15:19|WYC|If in this life only we be hoping in Christ, we be more wretches than all men.
15:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們在基督裡，若只在今生有指望，就是眾人中最可憐的。
15:20|ASV|But now hath Christ been raised from the dead, the firstfruits of them that are asleep.
15:20|Darby|(But now Christ is raised from among [the] dead,  first-fruits of those fallen asleep.
15:20|KJV|But now is Christ risen from the dead, and become the firstfruits of them that slept.
15:20<version name="WYC">But now Christ hath risen again from death, the first fruit of dead men; [Now forsooth Christ rose again, <i>from dead</i>, the first fruits of sleeping men;]</version>
15:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但如今基督，就是睡了之人初熟的果子，已經從死人中復活。
15:21|ASV|For since by man came death, by man  came also the resurrection of the dead.
15:21|Darby|For since by man [came] death, by man also resurrection of  [those that are] dead.
15:21|KJV|For since by man came death, by man came also the resurrection of the dead.
15:21<version name="WYC">for death <i>was</i> by a man, and by a man <i>is</i> again-rising from death. [for soothly by a man death, and by a man again-rising of dead.]</version>
15:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|死既是藉著人來的，死人的復活也是藉著人來的；
15:22|ASV|For as in Adam all die, so also in Christ shall all be made alive.
15:22|Darby|For as in the Adam all die, thus also in the Christ all  shall be made alive.
15:22|KJV|For as in Adam all die, even so in Christ shall all be made alive.
15:22|WYC|And as in Adam all men die, so [and] in Christ all men shall be quickened.
15:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為在亞當裡眾人都死了，照樣，在基督裡眾人也都要活過來。
15:23|ASV|But each in his own order: Christ the firstfruits; then they that are Christ's, at his coming.
15:23|Darby|But each in his own rank: [the] first-fruits, Christ; then  those that are the Christ's at his coming.
15:23|KJV|But every man in his own order: Christ the firstfruits; afterward they that are Christ's at his coming.
15:23|WYC|But each man in his order; the first fruit, Christ [first fruits, Christ], afterward they that be of Christ, that believed in the coming of Christ;
15:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只是各人要按著自己的等次：初熟的果子，是基督，以後在祂來臨的時候，是那些屬基督的。
15:24|ASV|Then cometh the end, when he shall deliver up the kingdom to God, even the Father; when he shall have abolished all rule and all authority and power.
15:24|Darby|Then the end, when he gives up the kingdom to him [who is]  God and Father; when he shall have annulled all rule and all  authority and power.
15:24|KJV|Then cometh the end, when he shall have delivered up the kingdom to God, even the Father; when he shall have put down all rule and all authority and power.
15:24|WYC|afterward an end, when he shall betake the kingdom to God and to the Father, when he shall void all princehood, and power, and virtue.
15:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|再後，是末期，那時基督要將國交與神，就是父，那時祂已將一切執政的、掌權的、有能的都廢除了。
15:25|ASV|For he must reign, till he hath put all his enemies under his feet.
15:25|Darby|For he must reign until he put all enemies under his feet.
15:25|KJV|For he must reign, till he hath put all enemies under his feet.
15:25|WYC|But it behooveth him to reign, till he put all his enemies under his feet.
15:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為基督必要作王，直到神把一切仇敵都放在祂的腳下。
15:26|ASV|The last enemy that shall be abolished is death.
15:26|Darby|[The] last enemy [that] is annulled [is] death.
15:26|KJV|The last enemy that shall be destroyed is death.
15:26|WYC|And at the last, death the enemy shall be destroyed; [Forsooth at the last, the enemy death shall be destroyed;]
15:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|最後所廢除的仇敵，就是死，
15:27|ASV|For, He put all things in subjection under his feet. But when he saith, All things are put in subjection, it is evident that he is excepted who did subject all things unto him.
15:27|Darby|For he has put all things in subjection under his feet.  But when he says that all things are put in subjection, [it is]  evident that [it is] except him who put all things in  subjection to him.
15:27|KJV|For he hath put all things under his feet. But when he saith all things are put under him, it is manifest that he is excepted, which did put all things under him.
15:27|WYC|for he hath made subject all things under his feet.  And when he saith, all things be subject to him, without doubt except him that subjected all things to him.
15:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神已叫萬有都服在祂的腳下。祂既說萬有都服了，明顯那叫萬有服祂的，就不在其內了。
15:28|ASV|And when all things have been subjected unto him, then shall the Son also himself be subjected to him that did subject all things unto him, that God may be all in all.
15:28|Darby|But when all things shall have been brought into  subjection to him, then the Son also himself shall be placed in  subjection to him who put all things in subjection to him, that  God may be all in all.)
15:28|KJV|And when all things shall be subdued unto him, then shall the Son also himself be subject unto him that put all things under him, that God may be all in all.
15:28|WYC|And when all things [shall] be subjected to him, then the Son himself shall be subject to him, that made all things subject to him [that subjected all things to him], that God be all things in all things.
15:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬有既服了祂，那時，子自己也要服那叫萬有服祂的，叫神在萬有中作一切。
15:29|ASV|Else what shall they do that are baptized for the dead? If the dead are not raised at all, why then are they baptized for them?
15:29|Darby|Since what shall the baptised for the dead do if [those  that are] dead rise not at all? why also are they baptised for  them?
15:29|KJV|Else what shall they do which are baptized for the dead, if the dead rise not at all? why are they then baptized for the dead?
15:29|WYC|Else what shall they do, that be baptized for dead men, if in no wise dead men rise again [if in all manner dead men rise not again]? whereto [also] be they baptized for them?
15:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不然，那些替死人受浸的，將作甚麼？若死人真不復活，為甚麼還替他們受浸？
15:30|ASV|Why do we also stand in jeopardy every hour?
15:30|Darby|Why do *we* also endanger ourselves every hour?
15:30|KJV|And why stand we in jeopardy every hour?
15:30|WYC|And whereto be we in peril every hour?
15:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們又為甚麼時刻冒險？
15:31|ASV|I protest by that glorifying in you, brethren, which I have in Christ Jesus our Lord, I die daily.
15:31|Darby|Daily I die, by your boasting which I have in Christ Jesus  our Lord.
15:31|KJV|I protest by your rejoicing which I have in Christ Jesus our Lord, I die daily.
15:31<version name="WYC">Each day I die for your glory, brethren, which <i>glory</i> I have in Christ Jesus our Lord.</version>
15:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，我指著我為你們在我們主基督耶穌裡所有的誇耀，鄭重的說，我是天天死。
15:32|ASV|If after the manner of men I fought with beasts at Ephesus, what doth it profit me? If the dead are not raised, let us eat and drink, for to-morrow we die.
15:32|Darby|If, [to speak] after the manner of man, I have fought with  beasts in Ephesus, what is the profit to me if [those that are]  dead do not rise? let us eat and drink; for to-morrow we die.
15:32|KJV|If after the manner of men I have fought with beasts at Ephesus, what advantageth it me, if the dead rise not? let us eat and drink; for to morrow we die.
15:32<version name="WYC">If after man I have fought to beasts at Ephesus [If after man I have fought to beasts, <i>or against beasts</i>, at Ephesus], what profiteth it to me, if dead men rise not again?  Eat we, and drink we, for we shall die to morrow [Eat we, and drink we, to morrow forsooth we shall die].</version>
15:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我若照人的作法，在以弗所同野獸戰鬥，那對我有甚麼益處？若死人不復活，我們就喫喫喝喝罷，因為明天要死了。
15:33|ASV|Be not deceived: Evil companionships corrupt good morals.
15:33|Darby|Be not deceived: evil communications corrupt good manners.
15:33|KJV|Be not deceived: evil communications corrupt good manners.
15:33<version name="WYC">Do not ye be deceived; for evil speeches destroy good conduct. [Do not ye be deceived; forsooth evil speeches corrupt, <i>or destroy</i>, good conduct, <i>or virtues</i>.]</version>
15:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們不要受迷惑：濫交敗壞善行。
15:34|ASV|Awake to soberness righteously, and sin not; for some have no knowledge of God: I speak this to move you to shame.
15:34|Darby|Awake up righteously, and sin not; for some are ignorant  of God: I speak to you as a matter of shame.
15:34|KJV|Awake to righteousness, and sin not; for some have not the knowledge of God: I speak this to your shame.
15:34|WYC|Awake ye, just men, and do not ye do sin; for some men have ignorance of God, but to reverence I speak to you. [Wake ye, just, and do not ye sin; forsooth some have ignorance of God, to reverence I speak to you.]
15:34|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要按著義清醒過來，不要犯罪，因為你們中間有人對神是無知的。我說這話，是要叫你們羞愧。
15:35|ASV|But some one will say, How are the dead raised? and with what manner of body do they come?
15:35|Darby|But some one will say, How are the dead raised? and with  what body do they come?
15:35|KJV|But some man will say, How are the dead raised up? and with what body do they come?
15:35|WYC|But some man saith, How shall dead men rise again, or in what manner body shall they come?
15:35|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但有人要說，死人怎樣復活？帶著甚麼樣的身體來？
15:36|ASV|Thou foolish one, that which thou thyself sowest is not quickened except it die:
15:36|Darby|Fool; what *thou* sowest is not quickened unless it die.
15:36|KJV|Thou fool, that which thou sowest is not quickened, except it die:
15:36|WYC|[O!] unwise man, that thing that thou sowest, is not quickened, but it die first;
15:36|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|愚昧的人，你所種的，若不死就不能生；
15:37|ASV|and that which thou sowest, thou sowest not the body that shall be, but a bare grain, it may chance of wheat, or of some other kind;
15:37|Darby|And what thou sowest, thou sowest not the body that shall  be, but a bare grain: it may be of wheat, or some one of the  rest:
15:37|KJV|And that which thou sowest, thou sowest not that body that shall be, but bare grain, it may chance of wheat, or of some other grain:
15:37<version name="WYC">and that thing that thou sowest, thou sowest not the body that is to come, but a naked corn, as of wheat, or of some other<i> seeds</i>;</version>
15:37|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且你所種的，不是那將來的形體，乃是赤裸的子粒，也許是麥子，或其他的穀。
15:38|ASV|but God giveth it a body even as it pleased him, and to each seed a body of its own.
15:38|Darby|and God gives to it a body as he has pleased, and to each  of the seeds its own body.
15:38|KJV|But God giveth it a body as it hath pleased him, and to every seed his own body.
15:38|WYC|and God giveth to it a body, as he will, and to each of seeds a proper body.
15:38|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但神隨自己的意思，給牠一個形體，並叫各等子粒，各有自己的形體。
15:39|ASV|All flesh is not the same flesh: but there is one  flesh of men, and another flesh of beasts, and another flesh of birds, and another of fishes.
15:39|Darby|Every flesh [is] not the same flesh, but one [is] of men,  and another flesh of beasts, and another [flesh] of birds, and  another of fishes.
15:39|KJV|All flesh is not the same flesh: but there is one kind of flesh of men, another flesh of beasts, another of fishes, and another of birds.
15:39<version name="WYC">Not each flesh <i>is</i> the same flesh, but one <i>is</i> of men, another <i>is</i> of beasts, another <i>is</i> of birds, another <i>is</i> of fishes.</version>
15:39|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|一切肉體不都是一樣的肉體：人的是一樣，牲畜的肉體又是一樣，鳥的肉體又是一樣，魚的又是一樣。
15:40|ASV|There are also celestial bodies, and bodies terrestrial: but the glory of the celestial is one, and the glory of the terrestrial is another.
15:40|Darby|And [there are] heavenly bodies, and earthly bodies: but  different is the glory of the heavenly, different that of the  earthly:
15:40|KJV|There are also celestial bodies, and bodies terrestrial: but the glory of the celestial is one, and the glory of the terrestrial is another.
15:40<version name="WYC">And <i>there be</i> heavenly bodies, and <i>there be</i> earthly bodies [and earthly bodies]; but one glory <i>is</i> of heavenly bodies, and another <i>is</i> of earthly [<i>bodies</i>].</version>
15:40|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有天上的形體，也有地上的形體；但天上形體的榮耀是一樣，地上形體的榮耀又是一樣。
15:41|ASV|There is one glory of the sun, and another glory of the moon, and another glory of the stars; for one star differeth from another star in glory.
15:41|Darby|one [the] sun's glory, and another [the] moon's glory, and  another [the] stars' glory; for star differs from star in  glory.
15:41|KJV|There is one glory of the sun, and another glory of the moon, and another glory of the stars: for one star differeth from another star in glory.
15:41<version name="WYC">Another clearness <i>is</i> of the sun, another clearness <i>is</i> of the moon, and another clearness <i>is</i> of the stars; and a star diverseth from a star in clearness [forsooth a star diverseth from a star in clearness].</version>
15:41|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|日的榮耀是一樣，月的榮耀又是一樣，星的榮耀另是一樣，這星和那星在榮耀上也有分別。
15:42|ASV|So also is the resurrection of the dead. It is sown in corruption; it is raised in incorruption:
15:42|Darby|Thus also [is] the resurrection of the dead. It is sown in  corruption, it is raised in incorruptibility.
15:42|KJV|So also is the resurrection of the dead. It is sown in corruption; it is raised in incorruption:
15:42|WYC|And so the again-rising of dead men.  It is sown in corruption, it shall rise in uncorruption;
15:42|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|死人的復活也是這樣。在朽壞中所種的，在不朽壞中復活；
15:43|ASV|it is sown in dishonor; it is raised in glory: it is sown in weakness; it is raised in power:
15:43|Darby|It is sown in dishonour, it is raised in glory. It is sown  in weakness, it is raised in power.
15:43|KJV|It is sown in dishonour; it is raised in glory: it is sown in weakness; it is raised in power:
15:43|WYC|it is sown in unnobleness [it is sown in unnobility], it shall rise in glory; it is sown in infirmity, it shall rise in virtue;
15:43|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在羞辱中所種的，在榮耀中復活；在軟弱中所種的，在能力中復活。
15:44|ASV|it is sown a natural body; it is raised a spiritual body. If there is a natural body, there is also a spiritual body.
15:44|Darby|It is sown a natural body, it is raised a spiritual body:  if there is a natural body, there is also a spiritual [one].
15:44|KJV|It is sown a natural body; it is raised a spiritual body. There is a natural body, and there is a spiritual body.
15:44|WYC|it is sown a beastly body, it shall rise a spiritual body.  If there is a beastly body, there is also a spiritual body;
15:44|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所種的是屬魂的身體，復活的是屬靈的身體。若有屬魂的身體，也就有屬靈的身體。
15:45|ASV|So also it is written, The first man Adam became a living soul. The last Adam became a life-giving spirit.
15:45|Darby|Thus also it is written, The first man Adam became a  living soul; the last Adam a quickening spirit.
15:45|KJV|And so it is written, The first man Adam was made a living soul; the last Adam was made a quickening spirit.
15:45|WYC|as it is written, The first man Adam was made into a soul living, the last Adam into a spirit quickening.
15:45|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|經上也是這樣記著：“首先的人亞當成了活的魂；”末後的亞當成了賜生命的靈。
15:46|ASV|Howbeit that is not first which is spiritual, but that which is natural; then that which is spiritual.
15:46|Darby|But that which is spiritual [was] not first, but that  which is natural, then that which is spiritual:
15:46|KJV|Howbeit that was not first which is spiritual, but that which is natural; and afterward that which is spiritual.
15:46<version name="WYC">But the first <i>is </i>not that that is spiritual [But not first <i>was</i> that <i>body</i> that is spiritual], but that that is beast-like, afterward that that is spiritual.</version>
15:46|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但不是屬靈的在先，乃是屬魂的在先，以後纔是屬靈的：
15:47|ASV|The first man is of the earth, earthy: the second man is of heaven.
15:47|Darby|the first man out of [the] earth, made of dust; the second  man, out of heaven.
15:47|KJV|The first man is of the earth, earthy; the second man is the Lord from heaven.
15:47<version name="WYC">The first man of earth <i>is</i> earthly; the second man of heaven <i>is</i> heavenly [the second man of heaven<i> is</i> heaven-like].</version>
15:47|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|頭一個人是出於地，乃屬土；第二個人是出於天。
15:48|ASV|As is the earthy, such are they also that are earthy: and as is the heavenly, such are they also that are heavenly.
15:48|Darby|Such as he made of dust, such also those made of dust; and  such as the heavenly [one], such also the heavenly [ones].
15:48|KJV|As is the earthy, such are they also that are earthy: and as is the heavenly, such are they also that are heavenly.
15:48<version name="WYC">Such as the earthly man <i>is</i>, such <i>be </i>[and] the earthly men; and such as the heavenly man <i>is</i>, such <i>be</i> also the heavenly men.</version>
15:48|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那屬土的怎樣，凡屬土的也怎樣；那屬天的怎樣，凡屬天的也怎樣。
15:49|ASV|And as we have borne the image of the earthy, we shall also bear the image of the heavenly.
15:49|Darby|And as we have borne the image of the [one] made of dust,  we shall bear also the image of the heavenly [one].
15:49|KJV|And as we have borne the image of the earthy, we shall also bear the image of the heavenly.
15:49<version name="WYC">Therefore as we have borne the image of the earthly man, bear we also the image of the heavenly <i>man </i>[bear we and the image of the heavenly].</version>
15:49|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們既有屬土者的形像，將來也必有屬天者的形像。
15:50|ASV|Now this I say, brethren, that flesh and blood cannot inherit the kingdom of God; neither doth corruption inherit incorruption.
15:50|Darby|But this I say, brethren, that flesh and blood cannot  inherit God's kingdom, nor does corruption inherit  incorruptibility.
15:50|KJV|Now this I say, brethren, that flesh and blood cannot inherit the kingdom of God; neither doth corruption inherit incorruption.
15:50|WYC|Brethren, I say this thing, that flesh and blood be not able to wield the kingdom of God, neither corruption shall wield uncorruption. [Brethren, I say this thing, that flesh and blood may not wield the kingdom of God, neither corruption shall wield incorruption.]
15:50|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，我告訴你們，血肉之人不能承受神的國，朽壞的也不能承受不朽壞的。
15:51|ASV|Behold, I tell you a mystery: We all shall not sleep, but we shall all be changed,
15:51|Darby|Behold, I tell you a mystery: We shall not all fall  asleep, but we shall all be changed,
15:51|KJV|Behold, I shew you a mystery; We shall not all sleep, but we shall all be changed,
15:51<version name="WYC">Lo! I say to you private of holy things [Lo! I say to you mystery, <i>or private</i>, of holy things].  And all we shall rise again, but not all we shall be changed;</version>
15:51|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|看哪，我把一個奧祕告訴你們：我們不是都要睡覺，乃是都要改變，
15:52|ASV|in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye, at the last trump: for the trumpet shall sound, and the dead shall be raised incorruptible, and we shall be changed.
15:52|Darby|in an instant, in [the] twinkling of an eye, at the last  trumpet; for the trumpet shall sound, and the dead shall be  raised incorruptible, and *we* shall be changed.
15:52|KJV|In a moment, in the twinkling of an eye, at the last trump: for the trumpet shall sound, and the dead shall be raised incorruptible, and we shall be changed.
15:52|WYC|in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye, in the last trump; for the trumpet shall sound, and dead men shall rise again, without corruption [forsooth the trump shall sing, and dead men shall rise again, incorrupt], and we shall be changed.
15:52|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就是在一剎那，眨眼之間，末次號筒的時候；因號筒要響，死人要復活，成為不朽壞的，我們也要改變。
15:53|ASV|For this corruptible must put on incorruption, and this mortal must put on immortality.
15:53|Darby|For this corruptible must needs put on incorruptibility,  and this mortal put on immortality.
15:53|KJV|For this corruptible must put on incorruption, and this mortal must put on immortality.
15:53|WYC|For it behooveth this corruptible thing to clothe uncorruption, and this deadly thing to put away undeadliness. [For it behooveth this corruptible thing for to clothe incorruption, and this deadly thing for to cloth undeadliness.]
15:53|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因這必朽壞的，必要穿上不朽壞；這必死的，必要穿上不死。
15:54|ASV|But when this corruptible shall have put on incorruption, and this mortal shall have put on immortality, then shall come to pass the saying that is written, Death is swallowed up in victory.
15:54|Darby|But when this corruptible shall have put on  incorruptibility, and this mortal shall have put on  immortality, then shall come to pass the word written: Death  has been swallowed up in victory.
15:54|KJV|So when this corruptible shall have put on incorruption, and this mortal shall have put on immortality, then shall be brought to pass the saying that is written, Death is swallowed up in victory.
15:54<version name="WYC">But when this deadly thing shall clothe undeadliness, then shall the word be done, that is written, Death is swallowed up in victory <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21790c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup>.</version>
15:54|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|幾時這必朽壞的穿上不朽壞，這必死的穿上不死，經上所記“死被吞滅而致成得勝”的話，就應驗了。
15:55|ASV|O death, where is thy victory? O death, where is thy sting?
15:55|Darby|Where, O death, [is] thy sting? where, O death, thy  victory?
15:55|KJV|O death, where is thy sting? O grave, where is thy victory?
15:55|WYC|Death, where is thy victory?  Death, where is thy prick?
15:55|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|死阿，你的得勝在那裡？死阿，你的毒刺在那裡？
15:56|ASV|The sting of death is sin; and the power of sin is the law:
15:56|Darby|Now the sting of death [is] sin, and the power of sin the  law;
15:56|KJV|The sting of death is sin; and the strength of sin is the law.
15:56|WYC|But the prick of death is sin; and the virtue of sin is the law.
15:56|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|死的毒刺就是罪，罪的權勢就是律法。
15:57|ASV|but thanks be to God, who giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.
15:57|Darby|but thanks to God, who gives us the victory by our Lord  Jesus Christ.
15:57|KJV|But thanks be to God, which giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.
15:57|WYC|But do we thankings to God [Forsooth thankings to God], that gave to us victory by our Lord Jesus Christ.
15:57|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|感謝神，祂藉著我們的主耶穌基督，使我們得勝。
15:58<version name="ASV">Wherefore, my beloved brethren, be ye stedfast, unmoveable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, forasmuch as ye know that your labor is not vain in the Lord. </p><p /><br /></version>
15:58<version name="Darby">So then, my beloved brethren, be firm, immovable,  abounding always in the work of the Lord, knowing that your  toil is not in vain in [the] Lord. </p><p /><br /></version>
15:58<version name="KJV">Therefore, my beloved brethren, be ye stedfast, unmoveable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, forasmuch as ye know that your labour is not in vain in the Lord.</p><p /><br /></version>
15:58|WYC|Therefore, my dear-worthy brethren, be ye steadfast, and unmoveable, being plenteous in work of the Lord, evermore witting that your travail is not idle in the Lord.
15:58|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我親愛的弟兄們，你們務要堅固，不可搖動，常常竭力多作主工，因為知道你們的勞苦，在主裡面不是徒然的。
16:1|ASV|Now concerning the collection for the saints, as I gave order to the churches of Galatia, so also do ye.
16:1|Darby|Now concerning the collection for the saints, as I directed  the assemblies of Galatia, so do *ye* do also.
16:1|KJV|Now concerning the collection for the saints, as I have given order to the churches of Galatia, even so do ye.
16:1<version name="WYC">But of the gathering <i>of money </i>that be made into saints [Forsooth of the collects, <i>or gatherings of money</i>, that be made into saints], as I <i>have</i> ordained in the churches of Galatia, so also do ye</version>
16:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|關於為聖徒收集餽送，我從前怎樣吩咐加拉太的眾召會，你們也當怎樣行。
16:2|ASV|Upon the first day of the week let each one of you lay by him in store, as he may prosper, that no collections be made when I come.
16:2|Darby|On [the] first of [the] week let each of you put by at  home, laying up [in] whatever [degree] he may have prospered,  that there may be no collections when I come.
16:2|KJV|Upon the first day of the week let every one of you lay by him in store, as God hath prospered him, that there be no gatherings when I come.
16:2<version name="WYC">one day of the week.  Each of you keep at himself [Each of you keep, <i>or lay up</i>, at himself], keeping that that pleaseth to him(self), that when I come, the gatherings be not made.</version>
16:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|每逢七日的第一日，你們各人要照所得的昌盛，拿出來儲存著，免得我來的時候纔收集。
16:3|ASV|And when I arrive, whomsoever ye shall approve, them will I send with letters to carry your bounty unto Jerusalem:
16:3|Darby|And when I am arrived, whomsoever ye shall approve, these I  will send with letters to carry your bounty to Jerusalem:
16:3|KJV|And when I come, whomsoever ye shall approve by your letters, them will I send to bring your liberality unto Jerusalem.
16:3|WYC|And when I shall be present, which men ye approve, I shall send them by epistles to bear your grace into Jerusalem. [Forsooth when I shall be present, whom ye shall prove by epistles, them I shall send to perfectly bear your grace into Jerusalem.]
16:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|及至我來到，你們稱許誰，我就打發他們帶著信，把你們的餽送送到耶路撒冷去；
16:4|ASV|and if it be meet for me to go also, they shall go with me.
16:4|Darby|and if it be suitable that *I* also should go, they shall  go with me.
16:4|KJV|And if it be meet that I go also, they shall go with me.
16:4|WYC|That if it be worthy that also I go, they shall go with me.
16:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若我去也合式，他們可以和我同去。
16:5|ASV|But I will come unto you, when I shall have passed through Macedonia; for I pass through Macedonia;
16:5|Darby|But I will come to you when I shall have gone through  Macedonia; for I do go through Macedonia.
16:5|KJV|Now I will come unto you, when I shall pass through Macedonia: for I do pass through Macedonia.
16:5|WYC|But I shall come to you, when I shall pass by Macedonia; for why I shall pass by Macedonia.
16:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我正要經過馬其頓，經過了，就要到你們那裡去，
16:6|ASV|but with you it may be that I shall abide, or even winter, that ye may set me forward on my journey whithersoever I go.
16:6|Darby|But perhaps I will stay with you, or even winter with you,  that *ye* may set me forward wheresoever I may go.
16:6|KJV|And it may be that I will abide, yea, and winter with you, that ye may bring me on my journey whithersoever I go.
16:6|WYC|But peradventure I shall dwell at you, or also dwell the winter, that ye lead me whither ever I shall go.
16:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|或許和你們同住幾時，或者也過冬，以便我無論往那裡去，你們都可以給我送行。
16:7|ASV|For I do not wish to see you now by the way; for I hope to tarry a while with you, if the Lord permit.
16:7|Darby|For I will not see you now in passing, for I hope to remain  a certain time with you, if the Lord permit.
16:7|KJV|For I will not see you now by the way; but I trust to tarry a while with you, if the Lord permit.
16:7|WYC|And I will not now see you in my passing [Soothly I will not now see you in passing], for I hope to dwell with you a while, if the Lord shall suffer.
16:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我不願意只是路過見你們，主若許，我指望和你們同住幾時。
16:8|ASV|But I will tarry at Ephesus until Pentecost;
16:8|Darby|But I remain in Ephesus until Pentecost.
16:8|KJV|But I will tarry at Ephesus until Pentecost.
16:8|WYC|But I shall dwell at Ephesus, unto Whitsuntide [till Whitsuntide].
16:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但我要仍舊住在以弗所，直到五旬節，
16:9|ASV|for a great door and effectual is opened unto me, and there are many adversaries.
16:9|Darby|For a great door is opened to me and an effectual [one],  and [the] adversaries many.
16:9|KJV|For a great door and effectual is opened unto me, and there are many adversaries.
16:9<version name="WYC">For a great door and an open is opened to me [For why a great door and evident, <i>or open</i>, is opened to me], and many adversaries.</version>
16:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為有寬大又有功效的門為我開了，並且反對的人也多。
16:10|ASV|Now if Timothy come, see that he be with you without fear; for he worketh the work of the Lord, as I also do:
16:10|Darby|Now if Timotheus come, see that he may be with you without  fear; for he works the work of the Lord, even as I.
16:10|KJV|Now if Timotheus come, see that he may be with you without fear: for he worketh the work of the Lord, as I also do.
16:10|WYC|And if Timothy come, see ye that he be without dread with you, for he worketh the work of the Lord, as [and] I.
16:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若是提摩太來到，你們要留心，叫他在你們那裡無所懼怕，因為他作主的工像我一樣。
16:11|ASV|let no man therefore despise him. But set him forward on his journey in peace, that he may come unto me: for I expect him with the brethren.
16:11|Darby|Let not therefore any one despise him; but set him forward  in peace, that he may come to me; for I expect him with the  brethren.
16:11|KJV|Let no man therefore despise him: but conduct him forth in peace, that he may come unto me: for I look for him with the brethren.
16:11|WYC|Therefore no man despise him; but lead him forth in peace, that he come to me; for I abide him with brethren.
16:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以無論誰，都不可藐視他。但你們要送他平安前行，使他可以到我這裡來，因我正等待他和弟兄們同來。
16:12|ASV|But as touching Apollos the brother, I besought him much to come unto you with the brethren: and it was not all his will to come now; but he will come when he shall have opportunity.
16:12|Darby|Now concerning the brother Apollos, I begged him much that  he would go to you with the brethren; but it was not at all  [his] will to go now; but he will come when he shall have good  opportunity.
16:12|KJV|As touching our brother Apollos, I greatly desired him to come unto you with the brethren: but his will was not at all to come at this time; but he will come when he shall have convenient time.
16:12|WYC|But, brethren, I make known to you of Apollos, that I prayed him much, that he should come to you, with brethren.  But it was not his will to come now; but he shall come, when he shall have leisure.
16:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於亞波羅弟兄，我再三的勸他，要同弟兄們到你們那裡去；但現在他絕不願意去，幾時有了機會他必去。
16:13|ASV|Watch ye, stand fast in the faith, quit you like men, be strong.
16:13|Darby|Be vigilant; stand fast in the faith; quit yourselves like  men; be strong.
16:13|KJV|Watch ye, stand fast in the faith, quit you like men, be strong.
16:13|WYC|Walk ye, and stand ye in the faith; do ye manly, and be ye comforted in the Lord, [Wake ye, and stand ye in the faith; do ye manly, and be comforted in the Lord,]
16:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要儆醒，在信仰上站立得住，要作大丈夫，要剛強。
16:14|ASV|Let all that ye do be done in love.
16:14|Darby|Let all things ye do be done in love.
16:14|KJV|Let all your things be done with charity.
16:14|WYC|and be all your things done in charity.
16:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡事你們都要在愛裡作。
16:15|ASV|Now I beseech you, brethren (ye know the house of Stephanas, that it is the firstfruits of Achaia, and that they have set themselves to minister unto the saints),
16:15|Darby|But I beseech you, brethren, (ye know the house of  Stephanas, that it is the first-fruits of Achaia, and they have  devoted themselves to the saints for service,)
16:15|KJV|I beseech you, brethren, (ye know the house of Stephanas, that it is the firstfruits of Achaia, and that they have addicted themselves to the ministry of the saints,)
16:15|WYC|And, brethren, I beseech you, ye know the house of Stephanas, and of Fortunatus, and Achaicus, for they be the first fruits of Achaia, and into ministry of saints they have ordained themselves;
16:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，你們曉得司提反一家，是亞該亞初結的果子，並且他們委身服事聖徒；
16:16|ASV|that ye also be in subjection unto such, and to every one that helpeth in the work and laboreth.
16:16|Darby|that *ye* should also be subject to such, and to every one  joined in the work and labouring.
16:16|KJV|That ye submit yourselves unto such, and to every one that helpeth with us, and laboureth.
16:16|WYC|that also ye be subjects to such, and to each working together and travailing.
16:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我勸你們也服從這樣的人，並一切同工同勞的人。
16:17|ASV|And I rejoice at the coming of Stephanas and Fortunatus and Achaicus: for that which was lacking on your part they supplied.
16:17|Darby|But I rejoice in the coming of Stephanas and Fortunatus  and Achaicus; because *they* have supplied what was lacking on  your part.
16:17|KJV|I am glad of the coming of Stephanas and Fortunatus and Achaicus: for that which was lacking on your part they have supplied.
16:17|WYC|For I have joy in the presence of Stephanas, and Fortunatus, and Achaicus; for they filled that thing that failed to you [for they full-filled that thing that failed to you];
16:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我因司提反和福徒拿都並亞該古的來臨而喜樂，因為你們的不在所致使的短缺，他們都補足了，
16:18|ASV|For they refreshed my spirit and yours: acknowledge ye therefore them that are such.
16:18|Darby|For they have refreshed my spirit and yours: own therefore  such.
16:18|KJV|For they have refreshed my spirit and yours: therefore acknowledge ye them that are such.
16:18<version name="WYC">for they have refreshed both my spirit and yours.  Therefore know ye them, that be such manner <i>men</i>.</version>
16:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們使我和你們的靈都暢快。這樣的人你們務要賞識。
16:19|ASV|The churches of Asia salute you. Aquila and Prisca salute you much in the Lord, with the church that is in their house.
16:19|Darby|The assemblies of Asia salute you. Aquila and Priscilla,  with the assembly in their house, salute you much in [the]  Lord.
16:19|KJV|The churches of Asia salute you. Aquila and Priscilla salute you much in the Lord, with the church that is in their house.
16:19|WYC|All the churches of Asia greet you well.  Aquila and Priscilla, with their home-church, greet you much in the Lord, at the which also I am harboured [Aquila and Priscilla greet you much in the Lord, at whom I am harboured, with their home-church].
16:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞西亞的眾召會問你們安。亞居拉和百基拉，並在他們家中的召會，在主裡多多的問你們安。
16:20|ASV|All the brethren salute you. Salute one another with a holy kiss.
16:20|Darby|All the brethren salute you. Salute one another with a  holy kiss.
16:20|KJV|All the brethren greet you. Greet ye one another with an holy kiss.
16:20|WYC|All brethren greet you well.  Greet ye well together in holy kiss.
16:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|眾弟兄都問你們安。你們要用聖別的親嘴彼此問安。
16:21|ASV|The salutation of me Paul with mine own hand.
16:21|Darby|The salutation of [me] Paul with my own hand.
16:21|KJV|The salutation of me Paul with mine own hand.
16:21|WYC|My greeting by Paul's hand.
16:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我保羅親筆問安。
16:22|ASV|If any man loveth not the Lord, let him be anathema. Maranatha.
16:22|Darby|If any one love not the Lord [Jesus Christ] let him be  Anathema Maranatha.
16:22|KJV|If any man love not the Lord Jesus Christ, let him be Anathema Maranatha.
16:22<version name="WYC">If any man loveth not our Lord Jesus Christ, be he cursed, Maranatha. [If any man love not our Lord Jesus Christ, be he cursed, Maranatha, <i>that is, in the coming of the Lord</i>.]</version>
16:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若有人不愛主，他就是可咒可詛的。主來了！
16:23|ASV|The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ be with you.
16:23|Darby|The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ [be] with you.
16:23|KJV|The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you.
16:23|WYC|The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you.
16:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願主耶穌的恩，與你們同在。
16:24<version name="ASV">My love be with you all in Christ Jesus. Amen. </p><p /><br /></version>
16:24<version name="Darby">My love [be] with you all in Christ Jesus. Amen. </p><p /><br /></version>
16:24<version name="KJV">My love be with you all in Christ Jesus. Amen.</p><p /><br /></version>
16:24|WYC|My charity be with you all in Christ Jesus our Lord.  Amen.
16:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在基督耶穌裡的愛，與你們眾人同在。
