1:1|ASV|That which was from the beginning, that which we have heard, that which we have seen with our eyes, that which we beheld, and our hands handled, concerning the Word of life
1:1|Darby|That which was from [the] beginning, that which we have  heard, which we have seen with our eyes; that which we  contemplated, and our hands handled, concerning the word of  life;
1:1|KJV|That which was from the beginning, which we have heard, which we have seen with our eyes, which we have looked upon, and our hands have handled, of the Word of life;
1:1|WYC|That thing that was from the beginning [Which thing was from the beginning], which we heard, which we saw with our eyes, which we beheld, and our hands touched, of the word of life;
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|論到那從起初原有的生命之話，就是我們所聽見過的，我們親眼所看見過的，我們所注視過，我們的手也摸過的；
1:2|ASV|(and the life was manifested, and we have seen, and bear witness, and declare unto you the life, the eternal life, which was with the Father, and was manifested unto us);
1:2|Darby|(and the life has been manifested, and we have seen, and  bear witness, and report to you the eternal life, which was  with the Father, and has been manifested to us:)
1:2|KJV|(For the life was manifested, and we have seen it, and bear witness, and shew unto you that eternal life, which was with the Father, and was manifested unto us;)
1:2|WYC|and the life is showed.  And we saw, and witness, and tell to you the everlasting life, that was with the Father, and appeared to us.
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|（這生命已經顯現出來，我們也看見過，現在又作見證，將原與父同在，且顯現與我們那永遠的生命傳與你們；）
1:3|ASV|that which we have seen and heard declare we unto you also, that ye also may have fellowship with us: yea, and our fellowship is with the Father, and with his Son Jesus Christ:
1:3|Darby|that which we have seen and heard we report to you, that  *ye* also may have fellowship with us; and our fellowship [is]  indeed with the Father, and with his Son Jesus Christ.
1:3|KJV|That which we have seen and heard declare we unto you, that ye also may have fellowship with us: and truly our fellowship is with the Father, and with his Son Jesus Christ.
1:3|WYC|Therefore that thing, that we saw, and heard, we tell to you, that also ye have fellowship with us, and our fellowship be with the Father, and with his Son Jesus Christ.
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們將所看見並聽見的，也傳與你們，使你們也可以與我們有交通；而且我們的交通，又是與父並與祂兒子耶穌基督所有的。
1:4|ASV|and these things we write, that our joy may be made full.
1:4|Darby|And these things write we to you that your joy may be full.
1:4|KJV|And these things write we unto you, that your joy may be full.
1:4|WYC|And we write this thing to you [And this thing we write to you], that ye have joy, and that your joy be full.
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們寫這些事，是要叫我們的喜樂得以滿足。
1:5|ASV|And this is the message which we have heard from him and announce unto you, that God is light, and in him is no darkness at all.
1:5|Darby|And this is the message which we have heard from him, and  declare to you, that God is light, and in him is no darkness at  all.
1:5|KJV|This then is the message which we have heard of him, and declare unto you, that God is light, and in him is no darkness at all.
1:5|WYC|And this is the telling, that we heard of him, and tell to you, that God is light, and there be no darknesses in him.
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神就是光，在祂裡面毫無黑暗；這是我們從祂所聽見，現在又報給你們的信息。
1:6|ASV|If we say that we have fellowship with him and walk in the darkness, we lie, and do not the truth:
1:6|Darby|If we say that we have fellowship with him, and walk in  darkness, we lie, and do not practise the truth.
1:6|KJV|If we say that we have fellowship with him, and walk in darkness, we lie, and do not the truth:
1:6|WYC|If we say, that we have fellowship with him, and we wander in darknesses, we lie, and do not truth.
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們若說我們與神有交通，卻在黑暗裡行，就是說謊話，不行真理了；
1:7|ASV|but if we walk in the light, as he is in the light, we have fellowship one with another, and the blood of Jesus his Son cleanseth us from all sin.
1:7|Darby|But if we walk in the light as *he* is in the light, we have  fellowship with one another, and the blood of Jesus Christ his  Son cleanses us from all sin.
1:7|KJV|But if we walk in the light, as he is in the light, we have fellowship one with another, and the blood of Jesus Christ his Son cleanseth us from all sin.
1:7|WYC|But if we walk in light, as also he is in light, we have fellowship together; and the blood of Jesus Christ, his Son, cleanseth us from all sin.
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但我們若在光中行，如同神在光中，就彼此有交通，祂兒子耶穌的血也洗淨我們一切的罪。
1:8|ASV|If we say that we have no sin, we deceive ourselves, and the truth is not in us.
1:8|Darby|If we say that we have no sin, we deceive ourselves, and the  truth is not in us.
1:8|KJV|If we say that we have no sin, we deceive ourselves, and the truth is not in us.
1:8|WYC|If we say, that we have no sin, we deceive ourselves, and truth is not in us.
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們若說自己沒有罪，便是自欺，真理就不在我們裡面了。
1:9|ASV|If we confess our sins, he is faithful and righteous to forgive us our sins, and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness.
1:9|Darby|If we confess our sins, he is faithful and righteous to  forgive us [our] sins, and cleanse us from all unrighteousness.
1:9|KJV|If we confess our sins, he is faithful and just to forgive us our sins, and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness.
1:9|WYC|If we acknowledge our sins, he is faithful and just, that he forgive to us our sins, and cleanse us from all wickedness.
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們若認自己的罪，神是信實的，是公義的，必要赦免我們的罪，洗淨我們一切的不義。
1:10<version name="ASV">If we say that we have not sinned, we make him a liar, and his word is not in us. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:10<version name="Darby">If we say that we have not sinned, we make him a liar, and  his word is not in us. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:10<version name="KJV">If we say that we have not sinned, we make him a liar, and his word is not in us.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:10|WYC|And if we say [If we say], that we have not sinned, we make him a liar, and his word is not in us.
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們若說自己沒有犯過罪，便是以神為說謊的，祂的話就不在我們裡面了。
2:1|ASV|My little children, these things write I unto you that ye may not sin. And if any man sin, we have an Advocate with the Father, Jesus Christ the righteous:
2:1|Darby|My children, these things I write to you in order that ye  may not sin; and if any one sin, we have a patron with the  Father, Jesus Christ [the] righteous;
2:1|KJV|My little children, these things write I unto you, that ye sin not. And if any man sin, we have an advocate with the Father, Jesus Christ the righteous:
2:1|WYC|My little sons, I write to you these things, that ye sin not.  But if any man sinneth, we have an advocate with the Father, Jesus Christ [just],
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的孩子們，我將這些事寫給你們，是要叫你們不犯罪。若有人犯罪，我們有一位與父同在的辯護者，就是那義者耶穌基督；
2:2|ASV|and he is the propitiation for our sins; and not for ours only, but also for the whole world.
2:2|Darby|and *he* is the propitiation for our sins; but not for ours  alone, but also for the whole world.
2:2|KJV|And he is the propitiation for our sins: and not for ours only, but also for the sins of the whole world.
2:2<version name="WYC">and he is the forgiveness for our sins; and not only for our <i>sins </i>[and he is helping for our sins; soothly not only for ours], but also for <i>the sins </i>of all the world.</version>
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂為我們的罪，作了平息的祭物，不是單為我們的罪，也是為所有的世人。
2:3|ASV|And hereby we know that we know him, if we keep his commandments.
2:3|Darby|And hereby we know that we know him, if we keep his  commandments.
2:3|KJV|And hereby we do know that we know him, if we keep his commandments.
2:3|WYC|And in this thing we know, that we know him, if we keep his commandments.
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們若遵守祂的誡命，在此就知道我們是認識祂。
2:4|ASV|He that saith, I know him, and keepeth not his commandments, is a liar, and the truth is not in him;
2:4|Darby|He that says, I know him, and does not keep his  commandments, is a liar, and the truth is not in him;
2:4|KJV|He that saith, I know him, and keepeth not his commandments, is a liar, and the truth is not in him.
2:4|WYC|He that saith that he knoweth God, and keepeth not his commandments, is a liar, and truth is not in him.
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那說我認識祂，卻不遵守祂誡命的，便是說謊的，真理也不在這人裡面了；
2:5|ASV|but whoso keepeth his word, in him verily hath the love of God been perfected. Hereby we know that we are in him:
2:5|Darby|but whoever keeps his word, in him verily the love of God is  perfected. Hereby we know that we are in him.
2:5|KJV|But whoso keepeth his word, in him verily is the love of God perfected: hereby know we that we are in him.
2:5|WYC|But the charity of God is perfect verily in him, that keepeth his word [Forsooth who keepeth his word, verily in him is perfect charity].  In this thing we know, that we be in him, if we be perfect in him.
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而凡遵守祂話的，神的愛在這人裡面實在是得了成全。在此我們就知道我們是在祂裡面。
2:6|ASV|he that saith he abideth in him ought himself also to walk even as he walked.
2:6|Darby|He that says he abides in him ought, even as *he* walked,  himself also [so] to walk.
2:6|KJV|He that saith he abideth in him ought himself also so to walk, even as he walked.
2:6|WYC|He that saith, that he dwelleth in him, he oweth to walk, as he walked.
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那說自己住在祂裡面的，就該照祂所行的去行。
2:7|ASV|Beloved, no new commandment write I unto you, but an old commandment which ye had from the beginning: the old commandment is the word which ye heard.
2:7|Darby|Beloved, I write no new commandment to you, but an old  commandment, which ye have had from the beginning. The old  commandment is the word which ye heard.
2:7|KJV|Brethren, I write no new commandment unto you, but an old commandment which ye had from the beginning. The old commandment is the word which ye have heard from the beginning.
2:7<version name="WYC">Most dear <i>brethren</i>, I write to you, not a new commandment, but the old commandment, that ye had from the beginning.  The old commandment is the word, that ye heard.</version>
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|親愛的，我寫給你們的，不是一條新誡命，乃是一條你們從起初就有的舊誡命，這舊誡命就是你們所聽見的話。
2:8|ASV|Again, a new commandment write I unto you, which thing is true in him and in you; because the darkness is passing away, and the true light already shineth.
2:8|Darby|Again, I write a new commandment to you, which thing is true  in him and in you, because the darkness is passing and the true  light already shines.
2:8|KJV|Again, a new commandment I write unto you, which thing is true in him and in you: because the darkness is past, and the true light now shineth.
2:8|WYC|Again I write to you a new commandment, that is true both in him and in you; for darknesses be passed, and very light shineth now [and very light now shineth].
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|再者，我寫給你們的是一條新誡命，這在主並在你們都是真的；因為黑暗漸漸過去，真光已經照耀。
2:9|ASV|He that saith he is in the light and hateth his brother, is in the darkness even until now.
2:9|Darby|He who says he is in the light, and hates his brother, is in  the darkness until now.
2:9|KJV|He that saith he is in the light, and hateth his brother, is in darkness even until now.
2:9|WYC|He that saith, that he is in light, and hateth his brother, is in darknesses yet [is in darkness till to yet].
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那說自己在光中，卻恨他弟兄的，到如今還是在黑暗裡。
2:10|ASV|He that loveth his brother abideth in the light, and there is no occasion of stumbling in him.
2:10|Darby|He that loves his brother abides in light, and there is no  occasion of stumbling in him.
2:10|KJV|He that loveth his brother abideth in the light, and there is none occasion of stumbling in him.
2:10|WYC|He that loveth his brother, dwelleth in light, and cause of stumbling is not in him [and offence is not in him].
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那愛他弟兄的，就住在光中，在他並沒有絆跌的緣由；
2:11|ASV|But he that hateth his brother is in the darkness, and walketh in the darkness, and knoweth not whither he goeth, because the darkness hath blinded his eyes.
2:11|Darby|But he that hates his brother is in the darkness, and walks  in the darkness, and knows not where he goes, because the  darkness has blinded his eyes.
2:11|KJV|But he that hateth his brother is in darkness, and walketh in darkness, and knoweth not whither he goeth, because that darkness hath blinded his eyes.
2:11|WYC|But he that hateth his brother, is in darknesses, and wandereth in darknesses, and knoweth not whither he goeth; for darknesses have blinded his eyes.
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但那恨他弟兄的，是在黑暗裡，且在黑暗裡行，也不知道往那裡去，因為黑暗弄瞎了他的眼睛。
2:12|ASV|I write unto you,  my little children, because your sins are forgiven you for his name's sake.
2:12|Darby|I write to you, children, because [your] sins are forgiven  you for his name's sake.
2:12|KJV|I write unto you, little children, because your sins are forgiven you for his name's sake.
2:12|WYC|Little sons, I write to you, that your sins be forgiven to you for his name.
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|孩子們，我寫信給你們，因為你們的罪因著祂的名得了赦免。
2:13|ASV|I write unto you, fathers, because ye know him who is from the beginning. I write unto you, young men, because ye have overcome the evil one. I have written unto you, little children, because ye know the Father.
2:13|Darby|I write to you, fathers, because ye have known him [that  is] from the beginning. I write to you, young men, because ye  have overcome the wicked [one]. I write to you, little  children, because ye have known the Father.
2:13|KJV|I write unto you, fathers, because ye have known him that is from the beginning. I write unto you, young men, because ye have overcome the wicked one. I write unto you, little children, because ye have known the Father.
2:13<version name="WYC">Fathers, I write to you, for ye have known him, that is from the beginning.  Young men, I write to you, for ye have overcome the wicked.  I write to you, young children [I write to you, infants, <i>or young children</i>], for ye have known the Father.</version>
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|父老們，我寫信給你們，因為你們認識那從起初原有的。青年人，我寫信給你們，因為你們勝了那惡者。小孩子們，我寫信給你們，因為你們認識父。
2:14|ASV|I have written unto you, fathers, because ye know him who is from the beginning. I have written unto you, young men, because ye are strong, and the word of God abideth in you, and ye have overcome the evil one.
2:14|Darby|I have written to you, fathers, because ye have known him  [that is] from the beginning. I have written to you, young men,  because ye are strong, and the word of God abides in you, and  ye have overcome the wicked [one].
2:14|KJV|I have written unto you, fathers, because ye have known him that is from the beginning. I have written unto you, young men, because ye are strong, and the word of God abideth in you, and ye have overcome the wicked one.
2:14|WYC|I write to you, brethren, for ye have known him, that is from the beginning.  I write to you, young men, for ye be strong, and the word of God dwelleth in you, and ye have overcome the wicked.
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|父老們，我剛寫信給你們，因為你們認識那從起初原有的。青年人，我剛寫信給你們，因為你們剛強，神的話住在你們裡面，你們也勝了那惡者。
2:15|ASV|Love not the world, neither the things that are in the world. If any man love the world, the love of the Father is not in him.
2:15|Darby|Love not the world, nor the things in the world. If any one  love the world, the love of the Father is not in him;
2:15|KJV|Love not the world, neither the things that are in the world. If any man love the world, the love of the Father is not in him.
2:15|WYC|Do not ye love the world, nor those things that be in the world [neither those things that be in the world].  If any man loveth the world, the charity of the Father is not in him.
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不要愛世界，和世界上的事。人若愛世界，愛父的心就不在他裡面了；
2:16|ASV|For all that is in the world, the lust of the flesh and the lust of the eyes and the vain glory of life, is not of the Father, but is of the world.
2:16|Darby|because all that [is] in the world, the lust of the flesh,  and the lust of the eyes, and the pride of life, is not of the  Father, but is of the world.
2:16|KJV|For all that is in the world, the lust of the flesh, and the lust of the eyes, and the pride of life, is not of the Father, but is of the world.
2:16|WYC|For all thing that is in the world, is covetousness of flesh, and covetousness of eyes, and pride of life, which is not of the Father, but it is of the world.
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為凡世界上的事，就是肉體的情慾、眼目的情慾、並今生的驕傲，都不是出於父，乃是出於世界。
2:17|ASV|And the world passeth away, and the lust thereof: but he that doeth the will of God abideth for ever.
2:17|Darby|And the world is passing, and its lust, but he that does  the will of God abides for eternity.
2:17|KJV|And the world passeth away, and the lust thereof: but he that doeth the will of God abideth for ever.
2:17|WYC|And the world shall pass, and the covetousness of it; but he that doeth the will of God, dwelleth without end [dwelleth into without end].
2:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這世界和其上的情慾，正在過去；惟獨實行神旨意的，永遠長存。
2:18|ASV|Little children, it is the last hour: and as ye heard that antichrist cometh, even now have there arisen many antichrists; whereby we know that it is the last hour.
2:18|Darby|Little children, it is [the] last hour, and, according as  ye have heard that antichrist comes, even now there have come  many antichrists, whence we know that it is [the] last hour.
2:18|KJV|Little children, it is the last time: and as ye have heard that antichrist shall come, even now are there many antichrists; whereby we know that it is the last time.
2:18|WYC|My little sons, the last hour is; and as ye have heard, that antichrist cometh, now many antichrists be made; wherefore we know [whereof we know], that it is the last hour.
2:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|小孩子們，如今是末時了；你們曾聽見，那敵基督的要來，現在已經有好些敵基督的出來了，從此我們就知道如今是末時了。
2:19|ASV|They went out from us, but they were not of us; for if they had been of us, they would have continued with us: but they went out, that they might be made manifest that they all are not of us.
2:19|Darby|They went out from among us, but they were not of us; for  if they had been of us, they would have surely remained with  us, but that they might be made manifest that none are of us.
2:19|KJV|They went out from us, but they were not of us; for if they had been of us, they would no doubt have continued with us: but they went out, that they might be made manifest that they were not all of us.
2:19|WYC|They went forth from us, but they were not of us; for if they had been of us, they had dwelt with us; but that they be known, that they be not all of us [but that they be known, that they be not of us].
2:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們從我們中間出去，卻不是屬我們的；若是屬我們的，就會仍舊與我們同在；但他們出去，是要顯明他們都不是屬我們的。
2:20|ASV|And ye have an anointing from the Holy One, and ye know all the things.
2:20|Darby|And *ye* have [the] unction from the holy [one], and ye  know all things.
2:20|KJV|But ye have an unction from the Holy One, and ye know all things.
2:20|WYC|But ye have anointing of the Holy Ghost, and know all things. [But ye have unction of the Holy Ghost, and know all things.]
2:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們有從那聖者來的膏油塗抹，並且你們眾人都知道。
2:21|ASV|I have not written unto you because ye know not the truth, but because ye know it, and because no lie is of the truth.
2:21|Darby|I have not written to you because ye do not know the truth,  but because ye know it, and that no lie is of the truth.
2:21|KJV|I have not written unto you because ye know not the truth, but because ye know it, and that no lie is of the truth.
2:21|WYC|I wrote not to you, as to men that know not the truth, but as to men that know it, and for each lying is not of truth.
2:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我剛寫信給你們，不是因你們不曉得真理，正是因為你們曉得，又因為沒有虛謊是出於真理的。
2:22|ASV|Who is the liar but he that denieth that Jesus is the Christ? This is the antichrist, even he that denieth the Father and the Son.
2:22|Darby|Who is the liar but he who denies that Jesus is the Christ?  *He* is the antichrist who denies the Father and the Son.
2:22|KJV|Who is a liar but he that denieth that Jesus is the Christ? He is antichrist, that denieth the Father and the Son.
2:22|WYC|Who is a liar, but this that denieth that Jesus is not Christ?  This is antichrist, that denieth the Father, and the Son.
2:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|誰是說謊的？不是那否認耶穌是基督的麼？否認父與子的，這就是敵基督的。
2:23|ASV|Whosoever denieth the Son, the same hath not the Father: he that confesseth the Son hath the Father also.
2:23|Darby|Whoever denies the Son has not the Father either; he who  confesses the Son has the Father also.
2:23|KJV|Whosoever denieth the Son, the same hath not the Father: he that acknowledgeth the Son hath the Father also.
2:23|WYC|For each that denieth the Son, hath not the Father; but he that acknowledgeth the Son, hath also the Father.
2:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡否認子的就沒有父，承認子的連父也有了。
2:24|ASV|As for you, let that abide in you which ye heard from the beginning. If that which ye heard from the beginning abide in you, ye also shall abide in the Son, and in the Father.
2:24|Darby|As for *you* let that which ye have heard from the  beginning abide in you: if what ye have heard from the  beginning abides in you, *ye* also shall abide in the Son and  in the Father.
2:24|KJV|Let that therefore abide in you, which ye have heard from the beginning. If that which ye have heard from the beginning shall remain in you, ye also shall continue in the Son, and in the Father.
2:24|WYC|That thing that ye heard at the beginning, dwell it in you [That thing that ye heard from the beginning, dwell in you]; for if that thing dwelleth in you [for if it shall dwell in you], which ye heard at the beginning, [and] ye shall dwell in the Son and in the Father.
2:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於你們，務要讓那從起初所聽見的住在你們裡面；那從起初所聽見的若住在你們裡面，你們也就住在子裡面，並住在父裡面。
2:25|ASV|And this is the promise which he promised us, even the life eternal.
2:25|Darby|And this is the promise which *he* has promised us, life  eternal.
2:25|KJV|And this is the promise that he hath promised us, even eternal life.
2:25|WYC|And this is the promise, that he promised to us everlasting life.
2:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂所應許我們的，就是那永遠的生命。
2:26|ASV|These things have I written unto you concerning them that would lead you astray.
2:26|Darby|These things have I written to you concerning those who  lead you astray:
2:26|KJV|These things have I written unto you concerning them that seduce you.
2:26|WYC|I wrote these things to you, of them that deceive you,
2:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我剛將這些話寫給你們，是指著那些迷惑你們的人說的。
2:27|ASV|And as for you, the anointing which ye received of him abideth in you, and ye need not that any one teach you; but as his anointing teacheth you; concerning all things, and is true, and is no lie, and even as it taught you, ye abide in him.
2:27|Darby|and *yourselves*, the unction which ye have received from  him abides in you, and ye have not need that any one should  teach you; but as the same unction teaches you as to all  things, and is true and is not a lie, and even as it has taught  you, ye shall abide in him.
2:27|KJV|But the anointing which ye have received of him abideth in you, and ye need not that any man teach you: but as the same anointing teacheth you of all things, and is truth, and is no lie, and even as it hath taught you, ye shall abide in him.
2:27|WYC|and that the anointing which ye received of him, dwell in you.  And ye have not need, that any man teach you, but as his anointing teacheth you of all things, and it is true, and it is not lying; and as he taught you, dwell ye in him.
2:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們從祂所領受的膏油塗抹，住在你們裡面，並不需要人教導你們，乃有祂的膏油塗抹，在凡事上教導你們；這膏油塗抹是真實的，不是虛謊的，你們要按這膏油塗抹所教導你們的，住在祂裡面。
2:28|ASV|And now, my little children, abide in him; that, if he shall be manifested, we may have boldness, and not be ashamed before him at his coming.
2:28|Darby|And now, children, abide in him, that if he be manifested  we may have boldness, and not be put to shame from before him  at his coming.
2:28|KJV|And now, little children, abide in him; that, when he shall appear, we may have confidence, and not be ashamed before him at his coming.
2:28|WYC|And now, ye little sons, dwell ye in him, that when he shall appear, we have trust, and be not confounded of him in his coming.
2:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現在，孩子們，你們要住在主裡面；這樣，祂若顯現，我們就可以坦然無懼，當祂來臨的時候，也不至於蒙羞離開祂。
2:29<version name="ASV">If ye know that he is righteous, ye know that every one also that doeth righteousness is begotten of him. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:29<version name="Darby">If ye know that he is righteous, know that every one who  practises righteousness is begotten of him. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:29<version name="KJV">If ye know that he is righteous, ye know that every one that doeth righteousness is born of him.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:29|WYC|If ye know that he is just, know ye that also each that doeth rightwiseness, is born of him.
2:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們若曉得祂是義的，就當知道凡行義的人也都是從祂生的。
3:1|ASV|Behold what manner of love the Father hath bestowed upon us, that we should be called children of God; and such we are. For this cause the world knoweth us not, because it knew him not.
3:1|Darby|See what love the Father has given to us, that we should be  called [the] children of God. For this reason the world knows  us not, because it knew him not.
3:1|KJV|Behold, what manner of love the Father hath bestowed upon us, that we should be called the sons of God: therefore the world knoweth us not, because it knew him not.
3:1<version name="WYC">See ye what manner charity the Father gave to us, that we be named the sons of God, and be <i>his sons</i>.  For this thing the world knew not us, for it knew not him [For this thing the world knoweth not us, for it knoweth not him].</version>
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們看，父賜給我們的是何等的愛，使我們得稱為神的兒女，我們也真是祂的兒女。世人所以不認識我們，是因未曾認識祂。
3:2|ASV|Beloved, now are we children of God, and it is not yet made manifest what we shall be. We know that, if he shall be manifested, we shall be like him; for we shall see him even as he is.
3:2|Darby|Beloved, now are we children of God, and what we shall be  has not yet been manifested; we know that if it is manifested  we shall be like him, for we shall see him as he is.
3:2|KJV|Beloved, now are we the sons of God, and it doth not yet appear what we shall be: but we know that, when he shall appear, we shall be like him; for we shall see him as he is.
3:2<version name="WYC">Most dear <i>brethren</i>, now we be the sons of God, and yet it appeared not, what we shall be.  We know, that when he shall appear, we shall be like him, for we shall see him as he is.</version>
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|親愛的，我們現在是神的兒女，將來如何，還未顯明；但我們曉得祂若顯現，我們必要像祂；因為我們必要看見祂，正如祂所是的。
3:3|ASV|And every one that hath this hope set on him purifieth himself, even as he is pure.
3:3|Darby|And every one that has this hope in him purifies himself,  even as *he* is pure.
3:3|KJV|And every man that hath this hope in him purifieth himself, even as he is pure.
3:3|WYC|And each man that hath this hope in him, maketh himself holy, as [and] he is holy.
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡向祂有這盼望的，就潔淨自己，正如祂是潔淨的一樣。
3:4|ASV|Every one that doeth sin doeth also lawlessness; and sin is lawlessness.
3:4|Darby|Every one that practises sin practises also lawlessness; and  sin is lawlessness.
3:4|KJV|Whosoever committeth sin transgresseth also the law: for sin is the transgression of the law.
3:4|WYC|Each man that doeth sin, doeth also wickedness, and sin is wickedness.
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡犯罪的，也行不法；罪就是不法。
3:5|ASV|And ye know that he was manifested to take away sins; and in him is no sin.
3:5|Darby|And ye know that *he* has been manifested that he might take  away our sins; and in him sin is not.
3:5|KJV|And ye know that he was manifested to take away our sins; and in him is no sin.
3:5|WYC|And ye know, that he appeared to do away sins, and sin is not in him.
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們曉得祂曾顯現，為要除去罪；在祂裡面並沒有罪。
3:6|ASV|Whosoever abideth in him sinneth not: whosoever sinneth hath not seen him, neither knoweth him.
3:6|Darby|Whoever abides in him, does not sin: whoever sins, has not  seen him or known him.
3:6|KJV|Whosoever abideth in him sinneth not: whosoever sinneth hath not seen him, neither known him.
3:6|WYC|Each man that dwelleth in him, sinneth not; and each that sinneth, seeth not him, neither knew him.
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡住在祂裡面的，就不犯罪；凡犯罪的，是未曾看見祂，也未曾認識祂。
3:7|ASV|My little children, let no man lead you astray: he that doeth righteousness is righteous, even as he is righteous:
3:7|Darby|Children, let no man lead you astray; he that practises  righteousness is righteous, even as *he* is righteous.
3:7|KJV|Little children, let no man deceive you: he that doeth righteousness is righteous, even as he is righteous.
3:7|WYC|Little sons, no man deceive you; he that doeth rightwiseness, is just, as also he is just.
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|孩子們，不要讓人迷惑你們，行義的人纔是義的，正如祂是義的一樣；
3:8|ASV|he that doeth sin is of the devil; for the devil sinneth from the beginning. To this end was the Son of God manifested, that he might destroy the works of the devil.
3:8|Darby|He that practises sin is of the devil; for from [the]  beginning the devil sins. To this end the Son of God has been  manifested, that he might undo the works of the devil.
3:8|KJV|He that committeth sin is of the devil; for the devil sinneth from the beginning. For this purpose the Son of God was manifested, that he might destroy the works of the devil.
3:8|WYC|He that doeth sin, is of the devil; for the devil sinneth from the beginning.  In this thing the Son of God appeared, that he undo the works of the devil.
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|犯罪的是出於魔鬼，因為魔鬼從起初就犯罪。為此，神的兒子顯現出來，是要消除魔鬼的作為。
3:9|ASV|Whosoever is begotten of God doeth no sin, because his seed abideth in him: and he cannot sin, because he is begotten of God.
3:9|Darby|Whoever has been begotten of God does not practise sin,  because his seed abides in him, and he cannot sin, because he  has been begotten of God.
3:9|KJV|Whosoever is born of God doth not commit sin; for his seed remaineth in him: and he cannot sin, because he is born of God.
3:9|WYC|Each man that is born of God, doeth not sin; for the seed of God dwelleth in him, and he may not do sin [and he may not sin], for he is born of God.
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡從神生的，就不犯罪，因為神的種子住在他裡面；他也不能犯罪，因為他是從神生的。
3:10|ASV|In this the children of God are manifest, and the children of the devil: whosoever doeth not righteousness is not of God, neither he that loveth not his brother.
3:10|Darby|In this are manifest the children of God and the children  of the devil. Whoever does not practise righteousness is not of  God, and he who does not love his brother.
3:10|KJV|In this the children of God are manifest, and the children of the devil: whosoever doeth not righteousness is not of God, neither he that loveth not his brother.
3:10<version name="WYC">In this thing the sons of God be known, and the sons of the fiend.  Each man that is not just, is not of God, and he that loveth not his brother [and he that loveth not his brother, <i>is not of God</i>].</version>
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在此，神的兒女和魔鬼的兒女就顯出來了。
3:11|ASV|For this is the message which ye heard from the beginning, that we should love one another:
3:11|Darby|For this is the message which ye have heard from the  beginning, that we should love one another:
3:11|KJV|For this is the message that ye heard from the beginning, that we should love one another.
3:11|WYC|For this is the telling, that ye heard at the beginning, that ye love each other;
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們應當彼此相愛，這就是你們從起初所聽見的信息；
3:12|ASV|not as Cain was of the evil one, and slew his brother. And wherefore slew he him? Because his works were evil, and his brother's righteous.
3:12|Darby|not as Cain was of the wicked one, and slew his brother;  and on account of what slew he him? because his works were  wicked, and those of his brother righteous.
3:12|KJV|Not as Cain, who was of that wicked one, and slew his brother. And wherefore slew he him? Because his own works were evil, and his brother's righteous.
3:12|WYC|not as Cain, that was of the devil, and slew his brother.  And for what thing slew he him? for his works were evil, and his brother's just.
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不要像該隱，他是出於那惡者，又殺了他的兄弟。為甚麼殺了他？因為自己的行為是惡的，兄弟的行為是義的。
3:13|ASV|Marvel not, brethren, if the world hateth you.
3:13|Darby|Do not wonder, brethren, if the world hate you.
3:13|KJV|Marvel not, my brethren, if the world hate you.
3:13|WYC|Brethren, do not ye wonder, if the world hateth you.
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，世人若恨你們，不要以為希奇。
3:14|ASV|We know that we have passed out of death into life, because we love the brethren. He that loveth not abideth in death.
3:14|Darby|*We* know that we have passed from death to life, because  we love the brethren. He who does not love [his] brother abides  in death.
3:14|KJV|We know that we have passed from death unto life, because we love the brethren. He that loveth not his brother abideth in death.
3:14|WYC|We know, that we be translated from death to life, for we love brethren.  He that loveth not, dwelleth in death.
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們因為愛弟兄，就曉得是已經出死入生了。不愛弟兄的，仍住在死中。
3:15|ASV|Whosoever hateth his brother is a murderer: and ye know that no murderer hath eternal life abiding in him.
3:15|Darby|Every one that hates his brother is a murderer, and ye know  that no murderer has eternal life abiding in him.
3:15|KJV|Whosoever hateth his brother is a murderer: and ye know that no murderer hath eternal life abiding in him.
3:15|WYC|Each man that hateth his brother, is a manslayer; and ye know, that each manslayer hath not everlasting life dwelling in him.
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡恨他弟兄的，就是殺人的；你們曉得凡殺人的，沒有永遠的生命住在他裡面。
3:16|ASV|Hereby know we love, because he laid down his life for us: and we ought to lay down our lives for the brethren.
3:16|Darby|Hereby we have known love, because *he* has laid down his  life for us; and *we* ought for the brethren to lay down [our]  lives.
3:16|KJV|Hereby perceive we the love of God, because he laid down his life for us: and we ought to lay down our lives for the brethren.
3:16|WYC|In this thing we have known the charity of God, for he put his life for us, and we owe to put our lives for our brethren.
3:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主為我們捨命，在此我們就知道何為愛；我們也當為弟兄捨命。
3:17|ASV|But whoso hath the world's goods, and beholdeth his brother in need, and shutteth up his compassion from him, how doth the love of God abide in him?
3:17|Darby|But whoso may have the world's substance, and see his  brother having need, and shut up his bowels from him, how  abides the love of God in him?
3:17|KJV|But whoso hath this world's good, and seeth his brother have need, and shutteth up his bowels of compassion from him, how dwelleth the love of God in him?
3:17|WYC|He that hath the chattel of this world, and seeth that his brother hath need [He that shall have the substance of this world, and shall see his brother have need], and closeth his entrails from him, how dwelleth the charity of God in him?
3:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡有世上養生之物的，看見弟兄有需要，卻向他塞住慈心，神的愛怎能住在他裡面？
3:18|ASV|My Little children, let us not love in word, neither with the tongue; but in deed and truth.
3:18|Darby|Children, let us not love with word, nor with tongue, but  in deed and in truth.
3:18|KJV|My little children, let us not love in word, neither in tongue; but in deed and in truth.
3:18|WYC|My little sons, love we not in word, neither in tongue, but in work and truth.
3:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|孩子們，我們相愛，不要只在言語和舌頭上，總要在行為和真誠上。
3:19|ASV|Hereby shall we know that we are of the truth, and shall assure our heart before him:
3:19|Darby|And hereby we shall know that we are of the truth, and  shall persuade our hearts before him --
3:19|KJV|And hereby we know that we are of the truth, and shall assure our hearts before him.
3:19|WYC|In this thing we know, that we be of truth, and in his sight we admonish our hearts.
3:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在此就知道，我們是屬真理的，並且我們在祂面前可以安心；
3:20|ASV|because if our heart condemn us, God is greater than our heart, and knoweth all things.
3:20|Darby|that if our heart condemn us, God is greater than our heart  and knows all things.
3:20|KJV|For if our heart condemn us, God is greater than our heart, and knoweth all things.
3:20|WYC|For if our heart reprove us, God is more than our heart, and knoweth all things.
3:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們的心若責備我們，神比我們的心大，一切事祂都知道。
3:21|ASV|Beloved, if our heart condemn us not, we have boldness toward God;
3:21|Darby|Beloved, if our heart condemn us not, we have boldness  towards God,
3:21|KJV|Beloved, if our heart condemn us not, then have we confidence toward God.
3:21<version name="WYC">Most dear <i>brethren</i>, if our heart reproveth not us, we have trust to God;</version>
3:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|親愛的，我們的心若不責備我們，我們就可以向神坦然無懼了；
3:22|ASV|and whatsoever we ask we receive of him, because we keep his commandments and do the things that are pleasing in his sight.
3:22|Darby|and whatsoever we ask we receive from him, because we keep  his commandments, and practise the things which are pleasing in  his sight.
3:22|KJV|And whatsoever we ask, we receive of him, because we keep his commandments, and do those things that are pleasing in his sight.
3:22|WYC|and whatever we shall ask, we shall receive of him, for we keep his commandments, and we do those things that be pleasant before him.
3:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且我們不論求甚麼，就從祂得著；因為我們遵守祂的誡命，也行祂看為可喜悅的事。
3:23|ASV|And this is his commandment, that we should believe in the name of his Son Jesus Christ, and love one another, even as he gave us commandment.
3:23|Darby|And this is his commandment, that we believe on the name of  his Son Jesus Christ, and that we love one another, even as he  has given us commandment.
3:23|KJV|And this is his commandment, That we should believe on the name of his Son Jesus Christ, and love one another, as he gave us commandment.
3:23|WYC|And this is the commandment of God, that we believe in the name of his Son Jesus Christ, and that we love each other [And this is the commandment of him, that we believe in the name of his Son Jesus Christ, and love each other], as he gave behest to us.
3:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神的誡命就是叫我們信祂兒子耶穌基督的名，並且照祂所賜給我們的誡命彼此相愛。
3:24<version name="ASV">And he that keepeth his commandments abideth in him, and he in him. And hereby we know that he abideth in us, by the Spirit which he gave us. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:24<version name="Darby">And he that keeps his commandments abides in him, and he in  him. And hereby we know that he abides in us, by the Spirit  which he has given to us. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:24<version name="KJV">And he that keepeth his commandments dwelleth in him, and he in him. And hereby we know that he abideth in us, by the Spirit which he hath given us.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:24|WYC|And he that keepeth his commandments, dwelleth in him, and he in him.  And in this thing we know, that he dwelleth in us, by the Spirit, whom he gave to us.
3:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|遵守神誡命的，就住在神裡面，神也住在他裡面。在此我們就知道神住在我們裡面，乃是由於祂所賜給我們的那靈。
4:1|ASV|Beloved, believe not every spirit, but prove the spirits, whether they are of God; because many false prophets are gone out into the world.
4:1|Darby|Beloved, believe not every spirit, but prove the spirits, if  they are of God; because many false prophets are gone out into  the world.
4:1|KJV|Beloved, believe not every spirit, but try the spirits whether they are of God: because many false prophets are gone out into the world.
4:1<version name="WYC">Most dear <i>brethren</i>, do not ye believe to each spirit, but prove ye the spirits, if they be of God; for many false prophets went out into the world.</version>
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|親愛的，一切的靈，你們不可都信，總要試證那些靈是出於神的不是；因為有許多假申言者已經出來，進到世界裡了。
4:2|ASV|Hereby know ye the Spirit of God: every spirit that confesseth that Jesus Christ is come in the flesh is of God:
4:2|Darby|Hereby ye know the Spirit of God: every spirit which  confesses Jesus Christ come in flesh is of God;
4:2|KJV|Hereby know ye the Spirit of God: Every spirit that confesseth that Jesus Christ is come in the flesh is of God:
4:2|WYC|In this thing the Spirit of God is known; each spirit that acknowledgeth that Jesus Christ hath come in flesh, is of God;
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡靈承認耶穌基督是在肉體裡來的，就是出於神的；在此你們可以認出神的靈來。
4:3|ASV|and every spirit that confesseth not Jesus is not of God: and this is the spirit of the antichrist, whereof ye have heard that it cometh; and now it is in the world already.
4:3|Darby|and every spirit which does not confess Jesus Christ come in  flesh is not of God: and this is that [power] of the  antichrist, [of] which ye have heard that it comes, and now it  is already in the world.
4:3|KJV|And every spirit that confesseth not that Jesus Christ is come in the flesh is not of God: and this is that spirit of antichrist, whereof ye have heard that it should come; and even now already is it in the world.
4:3|WYC|and each spirit that undoeth Jesus, is not of God.  And this is antichrist, of whom ye have heard, that he cometh; and right now he is in the world.
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡靈不承認耶穌，就不是出於神的，這是那敵基督者的靈；你們從前聽見這靈要來，現在已經在世界上了。
4:4|ASV|Ye are of God, my little children, and have overcome them: because greater is he that is in you than he that is in the world.
4:4|Darby|*Ye* are of God, children, and have overcome them, because  greater is he that [is] in you than he that [is] in the world.
4:4|KJV|Ye are of God, little children, and have overcome them: because greater is he that is in you, than he that is in the world.
4:4<version name="WYC">Ye, little sons, be of God, and ye have overcome him; for he that is in you is more, than he that <i>is</i> in the world.</version>
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|孩子們，你們是出於神的，並且勝了他們；因為那在你們裡面的，比那在世界上的更大。
4:5|ASV|They are of the world: therefore speak they as of the world, and the world heareth them.
4:5|Darby|*They* are of the world; for this reason they speak [as] of  the world, and the world hears them.
4:5|KJV|They are of the world: therefore speak they of the world, and the world heareth them.
4:5|WYC|They be of the world, therefore they speak of the world, and the world heareth them.
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們是出於世界的；所以他們的講說乃是出於世界，世人也聽從他們。
4:6|ASV|We are of God: he that knoweth God heareth us; he who is not of God heareth us not. By this we know the spirit of truth, and the spirit of error.
4:6|Darby|*We* are of God; he that knows God hears us; he who is not  of God does not hear us. From this we know the spirit of truth  and the spirit of error.
4:6|KJV|We are of God: he that knoweth God heareth us; he that is not of God heareth not us. Hereby know we the spirit of truth, and the spirit of error.
4:6|WYC|We be of God; he that knoweth God, heareth us; he that is not of God, heareth not us.  In this thing we know the spirit of truth, and the spirit of error.
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們是出於神的；認識神的就聽從我們，不出於神的就不聽從我們；從此我們可以認出真理的靈和謬妄的靈來。
4:7|ASV|Beloved, let us love one another: for love is of God; and every one that loveth is begotten of God, and knoweth God.
4:7|Darby|Beloved, let us love one another; because love is of God,  and every one that loves has been begotten of God, and knows  God.
4:7|KJV|Beloved, let us love one another: for love is of God; and every one that loveth is born of God, and knoweth God.
4:7<version name="WYC">Most dear <i>brethren</i>, love we together, for charity is of God; and each that loveth his brother, is born of God, and knoweth God.</version>
4:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|親愛的，我們應當彼此相愛，因為愛是出於神的；凡愛弟兄的，都是從神生的，並且認識神。
4:8|ASV|He that loveth not knoweth not God; for God is love.
4:8|Darby|He that loves not has not known God; for God is love.
4:8|KJV|He that loveth not knoweth not God; for God is love.
4:8|WYC|He that loveth not, knoweth not God; for God is charity.
4:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不愛弟兄的，未曾認識神，因為神就是愛。
4:9|ASV|Herein was the love of God manifested in us, that God hath sent his only begotten Son into the world that we might live through him.
4:9|Darby|Herein as to us has been manifested the love of God, that  God has sent his only begotten Son into the world, that we  might live through him.
4:9|KJV|In this was manifested the love of God toward us, because that God sent his only begotten Son into the world, that we might live through him.
4:9|WYC|In this thing the charity of God appeared in us, for God sent his one begotten Son into the world, that we live by him.
4:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神差祂的獨生子到世上來，使我們藉著祂得生並活著，在此神的愛就向我們顯明了。
4:10|ASV|Herein is love, not that we loved God, but that he loved us, and sent his Son to be the propitiation for our sins.
4:10|Darby|Herein is love, not that we loved God, but that he loved  us, and sent his Son a propitiation for our sins.
4:10|KJV|Herein is love, not that we loved God, but that he loved us, and sent his Son to be the propitiation for our sins.
4:10|WYC|In this thing is charity, not as we had loved God, but for he first loved us, and sent his Son forgiveness for our sins [and sent his Son helping for our sins].
4:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不是我們愛神，乃是神愛我們，差祂的兒子，為我們的罪作了平息的祭物，在此就是愛了。
4:11|ASV|Beloved, if God so loved us, we also ought to love one another.
4:11|Darby|Beloved, if God has so loved us, we also ought to love one  another.
4:11|KJV|Beloved, if God so loved us, we ought also to love one another.
4:11<version name="WYC">Ye most dear <i>brethren</i>, if God loved us, [and] we owe to love each other.</version>
4:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|親愛的，神既是這樣愛我們，我們也當彼此相愛。
4:12|ASV|No man hath beheld God at any time: if we love one another, God abideth in us, and his love is perfected in us:
4:12|Darby|No one has seen God at any time: if we love one another,  God abides in us, and his love is perfected in us.
4:12|KJV|No man hath seen God at any time. If we love one another, God dwelleth in us, and his love is perfected in us.
4:12|WYC|No man saw ever God; if we love together, God dwelleth in us, and the charity of him is perfect in us.
4:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|從來沒有人見過神；我們若彼此相愛，神就住在我們裡面，祂的愛也在我們裡面得了成全。
4:13|ASV|hereby we know that we abide in him and he in us, because he hath given us of his Spirit.
4:13|Darby|Hereby we know that we abide in him and he in us, that he  has given to us of his Spirit.
4:13|KJV|Hereby know we that we dwell in him, and he in us, because he hath given us of his Spirit.
4:13|WYC|In this thing we know, that we dwell in him, and he in us; for of his Spirit he gave to us.
4:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神已將祂的靈賜給我們，在此就知道我們住在祂裡面，祂也住在我們裡面。
4:14|ASV|And we have beheld and bear witness that the Father hath sent the Son to be the Saviour of the world.
4:14|Darby|And *we* have seen, and testify, that the Father has sent  the Son [as] Saviour of the world.
4:14|KJV|And we have seen and do testify that the Father sent the Son to be the Saviour of the world.
4:14|WYC|And we saw, and witness, that the Father sent his Son Saviour of the world.
4:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|父差子作世人的救主，這是我們所看見，現在又作見證的。
4:15|ASV|Whosoever shall confess that Jesus is the Son of God, God abideth in him, and he in God.
4:15|Darby|Whosoever shall confess that Jesus is the Son of God, God  abides in him, and he in God.
4:15|KJV|Whosoever shall confess that Jesus is the Son of God, God dwelleth in him, and he in God.
4:15|WYC|Whoever acknowledgeth [Who-ever shall acknowledge], that Jesus is the Son of God, God dwelleth in him, and he in God.
4:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡承認耶穌是神兒子的，神就住在他裡面，他也住在神裡面。
4:16|ASV|And we know and have believed the love which God hath in us. God is love; and he that abideth in love abideth in God, and God abideth in him.
4:16|Darby|And *we* have known and have believed the love which God  has to us. God is love, and he that abides in love abides in  God, and God in him.
4:16|KJV|And we have known and believed the love that God hath to us. God is love; and he that dwelleth in love dwelleth in God, and God in him.
4:16|WYC|And we have known, and believe to the charity, that God hath in us.  God is charity, and he that dwelleth in charity, dwelleth in God, and God in him.
4:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神在我們身上的愛，我們也知道也信。神就是愛，住在愛裡面的，就住在神裡面，神也住在他裡面。
4:17|ASV|Herein is love made perfect with us, that we may have boldness in the day of judgment; because as he is, even so are we in this world.
4:17|Darby|Herein has love been perfected with us that we may have  boldness in the day of judgment, that even as *he* is, *we*  also are in this world.
4:17|KJV|Herein is our love made perfect, that we may have boldness in the day of judgment: because as he is, so are we in this world.
4:17|WYC|In this thing is the perfect charity of God with us [In this thing is the perfect charity of God in us], that we have trust in the day of doom; for as he is, also we be in this world.
4:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在此，愛在我們便得了成全，使我們在審判的日子，可以坦然無懼；因為祂如何，我們在這世上也如何。
4:18|ASV|There is no fear in love: but perfect love casteth out fear, because fear hath punishment; and he that feareth is not made perfect in love.
4:18|Darby|There is no fear in love, but perfect love casts out fear;  for fear has torment, and he that fears has not been made  perfect in love.
4:18|KJV|There is no fear in love; but perfect love casteth out fear: because fear hath torment. He that feareth is not made perfect in love.
4:18|WYC|Dread is not in charity, but perfect charity putteth out dread [but perfect charity sendeth out dread]; for dread hath pain.  But he that dreadeth, is not perfect in charity.
4:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|愛裡沒有懼怕，完全的愛把懼怕驅除，因為懼怕含有刑罰，懼怕的人在愛裡未得成全。
4:19|ASV|We love, because he first loved us.
4:19|Darby|*We* love because *he* has first loved us.
4:19|KJV|We love him, because he first loved us.
4:19<version name="WYC">Therefore love we God, for he loved us before. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23639a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
4:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們愛，因為神先愛我們。
4:20|ASV|If a man say, I love God, and hateth his brother, he is a liar: for he that loveth not his brother whom he hath seen, cannot love God whom he hath not seen.
4:20|Darby|If any one say, I love God, and hate his brother, he is a  liar: for he that loves not his brother whom he has seen, how  can he love God whom he has not seen?
4:20|KJV|If a man say, I love God, and hateth his brother, he is a liar: for he that loveth not his brother whom he hath seen, how can he love God whom he hath not seen?
4:20|WYC|If any man saith, I love God, and hateth his brother, he is a liar.   For he that loveth not his brother, whom he seeth, how may he love God, whom he seeth not?
4:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人若說，我愛神，卻恨他的弟兄，就是說謊的；不愛他所看見的弟兄，就不能愛沒有看見的神。
4:21<version name="ASV">And this commandment have we from him, that he who loveth God love his brother also. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:21<version name="Darby">And this commandment have we from him, That he that loves  God love also his brother. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:21<version name="KJV">And this commandment have we from him, That he who loveth God love his brother also.</p><p /><br /></version>
4:21|WYC|And we have this commandment of God, that he that loveth God, love also his brother.
4:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|愛神的，也當愛他的弟兄，這是我們從祂所受的誡命。
5:1|ASV|Whosoever believeth that Jesus is the Christ is begotten of God: and whosoever loveth him that begat loveth him also that is begotten of him.
5:1|Darby|Every one that believes that Jesus is the Christ is begotten  of God; and every one that loves him that has begotten loves  also him that is begotten of him.
5:1|KJV|Whosoever believeth that Jesus is the Christ is born of God: and every one that loveth him that begat loveth him also that is begotten of him.
5:1|WYC|Each man that believeth that Jesus is Christ, is born of God; and each man that loveth him that engendered [and each that loveth him that gendereth], loveth him that is born of him.
5:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡信耶穌是基督的，都是從神生的；凡愛那生他的，也愛從祂生的。
5:2|ASV|Hereby we know that we love the children of God, when we love God and do his commandments.
5:2|Darby|Hereby know we that we love the children of God, when we  love God and keep his commandments.
5:2|KJV|By this we know that we love the children of God, when we love God, and keep his commandments.
5:2|WYC|In this thing we know, that we love the children of God, when we love God, and do his commandments.
5:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們若愛神，並行祂的誡命，在此就知道我們愛神的兒女。
5:3|ASV|For this is the love of God, that we keep his commandments: and his commandments are not grievous.
5:3|Darby|For this is the love of God, that we keep his commandments;  and his commandments are not grievous.
5:3|KJV|For this is the love of God, that we keep his commandments: and his commandments are not grievous.
5:3|WYC|For this is the charity of God, that we keep his commandments; and his commandments be not heavy [and his commandments be not grievous].
5:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們遵守神的誡命，這就是愛祂了；並且祂的誡命不是難擔的；
5:4|ASV|For whatsoever is begotten of God overcometh the world: and this is the victory that hath overcome the world, even our faith.
5:4|Darby|For all that has been begotten of God gets the victory over  the world; and this is the victory which has gotten the victory  over the world, our faith.
5:4|KJV|For whatsoever is born of God overcometh the world: and this is the victory that overcometh the world, even our faith.
5:4|WYC|For all thing that is born of God, overcometh the world; and this is the victory that overcometh the world, our faith.
5:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為凡從神生之物，就勝過世界，勝過世界的，就是我們的信。
5:5|ASV|And who is he that overcometh the world, but he that believeth that Jesus is the Son of God?
5:5|Darby|Who is he that gets the victory over the world, but he that  believes that Jesus is the Son of God?
5:5|KJV|Who is he that overcometh the world, but he that believeth that Jesus is the Son of God?
5:5|WYC|And who is he that overcometh the world, but he that believeth that Jesus is the Son of God?
5:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|勝過世界的是誰？不就是那信耶穌是神兒子的麼？
5:6|ASV|This is he that came by water and blood, even Jesus Christ; not with the water only, but with the water and with the blood.
5:6|Darby|This is he that came by water and blood, Jesus [the] Christ;  not by water only, but by water and blood. And it is the Spirit  that bears witness, for the Spirit is the truth.
5:6|KJV|This is he that came by water and blood, even Jesus Christ; not by water only, but by water and blood. And it is the Spirit that beareth witness, because the Spirit is truth.
5:6|WYC|This is Jesus Christ, that came by water and blood; not in water only, but in water and blood.  And the Spirit is he that witnesseth, that Christ is [the] truth.
5:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這藉著水與血來的，就是耶穌基督；不是單憑著水，乃是憑著水，又憑著血；並且作見證的就是那靈，因為那靈就是實際。
5:7|ASV|And it is the Spirit that beareth witness, because the Spirit is the truth.
5:7|Darby|For they that bear witness are three:
5:7|KJV|For there are three that bear record in heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghost: and these three are one.
5:7<version name="WYC">For three be, that give witnessing in heaven, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghost [For three be, that bear witness in heaven, the Father, the Word, <i>or Son</i>, and the Holy Ghost]; and these three be one.</version>
5:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|作見證的原來有三，
5:8|ASV|For there are three who bear witness, the Spirit, and the water, and the blood: and the three agree in one.
5:8|Darby|the Spirit, and the water, and the blood; and the three  agree in one.
5:8|KJV|And there are three that bear witness in earth, the Spirit, and the water, and the blood: and these three agree in one.
5:8|WYC|And three be, that give witnessing in earth, the Spirit, water, and blood; and these three be one.
5:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就是那靈、水與血，這三樣也都歸於一。
5:9|ASV|If we receive the witness of men, the witness of God is greater: for the witness of God is this, that he hath borne witness concerning his Son.
5:9|Darby|If we receive the witness of men, the witness of God is  greater. For this is the witness of God [which] he has  witnessed concerning his Son.
5:9|KJV|If we receive the witness of men, the witness of God is greater: for this is the witness of God which he hath testified of his Son.
5:9|WYC|If we receive the witnessing of men, the witnessing of God is more; for this is the witnessing of God, that is more, for he witnessed of his Son.
5:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們若領受人的見證，神的見證更大，因為這是神為祂兒子所作的見證。
5:10|ASV|He that believeth on the Son of God hath the witness in him: he that believeth not God hath made him a liar; because he hath not believed in the witness that God hath borne concerning his Son.
5:10|Darby|He that believes on the Son of God has the witness in  himself; he that does not believe God has made him a liar,  because he has not believed in the witness which God has  witnessed concerning his Son.
5:10|KJV|He that believeth on the Son of God hath the witness in himself: he that believeth not God hath made him a liar; because he believeth not the record that God gave of his Son.
5:10|WYC|He that believeth in the Son of God, hath the witnessing of God in him.  He that believeth not to the Son, maketh him a liar; for he believeth not in the witnessing, that God witnessed of his Son.
5:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|信入神兒子的，就有這見證在他裡面。不信神的，就是將神當作說謊的，因他不信入神為祂兒子所作的見證。
5:11|ASV|And the witness is this, that God gave unto us eternal life, and this life is in his Son.
5:11|Darby|And this is the witness, that God has given to us eternal  life; and this life is in his Son.
5:11|KJV|And this is the record, that God hath given to us eternal life, and this life is in his Son.
5:11|WYC|And this is the witnessing, for God gave to you everlasting life [for God gave to us everlasting life], and this life is in his Son.
5:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這見證就是神賜給我們永遠的生命，這生命也是在祂兒子裡面。
5:12|ASV|He that hath the Son hath the life; he that hath not the Son of God hath not the life.
5:12|Darby|He that has the Son has life: he that has not the Son of  God has not life.
5:12|KJV|He that hath the Son hath life; and he that hath not the Son of God hath not life.
5:12<version name="WYC">He that hath the Son <i>of God,</i> hath also life [He that hath the Son, hath life]; he that hath not the Son <i>of God,</i> hath not life.</version>
5:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人有了神的兒子，就有生命；沒有神的兒子，就沒有生命。
5:13|ASV|These things have I written unto you, that ye may know that ye have eternal life, even unto you that believe on the name of the Son of God.
5:13|Darby|These things have I written to you that ye may know that ye  have eternal life who believe on the name of the Son of God.
5:13|KJV|These things have I written unto you that believe on the name of the Son of God; that ye may know that ye have eternal life, and that ye may believe on the name of the Son of God.
5:13|WYC|I write to you these things, that ye know, that ye have everlasting life, which believe in the name of God's Son.
5:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我將這些話寫給你們信入神兒子之名的人，要叫你們曉得自己有永遠的生命。
5:14|ASV|And this is the boldness which we have toward him, that, if we ask anything according to his will, he heareth us:
5:14|Darby|And this is the boldness which we have towards him, that if  we ask him anything according to his will he hears us.
5:14|KJV|And this is the confidence that we have in him, that, if we ask any thing according to his will, he heareth us:
5:14|WYC|And this is the trust which we have to God [And this is the trust that we have in God], that whatever thing we ask after his will, he shall hear us.
5:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們若照祂的旨意求甚麼，祂就聽我們；這是我們向著祂所存坦然無懼的心。
5:15|ASV|and if we know that he heareth us whatsoever we ask, we know that we have the petitions which we have asked of him.
5:15|Darby|And if we know that he hears us, whatsoever we ask, we know  that we have the petitions which we have asked of him.
5:15|KJV|And if we know that he hear us, whatsoever we ask, we know that we have the petitions that we desired of him.
5:15|WYC|And we know, that he heareth us, whatever thing we ask; we know, that we have the askings, that we ask of him [which we ask of him].
5:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們若知道祂聽我們一切所求的，就知道我們所求於祂的無不得著。
5:16|ASV|If any man see his brother sinning a sin not unto death, he shall ask, and God will give him life for them that sin not unto death. There is a sin unto death: not concerning this do I say that he should make request.
5:16|Darby|If any one see his brother sinning a sin not unto death, he  shall ask, and he shall give him life, for those that do not  sin unto death. There is a sin to death: I do not say of that  that he should make a request.
5:16|KJV|If any man see his brother sin a sin which is not unto death, he shall ask, and he shall give him life for them that sin not unto death. There is a sin unto death: I do not say that he shall pray for it.
5:16|WYC|He that knoweth that his brother sinneth a sin not to death [He that knoweth his brother to sin a sin not to death], ask he, and life shall be given to him that sinneth not to death.  There is a sin to death; not for it I say, that any man pray.
5:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人若看見他的弟兄犯了不至於死的罪，就當為他祈求，將生命賜給他，就是給那些犯了不至於死之罪的。有至於死的罪，我不說當為那罪祈求。
5:17|ASV|All unrighteousness is sin: and there is a sin not unto death.
5:17|Darby|Every unrighteousness is sin; and there is a sin not to  death.
5:17|KJV|All unrighteousness is sin: and there is a sin not unto death.
5:17|WYC|Each wickedness is sin, and there is [a] sin to death.
5:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|一切的不義都是罪，也有不至於死的罪。
5:18|ASV|We know that whosoever is begotten of God sinneth not; but he that was begotten of God keepeth himself, and the evil one toucheth him not.
5:18|Darby|We know that every one begotten of God does not sin, but he  that has been begotten of God keeps himself, and the wicked  [one] does not touch him.
5:18|KJV|We know that whosoever is born of God sinneth not; but he that is begotten of God keepeth himself, and that wicked one toucheth him not.
5:18|WYC|We know, that each man that is born of God, sinneth not; but the generation of God keepeth him, and the wicked toucheth him not.
5:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們曉得凡從神生的都不犯罪，那從神生的，保守自己，那惡者也就不摸他。
5:19|ASV|We know that we are of God, and the whole world lieth in the evil one.
5:19|Darby|We know that we are of God, and the whole world lies in the  wicked [one].
5:19|KJV|And we know that we are of God, and the whole world lieth in wickedness.
5:19|WYC|We know, that we be of God, and all the world is set in evil [and all the world is put in wicked].
5:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們曉得我們是屬神的，而整個世界都臥在那惡者裡面。
5:20|ASV|And we know that the Son of God is come, and hath given us an understanding, that we know him that is true, and we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jesus Christ. This is the true God, and eternal life.
5:20|Darby|And we know that the Son of God has come, and has given us  an understanding that we should know him that [is] true; and we  are in him that [is] true, in his Son Jesus Christ. He is the  true God and eternal life.
5:20|KJV|And we know that the Son of God is come, and hath given us an understanding, that we may know him that is true, and we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jesus Christ. This is the true God, and eternal life.
5:20|WYC|And we know, that the Son of God came in flesh, and gave to us wit, that we know him very God, and be in the very Son [Jesus] of him [and be in the very Son Jesus of him].  This is very God, and everlasting life.
5:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們也曉得神的兒子已經來到，且將悟性賜給我們，使我們可以認識那位真實的；我們也在那位真實的裡面，就是在祂兒子耶穌基督裡面。這是真神，也是永遠的生命。
5:21<version name="ASV">My little children, guard yourselves from idols. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:21<version name="Darby">Children, keep yourselves from idols. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:21<version name="KJV">Little children, keep yourselves from idols. Amen.</p><p /><br /></version>
5:21<version name="WYC">My little sons, keep ye you from maumets. [Amen.] [Little sons, keep ye you from simulacra, <i>or covetousness</i>.  Amen.]</version>
5:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|孩子們，你們要保守自己，遠避偶像。
