1:1|ASV|Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus through the will of God, and Timothy our brother, unto the church of God which is at Corinth, with all the saints that are in the whole of Achaia:
1:1|Darby|Paul, apostle of Jesus Christ by God's will, and the brother  Timotheus, to the assembly of God which is in Corinth, with all  the saints who are in the whole of Achaia.
1:1|KJV|Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God, and Timothy our brother, unto the church of God which is at Corinth, with all the saints which are in all Achaia:
1:1|WYC|Paul, apostle of Jesus Christ, by the will of God, and Timothy, brother, to the church of God that is at Corinth, with all saints that be in all Achaia,
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|憑神旨意，作基督耶穌使徒的保羅，和弟兄提摩太，寫信給在哥林多神的召會，同著在全亞該亞的眾聖徒：
1:2|ASV|Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.
1:2|Darby|Grace to you, and peace from God our Father, and [the] Lord  Jesus Christ.
1:2|KJV|Grace be to you and peace from God our Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ.
1:2|WYC|grace to you, and peace of God our Father and of the Lord Jesus Christ.
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願恩典與平安，從神我們的父，並主耶穌基督歸與你們。
1:3|ASV|Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of mercies and God of all comfort;
1:3|Darby|Blessed [be] the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ,  the Father of compassions, and God of all encouragement;
1:3|KJV|Blessed be God, even the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of mercies, and the God of all comfort;
1:3<version name="WYC">Blessed <i>be</i> God and the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, Father of mercies, and God of all comfort,</version>
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們主耶穌基督的神與父，就是那憐恤人的父，和賜諸般安慰的神，是當受頌讚的；
1:4|ASV|who comforteth us in all our affliction, that we may be able to comfort them that are in any affliction, through the comfort wherewith we ourselves are comforted of God.
1:4|Darby|who encourages us in all our tribulation, that we may be  able to encourage those who are in any tribulation whatever,  through the encouragement with which we ourselves are  encouraged of God.
1:4|KJV|Who comforteth us in all our tribulation, that we may be able to comfort them which are in any trouble, by the comfort wherewith we ourselves are comforted of God.
1:4<version name="WYC">which comforteth us in all our tribulation, that also we be able to comfort them, that be in all dis-ease, by the admonishing by which also we be admonished of God [that and we may comfort them, that be in all pressure, <i>or overlaying</i>, by the exhortation, <i>or admonishing</i>, by which and we be admonished of God].</version>
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂在我們一切的患難中安慰我們，叫我們能用自己從神所受的安慰，安慰那些在各樣患難中的人。
1:5|ASV|For as the sufferings of Christ abound unto us, even so our comfort also aboundeth through Christ.
1:5|Darby|Because, even as the sufferings of the Christ abound towards  us, so through the Christ does our encouragement also abound.
1:5|KJV|For as the sufferings of Christ abound in us, so our consolation also aboundeth by Christ.
1:5|WYC|For as the passions of Christ be plenteous in us, so also by Christ our comfort is plenteous.
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為基督的苦難怎樣滿溢到我們身上，照樣我們所受的安慰，也藉著基督而洋溢。
1:6|ASV|But whether we are afflicted, it is for your comfort and salvation; or whether we are comforted, it is for your comfort, which worketh in the patient enduring of the same sufferings which we also suffer:
1:6|Darby|But whether we are in tribulation, [it is] for your  encouragement and salvation, wrought in the endurance of the  same sufferings which *we* also suffer,
1:6|KJV|And whether we be afflicted, it is for your consolation and salvation, which is effectual in the enduring of the same sufferings which we also suffer: or whether we be comforted, it is for your consolation and salvation.
1:6<version name="WYC">And whether we be in tribulation, for your tribulation and health, either we be comforted, for your comfort <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21824a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>, either we be admonished, for your admonishing and health.  Which worketh in you the suffering of the same passions, which also we suffer,</version>
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們或是受患難，是為了你們受安慰，得拯救；或是受安慰，也是為了你們受安慰；這安慰叫你們能忍受我們所受的同樣苦難。
1:7|ASV|and our hope for you is stedfast; knowing that, as ye are partakers of the sufferings, so also are ye of the comfort.
1:7|Darby|(and our hope for you [is] sure;) or whether we are  encouraged, [it is] for your encouragement and salvation:  knowing that as ye are partakers of the sufferings, so also of  the encouragement.
1:7|KJV|And our hope of you is stedfast, knowing, that as ye are partakers of the sufferings, so shall ye be also of the consolation.
1:7|WYC|that our hope be firm for you; witting for as ye be fellows of passions, so ye shall be also of comfort.
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們為你們所存的盼望是確定的，知道你們既是同受苦難，也必照樣同受安慰。
1:8|ASV|For we would not have you ignorant, brethren, concerning our affliction which befell us in Asia, that we were weighed down exceedingly, beyond our power, insomuch that we despaired even of life:
1:8|Darby|For we do not wish you to be ignorant, brethren, as to our  tribulation which happened [to us] in Asia, that we were  excessively pressed beyond [our] power, so as to despair even  of living.
1:8|KJV|For we would not, brethren, have you ignorant of our trouble which came to us in Asia, that we were pressed out of measure, above strength, insomuch that we despaired even of life:
1:8<version name="WYC">For, brethren, we will that ye know of our tribulation, that was done in Asia; for over measure we were grieved over might, so that it distressed us, yea, to live. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21826b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，關於我們在亞西亞所遭遇的患難，我們不願意你們不知道，就是我們被壓太重，力不能勝，甚至連活命的指望都絕了，
1:9|ASV|yea, we ourselves have had the sentence of death within ourselves, that we should not trust in ourselves, but in God who raiseth the dead:
1:9|Darby|But we ourselves had the sentence of death in ourselves,  that we should not have our trust in ourselves, but in God who  raises the dead;
1:9|KJV|But we had the sentence of death in ourselves, that we should not trust in ourselves, but in God which raiseth the dead:
1:9<version name="WYC">But we in us selves had answer of death, that we trust not in us, but in God that raiseth dead men. [But we ourselves in ourselves had answer, <i>or</i> <i>certainty</i>, of death, that we be not trusting in ourselves, but in God that raiseth dead men.]</version>
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|自己裡面也斷定是必死的，叫我們不信靠自己，只信靠那叫死人復活的神；
1:10|ASV|who delivered us out of so great a death, and will deliver: on whom we have set our hope that he will also still deliver us;
1:10|Darby|who has delivered us from so great a death, and does  deliver; in whom we confide that he will also yet deliver;
1:10|KJV|Who delivered us from so great a death, and doth deliver: in whom we trust that he will yet deliver us;
1:10|WYC|Which delivered us, and delivereth from so great perils, into whom we hope, also yet he shall deliver,
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂曾救我們脫離那極大的死亡，並且仍要救我們，我們指望祂將來還要救我們，
1:11|ASV|ye also helping together on our behalf by your supplication; that, for the gift bestowed upon us by means of many, thanks may be given by many persons on our behalf.
1:11|Darby|ye also labouring together by supplication for us that the  gift towards us, through means of many persons, may be the  subject of the thanksgiving of many for us.
1:11|KJV|Ye also helping together by prayer for us, that for the gift bestowed upon us by the means of many persons thanks may be given by many on our behalf.
1:11<version name="WYC">while also ye help in prayer for us [helping and you in prayer for us]; that of the persons of many faces of that giving that is in us, thankings be done for us by many men to God [by many partners, graces, <i>or</i> <i>thanks</i>, be done to God for us].</version>
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只要你們也為著我們以祈求配合幫助，好叫許多人因我們藉著許多人所得的恩賜，為我們獻上感謝。
1:12|ASV|For our glorifying is this, the testimony of our conscience, that in holiness and sincerity of God, not in fleshly wisdom but in the grace of God, we behaved ourselves in the world, and more abundantly to you-ward.
1:12|Darby|For our boasting is this, the testimony of our conscience,  that in simplicity and sincerity before God, (not in fleshly  wisdom but in God's grace,) we have had our conversation in the  world, and more abundantly towards you.
1:12|KJV|For our rejoicing is this, the testimony of our conscience, that in simplicity and godly sincerity, not with fleshly wisdom, but by the grace of God, we have had our conversation in the world, and more abundantly to you-ward.
1:12|WYC|For our glory is this, the witnessing of our conscience, that in simpleness and cleanness of God, and not in fleshly wisdom, but in the grace of God, we lived in this world, but more plenteously to you.
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們所誇的，是我們的良心見證我們憑著神的單純和純誠，在世為人，不靠屬肉體的智慧，乃靠神的恩典，對你們更是這樣。
1:13|ASV|For we write no other things unto you, than what ye read or even acknowledge, and I hope ye will acknowledge unto the end:
1:13|Darby|For we do not write other things to you but what ye well  know and recognise; and I hope that ye will recognise to the  end,
1:13|KJV|For we write none other things unto you, that what ye read or acknowledge; and I trust ye shall acknowledge even to the end;
1:13|WYC|And we write not other things to you, than those that ye have read and know, and I hope that into the end ye shall know,
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們寫給你們的，並不外乎你們所誦讀，甚至所明白的，我也盼望你們能明白到底，
1:14|ASV|as also ye did acknowledge us in part, that we are your glorying, even as ye also are ours, in the day of our Lord Jesus.
1:14|Darby|even as also ye have recognised us in part, that we are  your boast, even as *ye* [are] ours in the day of the Lord  Jesus.
1:14|KJV|As also ye have acknowledged us in part, that we are your rejoicing, even as ye also are our's in the day of the Lord Jesus.
1:14|WYC|as also ye have known us a part [as and ye have known us of part]; for we be your glory, as also ye be ours in the day of our Lord Jesus Christ.
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|正如你們已經有幾分明白我們：我們乃是你們的誇耀，好像在我們主耶穌的日子，你們也是我們的誇耀一樣。
1:15|ASV|And in this confidence I was minded to come first unto you, that ye might have a second benefit;
1:15|Darby|And with this confidence I purposed to come to you  previously, that ye might have a second favour;
1:15|KJV|And in this confidence I was minded to come unto you before, that ye might have a second benefit;
1:15|WYC|And in this trusting I would first come to you, that ye should have the second grace,
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我既然這樣深信，先前就有意到你們那裡去，叫你們得著兩次的恩典，
1:16|ASV|and by you to pass into Macedonia, and again from Macedonia to come unto you, and of you to be set forward on my journey unto Judaea.
1:16|Darby|and to pass through to Macedonia by you, and again from  Macedonia to come to you, and to be set forward by you to  Judaea.
1:16|KJV|And to pass by you into Macedonia, and to come again out of Macedonia unto you, and of you to be brought on my way toward Judaea.
1:16|WYC|and pass by you into Macedonia, and again from Macedonia come to you, and of you be led into Judaea.
1:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|也要從你們那裡經過，往馬其頓去，再從馬其頓回到你們那裡，然後蒙你們送行往猶太去。
1:17|ASV|When I therefore was thus minded, did I show fickleness? or the things that I purpose, do I purpose according to the flesh, that with me there should be the yea yea and the nay nay?
1:17|Darby|Having therefore this purpose, did I then use lightness? Or  what I purpose, do I purpose according to flesh, that there  should be with me yea yea, and nay nay?
1:17|KJV|When I therefore was thus minded, did I use lightness? or the things that I purpose, do I purpose according to the flesh, that with me there should be yea yea, and nay nay?
1:17<version name="WYC">But when I would this thing, whether I used unsteadfastness, either those things that I think, I think after the flesh, that at me be, it is and it is not? <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21835c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup></version>
1:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我有這樣的意思，難道是行事輕浮麼？還是我所定的意是按著肉體定的，以致在我有忽是忽非麼？
1:18|ASV|But as God is faithful, our word toward you is not yea and nay.
1:18|Darby|Now God [is] faithful, that our word to you is not yea and  nay.
1:18|KJV|But as God is true, our word toward you was not yea and nay.
1:18<version name="WYC">But God is true, for our word that was at you, is and is not, is not therein, but is is in it. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21836d" title="See footnote d">d</a>]</sup></version>
1:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但神既是信實的，我們對你們所說的話，就沒有是而又非的，
1:19|ASV|For the Son of God, Jesus Christ, who was preached among you by us, even by me and Silvanus and Timothy, was not yea and nay, but in him is yea.
1:19|Darby|For the Son of God, Jesus Christ, he who has been preached  by us among you (by me and Silvanus and Timotheus), did not  become yea and nay, but yea *is* in him.
1:19|KJV|For the Son of God, Jesus Christ, who was preached among you by us, even by me and Silvanus and Timotheus, was not yea and nay, but in him was yea.
1:19<version name="WYC">For why Jesus Christ, the Son of God, which is preached among you by us, by me, and Silvanus, and Timothy, there was not in him, is and is not, but is was in him <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21837e" title="See footnote e">e</a>]</sup>.</version>
1:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為藉著我和西拉並提摩太，在你們中間所傳神的兒子耶穌基督，並不是是而又非的，在祂只有一是。
1:20|ASV|For how many soever be the promises of God, in him is the yea: wherefore also through him is the Amen, unto the glory of God through us.
1:20|Darby|For whatever promises of God [there are], in him is the  yea, and in him the amen, for glory to God by us.
1:20|KJV|For all the promises of God in him are yea, and in him Amen, unto the glory of God by us.
1:20<version name="WYC">For why how many ever be promises of God, in that is,<i> be fulfilled </i>[Forsooth how many ever be promises of God, in him is, <i>that is, in him they be fulfilled</i>].   And therefore by him we say Amen to God, to our glory.</version>
1:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神的應許，不論有多少，在基督裡都是是的，所以藉著祂，對神也都是阿們的，好叫榮耀藉著我們歸與神。
1:21|ASV|Now he that establisheth us with you in Christ, and anointed us, is God;
1:21|Darby|Now he that establishes us with you in Christ, and has  anointed us, [is] God,
1:21|KJV|Now he which stablisheth us with you in Christ, and hath anointed us, is God;
1:21|WYC|Soothly it is God that confirmeth us with you in Christ, and which anointed us, [The which soothly confirmeth us with you in Christ, and the which God anointed us,]
1:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而那把我們同你們，堅固的聯於基督，並且膏了我們的，就是神；
1:22|ASV|who also sealed us, and gave us the earnest of the Spirit in our hearts.
1:22|Darby|who also has sealed us, and given the earnest of the Spirit  in our hearts.
1:22|KJV|Who hath also sealed us, and given the earnest of the Spirit in our hearts.
1:22|WYC|and which marked us [and that marked us], and gave earnest of the Spirit in our hearts.
1:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂既印了我們，又賜那靈在我們心裡作質。
1:23|ASV|But I call God for a witness upon my soul, that to spare you I forbare to come unto Corinth.
1:23|Darby|But I call God to witness upon my soul that to spare you I  have not yet come to Corinth.
1:23|KJV|Moreover I call God for a record upon my soul, that to spare you I came not as yet unto Corinth.
1:23|WYC|For I call God to witness against my soul [Forsooth I in-call God witness into my soul], that I sparing you came not over to Corinth;
1:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我呼求神給我作見證，我還未往哥林多去，是為要寬容你們。
1:24<version name="ASV">Not that we have lordship over your faith, but are helpers of your joy: for in faith ye stand fast. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:24<version name="Darby">Not that we rule over your faith, but are fellow-workmen of  your joy: for by faith ye stand. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:24<version name="KJV">Not for that we have dominion over your faith, but are helpers of your joy: for by faith ye stand.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:24|WYC|not that we be lords of your faith [not for we be lords of your faith], but we be helpers of your joy; for through belief ye stand.
1:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們並不是作主管轄你們的信心，乃是與你們同工，使你們喜樂，因為你們是憑信而立。
2:1|ASV|But I determined this for myself, that I would not come again to you with sorrow.
2:1|Darby|But I have judged this with myself, not to come back to you  in grief.
2:1|KJV|But I determined this with myself, that I would not come again to you in heaviness.
2:1|WYC|And I ordained this [same] thing at me, that I should not come again in heaviness to you [in sorrow to you].
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但為了我自己，我已經這樣斷定，不再帶著憂愁到你們那裡去。
2:2|ASV|For if I make you sorry, who then is he that maketh me glad but he that is made sorry by me?
2:2|Darby|For if *I* grieve you, who also [is] it that gladdens me, if  not he that is grieved through me?
2:2|KJV|For if I make you sorry, who is he then that maketh me glad, but the same which is made sorry by me?
2:2|WYC|For if I make you sorry, who is he that gladdeth me, but he that is sorrowful of me?
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我若叫你們憂愁，這樣，除了我叫他憂愁的那人以外，誰能叫我快樂？
2:3|ASV|And I wrote this very thing, lest, when I came, I should have sorrow from them of whom I ought to rejoice; having confidence in you all, that my joy is the joy of you all.
2:3|Darby|And I have written this very [letter] [to you], that coming  I may not have grief from those from whom I ought to have joy;  trusting in you all that my joy is [that] of you all.
2:3|KJV|And I wrote this same unto you, lest, when I came, I should have sorrow from them of whom I ought to rejoice; having confidence in you all, that my joy is the joy of you all.
2:3<version name="WYC">And this same thing I wrote to you, that when I come, I have not sorrow on sorrow, of the which it behooved me to have joy.  And I trust in you all, that my joy is of all you <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21845a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>.</version>
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我曾把這事寫給你們，免得我來的時候，那些應該叫我喜樂的人，反倒叫我憂愁；我深信你們眾人，都以我的喜樂為你們眾人的喜樂。
2:4|ASV|For out of much affliction and anguish of heart I wrote unto you with many tears; not that ye should be made sorry, but that ye might know the love that I have more abundantly unto you.
2:4|Darby|For out of much tribulation and distress of heart I wrote to  you, with many tears; not that ye may be grieved, but that ye  may know the love which I have very abundantly towards you.
2:4|KJV|For out of much affliction and anguish of heart I wrote unto you with many tears; not that ye should be grieved, but that ye might know the love which I have more abundantly unto you.
2:4|WYC|For of much tribulation and anguish of heart I wrote to you by many tears, not that ye be sorry, but that ye know what charity I have more plenteously in you.
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我先前由於許多的患難，和心中的困苦，多多的流淚，寫信給你們，不是要叫你們憂愁，乃是要叫你們知道，我對你們的愛是格外充盈的。
2:5|ASV|But if any hath caused sorrow, he hath caused sorrow, not to me, but in part (that I press not too heavily) to you all.
2:5|Darby|But if any one has grieved, he has grieved, not me, but in  part (that I may not overcharge [you]) all of you.
2:5|KJV|But if any have caused grief, he hath not grieved me, but in part: that I may not overcharge you all.
2:5|WYC|For if any man hath made me sorrowful, he hath not made me sorrowful but a part [he hath not made me sorrowful but in part], that I charge not you all.
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只是若有叫人憂愁的，他不是叫我憂愁，乃是有幾分叫你們眾人憂愁。（我說幾分，免得我說得太重。）
2:6|ASV|Sufficient to such a one is this punishment which was inflicted by the many;
2:6|Darby|Sufficient to such a one [is] this rebuke which [has been  inflicted] by the many;
2:6|KJV|Sufficient to such a man is this punishment, which was inflicted of many.
2:6<version name="WYC">This blaming that is made of many, sufficeth to him, that is such one [that is such a manner <i>man</i>];</version>
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣的人，受了多數人的責罰，也就彀了，
2:7|ASV|so that contrariwise ye should rather forgive him and comfort him, lest by any means such a one should be swallowed up with his overmuch sorrow.
2:7|Darby|so that on the contrary ye should rather shew grace and  encourage, lest perhaps such a one should be swallowed up with  excessive grief.
2:7|KJV|So that contrariwise ye ought rather to forgive him, and comfort him, lest perhaps such a one should be swallowed up with overmuch sorrow.
2:7<version name="WYC">so that on the contrary ye rather forgive and comfort, lest peradventure he that is such a manner <i>man</i>, be swallowed up [be sopped up, <i>or despair</i>,] by more great heaviness.</version>
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們倒不如饒恕他，安慰他，免得這樣的人或者憂愁太過，就被吞滅了。
2:8|ASV|Wherefore I beseech you to confirm your love toward him.
2:8|Darby|Wherefore I exhort you to assure him of [your] love.
2:8|KJV|Wherefore I beseech you that ye would confirm your love toward him.
2:8|WYC|For which thing I beseech you, that ye confirm charity into him.
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我勸你們，要向他證實你們的愛。
2:9|ASV|For to this end also did I write, that I might know the proof of you, whether ye are obedient in all things.
2:9|Darby|For to this end also I have written, that I might know, by  putting you to the test, if as to everything ye are obedient.
2:9|KJV|For to this end also did I write, that I might know the proof of you, whether ye be obedient in all things.
2:9|WYC|For why therefore [and] I wrote this, that I know your proof, whether in all things ye be obedient.
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|為此我也曾寫信給你們，要知道你們經過試驗的品德，看你們是否在凡事上都順從。
2:10|ASV|But to whom ye forgive anything, I forgive also: for what I also have forgiven, if I have forgiven anything, for your sakes have I forgiven it in the presence of Christ;
2:10|Darby|But to whom ye forgive anything, *I* also; for I also, what  I have forgiven, if I have forgiven anything, [it is] for your  sakes in [the] person of Christ;
2:10|KJV|To whom ye forgive any thing, I forgive also: for if I forgave any thing, to whom I forgave it, for your sakes forgave I it in the person of Christ;
2:10<version name="WYC">For to whom ye have forgiven any thing, also I have forgiven.  For I, that that I forgave, if I forgave any thing, <i>have forgiven</i> for you in the person of Christ,</version>
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們饒恕誰甚麼，我也饒恕；我若曾有所饒恕，我所已經饒恕的，是在基督的面前，為你們饒恕的；
2:11|ASV|that no advantage may be gained over us by Satan: for we are not ignorant of his devices.
2:11|Darby|that we might not have Satan get an advantage against us,  for we are not ignorant of *his* thoughts.
2:11|KJV|Lest Satan should get an advantage of us: for we are not ignorant of his devices.
2:11|WYC|that we be not deceived of Satan; for we know his thoughts. [that we be not deceived of Satan; soothly we unknow not his thoughts.]
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|免得我們給撒但佔了便宜，因我們並非不曉得他的陰謀。
2:12|ASV|Now when I came to Troas for the gospel of Christ, and when a door was opened unto me in the Lord,
2:12|Darby|Now when I came to Troas for the [publication of the] glad  tidings of the Christ, a door also being opened to me in [the]  Lord,
2:12|KJV|Furthermore, when I came to Troas to preach Christ's gospel, and a door was opened unto me of the Lord,
2:12|WYC|But when I was come to Troas [Forsooth when I had come to Troas] for the gospel of Christ, and a door was opened to me in the Lord,
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|再者，我從前為基督的福音到了特羅亞，藉著主也有門向我開了，
2:13|ASV|I had no relief for my spirit, because I found not Titus my brother: but taking my leave of them, I went forth into Macedonia.
2:13|Darby|I had no rest in my spirit at not finding Titus my brother;  but bidding them adieu, I came away to Macedonia.
2:13|KJV|I had no rest in my spirit, because I found not Titus my brother: but taking my leave of them, I went from thence into Macedonia.
2:13|WYC|I had not rest to my spirit, for I found not my brother Titus, but I said to them farewell, and I passed into Macedonia. [I had not rest in my spirit, for I found not my brother Titus, but I saying to them farewell, passed into Macedonia.]
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時沒有找到我的弟兄提多，我靈裡不安，便辭別那裡的人，往馬其頓去了。
2:14|ASV|But thanks be unto God, who always leadeth us in triumph in Christ, and maketh manifest through us the savor of his knowledge in every place.
2:14|Darby|But thanks [be] to God, who always leads us in triumph in  the Christ, and makes manifest the odour of his knowledge  through us in every place.
2:14|KJV|Now thanks be unto God, which always causeth us to triumph in Christ, and maketh manifest the savour of his knowledge by us in every place.
2:14<version name="WYC">And I do thankings to God, that evermore maketh us to have victory in Christ Jesus, and showeth by us the odour of his knowing in each place; <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21856b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|感謝神，祂常在基督裡，在凱旋的行列中帥領我們，並藉著我們在各處顯揚那因認識基督而有的香氣；
2:15|ASV|For we are a sweet savor of Christ unto God, in them that are saved, and in them that perish;
2:15|Darby|For we are a sweet odour of Christ to God, in the saved and  in those that perish:
2:15|KJV|For we are unto God a sweet savour of Christ, in them that are saved, and in them that perish:
2:15<version name="WYC">for we be the good odour of Christ to God, among these that be made safe, and among these that perish. [for we be the good odour, <i>or savour</i>, of Christ to God, in these that be made safe, and in these that perish.]</version>
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為無論在那些正在得救的人中，或是在那些正在滅亡的人中，我們都是獻給神的基督馨香之氣：
2:16|ASV|to the one a savor from death unto death; to the other a savor from life unto life. And who is sufficient for these things?
2:16|Darby|to the one an odour from death unto death, but to the  others an odour from life unto life; and who [is] sufficient  for these things?
2:16|KJV|To the one we are the savour of death unto death; and to the other the savour of life unto life. And who is sufficient for these things?
2:16<version name="WYC">To others soothly odour of death into death [Soothly to others <i>we be </i>odour of death into death], but to the others <i>we be </i>odour of life into life.  And to these things who <i>is</i> so able?</version>
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在這等人，就是出於死的香氣叫人死；在那等人，就是出於生命的香氣叫人活；對這些事，誰彀資格？
2:17<version name="ASV">For we are not as the many, corrupting the word of God: but as of sincerity, but as of God, in the sight of God, speak we in Christ. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:17<version name="Darby">For we do not, as the many, make a trade of the word of  God; but as of sincerity, but as of God, before God, we speak  in Christ. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:17<version name="KJV">For we are not as many, which corrupt the word of God: but as of sincerity, but as of God, in the sight of God speak we in Christ.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:17|WYC|For we be not as many, that do adultery by the word of God, but we speak of cleanness, as of God, before God in Christ. [Soothly we be not as full many, adulterating the word of God, but of cleanness, but as of God, before God in Christ we speak.]
2:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們不像那許多人，為利混亂神的話，而是出於純誠，出於神，在神面前在基督裡講神的話。
3:1|ASV|Are we beginning again to commend ourselves? or need we, as do some, epistles of commendation to you or from you?
3:1|Darby|Do we begin again to commend ourselves? or do we need, as  some, commendatory letters to you, or [commendatory] from you?
3:1|KJV|Do we begin again to commend ourselves? or need we, as some others, epistles of commendation to you, or letters of commendation from you?
3:1<version name="WYC">Begin we therefore again to praise us selves? or whether we need, as some men, epistles of praising to you, or of you? [Begin we again to commend, <i>or praise</i>, ourselves? or whether we need, as some, praising letters to you, or of you?]</version>
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們豈是又開始推薦自己麼？豈像有些人，需要給你們薦信，或由你們寫薦信麼？
3:2|ASV|Ye are our epistle, written in our hearts, known and read of all men;
3:2|Darby|*Ye* are our letter, written in our hearts, known and read  of all men,
3:2|KJV|Ye are our epistle written in our hearts, known and read of all men:
3:2|WYC|Ye be our epistle, written in our hearts, which is known and read of all men,
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們就是我們的信，寫在我們的心裡，是眾人所認識、所誦讀的，
3:3|ASV|being made manifest that ye are an epistle of Christ, ministered by us, written not with ink, but with the Spirit of the living God; not in tables of stone, but in tables that are hearts of flesh.
3:3|Darby|being manifested to be Christ's epistle ministered by us,  written, not with ink, but [the] Spirit of [the] living God;  not on stone tables, but on fleshy tables of [the] heart.
3:3|KJV|Forasmuch as ye are manifestly declared to be the epistle of Christ ministered by us, written not with ink, but with the Spirit of the living God; not in tables of stone, but in fleshy tables of the heart.
3:3<version name="WYC">and made open [and <i>ye be</i> made open], for ye be the epistle of Christ ministered of us, and written, not with ink, but by the Spirit of the living God; not in stone tables [not in stony tables], but in fleshly tables of heart.</version>
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們顯明是基督的信，由我們供職所寫的，不是用墨，乃是用活神的靈寫的，不是寫在石版上，乃是寫在肉版，就是心上。
3:4|ASV|And such confidence have we through Christ to God-ward:
3:4|Darby|And such confidence have we through the Christ towards God:
3:4|KJV|And such trust have we through Christ to God-ward:
3:4|WYC|For we have such trust by Christ to God;
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們藉著基督，對神有這樣的深信。
3:5|ASV|not that we are sufficient of ourselves, to account anything as from ourselves; but our sufficiency is from God;
3:5|Darby|not that we are competent of ourselves to think anything as  of ourselves, but our competency [is] of God;
3:5|KJV|Not that we are sufficient of ourselves to think any thing as of ourselves; but our sufficiency is of God;
3:5|WYC|not that we be sufficient to think any thing of us[selves], as of us, but our sufficience is of God.
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並不是我們憑自己彀資格將甚麼估計作像是出於我們自己的；我們之所以彀資格，乃是出於神；
3:6|ASV|who also made us sufficient as ministers of a new covenant; not of the letter, but of the spirit: for the letter killeth, but the spirit giveth life.
3:6|Darby|who has also made us competent, [as] ministers of [the] new  covenant; not of letter, but of spirit. For the letter kills,  but the Spirit quickens.
3:6|KJV|Who also hath made us able ministers of the new testament; not of the letter, but of the spirit: for the letter killeth, but the spirit giveth life.
3:6|WYC|Which also made us able ministers of the new testament, not by letter, but by Spirit; for the letter slayeth, but the Spirit quickeneth.
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂使我們彀資格作新約的執事，這些執事不是屬於字句，乃是屬於靈，因為那字句殺死人，那靈卻叫人活。
3:7|ASV|But if the ministration of death, written, and engraven on stones, came with glory, so that the children of Israel could not look stedfastly upon the face of Moses for the glory of his face; which glory was passing away:
3:7|Darby|(But if the ministry of death, in letters, graven in stones,  began with glory, so that the children of Israel could not fix  their eyes on the face of Moses, on account of the glory of his  face, [a glory] which is annulled;
3:7|KJV|But if the ministration of death, written and engraven in stones, was glorious, so that the children of Israel could not stedfastly behold the face of Moses for the glory of his countenance; which glory was to be done away:
3:7<version name="WYC">And if the ministration of death written by letter in stones [formed by letters in stones] was in glory, so that the children of Israel might not behold into the face of Moses, for the glory of his face, which is voided <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21866a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>,</version>
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若那用字刻在石頭上屬死的職事，尚且是帶著榮光立的，以致以色列子孫因摩西面上漸漸廢去的榮光，不能定睛看他的臉，
3:8|ASV|how shall not rather the ministration of the spirit be with glory?
3:8|Darby|how shall not rather the ministry of the Spirit subsist in  glory?
3:8|KJV|How shall not the ministration of the spirit be rather glorious?
3:8|WYC|how shall not the ministration of the Spirit be more in glory?
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|何況那靈的職事，豈不更帶著榮光？
3:9|ASV|For if the ministration of condemnation hath glory, much rather doth the ministration of righteousness exceed in glory.
3:9|Darby|For if the ministry of condemnation [be] glory, much rather  the ministry of righteousness abounds in glory.
3:9|KJV|For if the ministration of condemnation be glory, much more doth the ministration of righteousness exceed in glory.
3:9|WYC|For if the ministration of condemnation was in glory [For why if the ministration of condemnation is in glory], much more the ministration of rightwiseness is plenteous in glory.
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若定罪的職事有榮光，那稱義的職事，就越發充盈著榮光了。
3:10|ASV|For verily that which hath been made glorious hath not been made glorious in this respect, by reason of the glory that surpasseth.
3:10|Darby|For also that [which was] glorified is not glorified in  this respect, on account of the surpassing glory.
3:10|KJV|For even that which was made glorious had no glory in this respect, by reason of the glory that excelleth.
3:10|WYC|For neither that that was clear was glorified in this part for the excellent glory;
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那從前得榮光的，在這一點上，因這超越的榮光，就算不得有榮光；
3:11|ASV|For if that which passeth away was with glory, much more that which remaineth is in glory.
3:11|Darby|For if that annulled [was introduced] with glory, much  rather that which abides [subsists] in glory.
3:11|KJV|For if that which is done away was glorious, much more that which remaineth is glorious.
3:11|WYC|and if that that is voided [for why if that that is voided], was by glory, much more that that dwelleth still is in glory.
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為那漸漸廢去的，如果是經過榮光的，這長存的就更多在榮光裡了。
3:12|ASV|Having therefore such a hope, we use great boldness of speech,
3:12|Darby|Having therefore such hope, we use much boldness:
3:12|KJV|Seeing then that we have such hope, we use great plainness of speech:
3:12|WYC|Therefore we that have such hope, use much trust;
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，我們既有這樣的盼望，就大大放膽，
3:13|ASV|and are not as Moses, who put a veil upon his face, that the children of Israel should not look stedfastly on the end of that which was passing away:
3:13|Darby|and not according as Moses put a veil on his own face, so  that the children of Israel should not fix their eyes on the  end of that annulled.
3:13|KJV|And not as Moses, which put a veil over his face, that the children of Israel could not stedfastly look to the end of that which is abolished:
3:13<version name="WYC">and not as Moses laid a veil on his face [and not as Moses put a veil on his face], that the children of Israel should not behold into his face, which <i>veil</i> is voided.</version>
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不像摩西將帕子蒙在臉上，為要叫以色列子孫，不能定睛看到那漸漸廢去者的結局。
3:14|ASV|but their minds were hardened: for until this very day at the reading of the old covenant the same veil remaineth, it not being revealed to them that it is done away in Christ.
3:14|Darby|But their thoughts have been darkened, for unto this day  the same veil remains in reading the old covenant, unremoved,  which in Christ is annulled.
3:14|KJV|But their minds were blinded: for until this day remaineth the same vail untaken away in the reading of the old testament; which vail is done away in Christ.
3:14|WYC|But the wits of them be astonished; for [till] into this day the same veil in [the] reading of the old testament dwelleth not showed [dwelleth unshowed], for it is voided in Christ,
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但他們的心思剛硬，因為直到今日他們誦讀舊約的時候，同樣的帕子還存留著，他們還未得啟示這帕子在基督裡已經廢去了。
3:15|ASV|But unto this day, whensoever Moses is read, a veil lieth upon their heart.
3:15|Darby|But unto this day, when Moses is read, the veil lies upon  their heart.
3:15|KJV|But even unto this day, when Moses is read, the vail is upon their heart.
3:15|WYC|but [till] into this day, when Moses is read, the veil is put on their hearts [the veil is put upon their hearts].
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|是的，直到今日，每逢誦讀摩西書的時候，帕子還留在他們心上；
3:16|ASV|But whensoever it shall turn to the Lord, the veil is taken away.
3:16|Darby|But when it shall turn to [the] Lord, the veil is taken  away.)
3:16|KJV|Nevertheless when it shall turn to the Lord, the vail shall be taken away.
3:16|WYC|But when Israel shall be converted to God, the veil shall be done away.
3:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但他們的心幾時轉向主，帕子就幾時除去了。
3:17|ASV|Now the Lord is the Spirit: and where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is liberty.
3:17|Darby|Now the Lord is the Spirit, but where the Spirit of [the]  Lord [is, there is] liberty.
3:17|KJV|Now the Lord is that Spirit: and where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is liberty.
3:17<version name="WYC">And the Spirit is the Lord; and where the Spirit of the Lord is, there <i>is</i> freedom. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21876b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
3:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|而且主就是那靈；主的靈在那裡，那裡就有自由。
3:18<version name="ASV">But we all, with unveiled face beholding as in a mirror the glory of the Lord, are transformed into the same image from glory to glory, even as from the Lord the Spirit. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:18<version name="Darby">But *we* all, looking on the glory of the Lord, with  unveiled face, are transformed according to the same image from  glory to glory, even as by [the] Lord [the] Spirit. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:18<version name="KJV">But we all, with open face beholding as in a glass the glory of the Lord, are changed into the same image from glory to glory, even as by the Spirit of the Lord.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:18|WYC|And all we that with open face see the glory of the Lord, be transformed into the same image, from clearness into clearness, as of the Spirit of the Lord. [Forsooth all we with showed face beholding the glory of the Lord, be transformed into the same image, from clearness to clearness, as of the Spirit of the Lord.]
3:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但我們眾人既然以沒有帕子遮蔽的臉，好像鏡子觀看並返照主的榮光，就漸漸變化成為與祂同樣的形像，從榮耀到榮耀，乃是從主靈變化成的。
4:1|ASV|Therefore seeing we have this ministry, even as we obtained mercy, we faint not:
4:1|Darby|Therefore, having this ministry, as we have had mercy shewn  us, we faint not.
4:1|KJV|Therefore seeing we have this ministry, as we have received mercy, we faint not;
4:1<version name="WYC">Therefore we that have this administration [Therefore we having this administration, <i>or office</i>], after this that we have gotten mercy, fail we not,</version>
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此，我們既照所蒙的憐憫，受了這職事，就不喪膽，
4:2|ASV|but we have renounced the hidden things of shame, not walking in craftiness, nor handling the word of God deceitfully; but by the manifestation of the truth commending ourselves to every man's conscience in the sight of God.
4:2|Darby|But we have rejected the hidden things of shame, not walking  in deceit, nor falsifying the word of God, but by manifestation  of the truth commending ourselves to every conscience of men  before God.
4:2|KJV|But have renounced the hidden things of dishonesty, not walking in craftiness, nor handling the word of God deceitfully; but by manifestation of the truth commending ourselves to every man's conscience in the sight of God.
4:2|WYC|but do we away the privy things of shame, not walking in subtle guile, neither doing adultery by the word of God, but in showing of the truth commending us selves to each conscience of men before God. [but do away the privy things of shame, not walking in subtle guile, neither adulterating the word of God, but in showing of the truth commending ourselves to each conscience of men before God.]
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|乃將那些可恥隱密的事棄絕了，不以詭詐行事，也不攙混神的話，只將真理顯揚出來，藉以在神面前將自己薦與各人的良心。
4:3|ASV|And even if our gospel is veiled, it is veiled in them that perish:
4:3|Darby|But if also our gospel is veiled, it is veiled in those that  are lost;
4:3|KJV|But if our gospel be hid, it is hid to them that are lost:
4:3<version name="WYC">For if also our gospel is covered, <i>or hid</i>, in these that perish it is covered;</version>
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|如果我們的福音真的受蒙蔽，也是蒙蔽在滅亡的人身上；
4:4|ASV|in whom the god of this world hath blinded the minds of the unbelieving, that the light of the gospel of the glory of Christ, who is the image of God, should not dawn upon them.
4:4|Darby|in whom the god of this world has blinded the thoughts of  the unbelieving, so that the radiancy of the glad tidings of  the glory of the Christ, who is [the] image of God, should not  shine forth [for them].
4:4|KJV|In whom the god of this world hath blinded the minds of them which believe not, lest the light of the glorious gospel of Christ, who is the image of God, should shine unto them.
4:4<version name="WYC">in which [the] god of this world, <i>that is, the devil</i>, hath blinded the souls of unfaithful men, that the lightening of the gospel of the glory of Christ, which is the image of God, shine not. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21881a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在他們裡面，這世代的神弄瞎了他們這不信者的心思，叫基督榮耀之福音的光照，不照亮他們；基督本是神的像。
4:5|ASV|For we preach not ourselves, but Christ Jesus as Lord, and ourselves as your servants for Jesus' sake.
4:5|Darby|For we do not preach ourselves, but Christ Jesus Lord, and  ourselves your bondmen for Jesus' sake.
4:5|KJV|For we preach not ourselves, but Christ Jesus the Lord; and ourselves your servants for Jesus' sake.
4:5|WYC|But we preach not us selves, but our Lord Jesus Christ [Soothly we preach not ourselves, but Jesus Christ our Lord]; and us your servants by Jesus.
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們不是傳自己，乃是傳基督耶穌為主，也傳自己為耶穌的緣故，作你們的奴僕。
4:6|ASV|Seeing it is God, that said, Light shall shine out of darkness, who shined in our hearts, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ.
4:6|Darby|Because [it is] the God who spoke that out of darkness light  should shine who has shone in our hearts for the shining forth  of the knowledge of the glory of God in [the] face of [Jesus]  Christ.
4:6|KJV|For God, who commanded the light to shine out of darkness, hath shined in our hearts, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ.
4:6|WYC|For God, that said [the] light to shine of darknesses, he hath given light in our hearts, to the lightening of the science of the clearness of God [he hath enlightened in our hearts, to the illumining of the science of the clearness of God], in the face of Jesus Christ.
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為那說光要從黑暗裡照出來的神，已經照在我們心裡，為著光照人，使人認識那顯在耶穌基督面上之神的榮耀。
4:7|ASV|But we have this treasure in earthen vessels, that the exceeding greatness of the power may be of God, and not from ourselves;
4:7|Darby|But we have this treasure in earthen vessels, that the  surpassingness of the power may be of God, and not from us:
4:7|KJV|But we have this treasure in earthen vessels, that the excellency of the power may be of God, and not of us.
4:7|WYC|And we have this treasure in brittle vessels, that the worthiness be of God's virtue [that the highness be of God's virtue], and not of us.
4:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但我們有這寶貝在瓦器裡，要顯明這超越的能力，是屬於神，不是出於我們；
4:8|ASV|we are pressed on every side, yet not straitened; perplexed, yet not unto despair;
4:8|Darby|every way afflicted, but not straitened; seeing no apparent  issue, but our way not entirely shut up;
4:8|KJV|We are troubled on every side, yet not distressed; we are perplexed, but not in despair;
4:8<version name="WYC">In all things we suffer tribulation, but we be not anguished, <i>or distressed</i>; we be made poor, but we lack nothing; <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21885b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
4:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們四面受壓，卻不被困住；出路絕了，卻非絕無出路；
4:9|ASV|pursued, yet not forsaken; smitten down, yet not destroyed;
4:9|Darby|persecuted, but not abandoned; cast down, but not destroyed;
4:9|KJV|Persecuted, but not forsaken; cast down, but not destroyed;
4:9|WYC|we suffer persecution, but we be not forsaken; we be made low, but we be not confounded; we be cast down, but we perish not.
4:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|遭逼迫，卻不被撇棄；打倒了，卻不至滅亡；
4:10|ASV|always bearing about in the body the dying of Jesus, that the life also of Jesus may be manifested in our body.
4:10|Darby|always bearing about in the body the dying of Jesus, that  the life also of Jesus may be manifested in our body;
4:10|KJV|Always bearing about in the body the dying of the Lord Jesus, that the life also of Jesus might be made manifest in our body.
4:10|WYC|And evermore we bear about the slaying of Jesus in our body [Evermore bearing about the mortifying of Jesus Christ in our body], that also the life of Jesus be showed in our bodies.
4:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|身體上常帶著耶穌的治死，使耶穌的生命也顯明在我們的身體上。
4:11|ASV|For we who live are always delivered unto death for Jesus' sake, that the life also of Jesus may be manifested in our mortal flesh.
4:11|Darby|for we who live are always delivered unto death on account  of Jesus, that the life also of Jesus may be manifested in our  mortal flesh;
4:11|KJV|For we which live are always delivered unto death for Jesus' sake, that the life also of Jesus might be made manifest in our mortal flesh.
4:11|WYC|For evermore we that live, be taken into death for Jesus, that [and] the life of Jesus be showed in our deadly flesh.
4:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們這活著的人，是常為耶穌被交於死，使耶穌的生命，也在我們這必死的肉身上顯明出來。
4:12|ASV|So then death worketh in us, but life in you.
4:12|Darby|so that death works in us, but life in you.
4:12|KJV|So then death worketh in us, but life in you.
4:12|WYC|Therefore death worketh in us, but life in you.
4:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，死是在我們身上發動，生命卻在你們身上發動。
4:13|ASV|But having the same spirit of faith, according to that which is written, I believed, and therefore did I speak; we also believe, and therefore also we speak;
4:13|Darby|And having the same spirit of faith, according to what is  written, I have believed, therefore have I spoken; *we* also  believe, therefore also we speak;
4:13|KJV|We having the same spirit of faith, according as it is written, I believed, and therefore have I spoken; we also believe, and therefore speak;
4:13|WYC|And we have the same spirit of faith [Forsooth having the same spirit of faith], as it is written, I have believed, wherefore I have spoken; and we believe, wherefore also we speak;
4:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且照經上所記：“我信，所以我說話；”我們既有這同樣信心的靈，也就信，所以也就說話，
4:14|ASV|knowing that he that raised up the Lord Jesus shall raise up us also with Jesus, and shall present us with you.
4:14|Darby|knowing that he who has raised the Lord Jesus shall raise  us also with Jesus, and shall present [us] with you.
4:14|KJV|Knowing that he which raised up the Lord Jesus shall raise up us also by Jesus, and shall present us with you.
4:14|WYC|witting that he that raised Jesus, shall raise up also us with Jesus, and shall ordain [us] with you.
4:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|知道那叫主耶穌復活的，也必叫我們與耶穌一同復活，並且叫我們與你們一同站在祂面前。
4:15|ASV|For all things are for your sakes, that the grace, being multiplied through the many, may cause the thanksgiving to abound unto the glory of God.
4:15|Darby|For all things [are] for your sakes, that the grace  abounding through the many may cause thanksgiving to abound to  the glory of God.
4:15|KJV|For all things are for your sakes, that the abundant grace might through the thanksgiving of many redound to the glory of God.
4:15<version name="WYC">And all things [<i>be done</i>] for you, that a plenteous grace by many thankings be plenteous into the glory of God. [Soothly all things <i>be done</i> for you, that grace being plenteous by many in doing of thanks be plenteous into glory of God.]</version>
4:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為凡事都是為你們，好叫恩典藉著更多的人而增多，使感謝洋溢，以致榮耀歸與神。
4:16|ASV|Wherefore we faint not; but though our outward man is decaying, yet our inward man is renewed day by day.
4:16|Darby|Wherefore we faint not; but if indeed our outward man is  consumed, yet the inward is renewed day by day.
4:16|KJV|For which cause we faint not; but though our outward man perish, yet the inward man is renewed day by day.
4:16|WYC|For which thing we fail not, for though [but though] our outer man be corrupted; nevertheless the inner man is renewed from day to day.
4:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我們不喪膽，反而我們外面的人雖然在毀壞，我們裡面的人卻日日在更新。
4:17|ASV|For our light affliction, which is for the moment, worketh for us more and more exceedingly an eternal weight of glory;
4:17|Darby|For our momentary [and] light affliction works for us in  surpassing measure an eternal weight of glory;
4:17|KJV|For our light affliction, which is but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory;
4:17<version name="WYC">But that light thing [light,<i> or easy</i>, thing] of our tribulation that lasteth now, but as it were by a moment, worketh in us over measure an everlasting burden into the highness of glory [worketh over manner, <i>or</i> <i>measure</i>, into highness the everlasting weight of glory in us];</version>
4:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們這短暫輕微的苦楚，要極盡超越的為我們成就永遠重大的榮耀。
4:18<version name="ASV">while we look not at the things which are seen, but at the things which are not seen: for the things which are seen are temporal; but the things which are not seen are eternal. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:18<version name="Darby">while we look not at the things that are seen, but at the  things that are not seen; for the things that are seen [are]  for a time, but those that are not seen eternal. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:18<version name="KJV">While we look not at the things which are seen, but at the things which are not seen: for the things which are seen are temporal; but the things which are not seen are eternal.</p><p /><br /></version>
4:18<version name="WYC">while that we behold not those things that be seen, but those [<i>things</i>] that be not seen.  For those things that be seen, be but during for a short time; but those things that be not seen, be everlasting <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21895c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup>.</version>
4:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們原不是顧念所見的，乃是顧念所不見的，因為所見的是暫時的，所不見的纔是永遠的。
5:1|ASV|For we know that if the earthly house of our tabernacle be dissolved, we have a building from God, a house not made with hands, eternal, in the heavens.
5:1|Darby|For we know that if our earthly tabernacle house be  destroyed, we have a building from God, a house not made with  hands, eternal in the heavens.
5:1|KJV|For we know that if our earthly house of this tabernacle were dissolved, we have a building of God, an house not made with hands, eternal in the heavens.
5:1|WYC|And we know, that if our earthly house of this dwelling be dissolved, that we have a building of God, an house not made with hands, everlasting in heavens.
5:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們知道，我們這地上的帳幕房屋若拆毀了，必得著從神來的房舍，非人手所造，在諸天之上永遠的房屋。
5:2|ASV|For verily in this we groan, longing to be clothed upon with our habitation which is from heaven:
5:2|Darby|For indeed in this we groan, ardently desiring to have put  on our house which [is] from heaven;
5:2|KJV|For in this we groan, earnestly desiring to be clothed upon with our house which is from heaven:
5:2|WYC|For why in this thing we mourn, coveting to be clothed above with our dwelling, which is of heaven;
5:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|原來我們確是在這帳幕裡歎息，深想穿上我們從天上來的住處；
5:3|ASV|if so be that being clothed we shall not be found naked.
5:3|Darby|if indeed being also clothed we shall not be found naked.
5:3|KJV|If so be that being clothed we shall not be found naked.
5:3|WYC|if nevertheless we be found clothed, and not naked.
5:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若真的穿上，就不至於顯為赤身了。
5:4|ASV|For indeed we that are in this tabernacle do groan, being burdened; not for that we would be unclothed, but that we would be clothed upon, that what is mortal may be swallowed up of life.
5:4|Darby|For indeed we who are in the tabernacle groan, being  burdened; while yet we do not wish to be unclothed, but  clothed, that [what is] mortal may be swallowed up by life.
5:4|KJV|For we that are in this tabernacle do groan, being burdened: not for that we would be unclothed, but clothed upon, that mortality might be swallowed up of life.
5:4<version name="WYC">For why we that be in this tabernacle, sorrow within, and be heavied [grieved], for that we will not be spoiled, but be clothed above; that that thing that is deadly, be swallowed up of life <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21899a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>.</version>
5:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們在這帳幕裡的人，負重歎息，是因不願脫下這個，乃願穿上那個，好叫這必死的被生命吞滅了。
5:5|ASV|Now he that wrought us for this very thing is God, who gave unto us the earnest of the Spirit.
5:5|Darby|Now he that has wrought us for this very thing [is] God, who  also has given to us the earnest of the Spirit.
5:5|KJV|Now he that hath wrought us for the selfsame thing is God, who also hath given unto us the earnest of the Spirit.
5:5<version name="WYC">But who is it that maketh us into this same thing?  God, that gave to us the earnest of the Spirit. [Forsooth he that maketh us into this same thing, <i>is</i> God, that gave to us the earnest of Spirit.]</version>
5:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那為這事培植我們的乃是神，祂已將那靈賜給我們作質。
5:6|ASV|Being therefore always of good courage, and knowing that, whilst we are at home in the body, we are absent from the Lord
5:6|Darby|Therefore [we are] always confident, and know that while  present in the body we are absent from the Lord,
5:6|KJV|Therefore we are always confident, knowing that, whilst we are at home in the body, we are absent from the Lord:
5:6<version name="WYC">Therefore we be hardy always, and know that the while we be in this body, we go in pilgrimage from the Lord; <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21901b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
5:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我們常是放心振作，並且曉得我們居家在身內，便是離家與主分開；
5:7|ASV|(for we walk by faith, not by sight);
5:7|Darby|(for we walk by faith, not by sight;)
5:7|KJV|(For we walk by faith, not by sight:)
5:7|WYC|for we walk by faith, and not by clear sight.
5:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|（因我們行事為人，是憑著信心，不是憑著眼見；）
5:8|ASV|we are of good courage, I say, and are willing rather to be absent from the body, and to be at home with the Lord.
5:8|Darby|we are confident, I say, and pleased rather to be absent  from the body and present with the Lord.
5:8|KJV|We are confident, I say, and willing rather to be absent from the body, and to be present with the Lord.
5:8|WYC|But we be hardy [Forsooth we be hardy], and have good will, more to be in pilgrimage from the body, and to be present to God.
5:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|是的，我們是放心振作，寧願離家出到身外，與主同在家中。
5:9|ASV|Wherefore also we make it our aim, whether at home or absent, to be well-pleasing unto him.
5:9|Darby|Wherefore also we are zealous, whether present or absent, to  be agreeable to him.
5:9|KJV|Wherefore we labour, that, whether present or absent, we may be accepted of him.
5:9|WYC|And therefore we strive, whether absent, whether present, to please him.
5:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我們也懷著雄心大志，無論是在家，或是離家，都要討主的喜悅。
5:10|ASV|For we must all be made manifest before the judgment-seat of Christ; that each one may receive the things done in the body, according to what he hath done, whether it be good or bad.
5:10|Darby|For we must all be manifested before the judgment-seat of  the Christ, that each may receive the things [done] in the  body, according to those he has done, whether [it be] good or  evil.
5:10|KJV|For we must all appear before the judgment seat of Christ; that every one may receive the things done in his body, according to that he hath done, whether it be good or bad.
5:10<version name="WYC">For it behooveth us all to be showed before the throne of Christ, that every man tell the proper things of the body <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21905c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup>, as he hath done, either good, either evil.</version>
5:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們眾人，必要在基督的審判臺前顯露出來，叫各人按著本身所行的，或善或惡，受到應得的報應。
5:11|ASV|Knowing therefore the fear of the Lord, we persuade men, but we are made manifest unto God; and I hope that we are made manifest also in your consciences.
5:11|Darby|Knowing therefore the terror of the Lord we persuade men,  but have been manifested to God, and I hope also that we have  been manifested in your consciences.
5:11|KJV|Knowing therefore the terror of the Lord, we persuade men; but we are made manifest unto God; and I trust also are made manifest in your consciences.
5:11|WYC|Therefore we witting the dread of the Lord, counsel men, for to God we be open; and I hope, that we be open also in your consciences.
5:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我們既曉得主的可畏，就勸服人，但我們向神是顯明的，只是我盼望在你們的良心裡，也是顯明的。
5:12|ASV|We are not again commending ourselves unto you, but speak as giving you occasion of glorying on our behalf, that ye may have wherewith to answer them that glory in appearance, and not in heart.
5:12|Darby|[For] we do not again commend ourselves to you, but [we  are] giving to you occasion of boast in our behalf, that ye may  have [such] with those boasting in countenance, and not in  heart.
5:12|KJV|For we commend not ourselves again unto you, but give you occasion to glory on our behalf, that ye may have somewhat to answer them which glory in appearance, and not in heart.
5:12<version name="WYC">We commend not us selves again to you, but we give to you occasion to have glory for us [We commend not ourselves again to you, but we give to you occasion to glory for us], that ye have [<i>understanding</i>] to them that glory in the face, and not in the heart.</version>
5:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們不是再向你們推薦自己，乃是給你們一個為我們誇耀的機會，好叫你們對那憑外貌不憑內心誇口的人，有可應對的。
5:13|ASV|For whether we are beside ourselves, it is unto God; or whether we are of sober mind, it is unto you.
5:13|Darby|For whether we are beside ourselves, [it is] to God; or are  sober, [it is] for you.
5:13|KJV|For whether we be beside ourselves, it is to God: or whether we be sober, it is for your cause.
5:13<version name="WYC">For either we by mind pass to God, either we be sober to you. [Soothly whether we by mind, <i>or reason</i>, pass <i>it is</i> to God, whether we be sober <i>it is</i> to you?]</version>
5:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因我們或是癲狂，乃是向著神；或是謹守，乃是為著你們。
5:14|ASV|For the love of Christ constraineth us; because we thus judge, that one died for all, therefore all died;
5:14|Darby|For the love of the Christ constrains us, having judged  this: that one died for all, then all have died;
5:14|KJV|For the love of Christ constraineth us; because we thus judge, that if one died for all, then were all dead:
5:14<version name="WYC">For the charity of Christ driveth us; guessing this thing [guessing,<i> or deeming</i>, this thing], that if one died for all, then all were dead.</version>
5:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|原來基督的愛困迫我們，因我們斷定：一人既替眾人死，眾人就都死了；
5:15|ASV|and he died for all, that they that live should no longer live unto themselves, but unto him who for their sakes died and rose again.
5:15|Darby|and he died for all, that they who live should no longer  live to themselves, but to him who died for them and has been  raised.
5:15|KJV|And that he died for all, that they which live should not henceforth live unto themselves, but unto him which died for them, and rose again.
5:15|WYC|And Christ died for all, that they that live, live not now to themselves, but to him that died for them, and rose again.
5:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且祂替眾人死，是叫那些活著的人，不再向自己活，乃向那替他們死而復活者活。
5:16|ASV|Wherefore we henceforth know no man after the flesh: even though we have known Christ after the flesh, yet now we know him so no more.
5:16|Darby|So that *we* henceforth know no one according to flesh; but  if even we have known Christ according to flesh, yet now we  know [him thus] no longer.
5:16|KJV|Wherefore henceforth know we no man after the flesh: yea, though we have known Christ after the flesh, yet now henceforth know we him no more.
5:16|WYC|Therefore we from this time know no man after the flesh; though we (have) known Christ after the flesh [And so we from this time have known no man after the flesh; and if we knew Christ after the flesh], but [right] now we know not.
5:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我們從今以後，不按著肉體認人了；雖然按著肉體認過基督，如今卻不再這樣認祂了。
5:17|ASV|Wherefore if any man is in Christ, he is a new creature: the old things are passed away; behold, they are become new.
5:17|Darby|So if any one [be] in Christ, [there is] a new creation;  the old things have passed away; behold all things have become  new:
5:17|KJV|Therefore if any man be in Christ, he is a new creature: old things are passed away; behold, all things are become new.
5:17|WYC|Therefore if any new creature is in Christ, the old things be passed [old things have passed].  Lo! all things be made new,
5:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此，若有人在基督裡，他就是新造；舊事已過，看哪，都變成新的了。
5:18|ASV|But all things are of God, who reconciled us to himself through Christ, and gave unto us the ministry of reconciliation;
5:18|Darby|and all things [are] of the God who has reconciled us to  himself by [Jesus] Christ, and given to us the ministry of that  reconciliation:
5:18|KJV|And all things are of God, who hath reconciled us to himself by Jesus Christ, and hath given to us the ministry of reconciliation;
5:18<version name="WYC">and all things be of God, which reconciled us to him by Christ, and gave to us the service of reconciling [and gave to us the ministry, <i>or service</i>, of reconciling].</version>
5:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|一切都是出於神，祂藉著基督使我們與祂自己和好，又將這和好的職事賜給我們；
5:19|ASV|to wit, that God was in Christ reconciling the world unto himself, not reckoning unto them their trespasses, and having committed unto us the word of reconciliation.
5:19|Darby|how that God was in Christ, reconciling the world to  himself, not reckoning to them their offences; and putting in  us the word of that reconciliation.
5:19|KJV|To wit, that God was in Christ, reconciling the world unto himself, not imputing their trespasses unto them; and hath committed unto us the word of reconciliation.
5:19|WYC|And God was in Christ [Soothly, for God was in Christ], reconciling to him the world, not reckoning to them their guilts, and putted in us the word of reconciling [and put in us the word of reconciling].
5:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這就是神在基督裡，叫世人與祂自己和好，不將他們的過犯算給他們，且將這和好的話語託付了我們。
5:20|ASV|We are ambassadors therefore on behalf of Christ, as though God were entreating by us: we beseech you on behalf of Christ, be ye reconciled to God.
5:20|Darby|We are ambassadors therefore for Christ, God as [it were]  beseeching by us, we entreat for Christ, Be reconciled to God.
5:20|KJV|Now then we are ambassadors for Christ, as though God did beseech you by us: we pray you in Christ's stead, be ye reconciled to God.
5:20<version name="WYC">Therefore we use message for Christ [Therefore we be set in legacy, <i>or message</i>, for Christ], as if God admonisheth by us; we beseech you for Christ, be ye reconciled to God.</version>
5:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我們為基督作了大使，就好像神藉我們勸你們一樣；我們替基督求你們：要與神和好。
5:21<version name="ASV">Him who knew no sin he made to be sin on our behalf; that we might become the righteousness of God in him. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:21<version name="Darby">Him who knew not sin he has made sin for us, that *we*  might become God's righteousness in him. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:21<version name="KJV">For he hath made him to be sin for us, who knew no sin; that we might be made the righteousness of God in him.</p><p /><br /></version>
5:21|WYC|God the Father made him sin for us, which knew not sin, that we should be made [the] rightwiseness of God in him.
5:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神使那不知罪的，替我們成為罪，好叫我們在祂裡面成為神的義。
6:1|ASV|And working together with him we entreat also that ye receive not the grace of God in vain
6:1|Darby|But [as] fellow-workmen, we also beseech that ye receive not  the grace of God in vain:
6:1|KJV|We then, as workers together with him, beseech you also that ye receive not the grace of God in vain.
6:1<version name="WYC">But we helping [<i>you in work and word</i>] admonish [you], that ye receive not the grace of God in vain.</version>
6:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|而且我們既與神同工，也就勸你們不可徒受祂的恩典，
6:2|ASV|(for he saith, At an acceptable time I hearkened unto thee, And in a day of salvation did I succor thee: behold, now is the acceptable time; behold, now is the day of salvation):
6:2|Darby|(for he says, I have listened to thee in an accepted time,  and I have helped thee in a day of salvation: behold, now [is  the] well-accepted time; behold, now [the] day of salvation:)
6:2|KJV|(For he saith, I have heard thee in a time accepted, and in the day of salvation have I succoured thee: behold, now is the accepted time; behold, now is the day of salvation.)
6:2<version name="WYC">For he saith, In time well pleasing I have heard thee [In time accepted, <i>or well pleasing</i>, I have heard thee], and in the day of health I have helped thee.  Lo! now a time acceptable, lo! now a day of health.</version>
6:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為祂說，“在悅納的時候，我應允了你；在拯救的日子，我濟助了你。”看哪，現在正是最可蒙悅納的時候；看哪，現在正是拯救的日子。
6:3|ASV|giving no occasion of stumbling in anything, that our ministration be not blamed;
6:3|Darby|giving no manner of offence in anything, that the ministry  be not blamed;
6:3|KJV|Giving no offence in any thing, that the ministry be not blamed:
6:3<version name="WYC">Give we to no man any offence, that our service be not reproved; [To no man giving any offence, <i>or</i> <i>hurting</i>, that our ministry, <i>or service</i>, be not reproved;]</version>
6:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們凡事都不使人絆跌，免得這職事被人挑剔，
6:4|ASV|but in everything commending ourselves, as ministers of God, in much patience, in afflictions, in necessities, in distresses,
6:4|Darby|but in everything commending ourselves as God's ministers,  in much endurance, in afflictions, in necessities, in straits,
6:4|KJV|But in all things approving ourselves as the ministers of God, in much patience, in afflictions, in necessities, in distresses,
6:4|WYC|but in all things give we us selves [but in all things give we ourselves] as the ministers of God, in much patience, in tribulations, in needs, in anguishes,
6:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|反倒在各樣的事上，在多方的忍耐上、在患難上、在貧困上、在困苦上、
6:5|ASV|in stripes, in imprisonments, in tumults, in labors, in watchings, in fastings;
6:5|Darby|in stripes, in prisons, in riots, in labours, in watchings,  in fastings,
6:5|KJV|In stripes, in imprisonments, in tumults, in labours, in watchings, in fastings;
6:5|WYC|in beatings [in scourgings], in prisons, in dissensions within, in travails, in wakings, in fastings,
6:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在鞭打上、在監禁上、在擾亂上、在勞苦上、在不睡上、在不食上，
6:6|ASV|in pureness, in knowledge, in long suffering, in kindness, in the Holy Spirit, in love unfeigned,
6:6|Darby|in pureness, in knowledge, in longsuffering, in kindness, in  [the] Holy Spirit, in love unfeigned,
6:6|KJV|By pureness, by knowledge, by long suffering, by kindness, by the Holy Ghost, by love unfeigned,
6:6<version name="WYC">in chastity, in knowing [in science, <i>or knowing</i>], in long abiding, in sweetness, in the Holy Ghost, in charity not feigned,</version>
6:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以純潔、以知識、以恆忍、以恩慈、以聖別的靈、以無偽的愛、
6:7|ASV|in the word of truth, in the power of God; by the armor of righteousness on the right hand and on the left,
6:7|Darby|in [the] word of truth, in [the] power of God; through the  arms of righteousness on the right hand and left,
6:7|KJV|By the word of truth, by the power of God, by the armour of righteousness on the right hand and on the left,
6:7|WYC|in the word of truth, in the virtue of God; by armours of rightwiseness on the right half and on the left half;
6:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以真實的話、以神的大能，藉著在右在左義的兵器，
6:8|ASV|by glory and dishonor, by evil report and good report; as deceivers, and yet true;
6:8|Darby|through glory and dishonour, through evil report and good  report: as deceivers, and true;
6:8|KJV|By honour and dishonour, by evil report and good report: as deceivers, and yet true;
6:8|WYC|by glory and unnobleness [by glory and unnobility]; by evil fame and good fame; as deceivers, and true men;
6:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|藉著榮耀和羞辱，藉著惡名和美名，證薦自己是神的執事；似乎是迷惑人的，卻是真誠的；
6:9|ASV|as unknown, and yet well known; as dying, and behold, we live; as chastened, and not killed;
6:9|Darby|as unknown, and well known; as dying, and behold, we live;  as disciplined, and not put to death;
6:9|KJV|As unknown, and yet well known; as dying, and, behold, we live; as chastened, and not killed;
6:9|WYC|as they that be unknown and known; as men dying, and lo! we live; as chastised, and not made dead;
6:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|似乎不為人所知，卻是人所共知的；似乎在死，看哪，我們卻活著；似乎受管教，卻不被治死；
6:10|ASV|as sorrowful, yet always rejoicing; as poor, yet making many rich; as having nothing, and yet possessing all things.
6:10|Darby|as grieved, but always rejoicing; as poor, but enriching  many; as having nothing, and possessing all things.
6:10|KJV|As sorrowful, yet alway rejoicing; as poor, yet making many rich; as having nothing, and yet possessing all things.
6:10|WYC|as sorrowful, and evermore joying; as having need, but making many men rich [as sorrowful, but evermore joying; as needy men, soothly making many rich]; as nothing having, and wielding all things.
6:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|似乎憂愁，卻常常喜樂；似乎貧窮，卻叫許多人富足；似乎一無所有，卻擁有萬有。
6:11|ASV|Our mouth is open unto you, O Corinthians, our heart is enlarged.
6:11|Darby|Our mouth is opened to you, Corinthians, our heart is  expanded.
6:11|KJV|O ye Corinthians, our mouth is open unto you, our heart is enlarged.
6:11|WYC|A! ye Corinthians [O! ye Corinthians], our mouth is open to you, our heart is alarged;
6:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哥林多人哪，我們的口向你們是張開的，我們的心是寬宏的；
6:12|ASV|Ye are not straitened in us, but ye are straitened in your own affections.
6:12|Darby|Ye are not straitened in us, but ye are straitened in your  affections;
6:12|KJV|Ye are not straitened in us, but ye are straitened in your own bowels.
6:12<version name="WYC">ye be not anguished in us, but ye be anguished in your inwardnesses. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21928a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
6:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在我們裡面，你們並不受限制，你們乃是限制在自己的心腸裡。
6:13|ASV|Now for a recompense in like kind (I speak as unto my children), be ye also enlarged.
6:13|Darby|but for an answering recompense, (I speak as to children,)  let *your* heart also expand itself.
6:13|KJV|Now for a recompence in the same, (I speak as unto my children,) be ye also enlarged.
6:13|WYC|And I say as to sons, ye that have the same reward, be ye alarged. [Forsooth, we having the same reward, I say as to sons, and be ye alarged.]
6:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但你們也要寬宏，作同樣的報答，我像對孩子說的。
6:14|ASV|Be not unequally yoked with unbelievers: for what fellowship have righteousness and iniquity? or what communion hath light with darkness?
6:14|Darby|Be not diversely yoked with unbelievers; for what  participation [is there] between righteousness and lawlessness?  or what fellowship of light with darkness?
6:14|KJV|Be ye not unequally yoked together with unbelievers: for what fellowship hath righteousness with unrighteousness? and what communion hath light with darkness?
6:14<version name="WYC">Do not ye bear the yoke with unfaithful men.  For what parting of rightwiseness with wickedness [Soothly what parting, <i>or communing</i>, of rightwiseness with wickedness]? or what fellowship of light to darknesses?</version>
6:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們跟不信的，不要不配的同負一軛，因為義和不法有甚麼合夥？光對黑暗有甚麼交通？
6:15|ASV|And what concord hath Christ with Belial? or what portion hath a believer with an unbeliever?
6:15|Darby|and what consent of Christ with Beliar, or what part for a  believer along with an unbeliever?
6:15|KJV|And what concord hath Christ with Belial? or what part hath he that believeth with an infidel?
6:15<version name="WYC">and what according of Christ to Belial? or what part of a faithful [<i>man</i>] with the unfaithful [<i>or heathen</i>]?</version>
6:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|基督對彼列有甚麼和諧？信的同不信的有甚麼同分？
6:16|ASV|And what agreement hath a temple of God with idols? for we are a temple of the living God; even as God said, I will dwell in them, and walk in them; and I will be their God, and they shall be my people.
6:16|Darby|and what agreement of God's temple with idols? for *ye* are  [the] living God's temple; according as God has said, I will  dwell among them, and walk among [them]; and I will be their  God, and they shall be to me a people.
6:16|KJV|And what agreement hath the temple of God with idols? for ye are the temple of the living God; as God hath said, I will dwell in them, and walk in them; and I will be their God, and they shall be my people.
6:16|WYC|and what consent to the temple of God with maumets?  And ye be the temple of the living God, as the Lord saith, For I shall dwell in them, and I shall walk among them; and I shall be [the] God of them, and they shall be a people to me. [but what consent to the temple of God with idols?  Forsooth ye be the temple of quick God, as the Lord saith, For I shall dwell in them, and I shall walk in; and I shall be the God of them, and they shall be to me a people.]
6:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神的殿同偶像有甚麼一致？因為我們是活神的殿，就如神曾說，“我要在他們中間居住，在他們中間行走；我要作他們的神，他們要作我的子民。”
6:17|ASV|Wherefore Come ye out from among them, and be ye separate, saith the Lord, And touch no unclean thing; And I will receive you,
6:17|Darby|Wherefore come out from the midst of them, and be  separated, saith [the] Lord, and touch not [what is] unclean,  and *I* will receive you;
6:17|KJV|Wherefore come out from among them, and be ye separate, saith the Lord, and touch not the unclean thing; and I will receive you.
6:17|WYC|For which thing go ye out of the middle of them, and be ye separated [and be ye parted], saith the Lord, and touch not unclean thing; and I shall receive you,
6:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，“主說，你們務要從他們中間出來，得以分別，不要沾不潔之物，我就收納你們。”
6:18<version name="ASV">And will be to you a Father, And ye shall be to me sons and daughters, saith the Lord Almighty. </p><p /><br /></version>
6:18<version name="Darby">and I will be to you for a Father, and ye shall be to me  for sons and daughters, saith [the] Lord Almighty. </p><p /><br /></version>
6:18<version name="KJV">And will be a Father unto you, and ye shall be my sons and daughters, saith the Lord Almighty.</p><p /><br /></version>
6:18|WYC|and I shall be to you into a Father, and ye shall be to me into sons and daughters, saith the Lord almighty.
6:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|“我要作你們的父，你們要作我的兒子和女兒。這是全能的主說的。”
7:1|ASV|Having therefore these promises, beloved, let us cleanse ourselves from all defilement of flesh and spirit, perfecting holiness in the fear of God.
7:1|Darby|Having therefore these promises, beloved, let us purify  ourselves from every pollution of flesh and spirit, perfecting  holiness in God's fear.
7:1|KJV|Having therefore these promises, dearly beloved, let us cleanse ourselves from all filthiness of the flesh and spirit, perfecting holiness in the fear of God.
7:1<version name="WYC">Therefore, most dear-worthy <i>brethren</i>, we that have these promises, cleanse we us from all filth of the flesh and of the spirit, doing holiness in the dread of God. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21935a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
7:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以親愛的，我們既有這些應許，就當潔淨自己，除去肉身和靈一切的玷污，敬畏神，以成全聖別。
7:2|ASV|Open your hearts to us: we wronged no man, we corrupted no man, we took advantage of no man.
7:2|Darby|Receive us: we have injured no one, we have ruined no one,  we have made gain of no one.
7:2|KJV|Receive us; we have wronged no man, we have corrupted no man, we have defrauded no man.
7:2|WYC|Take ye us; we have hurt no man, we have impaired no man [we have corrupted no man], we have beguiled no man.
7:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要容納我們，我們未曾虧負誰，未曾敗壞誰，未曾佔誰的便宜。
7:3|ASV|I say it not to condemn you: for I have said before, that ye are in our hearts to die together and live together.
7:3|Darby|I do not speak for condemnation, for I have already said  that ye are in our hearts, to die together, and live together.
7:3|KJV|I speak not this to condemn you: for I have said before, that ye are in our hearts to die and live with you.
7:3|WYC|I say not to your condemning; for I said before, that ye be in our hearts, to die together and to live together [to die together, and live together].
7:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我說這話，不是為定罪你們，因我先前說過，你們是在我們的心裡，以至同死同活。
7:4|ASV|Great is my boldness of speech toward you, great is my glorying on your behalf: I am filled with comfort, I overflow with joy in all our affliction.
7:4|Darby|Great [is] my boldness towards you, great my exulting in  respect of you; I am filled with encouragement; I overabound in  joy under all our affliction.
7:4|KJV|Great is my boldness of speech toward you, great is my glorying of you: I am filled with comfort, I am exceeding joyful in all our tribulation.
7:4<version name="WYC">Much trust is to me with you, much glorying is to me for you.  I am filled with comfort, I am plenteous [I abound, <i>or am plenteous</i>,] in joy in all our tribulation.</version>
7:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我向你們大大的放膽，我為你們多多的誇口；我滿得安慰，在我們一切的患難中，我格外的洋溢喜樂。
7:5|ASV|For even when we were come into Macedonia our flesh had no relief, but we were afflicted on every side; without were fightings, within were fears.
7:5|Darby|For indeed, when we came into Macedonia, our flesh had no  rest, but [we were] afflicted in every way; without combats,  within fears.
7:5|KJV|For, when we were come into Macedonia, our flesh had no rest, but we were troubled on every side; without were fightings, within were fears.
7:5<version name="WYC">For when we were come to Macedonia, our flesh had no rest, but we suffered all tribulation; withoutforth fightings, and dreads [<i>were</i>] within [forsooth withoutforth, fightings, withinforth, dreads].</version>
7:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|原來我們就是到了馬其頓，我們的肉身也不得安寧，反而凡事遭患難，外有爭戰，內有懼怕。
7:6|ASV|Nevertheless he that comforteth the lowly, even God, comforted us by the coming of Titus;
7:6|Darby|But he who encourages those that are [brought] low, [even]  God, encouraged us by the coming of Titus;
7:6|KJV|Nevertheless God, that comforteth those that are cast down, comforted us by the coming of Titus;
7:6|WYC|But God that comforteth meek men, comforted us in the coming of Titus.
7:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但那安慰頹喪之人的神，藉著提多來，安慰了我們；
7:7|ASV|and not by his coming only, but also by the comfort wherewith he was comforted in you, while he told us your longing, your mourning, your zeal for me; so that I rejoiced yet more.
7:7|Darby|and not by his coming only, but also through the  encouragement with which he was encouraged as to you; relating  to us your ardent desire, your mourning, your zeal for me; so  that I the more rejoiced.
7:7|KJV|And not by his coming only, but by the consolation wherewith he was comforted in you, when he told us your earnest desire, your mourning, your fervent mind toward me; so that I rejoiced the more.
7:7|WYC|And not only in the coming of him, but also in the comfort by which he was comforted in you, telling to us your desire, your weeping, your love for me, so that I joyed more.
7:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不但藉著他來，也藉著他在你們身上所得的安慰，安慰了我們，因他把你們的切望、你們的哀慟、和你們為我的熱心，都告訴了我們，叫我更加喜樂。
7:8|ASV|For though I made you sorry with my epistle, I do not regret it: though I did regret it (for I see that that epistle made you sorry, though but for a season),
7:8|Darby|For if also I grieved you in the letter, I do not regret  [it], if even I have regretted it; for I see that that letter,  if even [it were] only for a time, grieved you.
7:8|KJV|For though I made you sorry with a letter, I do not repent, though I did repent: for I perceive that the same epistle hath made you sorry, though it were but for a season.
7:8|WYC|For though I made you sorry in an epistle, it rueth me not; though it rued, [I] seeing that though that epistle made you sorry at an hour,
7:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我雖曾寫信叫你們憂愁，我並不懊悔；雖然我曾懊悔過，（因我曉得那信曾叫你們憂愁，儘管是一時的，）
7:9|ASV|I now rejoice, not that ye were made sorry, but that ye were made sorry unto repentance; for ye were made sorry after a godly sort, that ye might suffer loss by us in nothing.
7:9|Darby|Now I rejoice, not that ye have been grieved, but that ye  have been grieved to repentance; for ye have been grieved  according to God, that in nothing ye might be injured by us.
7:9|KJV|Now I rejoice, not that ye were made sorry, but that ye sorrowed to repentance: for ye were made sorry after a godly manner, that ye might receive damage by us in nothing.
7:9|WYC|now I have joy; not for ye were made sorrowful [not for ye were made sorry], but for ye were made sorrowful to penance.  For why ye be made sorry after God, that in nothing ye suffer impairment of us.
7:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|如今我卻喜樂，不是因你們憂愁，乃是因你們憂愁以致悔改，因為你們照著神憂愁，就不至於在任何事上，因我們受虧損了。
7:10|ASV|For godly sorrow worketh repentance unto salvation, a repentance which bringeth no regret: but the sorrow of the world worketh death.
7:10|Darby|For grief according to God works repentance to salvation,  never to be regretted; but the grief of the world works death.
7:10|KJV|For godly sorrow worketh repentance to salvation not to be repented of: but the sorrow of the world worketh death.
7:10|WYC|For the sorrow that is after God, worketh penance into steadfast health; but sorrow of the world worketh death.
7:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為照著神憂愁，生出悔改以致得救，是沒有後悔的，但世上的憂愁是產生死亡。
7:11|ASV|For behold, this selfsame thing, that ye were made sorry after a godly sort, what earnest care it wrought in you, yea what clearing of yourselves, yea what indignation, yea what fear, yea what longing, yea what zeal, yea what avenging! In everything ye approved yourselves to be pure in the matter.
7:11|Darby|For, behold, this same thing, your being grieved according  to God, how much diligence it wrought in *you*, but [what]  excusing [of yourselves], but [what] indignation, but [what]  fear, but [what] ardent desire, but [what] zeal, but [what]  vengeance: in every way ye have proved yourselves to be pure in  the matter.
7:11|KJV|For behold this selfsame thing, that ye sorrowed after a godly sort, what carefulness it wrought in you, yea, what clearing of yourselves, yea, what indignation, yea, what fear, yea, what vehement desire, yea, what zeal, yea, what revenge! In all things ye have approved yourselves to be clear in this matter.
7:11|WYC|For lo! this same thing, that ye be sorrowful after God, how much busyness it worketh in you; but defending, but indignation, but dread, but desire, but love, but vengeance.  In all things ye have given yourselves to be undefouled in the cause.
7:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|且看這事，你們照著神憂愁，在你們中間已產生何等的熱誠、甚而自訴、甚而憤恨、甚而懼怕、甚而切望、甚而熱心、甚而責罰。在各方面，你們都證薦自己在那件事上是純潔的。
7:12|ASV|So although I wrote unto you, I wrote not for his cause that did the wrong, nor for his cause that suffered the wrong, but that your earnest care for us might be made manifest unto you in the sight of God.
7:12|Darby|So then, if also I wrote to you, [it was] not for the sake  of him that injured, nor for the sake of him that was injured,  but for the sake of our diligent zeal for you being manifested  to you before God.
7:12|KJV|Wherefore, though I wrote unto you, I did it not for his cause that had done the wrong, nor for his cause that suffered wrong, but that our care for you in the sight of God might appear unto you.
7:12<version name="WYC">Therefore though I wrote to you, <i>I wrote</i> not for him that did the injury, neither for him that suffered, but to show our busyness, which we have for you before God.</version>
7:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此，我雖曾寫信給你們，卻不是為那虧負人的，也不是為那受虧負的，乃是為要在神面前，向你們顯明你們對我們的熱誠。
7:13|ASV|Therefore we have been comforted: And in our comfort we joyed the more exceedingly for the joy of Titus, because his spirit hath been refreshed by you all.
7:13|Darby|For this reason we have been encouraged. And we the rather  rejoiced in our encouragement more abundantly by reason of the  joy of Titus, because his spirit has been refreshed by you all.
7:13|KJV|Therefore we were comforted in your comfort: yea, and exceedingly the more joyed we for the joy of Titus, because his spirit was refreshed by you all.
7:13|WYC|Therefore we be comforted, but in your comfort more plenteously we joyed more on the joy of Titus, for his spirit is fulfilled of all you.
7:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我們得了安慰，並且在這安慰之外，我們因提多的喜樂，就越發更加喜樂，因他的靈從你們眾人得了暢快。
7:14|ASV|For if in anything I have gloried to him on your behalf, I was not put to shame; but as we spake all things to you in truth, so our glorying also which I made before Titus was found to be truth.
7:14|Darby|Because if I boasted to him anything about you, I have not  been put to shame; but as we have spoken to you all things in  truth, so also our boasting to Titus has been [the] truth;
7:14|KJV|For if I have boasted any thing to him of you, I am not ashamed; but as we spake all things to you in truth, even so our boasting, which I made before Titus, is found a truth.
7:14<version name="WYC">And if I gloried any thing with him of you, I am not confounded [I am not confounded, <i>or</i> <i>shamed</i>]; but as we have spoken to you all things [in truth], so also our glory that was at Titus, is made truth.</version>
7:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我若對提多誇獎了你們甚麼，也不覺得羞愧。相反的，我們對你們所說的一切事，怎樣是真實的，我們在提多面前所誇獎你們的，也怎樣成了真實的。
7:15|ASV|And his affection is more abundantly toward you, while he remembereth the obedience of you all, how with fear and trembling ye received him.
7:15|Darby|and his affections are more abundantly towards you, calling  to mind the obedience of you all, how with fear and trembling  ye received him.
7:15|KJV|And his inward affection is more abundant toward you, whilst he remembereth the obedience of you all, how with fear and trembling ye received him.
7:15|WYC|And the inwardness of him be more plenteously in you [And the entrails of him be more plenteous in you], which hath in mind the obedience of you all, how with dread and trembling ye received him.
7:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且提多想起你們眾人的順從，就是怎樣恐懼戰兢的接待他，他的心腸就越發傾向你們了。
7:16<version name="ASV">I rejoice that in everything I am of good courage concerning you. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:16<version name="Darby">I rejoice that in everything I am confident as to you. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:16<version name="KJV">I rejoice therefore that I have confidence in you in all things.</p><p /><br /></version>
7:16|WYC|I have joy, that in all things I trust in you. [I joy, that in all things I trust in you.]
7:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我如今喜樂，能在凡事上為你們放心。
8:1|ASV|Moreover, brethren, we make known to you the grace of God which hath been given in the churches of Macedonia;
8:1|Darby|But we make known to you, brethren, the grace of God  bestowed in the assemblies of Macedonia;
8:1|KJV|Moreover, brethren, we do you to wit of the grace of God bestowed on the churches of Macedonia;
8:1|WYC|But, brethren, we make known to you the grace of God, that is given in the churches of Macedonia,
8:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|還有，弟兄們，我們把神在馬其頓眾召會中所賜的恩典告訴你們，
8:2|ASV|how that in much proof of affliction the abundance of their joy and their deep poverty abounded unto the riches of their liberality.
8:2|Darby|that in a great trial of affliction the abundance of their  joy and their deep poverty has abounded to the riches of their  [free-hearted] liberality.
8:2|KJV|How that in a great trial of affliction the abundance of their joy and their deep poverty abounded unto the riches of their liberality.
8:2<version name="WYC">that in much assaying of tribulation, the plenty of the joy of them was [the abundance, <i>or plenty</i>, of the joy of them was], and the highest poverty of them was plenteous into the riches of the simpleness of them.</version>
8:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就是在患難中受大試驗的時候，他們充盈的喜樂，和極深的貧困，匯溢出豐厚的慷慨。
8:3|ASV|For according to their power, I bear witness, yea and beyond their power, they gave of their own accord,
8:3|Darby|For according to [their] power, I bear witness, and beyond  [their] power, [they were] willing of their own accord,
8:3|KJV|For to their power, I bear record, yea, and beyond their power they were willing of themselves;
8:3<version name="WYC">For I bear witnessing to them, after might and above might they were willful [after virtue,<i> or power</i>, and above virtue they were willful],</version>
8:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我可以見證，他們是按著能力，而且也過了能力，
8:4|ASV|beseeching us with much entreaty in regard of this grace and the fellowship in the ministering to the saints:
8:4|Darby|begging of us with much entreaty [to give effect to] the  grace and fellowship of the service which [was to be rendered]  to the saints.
8:4|KJV|Praying us with much intreaty that we would receive the gift, and take upon us the fellowship of the ministering to the saints.
8:4|WYC|with much admonishing beseeching us the grace and the communing of [the] ministering, that is made to holy men.
8:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|自願的多方懇求，向我們要求這供給聖徒的恩典和交通，
8:5|ASV|and this, not as we had hoped, but first they gave their own selves to the Lord, and to us through the will of God.
8:5|Darby|And not according as we hoped, but they gave themselves  first to the Lord, and to us by God's will.
8:5|KJV|And this they did, not as we hoped, but first gave their own selves to the Lord, and unto us by the will of God.
8:5|WYC|And not as we hoped, but they gave themselves first to the Lord, afterward to us by the will of God.
8:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且他們未照著我們所盼望的，反而憑著神的旨意，先把自己給了主，也給了我們，
8:6|ASV|Insomuch that we exhorted Titus, that as he made a beginning before, so he would also complete in you this grace also.
8:6|Darby|So that we begged Titus that, according as he had before  begun, so he would also complete as to you this grace also;
8:6|KJV|Insomuch that we desired Titus, that as he had begun, so he would also finish in you the same grace also.
8:6|WYC|So that we prayed Titus, that as he began, so also he perform in you this grace.
8:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以致我們勸提多，他怎樣開始了，也當照樣為你們完成這恩典，像完成其他的事一樣。
8:7|ASV|But as ye abound in everything, in faith, and utterance, and knowledge, and in all earnestness, and in your love to us,  see that ye abound in this grace also.
8:7|Darby|but even as ye abound in every way, in faith, and word, and  knowledge, and all diligence, and in love from you to us, that  ye may abound in this grace also.
8:7|KJV|Therefore, as ye abound in every thing, in faith, and utterance, and knowledge, and in all diligence, and in your love to us, see that ye abound in this grace also.
8:7<version name="WYC">But as ye abound in all things, in faith, and word, and knowing [and science, <i>or knowing</i>], and all busyness, moreover and in your charity into us, that also in this grace ye abound.</version>
8:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但你們當在這恩典上也充盈滿溢，像你們在凡事上，在信心，在言語，在知識，在一切的熱誠，並在那出於我們而在你們裡面的愛心上，都充盈滿溢一樣。
8:8|ASV|I speak not by way of commandment, but as proving through the earnestness of others the sincerity also of your love.
8:8|Darby|I do not speak as commanding [it], but through the zeal of  others, and proving the genuineness of your love.
8:8|KJV|I speak not by commandment, but by occasion of the forwardness of others, and to prove the sincerity of your love.
8:8|WYC|I say not as commanding, but by the busyness of other men proving also the good wit of your charity.
8:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我說這話，不是命令你們，乃是藉著別人的熱誠，也試驗你們愛的真實。
8:9|ASV|For ye know the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, that, though he was rich, yet for your sakes he became poor, that ye through his poverty might become rich.
8:9|Darby|For ye know the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, that for  your sakes he, being rich, became poor, in order that *ye* by  *his* poverty might be enriched.
8:9|KJV|For ye know the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, that, though he was rich, yet for your sakes he became poor, that ye through his poverty might be rich.
8:9<version name="WYC">And ye know the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, for he was made needy for you, when he was rich, that ye should be made rich by his neediness [that ye should be made rich by his mis-ease, <i>or neediness</i>].</version>
8:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們知道我們主耶穌基督的恩典，祂本來富足，卻為你們成了貧窮，叫你們因祂的貧窮，可以成為富足。
8:10|ASV|And herein I give my judgment: for this is expedient for you, who were the first to make a beginning a year ago, not only to do, but also to will.
8:10|Darby|And I give [my] opinion in this, for this is profitable for  you who began before, not only to do, but also to be willing, a  year ago.
8:10|KJV|And herein I give my advice: for this is expedient for you, who have begun before, not only to do, but also to be forward a year ago.
8:10|WYC|And I give counsel in this thing; for this is profitable to you, that not only have begun to do, but also ye began to have will from the former year [but and to desire from the former year].
8:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在這事上題出意見，因這是與你們有益的；你們不但在實行上，也在意願上，在一年前就先開始了，
8:11|ASV|But now complete the doing also; that as  there was the readiness to will, so there may be the completion also out of your ability.
8:11|Darby|But now also complete the doing of it; so that as [there  was] the readiness to be willing, so also to complete out of  what ye have.
8:11|KJV|Now therefore perform the doing of it; that as there was a readiness to will, so there may be a performance also out of that which ye have.
8:11<version name="WYC">But now [Now forsooth] perform ye in deed, that as the discretion of will is ready [<i>to desire good</i>], so be it also of performing of that that ye have.</version>
8:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|如今也當辦成這事，好叫你們怎樣有願作的熱切，也怎樣照所有的辦成，
8:12|ASV|For if the readiness is there, it is acceptable according as a man hath, not according as he hath not.
8:12|Darby|For if the readiness be there, [a man is] accepted  according to what he may have, not according to what he has  not.
8:12|KJV|For if there be first a willing mind, it is accepted according to that a man hath, and not according to that he hath not.
8:12|WYC|For if the will be ready, it is accepted after that that it hath, not after that that it hath not.
8:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為人若熱切願作，必蒙悅納，乃是照他所有的，不是照他所無的。
8:13|ASV|For I say not this that others may be eased and ye distressed;
8:13|Darby|For [it is] not in order that there may be ease for others,  and for you distress,
8:13|KJV|For I mean not that other men be eased, and ye burdened:
8:13<version name="WYC">And not that it be remission to other <i>men </i><sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21963a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>, and to you tribulation;</version>
8:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這原不是要別人輕省，你們為難，
8:14|ASV|but by equality: your abundance being a supply at this present time for their want, that their abundance also may become a supply for your want; that there may be equality:
8:14|Darby|but [on the principle] of equality; in the present time  your abundance for their lack, that their abundance may be for  your lack, so that there should be equality.
8:14|KJV|But by an equality, that now at this time your abundance may be a supply for their want, that their abundance also may be a supply for your want: that there may be equality:
8:14<version name="WYC">but of evenness in the present time your abundance fulfill the need of them, that also the abundance of them be a fulfilling of your need, that evenness be made; [but of evenness, in <i>this</i> present time your abundance fulfill the mis-ease of them, that and the abundance of them be supplement, <i>or fulfilling</i>, of your mis-ease, <i>or need</i>, that evenness be made;]</version>
8:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|乃是要出於均平，就是要你們的富餘，今時可以補他們的不足，為使他們的富餘，將來也可以補你們的不足，這就均平了；
8:15|ASV|as it is written, He that gathered much had nothing over; and he that  gathered little had no lack.
8:15|Darby|According as it is written, He who [gathered] much had no  excess, and he who [gathered] little was nothing short.
8:15|KJV|As it is written, He that had gathered much had nothing over; and he that had gathered little had no lack.
8:15<version name="WYC">as it is written, He that [hath] gathered much, was not increased, and he that [had] <i>gathered</i> little, had not less.</version>
8:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|如經上所記：“多收的沒有餘，少收的也沒有缺。”
8:16|ASV|But thanks be to God, who putteth the same earnest care for you into the heart of Titus.
8:16|Darby|But thanks [be] to God, who gives the same diligent zeal  for you in the heart of Titus.
8:16|KJV|But thanks be to God, which put the same earnest care into the heart of Titus for you.
8:16|WYC|And I do thankings to God, that gave the same busyness for you in the heart of Titus,
8:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|感謝神，把我為你們同樣的熱誠，賜在提多心裡，
8:17|ASV|For he accepted indeed our exhortation; but being himself very earnest, he went forth unto you of his own accord.
8:17|Darby|For he received indeed the entreaty, but, being full of  zeal, he went of his own accord to you;
8:17|KJV|For indeed he accepted the exhortation; but being more forward, of his own accord he went unto you.
8:17|WYC|for [soothly] he received exhortation; but when he was busier, by his will he went forth to you [with his will he went forth to you].
8:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因他固然接受了懇求，但自己更是熱誠，自願往你們那裡去。
8:18|ASV|And we have sent together with him the brother whose praise in the gospel is spread through all the churches;
8:18|Darby|but we have sent with him the brother whose praise [is] in  the glad tidings through all the assemblies;
8:18|KJV|And we have sent with him the brother, whose praise is in the gospel throughout all the churches;
8:18|WYC|And we sent with him a brother, whose praising is in the gospel by all churches.
8:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們還打發一位弟兄和他同去，這人在福音上普遍的為眾召會所稱讚。
8:19|ASV|and not only so, but who was also appointed by the churches to travel with us in the matter of this grace, which is ministered by us to the glory of the Lord, and to show our readiness:
8:19|Darby|and not only [so], but [is] also chosen by the assemblies  as our fellow-traveller with this grace, ministered by us to  the glory of the Lord himself, and [a witness of] our  readiness;
8:19|KJV|And not that only, but who was also chosen of the churches to travel with us with this grace, which is administered by us to the glory of the same Lord, and declaration of your ready mind:
8:19|WYC|And not only [praised], but also he is ordained of churches the fellow of our pilgrimage into this grace, that is ministered of us to the glory of the Lord, and to our ordained will;
8:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不但這樣，他也被眾召會選出，在我們所服事的這恩典上，和我們同行，是為著主自己的榮耀，也是為著我們的熱切。
8:20|ASV|Avoiding this, that any man should blame us in the matter of this bounty which is ministered by us:
8:20|Darby|avoiding this, that any one should blame us in this  abundance [which is] administered by us;
8:20|KJV|Avoiding this, that no man should blame us in this abundance which is administered by us:
8:20|WYC|eschewing this thing, that no man blame us in this plenty, that is ministered of us to the glory of the Lord.
8:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這就避免人在我們所服事的這豐裕上，挑剔我們，
8:21|ASV|for we take thought for things honorable, not only in the sight of the Lord, but also in the sight of men.
8:21|Darby|for we provide for things honest, not only before [the]  Lord, but also before men.
8:21|KJV|Providing for honest things, not only in the sight of the Lord, but also in the sight of men.
8:21|WYC|For we purvey good things, not only before God, but also before all men.
8:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們留心作善美可敬的事，不但在主面前，也在人面前。
8:22|ASV|and we have sent with them our brother, whom we have many times proved earnest in many things, but now much more earnest, by reason of the great confidence which  he hath in you.
8:22|Darby|And we have sent with them our brother whom we have often  proved to be of diligent zeal in many things, and now more  diligently zealous through the great confidence [he has] as to  you.
8:22|KJV|And we have sent with them our brother, whom we have oftentimes proved diligent in many things, but now much more diligent, upon the great confidence which I have in you.
8:22|WYC|For we sent with them also our brother, whom we have proved in many things oft, that he was busy, but now much busier, for much trust in you, [Forsooth we sent with them and our brother, whom we have proved in many things oft, to be busy, now forsooth much busier, in much trust in you,]
8:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們又打發我們的弟兄和他們同去，這人是我們在許多事上，屢次試證為殷勤的，現在他因對你們極其深信，就極其更加殷勤了。
8:23|ASV|Whether any inquire about Titus, he is my partner and  my fellow-worker to you-ward, or our brethren, they are the messengers of the churches, they are the glory of Christ.
8:23|Darby|Whether as regards Titus, [he is] my companion and  fellow-labourer in your behalf; or our brethren, [they are]  deputed messengers of assemblies, Christ's glory.
8:23|KJV|Whether any do enquire of Titus, he is my partner and fellowhelper concerning you: or our brethren be enquired of, they are the messengers of the churches, and the glory of Christ.
8:23|WYC|either for Titus, that is my fellow and helper in you, either for our brethren [either our brethren], apostles of the churches of the glory of Christ.
8:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|論到提多，他是我的同夥和為著你們的同工；至於我們的弟兄們，他們是眾召會的使徒，是基督的榮耀。
8:24<version name="ASV">Show ye therefore unto them in the face of the churches the proof of your love, and of our glorying on your behalf. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:24<version name="Darby">Shew therefore to them, before the assemblies, the proof of  your love, and of our boasting about you. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:24<version name="KJV">Wherefore shew ye to them, and before the churches, the proof of your love, and of our boasting on your behalf.</p><p /><br /></version>
8:24|WYC|Therefore show ye to them in the face of churches, that showing that is of your charity [the showing that is of your charity] and of our glory for you.
8:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以你們要在眾召會面前，向他們顯示你們愛心的明證，並我們為你們誇耀的明證。
9:1|ASV|For as touching the ministering to the saints, it is superfluous for me to write to you:
9:1|Darby|For concerning the ministration which [is] for the saints,  it is superfluous my writing to you.
9:1|KJV|For as touching the ministering to the saints, it is superfluous for me to write to you:
9:1|WYC|For of the ministry that is made to holy men, it is to me of plenty to write to you.
9:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|關於供給聖徒的事，寫信給你們，於我原是多餘的。
9:2|ASV|for I know your readiness, of which I glory on your behalf to them of Macedonia, that Achaia hath been prepared for a year past; and your zeal hath stirred up very many of them.
9:2|Darby|For I know your readiness, which I boast of as respects you  to Macedonians, that Achaia is prepared since a year ago, and  the zeal [reported] of you has stimulated the mass [of the  brethren].
9:2|KJV|For I know the forwardness of your mind, for which I boast of you to them of Macedonia, that Achaia was ready a year ago; and your zeal hath provoked very many.
9:2|WYC|For I know your [ready] will, for the which I have glory of you with Macedonians, for also Achaia is ready from a year passed, and your love hath stirred full many.
9:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我知道你們的熱切，就是我常對馬其頓人所誇耀你們的，說亞該亞人在一年前就豫備好了；你們的熱心便激動了許多人。
9:3|ASV|But I have sent the brethren, that our glorying on your behalf may not be made void in this respect; that, even as I said, ye may be prepared:
9:3|Darby|But I have sent the brethren, in order that our boasting  about you may not be made void in this respect, in order that,  as I have said, ye may be prepared;
9:3|KJV|Yet have I sent the brethren, lest our boasting of you should be in vain in this behalf; that, as I said, ye may be ready:
9:3|WYC|And we have sent brethren, that this thing that we glory of you, be not voided in this part, that as I said, ye be ready.
9:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但我打發那幾位弟兄去，使我們在這方面為你們所誇耀的，不至於落空，好叫你們照我所說的豫備好，
9:4|ASV|lest by any means, if there come with me any of Macedonia and find you unprepared, we (that we say not, ye) should be put to shame in this confidence.
9:4|Darby|lest haply, if Macedonians come with me and find you  unprepared, *we*, that we say not *ye*, may be put to shame in  this confidence.
9:4|KJV|Lest haply if they of Macedonia come with me, and find you unprepared, we (that we say not, ye) should be ashamed in this same confident boasting.
9:4|WYC|Lest when Macedonians come with me, and find you unready, we be shamed, that we say you not/that we saw you not, in this substance.
9:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|免得萬一有馬其頓人與我同去，發現你們沒有豫備好，就叫我們所確信的蒙羞，你們就更不用說了。
9:5|ASV|I thought it necessary therefore to entreat the brethren, that they would go before unto you, and make up beforehand your aforepromised bounty, that the same might be ready as a matter of bounty, and not of extortion.
9:5|Darby|I thought it necessary therefore to beg the brethren that  they would come to you, and complete beforehand your  fore-announced blessing, that this may be ready thus as  blessing, and not as got out of you.
9:5|KJV|Therefore I thought it necessary to exhort the brethren, that they would go before unto you, and make up beforehand your bounty, whereof ye had notice before, that the same might be ready, as a matter of bounty, and not as of covetousness.
9:5|WYC|Therefore I guessed necessary to pray brethren, that they come before to you, and make ready this promised blessing to be ready, so as blessing, and not as avarice.
9:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，我想必須勸那幾位弟兄先到你們那裡去，把你們先前所應許的祝福事前安排好，使這事如此豫備好了，就成為受者的祝福，而不成為施者的貪婪。
9:6|ASV|But this I say, He that soweth sparingly shall reap also sparingly; and he that soweth bountifully shall reap also bountifully.
9:6|Darby|But this [is true], he that sows sparingly shall reap also  sparingly; and he that sows in [the spirit of] blessing shall  reap also in blessing:
9:6|KJV|But this I say, He which soweth sparingly shall reap also sparingly; and he which soweth bountifully shall reap also bountifully.
9:6|WYC|For I say this thing [This thing forsooth I say], he that soweth scarcely, shall also reap scarcely; and he that soweth in blessings, shall reap also of blessings.
9:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|還有，少種的少收，多種的多收。
9:7|ASV|Let each man do according as he hath purposed in his heart: not grudgingly, or of necessity: for God loveth a cheerful giver.
9:7|Darby|each according as he is purposed in his heart; not  grievingly, or of necessity; for God loves a cheerful giver.
9:7|KJV|Every man according as he purposeth in his heart, so let him give; not grudgingly, or of necessity: for God loveth a cheerful giver.
9:7|WYC|Each man as he casted in his heart [Each man as he cast in his heart], not of heaviness, or of need; for God loveth a glad giver.
9:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|各人要照心裡所酌定的，不要作難，不要勉強，因為神喜愛樂意施與的人。
9:8|ASV|And God is able to make all grace abound unto you; that ye, having always all sufficiency in everything, may abound unto every good work:
9:8|Darby|But God is able to make every gracious gift abound towards  you, that, having in every way always all-sufficiency, ye may  abound to every good work:
9:8|KJV|And God is able to make all grace abound toward you; that ye, always having all sufficiency in all things, may abound to every good work:
9:8|WYC|And God is mighty to make all grace abound in you, that ye in all things evermore have all sufficience, and abound into all good work [that ye, in all things evermore having all sufficience, abound into all good work];
9:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神能使各樣的恩典向你們洋溢，使你們在凡事上常常十分充足，能洋溢出各樣的善工。
9:9|ASV|as it is written, He hath scattered abroad, he hath given to the poor; His righteousness abideth for ever.
9:9|Darby|according as it is written, He has scattered abroad, he has  given to the poor, his righteousness remains for ever.
9:9|KJV|(As it is written, He hath dispersed abroad; he hath given to the poor: his righteousness remaineth for ever.
9:9|WYC|as it is written, He dealed abroad, he gave to poor men, his rightwiseness dwelleth without end [his rightwiseness dwelleth into without end].
9:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就如經上所記：“他分施賙濟貧賤，他的義存到永遠。”
9:10|ASV|And he that supplieth seed to the sower and bread for food, shall supply and multiply your seed for sowing, and increase the fruits of your righteousness:
9:10|Darby|Now he that supplies seed to the sower and bread for eating  shall supply and make abundant your sowing, and increase the  fruits of your righteousness:
9:10|KJV|Now he that ministereth seed to the sower both minister bread for your food, and multiply your seed sown, and increase the fruits of your righteousness;)
9:10<version name="WYC">And he that ministereth seed to the sower, shall give also bread to eat, and he shall multiply your seed, and make much the increasings of fruits of your rightwiseness; <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21984a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
9:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那豐富供應種子給撒種者，並豐富供應糧食作食物的，必供應並繁增你們的種子，又增添你們義的果子，
9:11|ASV|ye being enriched in everything unto all liberality, which worketh through us thanksgiving to God.
9:11|Darby|enriched in every way unto all free-hearted liberality,  which works through us thanksgiving to God.
9:11|KJV|Being enriched in every thing to all bountifulness, which causeth through us thanksgiving to God.
9:11|WYC|that in all things ye made rich wax plenteous into all simpleness [that in all things made rich abound into all simpleness], which worketh by us doing of thankings to God.
9:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|使你們凡事富足，以致十分慷慨，就藉著我們對神生出感謝；
9:12|ASV|For the ministration of this service not only filleth up the measure of the wants of the saints, but aboundeth also through many thanksgivings unto God;
9:12|Darby|Because the ministration of this service is not only  filling up the measure of what is lacking to the saints, but  also abounding by many thanksgivings to God;
9:12|KJV|For the administration of this service not only supplieth the want of the saints, but is abundant also by many thanksgivings unto God;
9:12|WYC|For the ministry of this office not only filleth those things that fail to holy men, but also multiplieth many thankings to God [but also aboundeth by many in doing of thankings to the Lord],
9:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為這服事的供應，不但補足聖徒的缺乏，也藉著許多對神的感謝而洋溢。
9:13|ASV|seeing that through the proving of you by this ministration they glorify God for the obedience of your confession unto the gospel of Christ, and for the liberality of your contribution unto them and unto all;
9:13|Darby|they glorifying God through the proof of this ministration,  by reason of your subjection, by profession, to the glad  tidings of the Christ, and your free-hearted liberality in  communicating towards them and towards all;
9:13|KJV|Whiles by the experiment of this ministration they glorify God for your professed subjection unto the gospel of Christ, and for your liberal distribution unto them, and unto all men;
9:13<version name="WYC">by the proving of this ministry, which glorify God in the obedience of your acknowledging in the gospel of Christ, and in simpleness of communication into them and into all [<i>others</i>],</version>
9:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們因著你們承認基督的福音而有的服從，以及你們對他們和眾人慷慨的交通，就稱許這供給的事，藉以榮耀神。
9:14|ASV|while they themselves also, with supplication on your behalf, long after you by reason of the exceeding grace of God in you.
9:14|Darby|and in their supplication for you, full of ardent desire  for you, on account of the exceeding grace of God [which is]  upon you.
9:14|KJV|And by their prayer for you, which long after you for the exceeding grace of God in you.
9:14|WYC|and in the beseeching of them for you, that desire you for the excellent grace of God in you.
9:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們也因神在你們身上超越的恩典，切切的想念你們，為你們祈求。
9:15<version name="ASV">Thanks be to God for his unspeakable gift. </p><p /><br /></version>
9:15<version name="Darby">Thanks [be] to God for his unspeakable free gift. </p><p /><br /></version>
9:15<version name="KJV">Thanks be unto God for his unspeakable gift.</p><p /><br /></version>
9:15<version name="WYC">I do thankings to God of the gift of him, that may not be told. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21989b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
9:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|感謝神，為著祂難以形容的恩賜。
10:1|ASV|Now I Paul myself entreat you by the meekness and gentleness of Christ, I who in your presence am lowly among you, but being absent am of good courage toward you:
10:1|Darby|But I myself, Paul, entreat you by the meekness and  gentleness of the Christ, who, as to appearance, [when present]  [am] mean among you, but absent am bold towards you;
10:1|KJV|Now I Paul myself beseech you by the meekness and gentleness of Christ, who in presence am base among you, but being absent am bold toward you:
10:1<version name="WYC">And I myself Paul beseech you, by the mildness and softness of Christ <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21990a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>, which in the face am meek among you, and I absent trust in you.</version>
10:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而我保羅，就是那如你們所說，在你們中間，見面的時候是卑鄙的，不在的時候，向你們卻是放膽的，親自藉著基督的溫柔與和藹勸你們，
10:2|ASV|yea, I beseech you, that I may not when present show courage with the confidence wherewith I count to be bold against some, who count of us as if we walked according to the flesh.
10:2|Darby|but I beseech that present I may not be bold with the  confidence with which I think to be daring towards some who  think of us as walking according to flesh.
10:2|KJV|But I beseech you, that I may not be bold when I am present with that confidence, wherewith I think to be bold against some, which think of us as if we walked according to the flesh.
10:2<version name="WYC">For I pray you, that lest I present be not bold by the trust, in which I am guessed to be bold into some, that deem us, as if we wander after the flesh. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21991b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
10:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我甚至求你們不要叫我同在的時候，因自信而放膽，我憑這自信認為，我該勇敢對付那些認為我們是照著肉體行事的人。
10:3|ASV|For though we walk in the flesh, we do not war according to the flesh
10:3|Darby|For walking in flesh, we do not war according to flesh.
10:3|KJV|For though we walk in the flesh, we do not war after the flesh:
10:3|WYC|For we walking in the flesh, fight not after the flesh.
10:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們雖然在肉體中行事，卻不照著肉體爭戰。
10:4|ASV|(for the weapons of our warfare are not of the flesh, but mighty before God to the casting down of strongholds),
10:4|Darby|For the arms of our warfare [are] not fleshly, but powerful  according to God to [the] overthrow of strongholds;
10:4|KJV|(For the weapons of our warfare are not carnal, but mighty through God to the pulling down of strong holds;)
10:4<version name="WYC">For the arms of our knighthood be not fleshly, but mighty by God to the destruction of strengths [to the destruction of wardings, <i>or strengths</i>].</version>
10:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們爭戰的兵器，本不是屬肉體的，乃是在神面前有能力，可以攻倒堅固的營壘，
10:5|ASV|casting down imaginations, and every high thing that is exalted against the knowledge of God, and bringing every thought into captivity to the obedience of Christ;
10:5|Darby|overthrowing reasonings and every high thing that lifts  itself up against the knowledge of God, and leading captive  every thought into the obedience of the Christ;
10:5|KJV|Casting down imaginations, and every high thing that exalteth itself against the knowledge of God, and bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of Christ;
10:5<version name="WYC">And we destroy counsels, and all highness that higheth itself against the science of God, and drive into captivity all understanding into the service of Christ. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21994c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup></version>
10:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|將理論和各樣阻擋人認識神而立起的高寨，都攻倒了，又將各樣的思想擄來，使牠順從基督，
10:6|ASV|and being in readiness to avenge all disobedience, when your obedience shall be made full.
10:6|Darby|and having in readiness to avenge all disobedience when  your obedience shall have been fulfilled.
10:6|KJV|And having in a readiness to revenge all disobedience, when your obedience is fulfilled.
10:6|WYC|And we have ready to venge all unobedience, when your obedience shall be filled. [Also having in readiness to venge all unobedience, when your obedience shall be fulfilled.]
10:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且我們已經豫備好了，等你們完全順從的時候，要責罰一切的不順從。
10:7|ASV|Ye look at the things that are before your face. If any man trusteth in himself that he is Christ's, let him consider this again with himself, that, even as he is Christ's, so also are we.
10:7|Darby|Do ye look at what concerns appearance? If any one has  confidence in himself that he is of Christ, let him think this  again in himself, that even as he [is] of Christ, so also [are]  we.
10:7|KJV|Do ye look on things after the outward appearance? if any man trust to himself that he is Christ's, let him of himself think this again, that, as he is Christ's, even so are we Christ's.
10:7|WYC|See ye the things that be after the face.  If any man trusteth to himself, that he is of Christ, think he this thing again with himself, for as he is Christ's, so also we [so and we].
10:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們是按外表看事情。若有人自信是屬基督的，關於他自己，他要再想想，他是怎樣屬基督，我們也怎樣是。
10:8|ASV|For though I should glory somewhat abundantly concerning our authority (which the Lord gave for building you up, and not for casting you down), I shall not be put to shame:
10:8|Darby|For and if I should boast even somewhat more abundantly of  our authority, which the Lord has given [to us] for building up  and not for your overthrowing, I shall not be put to shame;
10:8|KJV|For though I should boast somewhat more of our authority, which the Lord hath given us for edification, and not for your destruction, I should not be ashamed:
10:8|WYC|For if I shall glory any thing more of our power, which the Lord gave to us into edifying, and not into your destruction, I shall not be shamed.
10:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主賜給我們的權柄，是為建造，並不是為拆毀你們，我即使為這權柄稍微過多的誇口，也不至於慚愧。
10:9|ASV|that I may not seem as if I would terrify you by my letters.
10:9|Darby|that I may not seem as if I was frightening you by letters:
10:9|KJV|That I may not seem as if I would terrify you by letters.
10:9|WYC|But that I be not guessed as to frighten you by epistles, [Forsooth that I be not guessed as to fear you by epistles,]
10:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我說這話，為免我像是寫信威嚇你們。
10:10|ASV|For, His letters, they say, are weighty and strong; but his bodily presence is weak, and his speech of no account.
10:10|Darby|because his letters, he says, [are] weighty and strong,  but his presence in the body weak, and his speech naught.
10:10|KJV|For his letters, say they, are weighty and powerful; but his bodily presence is weak, and his speech contemptible.
10:10<version name="WYC">for they say, That epistles be grievous and strong, but the presence of the body<i> is </i>feeble, and the word worthy to be despised. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21999d" title="See footnote d">d</a>]</sup></version>
10:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為有人說，他的信又沉重，又強硬，他親身的同在卻是軟弱，言語又是可鄙。
10:11|ASV|Let such a one reckon this, that, what we are in word by letters when we are absent, such are we also in deed when we are present.
10:11|Darby|Let such a one think this, that such as we are in word by  letters [when] absent, such also present in deed.
10:11|KJV|Let such an one think this, that, such as we are in word by letters when we are absent, such will we be also in deed when we are present.
10:11<version name="WYC">He that is such one, think this, for such as we absent be in word by epistles, such <i>we be</i> present in deed.</version>
10:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這等人當想，我們不在的時候，信上的言語怎樣，同在的時候，行事也必怎樣。
10:12|ASV|For we are not bold to number or compare ourselves with certain of them that commend themselves: but they themselves, measuring themselves by themselves, and comparing themselves with themselves, are without understanding.
10:12|Darby|For we dare not class ourselves or compare ourselves with  some who commend themselves; but these, measuring themselves by  themselves, and comparing themselves with themselves, are not  intelligent.
10:12|KJV|For we dare not make ourselves of the number, or compare ourselves with some that commend themselves: but they measuring themselves by themselves, and comparing themselves among themselves, are not wise.
10:12<version name="WYC">For we dare not put us among, or comparison us to some men, that commend themselves; but we measure us in us selves, and comparison us selves to us. [Soothly we dare not put us among, or comparison us to some, that commend themselves; but we meting, <i>or</i> <i>measuring</i>, us in ourselves, and comparisoning ourselves to us.]</version>
10:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們不敢將自己，和那些自薦的人同列相比，他們拿自己度量自己，拿自己比較自己，乃是不通達的。
10:13|ASV|But we will not glory beyond our measure, but according to the measure of the province which God apportioned to us as a measure, to reach even unto you.
10:13|Darby|Now *we* will not boast out of measure, but according to  the measure of the rule which the God of measure has  apportioned to us, to reach to you also.
10:13|KJV|But we will not boast of things without our measure, but according to the measure of the rule which God hath distributed to us, a measure to reach even unto you.
10:13|WYC|For we shall not have glory over measure, but by the measure of the rule [but after the measure of rule] which God measured to us, the measure that stretcheth [till] to you.
10:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們卻不要過了度量誇口，只要照度量的神所分給我們尺度的度量誇口，這度量甚至遠達你們。
10:14|ASV|For we stretch not ourselves overmuch, as though we reached not unto you: for we came even as far as unto you in the gospel of Christ:
10:14|Darby|For we do not, as not reaching to you, overstretch  ourselves, (for we have come to you also in the glad tidings of  the Christ;)
10:14|KJV|For we stretch not ourselves beyond our measure, as though we reached not unto you: for we are come as far as to you also in preaching the gospel of Christ:
10:14|WYC|For we overstretch not forth us, as not stretching to you.  For [till] to you we came in the gospel of Christ,
10:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們並非過度伸展自己，好像達不到你們，因為在基督的福音上，我們是最先來的，甚至遠及你們。
10:15|ASV|not glorying beyond our measure, that is, in other men's labors; but having hope that, as your faith groweth, we shall be magnified in you according to our province unto further abundance,
10:15|Darby|not boasting out of measure in other people's labours, but  having hope, your faith increasing, to be enlarged amongst you,  according to our rule, yet more abundantly
10:15|KJV|Not boasting of things without our measure, that is, of other men's labours; but having hope, when your faith is increased, that we shall be enlarged by you according to our rule abundantly,
10:15|WYC|not glorying over measure in other men's travails.  For we have hope of your faith that waxeth in you to be magnified by our rule in abundance [Soothly we having hope of your faith waxing in you to be magnified after our rule in abundance],
10:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們不憑別人的勞碌過度誇口，但盼望隨著你們信心的增長，照著我們的尺度，因著你們得以豐盛的擴大，
10:16|ASV|so as to preach the gospel even unto the parts beyond you, and not to glory in another's province in regard of things ready to our hand.
10:16|Darby|to announce the glad tidings to that [which is] beyond  you, not to be boasting in another's rule of things made ready  to hand.
10:16|KJV|To preach the gospel in the regions beyond you, and not to boast in another man's line of things made ready to our hand.
10:16|WYC|also to preach into those things that be beyond you, not to have glory in other man's rule [not to glory in other man's rule], in these things that be made ready.
10:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|將福音傳到你們以外的地方，並不是在別人的尺度之內，憑現成的事誇口。
10:17|ASV|But he that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord.
10:17|Darby|But he that boasts, let him boast in the Lord.
10:17|KJV|But he that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord.
10:17|WYC|[Forsooth] He that glorieth, have glory in the Lord [glory he in the Lord].
10:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但誇口的當在主裡誇口，
10:18<version name="ASV">For not he that commendeth himself is approved, but whom the Lord commendeth. </p><p /><br /></version>
10:18<version name="Darby">For not *he* that commends himself is approved, but whom  the Lord commends. </p><p /><br /></version>
10:18<version name="KJV">For not he that commendeth himself is approved, but whom the Lord commendeth.</p><p /><br /></version>
10:18|WYC|For not he that commendeth himself is approved [is proved], but whom God commendeth.
10:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為蒙稱許的，不是自己推薦的，乃是主所推薦的。
11:1|ASV|Would that ye could bear with me in a little foolishness: but indeed ye do bear with me.
11:1|Darby|Would that ye would bear with me [in] a little folly; but  indeed bear with me.
11:1|KJV|Would to God ye could bear with me a little in my folly: and indeed bear with me.
11:1<version name="WYC">I would that ye would suffer a little thing of mine unwisdom, but also support ye me. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22008a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
11:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我願你們容忍我一點愚妄，其實你們確是容忍我的。
11:2|ASV|For I am jealous over you with a godly jealousy: for I espoused you to one husband, that I might present you as a pure virgin to Christ.
11:2|Darby|For I am jealous as to you with a jealousy [which is] of  God; for I have espoused you unto one man, to present [you] a  chaste virgin to Christ.
11:2|KJV|For I am jealous over you with godly jealousy: for I have espoused you to one husband, that I may present you as a chaste virgin to Christ.
11:2<version name="WYC">For I love you by the love of God; for I have espoused [<i>spoused</i>] you to one husband, to yield a chaste virgin to Christ [to give you, a chaste virgin, to one man, Christ].</version>
11:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我以神的妒忌，妒忌你們，因為我曾把你們許配一個丈夫，要將一個貞潔的童女獻給基督。
11:3|ASV|But I fear, lest by any means, as the serpent beguiled Eve in his craftiness, your minds should be corrupted from the simplicity and the purity that is toward Christ.
11:3|Darby|But I fear lest by any means, as the serpent deceived Eve  by his craft, [so] your thoughts should be corrupted from  simplicity as to the Christ.
11:3|KJV|But I fear, lest by any means, as the serpent beguiled Eve through his subtilty, so your minds should be corrupted from the simplicity that is in Christ.
11:3|WYC|But I dread, lest as the serpent deceived Eve with his subtle fraud, so your wits be corrupted, and fallen down from the simpleness that is in Christ.
11:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我只怕你們的心思或被敗壞，失去那向著基督的單純和純潔，就像蛇用詭詐誘騙了夏娃一樣。
11:4|ASV|For if he that cometh preacheth another Jesus, whom we did not preach, or if ye receive a different spirit, which ye did not receive, or a different gospel, which ye did not accept, ye do well to bear with him.
11:4|Darby|For if indeed he that comes preaches another Jesus, whom we  have not preached, or ye get a different Spirit, which ye have  not got, or a different glad tidings, which ye have not  received, ye might well bear with [it].
11:4|KJV|For if he that cometh preacheth another Jesus, whom we have not preached, or if ye receive another spirit, which ye have not received, or another gospel, which ye have not accepted, ye might well bear with him.
11:4|WYC|For if he that cometh, preacheth another Christ, whom we preached not, or if ye take another spirit, whom ye took not [whom ye received not], or another gospel, which ye received not, rightly ye should suffer.
11:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|假若有人來，傳另一位耶穌，不是我們所傳過的，或者你們接受了一個不同的靈，不是你們所接受過的，或者接受了一個不同的福音，不是你們所接受過的，你們還好好的容忍他！
11:5|ASV|For I reckon that I am not a whit behind the very chiefest apostles.
11:5|Darby|For I reckon that in nothing I am behind those who are in  surpassing degree apostles.
11:5|KJV|For I suppose I was not a whit behind the very chiefest apostles.
11:5|WYC|For I ween that I have done nothing less than the great apostles.
11:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但我認為，自己一點沒有趕不上那些超級的使徒。
11:6|ASV|But though I be rude in speech, yet am I not in knowledge; nay, in every way have we made this manifest unto you in all things.
11:6|Darby|But if [I am] a simple person in speech, yet not in  knowledge, but in everything making [the truth] manifest in all  things to you.
11:6|KJV|But though I be rude in speech, yet not in knowledge; but we have been throughly made manifest among you in all things.
11:6<version name="WYC">For though I be unlearned in word, but not in knowing.  For in all things I am open to you. [For why though I be unlearned in sermon, <i>or word</i>, but not in science, <i>or knowing</i>.  Forsooth in all things I am showed, <i>or made known</i>, to you.]</version>
11:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我即使在言語上是常人，在知識上卻不然；其實我們在凡事上，在各方面，都已經向你們顯明了。
11:7|ASV|Or did I commit a sin in abasing myself that ye might be exalted, because I preached to you the gospel of God for nought?
11:7|Darby|Have I committed sin, abasing myself in order that *ye*  might be exalted, because I gratuitously announced to you the  glad tidings of God?
11:7|KJV|Have I committed an offence in abasing myself that ye might be exalted, because I have preached to you the gospel of God freely?
11:7<version name="WYC">Or whether I have done sin, meeking myself [meeking, or<i> making low</i>, myself], that ye be enhanced, for freely I preached to you the gospel of God?</version>
11:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我因為白白傳神的福音給你們，就卑屈自己，為叫你們升高，這是我犯了罪麼？
11:8|ASV|I robbed other churches, taking wages of them that I might minister unto you;
11:8|Darby|I spoiled other assemblies, receiving hire for ministry  towards you.
11:8|KJV|I robbed other churches, taking wages of them, to do you service.
11:8<version name="WYC">I made naked other churches, and I took wages to your service. [I spoiled, <i>or made naked, or took gifts</i>, of other churches, taking wages to your service.]</version>
11:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我剝奪了別的召會，取了工價，為著服事你們。
11:9|ASV|and when I was present with you and was in want, I was not a burden on any man; for the brethren, when they came from Macedonia, supplied the measure of my want; and in everything I kept myself from being burdensome unto you, and so will I keep myself.
11:9|Darby|And being present with you and lacking, I did not lazily  burden any one, (for the brethren who came from Macedonia  supplied what I lacked,) and in everything I kept myself from  being a burden to you, and will keep myself.
11:9|KJV|And when I was present with you, and wanted, I was chargeable to no man: for that which was lacking to me the brethren which came from Macedonia supplied: and in all things I have kept myself from being burdensome unto you, and so will I keep myself.
11:9<version name="WYC">And when I was among you, and had need [And when I was with you, and needed], I was chargeous to no man; for brethren that came from Macedonia, fulfilled that that failed to me [supplied, <i>or fulfilled</i>, that that failed to me].  And in all things I have kept [me], and shall keep me without charge to you.</version>
11:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在你們那裡缺乏的時候，並沒有累著你們一個人，因我所缺乏的，那從馬其頓來的弟兄們都補足了。我向來凡事自守，不累著你們，將來也必自守。
11:10|ASV|As the truth of Christ is in me, no man shall stop me of this glorying in the regions of Achaia.
11:10|Darby|[The] truth of Christ is in me that this boasting shall  not be stopped as to me in the regions of Achaia.
11:10|KJV|As the truth of Christ is in me, no man shall stop me of this boasting in the regions of Achaia.
11:10<version name="WYC">The truth of Christ is in me; for this glory shall not be broken in me in the countries of Achaia [in the regions, <i>or countries</i>, of Achaia].</version>
11:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|基督的真實在我裡面，這誇口在亞該亞一帶，是不會在我身上被堵住的。
11:11|ASV|Wherefore? because I love you not? God knoweth.
11:11|Darby|Why? because I do not love you? God knows.
11:11|KJV|Wherefore? because I love you not? God knoweth.
11:11|WYC|Why? for I love not you?  God knoweth.
11:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|為甚麼？是因我不愛你們麼？神曉得。
11:12|ASV|But what I do, that I will do, that I may cut off occasion from them that desire an occasion; that wherein they glory, they may be found even as we.
11:12|Darby|But what I do, I will also do, that I may cut off the  opportunity of those wishing [for] an opportunity, that wherein  they boast they may be found even as we.
11:12|KJV|But what I do, that I will do, that I may cut off occasion from them which desire occasion; that wherein they glory, they may be found even as we.
11:12<version name="WYC">For that that I do, and that I shall do, <i>is</i> that I cut away the occasion of them that will occasion, that in the thing, in which they glory, they be found [such] as we.</version>
11:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我現在所作的，將來還要作，為要斷絕那些要得機會者的機會，使他們在所誇的事上，給人看出也不過與我們一樣。
11:13|ASV|For such men are false apostles, deceitful workers, fashioning themselves into apostles of Christ.
11:13|Darby|For such [are] false apostles, deceitful workers,  transforming themselves into apostles of Christ.
11:13|KJV|For such are false apostles, deceitful workers, transforming themselves into the apostles of Christ.
11:13<version name="WYC">For such false apostles be treacherous workmen, and transfigure them(selves) into apostles of Christ. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22020b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
11:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那等人是假使徒，是詭詐的工人，裝作基督的使徒。
11:14|ASV|And no marvel; for even Satan fashioneth himself into an angel of light.
11:14|Darby|And [it is] not wonderful, for Satan himself transforms  himself into an angel of light.
11:14|KJV|And no marvel; for Satan himself is transformed into an angel of light.
11:14|WYC|And no wonder, for Satan himself transfigureth him(self) into an angel of light. [And no wonder; soothly he Satan transfigured him into an angel of light.]
11:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這並不希奇，因為撒但自己也裝作光的使者。
11:15|ASV|It is no great thing therefore if his ministers also fashion themselves as ministers of righteousness, whose end shall be according to their works.
11:15|Darby|It is no great thing therefore if his ministers also  transform themselves as ministers of righteousness; whose end  shall be according to their works.
11:15|KJV|Therefore it is no great thing if his ministers also be transformed as the ministers of righteousness; whose end shall be according to their works.
11:15|WYC|Therefore it is not great, if his ministers be transfigured as the ministers of rightwiseness, whose end shall be after their works.
11:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以他的差役若也裝作義的差役，並不算大事，他們的結局，必然照著他們所作的。
11:16|ASV|I say again, let no man think me foolish; but if ye do, yet as foolish receive me, that I also may glory a little.
11:16|Darby|Again I say, Let not any one think me to be a fool; but if  otherwise, receive me then even as a fool, that *I* also may  boast myself some little.
11:16|KJV|I say again, let no man think me a fool; if otherwise, yet as a fool receive me, that I may boast myself a little.
11:16|WYC|Again I say, lest any man guess me to be unwise [lest any man deem me unwise]; else take ye me as unwise, that also I have glory a little what.
11:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我再說，人不可把我看作愚妄的；縱然如此，也要把我當作愚妄人接納，叫我也可以略略誇口。
11:17|ASV|That which I speak, I speak not after the Lord, but as in foolishness, in this confidence of glorying.
11:17|Darby|What I speak I do not speak according to [the] Lord, but  as in folly, in this confidence of boasting.
11:17|KJV|That which I speak, I speak it not after the Lord, but as it were foolishly, in this confidence of boasting.
11:17|WYC|That that I speak, I speak not after God, but as in unwisdom [but as to unwisdom], in this substance of glory.
11:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我所說的，不是照著主說的，乃像在愚妄中，因自信而這樣誇口。
11:18|ASV|Seeing that many glory after the flesh, I will glory also.
11:18|Darby|Since many boast according to flesh, *I* also will boast.
11:18|KJV|Seeing that many glory after the flesh, I will glory also.
11:18|WYC|For many men glory after the flesh, and I shall glory.
11:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|既有好些人照著肉體誇口，我也要誇口，
11:19|ASV|For ye bear with the foolish gladly, being wise yourselves.
11:19|Darby|For ye bear fools readily, being wise.
11:19|KJV|For ye suffer fools gladly, seeing ye yourselves are wise.
11:19|WYC|For ye suffer gladly unwise men, when ye yourselves be wise.
11:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因你們是精明人，喜歡容忍愚妄人。
11:20|ASV|For ye bear with a man, if he bringeth you into bondage, if he devoureth you, if he taketh you captive , if he exalteth himself, if he smiteth you on the face.
11:20|Darby|For ye bear if any one bring you into bondage, if any one  devour [you], if any one get [your money], if any one exalt  himself, if any one beat you on the face.
11:20|KJV|For ye suffer, if a man bring you into bondage, if a man devour you, if a man take of you, if a man exalt himself, if a man smite you on the face.
11:20<version name="WYC">For ye suffer, if any man driveth you into servage [if any man drive you into servage], if any man devoureth, if any man taketh, if any man is enhanced [<i>by pride</i>], if any man smiteth you on the face.</version>
11:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若有人強制你們作奴隸，若有人侵吞你們，若有人擄掠你們，若有人高舉自己，若有人打你們的臉，你們都會容忍！
11:21|ASV|I speak by way of disparagement, as though we had been weak. Yet whereinsoever any is bold (I speak in foolishness), I am bold also.
11:21|Darby|I speak as to dishonour, as though *we* had been weak; but  wherein any one is daring, (I speak in folly,) *I* also am  daring.
11:21|KJV|I speak as concerning reproach, as though we had been weak. Howbeit whereinsoever any is bold, (I speak foolishly,) I am bold also.
11:21<version name="WYC">By unnobleness I say, as if we were frail in this part <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22028c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup>.  In what thing any man dare, in unwisdom I say, and I dare.</version>
11:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我自賤的說，我們從前太軟弱了！然而，我愚妄的說，人在何事上勇敢，我也勇敢。
11:22|ASV|Are they Hebrews? so am I. Are they Israelites? so am I. Are they the seed of Abraham? so am I.
11:22|Darby|Are they Hebrews? *I* also. Are they Israelites? *I* also.  Are they seed of Abraham? *I* also.
11:22|KJV|Are they Hebrews? so am I. Are they Israelites? so am I. Are they the seed of Abraham? so am I.
11:22|WYC|They be Hebrews, and I; they be Israelites, and I; they be the seed of Abraham, and I;
11:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們是希伯來人麼？我也是。他們是以色列人麼？我也是。他們是亞伯拉罕的後裔麼？我也是。
11:23|ASV|Are they ministers of Christ? (I speak as one beside himself) I more; in labors more abundantly, in prisons more abundantly, in stripes above measure, in deaths oft.
11:23|Darby|Are they ministers of Christ? (I speak as being beside  myself) *I* above measure [so]; in labours exceedingly  abundant, in stripes to excess, in prisons exceedingly  abundant, in deaths oft.
11:23|KJV|Are they ministers of Christ? (I speak as a fool) I am more; in labours more abundant, in stripes above measure, in prisons more frequent, in deaths oft.
11:23<version name="WYC">they be the ministers of Christ, and I.  As less wise I say, I more; in full many travails, in prisons more plenteously, in wounds above manner [in wounds above manner, <i>or over measure</i>], in deaths oft times.</version>
11:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們是基督的執事麼？我瘋狂的說，我更是！論勞苦，是更多的；論下監，是更多的；論鞭打，是過重的；論冒死，是屢次有的。
11:24|ASV|Of the Jews five times received I forty  stripes save one.
11:24|Darby|From the Jews five times have I received forty [stripes],  save one.
11:24|KJV|Of the Jews five times received I forty stripes save one.
11:24<version name="WYC">I received of the Jews five times forty <i>strokes</i> one less;</version>
11:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我給猶太人鞭打五次，每次四十，減去一下；
11:25|ASV|Thrice was I beaten with rods, once was I stoned, thrice I suffered shipwreck, a night and a day have I been in the deep;
11:25|Darby|Thrice have I been scourged, once I have been stoned,  three times I have suffered shipwreck, a night and day I passed  in the deep:
11:25|KJV|Thrice was I beaten with rods, once was I stoned, thrice I suffered shipwreck, a night and a day I have been in the deep;
11:25|WYC|thrice I was beaten with rods, once I was stoned, thrice I was at ship-break, a night and a day I was in the deepness of the sea;
11:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|給棍打了三次，給石頭打了一次，遇著船壞三次，在深海裡過了一晝一夜；
11:26|ASV|in journeyings often,  in perils of rivers, in perils of robbers, in perils from  my countrymen, in perils from the Gentiles, in perils in the city, in perils in the wilderness, in perils in the sea, in perils among false brethren;
11:26|Darby|in journeyings often, in perils of rivers, in perils of  robbers, in perils from [my own] race, in perils from [the]  nations, in perils in [the] city, in perils in [the] desert, in  perils on [the] sea, in perils among false brethren;
11:26|KJV|In journeyings often, in perils of waters, in perils of robbers, in perils by mine own countrymen, in perils by the heathen, in perils in the city, in perils in the wilderness, in perils in the sea, in perils among false brethren;
11:26|WYC|in ways oft, in perils of rivers [in perils of floods], in perils of thieves, in perils of kin, in perils of heathen men, in perils in [the] city, in perils in desert, in perils in the sea, in perils among false brethren,
11:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|屢次行遠路，遭江河的危險、盜賊的危險、同族的危險、外邦人的危險、城裡的危險、曠野的危險、海中的危險、假弟兄中的危險；
11:27|ASV|in labor and travail, in watchings often, in hunger and thirst, in fastings often, in cold and nakedness.
11:27|Darby|in labour and toil, in watchings often, in hunger and  thirst, in fastings often, in cold and nakedness.
11:27|KJV|In weariness and painfulness, in watchings often, in hunger and thirst, in fastings often, in cold and nakedness.
11:27<version name="WYC">in travail and neediness, in many wakings, in hunger, in thirst [in travail and neediness, <i>either mis-ease</i>, in many wakings, in hunger and thirst], in many fastings, in cold and nakedness.</version>
11:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|勞碌辛苦，論儆醒，是多次的；論飢渴、論不食，是多次的；論寒冷和赤身─
11:28|ASV|Besides those things that are without, there is that which presseth upon me daily, anxiety for all the churches.
11:28|Darby|Besides those things that are without, the crowd [of  cares] pressing on me daily, the burden of all the assemblies.
11:28|KJV|Beside those things that are without, that which cometh upon me daily, the care of all the churches.
11:28<version name="WYC">Without those things that be withoutforth, mine each day's travailing <i>is </i>the busyness of all churches. [Without those things that be withoutforth; mine each day's waking, <i>or studying</i>, the busyness of all churches.]</version>
11:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|除了沒有題起的事，還有為眾召會的罣慮，天天壓在我身上。
11:29|ASV|Who is weak, and I am not weak? who is caused to stumble, and I burn not?
11:29|Darby|Who is weak, and I am not weak? Who is stumbled, and I  burn not?
11:29|KJV|Who is weak, and I am not weak? who is offended, and I burn not?
11:29|WYC|Who is frail, and I am not frail? who is caused to stumble, and I am not burnt? [Who is sick, and I am not sick? who is offended, and I am not burnt?]
11:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有誰軟弱，我不軟弱？有誰絆跌，我不焦急？
11:30|ASV|If I must needs glory, I will glory of the things that concern my weakness.
11:30|Darby|If it is needful to boast, I will boast in the things  which concern my infirmity.
11:30|KJV|If I must needs glory, I will glory of the things which concern mine infirmities.
11:30<version name="WYC">If it behooveth to glory, I shall glory <i>in those things </i>that be of mine infirmity [that be of my infirmity, <i>or  frailty</i>].</version>
11:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我若必須誇口，就要誇我軟弱的事。
11:31|ASV|The God and Father of the Lord Jesus, he who is blessed for evermore knoweth that I lie not.
11:31|Darby|The God and Father of the Lord Jesus knows -- he who is  blessed for ever -- that I do not lie.
11:31|KJV|The God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, which is blessed for evermore, knoweth that I lie not.
11:31<version name="WYC">[For] God and the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, that is blessed into worlds, knoweth that I lie not [knoweth, that I <i>gab not</i>, <i>or</i> lie not].</version>
11:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主耶穌的神與父，就是那當受頌讚直到永遠的，知道我不說謊。
11:32|ASV|In Damascus the governor under Aretas the king guarded the city of the Damascenes in order to take me:
11:32|Darby|In Damascus the ethnarch of Aretas the king kept the city  of the Damascenes shut up, wishing to take me;
11:32|KJV|In Damascus the governor under Aretas the king kept the city of the damascenes with a garrison, desirous to apprehend me:
11:32<version name="WYC">The provost of Damascus, of the king of the folk of Aretas [The provost, <i>or</i> <i>keeper</i>, of Damascus, of the king of the folk Arteas], kept the city of Damascenes to take me;</version>
11:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在大馬色，亞哩達王手下的提督，把守大馬色人的城，要捉拿我，
11:33<version name="ASV">and through a window was I let down in a basket by the wall, and escaped his hands. </p><p /><br /></version>
11:33<version name="Darby">and through a window in a basket I was let down by the  wall, and escaped his hands. </p><p /><br /></version>
11:33<version name="KJV">And through a window in a basket was I let down by the wall, and escaped his hands.</p><p /><br /></version>
11:33|WYC|and by a window in a basket I was let down by the wall, and so I escaped his hands.
11:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我就從窗戶中，在筐子裡給人從城牆上縋下去，逃脫了他的手。
12:1|ASV|I must needs glory, though it is not expedient; but I will come to visions and revelations of the Lord.
12:1|Darby|Well, it is not of profit to me to boast, for I will come  to visions and revelations of [the] Lord.
12:1|KJV|It is not expedient for me doubtless to glory. I will come to visions and revelations of the Lord.
12:1|WYC|If it behooveth to have glory, it speedeth not; but I shall come to the visions and the revelations of the Lord. [If it behooveth to glory, soothly it speedeth not; forsooth I shall come to the visions and revelations of the Lord.]
12:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|誇口固然無益，但我是不得已的。我要來說主的異象和啟示。
12:2|ASV|I know a man in Christ, fourteen years ago (whether in the body, I know not; or whether out of the body, I know not; God knoweth), such a one caught up even to the third heaven.
12:2|Darby|I know a man in Christ, fourteen years ago, (whether in  [the] body I know not, or out of the body I know not, God  knows;) such [a one] caught up to [the] third heaven.
12:2|KJV|I knew a man in Christ above fourteen years ago, (whether in the body, I cannot tell; or whether out of the body, I cannot tell: God knoweth;) such an one caught up to the third heaven.
12:2|WYC|I know a man in Christ that before fourteen years; whether in body, whether out of body, I know not, God knoweth; that such a man was snatched (up) unto the third heaven [such a man snatched (up) till to the third heaven].
12:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我認得一個在基督裡的人，十四年前，這樣的一位被提，直到第三層天裡，（或在身內，我不曉得，或在身外，我也不曉得，只有神曉得。）
12:3|ASV|And I know such a man (whether in the body, or apart from the body, I know not; God knoweth),
12:3|Darby|And I know such a man, (whether in [the] body or out of the  body I know not, God knows;)
12:3|KJV|And I knew such a man, (whether in the body, or out of the body, I cannot tell: God knoweth;)
12:3|WYC|And I know such a man; whether in body, or out of body, I know not, God knoweth;
12:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且我認得這樣一個人，（或在身內，或在身外，我都不曉得，只有神曉得，）
12:4|ASV|how that he was caught up into Paradise, and heard unspeakable words, which it is not lawful for a man to utter.
12:4|Darby|that he was caught up into paradise, and heard unspeakable  things said which it is not allowed to man to utter.
12:4|KJV|How that he was caught up into paradise, and heard unspeakable words, which it is not lawful for a man to utter.
12:4|WYC|that he was snatched (up) into paradise, and heard privy words, which it is not leaveful to a man [for] to speak.
12:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他被提進樂園裡，聽見不能言傳的話語，是人不可說的。
12:5|ASV|On behalf of such a one will I glory: but on mine own behalf I will not glory, save in my weaknesses.
12:5|Darby|Of such [a one] I will boast, but of myself I will not  boast, unless in my weaknesses.
12:5|KJV|Of such an one will I glory: yet of myself I will not glory, but in mine infirmities.
12:5|WYC|For such manner things I shall glory [For such manner thing I shall glory]; but for me nothing, but in mine infirmities.
12:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|為這樣的一位，我要誇口，但是為我自己，除了我的軟弱以外，我並不誇口。
12:6|ASV|For if I should desire to glory, I shall not be foolish; for I shall speak the truth: but I forbear, lest any man should account of me above that which he seeth me to be, or heareth from me.
12:6|Darby|For if I shall desire to boast, I shall not be a fool; for  I will say [the] truth; but I forbear, lest any one should  think as to me above what he sees me [to be], or whatever he  may hear of me.
12:6|KJV|For though I would desire to glory, I shall not be a fool; for I will say the truth: but now I forbear, lest any man should think of me above that which he seeth me to be, or that he heareth of me.
12:6|WYC|For if I shall desire to glory [For why and if I shall will to glory], I shall not be unwise, for I shall say truth; but I spare, lest any man guess me over that thing that he seeth in me, or heareth any thing of me.
12:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我即使願意誇口，也不是愚妄，因為我必說真話，只是我惜口不說，恐怕有人評估我，過於他在我身上所看見的，或從我所聽見的。
12:7|ASV|And by reason of the exceeding greatness of the revelations, that I should not be exalted overmuch, there was given to me a thorn in the flesh, a messenger of Satan to buffet me, that I should not be exalted overmuch.
12:7|Darby|And that I might not be exalted by the exceeding greatness  of the revelations, there was given to me a thorn for the  flesh, a messenger of Satan that he might buffet me, that I  might not be exalted.
12:7|KJV|And lest I should be exalted above measure through the abundance of the revelations, there was given to me a thorn in the flesh, the messenger of Satan to buffet me, lest I should be exalted above measure.
12:7<version name="WYC">And lest the greatness of revelations enhance me <i>in pride</i>, the prick of my flesh, an angel of Satan, is given to me, that he buffet me.</version>
12:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又恐怕我因所得啟示的超越，就過於高抬自己，所以有一根刺，就是撒但的使者，加在我的肉體上，為要攻擊我，免得我過於高抬自己。
12:8|ASV|Concerning this thing I besought the Lord thrice, that it might depart from me.
12:8|Darby|For this I thrice besought the Lord that it might depart  from me.
12:8|KJV|For this thing I besought the Lord thrice, that it might depart from me.
12:8|WYC|For which thing thrice I prayed the Lord, that it should go away from me.
12:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|為這事，我三次求過主，叫這刺離開我。
12:9|ASV|And he hath said unto me, My grace is sufficient for thee: for my power is made perfect in weakness. Most gladly therefore will I rather glory in my weaknesses, that the power of Christ may rest upon me.
12:9|Darby|And he said to me, My grace suffices thee; for [my] power  is perfected in weakness. Most gladly therefore will I rather  boast in my weaknesses, that the power of the Christ may dwell  upon me.
12:9|KJV|And he said unto me, My grace is sufficient for thee: for my strength is made perfect in weakness. Most gladly therefore will I rather glory in my infirmities, that the power of Christ may rest upon me.
12:9|WYC|And he said to me, My grace sufficeth to thee; for virtue is perfectly made in infirmity.  Therefore gladly I shall glory in mine infirmities, that the virtue of Christ dwell in me.
12:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂對我說，我的恩典彀你用的，因為我的能力，是在人的軟弱上顯得完全。所以我極其喜歡誇我的軟弱，好叫基督的能力覆庇我。
12:10|ASV|Wherefore I take pleasure in weaknesses, in injuries, in necessities, in persecutions, in distresses, for Christ's sake: for when I am weak, then am I strong.
12:10|Darby|Wherefore I take pleasure in weaknesses, in insults, in  necessities, in persecutions, in straits, for Christ: for when  I am weak, then I am powerful.
12:10|KJV|Therefore I take pleasure in infirmities, in reproaches, in necessities, in persecutions, in distresses for Christ's sake: for when I am weak, then am I strong.
12:10<version name="WYC">For which thing I am pleased in mine infirmities, in despisings [in wrong despisings, <i>or reprovings</i>], in needs, in persecutions, in anguishes, for Christ; for when I am frail [for when I am sick], then I am mighty.</version>
12:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此，我為基督的緣故，就以軟弱、凌辱、貧困、逼迫、困苦為可喜悅的，因我甚麼時候軟弱，甚麼時候就有能力了。
12:11|ASV|I am become foolish: ye compelled me; for I ought to have been commended of you: for in nothing was I behind the very chiefest apostles, though I am nothing.
12:11|Darby|I have become a fool; *ye* have compelled me; for *I*  ought to have been commended by you; for I have been nothing  behind those who were in surpassing degree apostles, if also I  am nothing.
12:11|KJV|I am become a fool in glorying; ye have compelled me: for I ought to have been commended of you: for in nothing am I behind the very chiefest apostles, though I be nothing.
12:11|WYC|I am made witless [I am made unwitty], ye constrained me.  For I ought to be commended of you; for I did nothing less than they that be apostles over measure.  Though I am nought [Though I be nought],
12:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我成了愚妄人，是你們強逼我的。我本該為你們所推薦，因為我即使算不了甚麼，也沒有一點趕不上那些超級的使徒。
12:12|ASV|Truly the signs of an apostle were wrought among you in all patience, by signs and wonders and mighty works.
12:12|Darby|The signs indeed of the apostle were wrought among you in  all endurance, signs, and wonders, and works of power.
12:12|KJV|Truly the signs of an apostle were wrought among you in all patience, in signs, and wonders, and mighty deeds.
12:12<version name="WYC">nevertheless the signs of mine apostlehood be made on you, in all patience, and signs, and great wonders, and works of power. [nevertheless the signs of my apostlehood be made on you, in all patience, and signs, <i>or miracles</i>, and great wonders, and virtues.]</version>
12:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我使徒的記號，確已在你們中間，以全般的忍耐，藉著神蹟、奇事和異能，完全顯出來了。
12:13|ASV|For what is there wherein ye were made inferior to the rest of the churches, except it be that I myself was not a burden to you? forgive me this wrong.
12:13|Darby|For in what is it that ye have been inferior to the other  assemblies, unless that I myself have not been in laziness a  charge upon you? Forgive me this injury.
12:13|KJV|For what is it wherein ye were inferior to other churches, except it be that I myself was not burdensome to you? forgive me this wrong.
12:13|WYC|And what is it, that ye had less than other churches [that ye had less before other churches], [no] but that I myself grieved you not?  Forgive ye to me this wrong.
12:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為除了我自己不累著你們以外，你們還有甚麼事不及其餘的召會？這不公之處，你們饒恕我罷！
12:14|ASV|Behold, this is the third time I am ready to come to you; and I will not be a burden to you: for I seek not yours, but you: for the children ought not to lay up for the parents, but the parents for the children.
12:14|Darby|Behold, this third time I am ready to come to you, and I  will not be in laziness a charge; for I do not seek yours, but  you; for the children ought not to lay up for the parents, but  the parents for the children.
12:14|KJV|Behold, the third time I am ready to come to you; and I will not be burdensome to you: for I seek not yours but you: for the children ought not to lay up for the parents, but the parents for the children.
12:14<version name="WYC">Lo! this third time I am ready to come to you, and I shall not be grievous to you; for I seek not those things that be yours, but you.  For neither sons owe to [<i>make</i>] treasure to father and mother, but the father and mother to the sons.</version>
12:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|看哪，這是我第三次豫備好，要到你們那裡去，也必不累著你們，因我所尋求的不是你們的東西，乃是你們自己。因為兒女不該為父母積蓄，父母乃該為兒女積蓄。
12:15|ASV|And I will most gladly spend and be spent for your souls. If I love you more abundantly, am I loved the less?
12:15|Darby|Now *I* shall most gladly spend and be utterly spent for  your souls, if even in abundantly loving you I should be less  loved.
12:15|KJV|And I will very gladly spend and be spent for you; though the more abundantly I love you, the less I be loved.
12:15|WYC|For I shall give most willfully [For I most willfully shall give], and I myself shall be given over for your souls; though I more love you, and be less loved.
12:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我極其喜歡為你們花費，並完全花上自己。難道我越發愛你們，就越發少得你們的愛麼？
12:16|ASV|But be it so, I did not myself burden you; but, being crafty, I caught you with guile.
12:16|Darby|But be it so. *I* did not burden you, but being crafty I  took you by guile.
12:16|KJV|But be it so, I did not burden you: nevertheless, being crafty, I caught you with guile.
12:16<version name="WYC">But be it; I grieved not you, but when I was subtle <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22056a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>, I took you with guile.</version>
12:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|罷了！我並沒有加給你們擔子，你們卻有人說，我是狡猾詭詐，用詭計牢籠你們。
12:17|ASV|Did I take advantage of you by any one of them whom I have sent unto you?
12:17|Darby|Did I make gain of you by any of those whom I have sent to  you?
12:17|KJV|Did I make a gain of you by any of them whom I sent unto you?
12:17|WYC|Whether I deceived you by any of them, which I sent to you [whom I sent to you]?
12:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我所差到你們那裡去的人，我藉著其中一個佔過你們的便宜麼？
12:18|ASV|I exhorted Titus, and I sent the brother with him. Did Titus take any advantage of you? walked we not in the same spirit? walked we not in the same steps?
12:18|Darby|I begged Titus, and sent the brother with [him]: did Titus  at all make gain of you? have we not walked in the same spirit?  [have we] not in the same steps?
12:18|KJV|I desired Titus, and with him I sent a brother. Did Titus make a gain of you? walked we not in the same spirit? walked we not in the same steps?
12:18|WYC|I prayed Titus, and I sent with him a brother.  Whether Titus beguiled you? whether we went not in the same spirit? whether not in the same steps?
12:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我勸了提多，又差了那位弟兄同去。提多佔過你們的便宜麼？我們行事，不是在同一的靈裡麼？不是在同一的腳蹤裡麼？
12:19|ASV|Ye think all this time that we are excusing ourselves unto you. In the sight of God speak we in Christ. But all things, beloved, are for your edifying.
12:19|Darby|Ye have long been supposing that we excuse ourselves to  you: we speak before God in Christ; and all things, beloved,  for your building up.
12:19|KJV|Again, think ye that we excuse ourselves unto you? we speak before God in Christ: but we do all things, dearly beloved, for your edifying.
12:19|WYC|Sometime ye ween, that we shall excuse us with you.  Before God in Christ we speak; and, most dear brethren [forsooth, most dear brethren], all things for your edifying.
12:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們一向以為我們是向你們分訴，我們乃是在基督裡當著神面前說話。親愛的，一切的事都是為建造你們。
12:20|ASV|For I fear, lest by any means, when I come, I should find you not such as I would, and should myself be found of you such as ye would not; lest by any means there should be strife, jealousy, wraths, factions, backbitings, whisperings, swellings, tumults;
12:20|Darby|For I fear lest perhaps coming I find you not such as I  wish, and that *I* be found by you such as ye do not wish: lest  [there might be] strifes, jealousies, angers, contentions, evil  speakings, whisperings, puffings up, disturbances;
12:20|KJV|For I fear, lest, when I come, I shall not find you such as I would, and that I shall be found unto you such as ye would not: lest there be debates, envyings, wraths, strifes, backbitings, whisperings, swellings, tumults:
12:20<version name="WYC">But I dread, lest when I come, I shall not find you such as I will, and I shall be found of you such as ye will not; lest peradventure strivings, envies, indignations [sturdinesses], dissensions and detractions, privy speeches of discord, swellings <i>by pride</i>, debates be among you;</version>
12:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我怕我來的時候，或許見到你們不合我所想要的，你們見到我也不合你們所想要的；又怕有爭競、嫉妒、惱怒、私圖好爭、誹謗、讒言、自高自大、混亂的事；
12:21<version name="ASV">lest again when I come my God should humble me before you, and I should mourn for many of them that have sinned heretofore, and repented not of the uncleanness and fornication and lasciviousness which they committed. </p><p /><br /></version>
12:21<version name="Darby">lest my God should humble me as to you when I come again,  and that I shall grieve over many of those who have sinned  before, and have not repented as to the uncleanness and  fornication and licentiousness which they have practised. </p><p /><br /></version>
12:21<version name="KJV">And lest, when I come again, my God will humble me among you, and that I shall bewail many which have sinned already, and have not repented of the uncleanness and fornication and lasciviousness which they have committed.</p><p /><br /></version>
12:21<version name="WYC"><i>and</i> lest again when I come, God make me low with you, and I bewail many of them, that before sinned, and did not penance on the uncleanness, and fornication, and unchastity, that they have done. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22061b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
12:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|且怕我再來的時候，我的神在你們面前卑屈我，我還要為那許多從前犯罪，還沒有悔改他們所行污穢淫亂邪蕩之事的人哀慟。
13:1|ASV|This is the third time I am coming to you. At the mouth of two witnesses or three shall every word established.
13:1|Darby|This third time I am coming to you. In the mouth of two or  three witnesses shall every matter be established.
13:1|KJV|This is the third time I am coming to you. In the mouth of two or three witnesses shall every word be established.
13:1|WYC|Lo! this third time I come to you, and in the mouth of two or of three witnesses [and in the mouth of two or three witnesses] every word shall stand.
13:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這是我第三次要到你們那裡去，憑兩三個見證人的口，句句都要定準。
13:2|ASV|I have said beforehand, and I do say beforehand, as when I was present the second time, so now, being absent, to them that have sinned heretofore, and to all the rest, that, if I come again, I will not spare;
13:2|Darby|I have declared beforehand, and I say beforehand as present  the second time, and now absent, to those that have sinned  before, and to all the rest, that if I come again I will not  spare.
13:2|KJV|I told you before, and foretell you, as if I were present, the second time; and being absent now I write to them which heretofore have sinned, and to all other, that, if I come again, I will not spare:
13:2|WYC|I said before, and [I] say before, as present twice, and now absent, to them that before have sinned, and to all others; for if I come again, I shall not spare.
13:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我從前說過，現今不在的時候，事先又對那些從前犯了罪的，和所有其餘的人說，正如我第二次同在的時候所說的；我若再來，必不寬容，
13:3|ASV|seeing that ye seek a proof of Christ that speaketh in me; who to you-ward is not weak, but is powerful in you:
13:3|Darby|Since ye seek a proof of Christ speaking in me, (who is not  weak towards you, but is powerful among you,
13:3|KJV|Since ye seek a proof of Christ speaking in me, which to you-ward is not weak, but is mighty in you.
13:3<version name="WYC">Whether ye seek the proof of that Christ, that speaketh in me, which is not feeble in you, [but is mighty in you]? <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22064a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
13:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為你們尋求基督在我裡面說話的憑證。基督向著你們不是軟弱的，在你們裡面乃是有大能的。
13:4|ASV|for he was crucified through weakness, yet he liveth through the power of God. For we also are weak in him, but we shall live with him through the power of God toward you.
13:4|Darby|for if indeed he has been crucified in weakness, yet he  lives by God's power; for indeed *we* are weak in him, but we  shall live with him by God's power towards you,)
13:4|KJV|For though he was crucified through weakness, yet he liveth by the power of God. For we also are weak in him, but we shall live with him by the power of God toward you.
13:4|WYC|For though he was crucified of infirmity, but he liveth of the virtue of God.  For also we be frail in him [For why and we be sick in him], but we shall live with him of the virtue of God in us.
13:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂固然由於軟弱被釘十字架，卻由於神的大能仍然活著。我們在祂裡面也是軟弱，但由於神向著你們的大能，必與祂同活。
13:5|ASV|Try your own selves, whether ye are in the faith; prove your own selves. Or know ye not as to your own selves, that Jesus Christ is in you? unless indeed ye be reprobate.
13:5|Darby|examine your own selves if ye be in the faith; prove your  own selves: do ye not recognise yourselves, that Jesus Christ  is in you, unless indeed ye be reprobates?
13:5|KJV|Examine yourselves, whether ye be in the faith; prove your own selves. Know ye not your own selves, how that Jesus Christ is in you, except ye be reprobates?
13:5|WYC|Assay yourselves, if ye be in the faith; ye yourselves prove.  Whether ye know not yourselves, for Christ Jesus is in you? but (it) happens ye be reprovable [no but peradventure, ye be reprovable].
13:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要試驗自己是否在信仰中；你們要驗證自己。豈不知你們有耶穌基督在你們裡面麼？除非你們是經不起試驗的。
13:6|ASV|But I hope that ye shall know that we are not reprobate.
13:6|Darby|Now I hope that ye will know that *we* are not reprobates.
13:6|KJV|But I trust that ye shall know that we are not reprobates.
13:6|WYC|But I hope, that ye know, that we be not reprovable.
13:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我卻盼望你們曉得，我們不是經不起試驗的。
13:7|ASV|Now we pray to God that ye do no evil; not that we may appear approved, but that ye may do that which is honorable, though we be as reprobate.
13:7|Darby|But we pray to God that ye may do nothing evil; not that  *we* may appear approved, but that *ye* may do what is right,  and *we* be as reprobates.
13:7|KJV|Now I pray to God that ye do no evil; not that we should appear approved, but that ye should do that which is honest, though we be as reprobates.
13:7|WYC|And we pray the Lord, that ye do nothing of evil; not that we seem approved [not that we seem proved], but that ye do that that is good, and that we be as reprovable.
13:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們求神，叫你們一件惡事都不作。這不是要顯明我們是經得起試驗的，乃是要你們行善，讓我們就像是經不起試驗的罷！
13:8|ASV|For we can do nothing against the truth, but for the truth.
13:8|Darby|For we can do nothing against the truth, but for the truth.
13:8|KJV|For we can do nothing against the truth, but for the truth.
13:8|WYC|For we be able to do nothing against truth, but for the truth. [Forsooth we may do nothing against the truth, but for the truth.]
13:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們不能作任何事抵擋真理，只能擁護真理。
13:9|ASV|For we rejoice, when we are weak, and ye are strong: this we also pray for, even your perfecting.
13:9|Darby|For we rejoice when *we* may be weak and *ye* may be  powerful. But this also we pray for, your perfecting.
13:9|KJV|For we are glad, when we are weak, and ye are strong: and this also we wish, even your perfection.
13:9|WYC|For we joy, when we be frail [when we be sick], but ye be mighty; and we pray this thing, your perfection.
13:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|無論何時我們軟弱，你們有能力，我們就喜樂了；我們還祈求一件事，就是你們被成全。
13:10|ASV|For this cause I write these things while absent, that I may not when present deal sharply, according to the authority which the Lord gave me for building up, and not for casting down.
13:10|Darby|On this account I write these things being absent, that  being present I may not use severity according to the authority  which the Lord has given me for building up, and not for  overthrowing.
13:10|KJV|Therefore I write these things being absent, lest being present I should use sharpness, according to the power which the Lord hath given me to edification, and not to destruction.
13:10<version name="WYC">Therefore I absent write these things, that I present do not harder, by the power, which the Lord gave to me into edification, and not into <i>your</i> destruction <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22071b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup>.</version>
13:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我不在的時候，寫這些事，好叫我同在的時候，不必照著主所賜給我的權柄，嚴厲的待你們；這權柄是為著建造人，並不是為著拆毀人。
13:11|ASV|Finally, brethren, farewell. Be perfected; be comforted; be of the same mind; live in peace: and the God of love and peace shall be with you.
13:11|Darby|For the rest, brethren, rejoice; be perfected; be  encouraged; be of one mind; be at peace; and the God of love  and peace shall be with you.
13:11|KJV|Finally, brethren, farewell. Be perfect, be of good comfort, be of one mind, live in peace; and the God of love and peace shall be with you.
13:11|WYC|Brethren, henceforward joy ye, be ye perfect, excite ye [be ye perfect, and teach ye]; understand ye the same thing; have ye peace, and God of peace and of love shall be with you [and God of peace and love shall be with you].
13:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|末了，弟兄們，要喜樂，要被成全，要受安慰，要思念相同的事，要和睦，如此那愛與和平的神，必與你們同在。
13:12|ASV|Salute one another with a holy kiss.
13:12|Darby|Salute one another with a holy kiss.
13:12|KJV|Greet one another with an holy kiss.
13:12|WYC|Greet ye well together in holy kiss.
13:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要用聖別的親嘴彼此問安。
13:13|ASV|All the saints salute you.
13:13|Darby|All the saints salute you.
13:13|KJV|All the saints salute you.
13:13|WYC|All holy men greet you well.
13:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|眾聖徒都問你們安。
13:14<version name="ASV">The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ, and the love of God, and the communion of the Holy Spirit, be with you all. </p><p /><br /></version>
13:14<version name="Darby">The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ, and the love of God,  and the communion of the Holy Spirit, [be] with you all. </p><p /><br /></version>
13:14<version name="KJV">The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ, and the love of God, and the communion of the Holy Ghost, be with you all. Amen.</p><p /><br /></version>
13:14|WYC|The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, and the charity of God, and the communing of the Holy Ghost, be with you all.  Amen.
13:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願主耶穌基督的恩，神的愛，聖靈的交通，與你們眾人同在。
