1:1|ASV|The elder unto the elect lady and her children, whom I love in truth; and not I only, but also all they that know the truth;
1:1|Darby|The elder to [the] elect lady and her children, whom *I*  love in truth, and not *I* only but also all who have known the  truth,
1:1|KJV|The elder unto the elect lady and her children, whom I love in the truth; and not I only, but also all they that have known the truth;
1:1<version name="WYC">The elder <i>man,</i> to the chosen lady [The elder <i>man</i> to the lady Electa], and to her children, which I love in truth; and not I alone, but also all men that know truth [but and all men that knew truth];</version>
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|作長老的寫信給蒙揀選的夫人和她的兒女，就是我真實所愛的；不單我愛，也是一切認識真理之人所愛的；
1:2|ASV|for the truth's sake which abideth in us, and it shall be with us for ever:
1:2|Darby|for the truth's sake which abides in us and shall be with us  to eternity.
1:2|KJV|For the truth's sake, which dwelleth in us, and shall be with us for ever.
1:2|WYC|for the truth that dwelleth in you, and with you shall be without end. [for the truth that dwelleth in you, and with you shall be into without end].
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|愛你們是因真理的緣故，這真理存在我們裡面，也必永遠與我們同在。
1:3|ASV|Grace, mercy, peace shall be with us, from God the Father, and from Jesus Christ, the Son of the Father, in truth and love.
1:3|Darby|Grace shall be with you, mercy, peace from God [the] Father,  and from [the] Lord Jesus Christ, the Son of the Father, in  truth and love.
1:3|KJV|Grace be with you, mercy, and peace, from God the Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ, the Son of the Father, in truth and love.
1:3|WYC|Grace be with you, mercy, and peace of God the Father, and of Jesus Christ, the Son of the Father, in truth and charity.
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|恩典、憐憫、平安從父神，並從父的兒子耶穌基督，在真理和愛中，必與我們同在。
1:4|ASV|I rejoice greatly that I have found certain of thy children walking in truth, even as we received commandment from the Father.
1:4|Darby|I rejoiced greatly that I have found of thy children walking  in truth, as we have received commandment from the Father.
1:4|KJV|I rejoiced greatly that I found of thy children walking in truth, as we have received a commandment from the Father.
1:4|WYC|I joyed full much, for I found of thy sons going in truth, as we received commandment of the Father.
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我看到你的兒女，有照著我們從父所受的誡命，在真理中行事為人的，就大大歡樂。
1:5|ASV|And now I beseech thee, lady, not as though I wrote to thee a new commandment, but that which we had from the beginning, that we love one another.
1:5|Darby|And now I beseech thee, lady, not as writing to thee a new  commandment, but that which we have had from [the] beginning,  that we should love one another.
1:5|KJV|And now I beseech thee, lady, not as though I wrote a new commandment unto thee, but that which we had from the beginning, that we love one another.
1:5|WYC|And now I pray thee, lady, not as writing a new commandment to thee, but that that we had from the beginning, that we love each other.
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|夫人阿，我現在請求你，我們要彼此相愛；我寫給你的並不是一條新誡命，乃是我們從起初就有的誡命。
1:6|ASV|And this is love, that we should walk after his commandments. This is the commandment, even as ye heard from the beginning, that ye should walk in it.
1:6|Darby|And this is love, that we should walk according to his  commandments. This is the commandment, according as ye have  heard from the beginning, that ye might walk in it.
1:6|KJV|And this is love, that we walk after his commandments. This is the commandment, That, as ye have heard from the beginning, ye should walk in it.
1:6|WYC|And this is charity, that we walk after his commandments.  For this is the commandment, that as ye heard at the beginning, walk ye in him.
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們要照祂的誡命行，這就是愛；你們要行在愛中，這就是誡命，正如你們從起初所聽見的。
1:7|ASV|For many deceivers are gone forth into the world, even they that confess not that Jesus Christ cometh in the flesh. This is the deceiver and the antichrist.
1:7|Darby|For many deceivers have gone out into the world, they who do  not confess Jesus Christ coming in flesh -- this is the  deceiver and the antichrist.
1:7|KJV|For many deceivers are entered into the world, who confess not that Jesus Christ is come in the flesh. This is a deceiver and an antichrist.
1:7|WYC|For many deceivers went out into the world, which acknowledge not that Jesus Christ hath come in flesh; this is a deceiver and antichrist.
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為有許多迷惑人的已經出來，進到世界裡，他們不承認耶穌基督是在肉體裡來的。這就是那迷惑人的和敵基督的。
1:8|ASV|Look to yourselves, that ye lose not the things which we have wrought, but that ye receive a full reward.
1:8|Darby|See to yourselves, that we may not lose what we have  wrought, but may receive full wages.
1:8|KJV|Look to yourselves, that we lose not those things which we have wrought, but that we receive a full reward.
1:8|WYC|See ye yourselves, lest ye lose the things that ye have wrought, [but] that ye receive full meed;
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要小心，不要失去我們所已經作成的，乃要得著滿足的賞賜。
1:9|ASV|Whosoever goeth onward and abideth not in the teaching of Christ, hath not God: he that abideth in the teaching, the same hath both the Father and the Son.
1:9|Darby|Whosoever goes forward and abides not in the doctrine of the  Christ has not God. He that abides in the doctrine, *he* has  both the Father and the Son.
1:9|KJV|Whosoever transgresseth, and abideth not in the doctrine of Christ, hath not God. He that abideth in the doctrine of Christ, he hath both the Father and the Son.
1:9<version name="WYC">witting that each man that goeth before [witting that each man that goeth away], and dwelleth not in the teaching of Christ, hath not God.  He that dwelleth in the teaching [<i>of Christ</i>], hath both the Son and the Father.</version>
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡越過基督的教訓，不留於其中的，就沒有神；留於這教訓中的，這人就有父又有子。
1:10|ASV|If any one cometh unto you, and bringeth not this teaching, receive him not into your house, and give him no greeting:
1:10|Darby|If any one come to you and bring not this doctrine, do not  receive him into [the] house, and greet him not;
1:10|KJV|If there come any unto you, and bring not this doctrine, receive him not into your house, neither bid him God speed:
1:10<version name="WYC">If any man cometh to you, and bringeth not this teaching, do not ye receive him into <i>your</i> house, neither say to him, Hail.</version>
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若有人到你們那裡，不是傳講這教訓，不要接他到家裡，也不要對他說，願你喜樂；
1:11|ASV|for he that giveth him greeting partaketh in his evil works.
1:11|Darby|for he who greets him partakes in his wicked works.
1:11|KJV|For he that biddeth him God speed is partaker of his evil deeds.
1:11|WYC|For he that saith to him, Hail, communeth with his evil works.  Lo! I before-said to you, that ye be not confounded in the day of our Lord Jesus Christ.
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為對他說，願你喜樂的，就在他的惡行上有分。
1:12|ASV|Having many things to write unto you, I would not write them with paper and ink: but I hope to come unto you, and to speak face to face, that your joy may be made full.
1:12|Darby|Having many things to write to you, I would not with paper  and ink; but hope to come to you, and to speak mouth to mouth,  that our joy may be full.
1:12|KJV|Having many things to write unto you, I would not write with paper and ink: but I trust to come unto you, and speak face to face, that our joy may be full.
1:12|WYC|I have more things to write to you, and I would not by parchment and ink [I having more things to write to you, would not by parchment and ink]; for I hope that I shall come to you, and speak mouth to mouth, that our joy be full.
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我還有許多事要寫給你們，卻不願意用紙墨寫出來；但盼望到你們那裡，與你們當面交談，使我們的喜樂得以滿足。
1:13<version name="ASV">The children of thine elect sister salute thee. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:13<version name="Darby">The children of thine elect sister greet thee. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:13<version name="KJV">The children of thy elect sister greet thee. Amen.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:13<version name="WYC">The sons of thy chosen sister greet thee well [The sons of thy sister Electa greet thee well].  The grace of God <i>be</i> with thee.  Amen.</version>
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你那蒙揀選之姊妹的兒女都問你安。
