1:1|ASV|Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus through the will of God, according to the promise of the life which is in Christ Jesus,
1:1|Darby|Paul, apostle of Jesus Christ by God's will, according to  promise of life, the [life] which [is] in Christ Jesus,
1:1|KJV|Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God, according to the promise of life which is in Christ Jesus,
1:1|WYC|Paul, [the] apostle of Jesus Christ, by the will of God, by the promise of life [after the promise of life] that is in Christ Jesus,
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|憑神旨意，照著在基督耶穌裡生命的應許，作基督耶穌使徒的保羅，
1:2|ASV|to Timothy, my beloved child: Grace, mercy, peace, from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.
1:2|Darby|to Timotheus, [my] beloved child: grace, mercy, peace, from  God [the] Father, and Christ Jesus our Lord.
1:2|KJV|To Timothy, my dearly beloved son: Grace, mercy, and peace, from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.
1:2|WYC|to Timothy, his most dear-worthy son, grace, mercy, and peace of God the Father, and of Jesus Christ, our Lord [and Jesus Christ, our Lord].
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|寫信給我親愛的孩子提摩太：願恩典、憐憫、平安，從父神和我們的主基督耶穌歸與你。
1:3|ASV|I thank God, whom I serve from my forefathers in a pure conscience, how unceasing is my remembrance of thee in my supplications, night and day
1:3|Darby|I am thankful to God, whom I serve from [my] forefathers  with pure conscience, how unceasingly I have the remembrance of  thee in my supplications night and day,
1:3|KJV|I thank God, whom I serve from my forefathers with pure conscience, that without ceasing I have remembrance of thee in my prayers night and day;
1:3<version name="WYC">I do thankings to my God, to whom I serve from my progenitors [from my progenitors, <i>either ancestors</i>,] in clean conscience, that without ceasing I have mind of thee in my prayers, night and day,</version>
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我感謝神，就是我接續祖先，用清潔的良心所事奉的神，晝夜祈求的時候，不住的題到你，
1:4|ASV|longing to see thee, remembering thy tears, that I may be filled with joy;
1:4|Darby|earnestly desiring to see thee, remembering thy tears, that  I may be filled with joy;
1:4|KJV|Greatly desiring to see thee, being mindful of thy tears, that I may be filled with joy;
1:4|WYC|desiring to see thee; having mind of thy tears [mindful of thy tears], that I be filled with joy.
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|記念你的眼淚，渴望見你，好叫我充滿喜樂；
1:5|ASV|having been reminded of the unfeigned faith that is in thee; which dwelt first in thy grandmother Lois, and thy mother Eunice; and, I am persuaded, in thee also.
1:5|Darby|calling to mind the unfeigned faith which [has been] in  thee, which dwelt first in thy grandmother Lois, and in thy  mother Eunice, and I am persuaded that in thee also.
1:5|KJV|When I call to remembrance the unfeigned faith that is in thee, which dwelt first in thy grandmother Lois, and thy mother Eunice; and I am persuaded that in thee also.
1:5<version name="WYC">And I bethink of that faith [And I take recording, <i>or mind, </i>of that faith], that is in thee not feigned, which also dwelled first in thine aunt Lois, and in thy mother Eunice.  And I am certain, that also in thee.</version>
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|記得你裡面無偽的信心，就是先在你外祖母羅以，和你母親友尼基裡面的，我深信也在你裡面。
1:6|ASV|For which cause I put thee in remembrance that thou stir up the gift of God, which is in thee through the laying on of my hands.
1:6|Darby|For which cause I put thee in mind to rekindle the gift of  God which is in thee by the putting on of my hands.
1:6|KJV|Wherefore I put thee in remembrance that thou stir up the gift of God, which is in thee by the putting on of my hands.
1:6|WYC|For which cause I admonish thee, that thou raise again the grace of God, that is in thee by the setting on of mine hands [by the on-putting of mine hands].
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|為這緣故，我題醒你，將那藉我按手，在你裡面神的恩賜，再如火挑旺起來。
1:7|ASV|For God gave us not a spirit of fearfulness; but of power and love and discipline.
1:7|Darby|For God has not given us a spirit of cowardice, but of  power, and of love, and of wise discretion.
1:7|KJV|For God hath not given us the spirit of fear; but of power, and of love, and of a sound mind.
1:7|WYC|For why [Soothly] God gave not to us the spirit of dread, but of virtue, and of love, and of soberness.
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神賜給我們的，不是膽怯的靈，乃是能力、愛、並清明自守的靈。
1:8|ASV|Be not ashamed therefore of the testimony of our Lord, nor of me his prisoner: but suffer hardship with the gospel according to the power of God;
1:8|Darby|Be not therefore ashamed of the testimony of our Lord, nor  of me his prisoner; but suffer evil along with the glad  tidings, according to the power of God;
1:8|KJV|Be not thou therefore ashamed of the testimony of our Lord, nor of me his prisoner: but be thou partaker of the afflictions of the gospel according to the power of God;
1:8|WYC|Therefore do not thou shame the witnessing of our Lord Jesus Christ, neither me, his prisoner; but travail thou together in the gospel by the virtue of God [after the virtue of God];
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以你不要以給我們的主作見證為恥，也不要以我這主的囚犯為恥；總要按神的能力，與福音同受苦難。
1:9|ASV|who saved us, and called us with a holy calling, not according to our works, but according to his own purpose and grace, which was given us in Christ Jesus before times eternal,
1:9|Darby|who has saved us, and has called us with a holy calling, not  according to our works, but according to [his] own purpose and  grace, which [was] given to us in Christ Jesus before [the]  ages of time,
1:9|KJV|Who hath saved us, and called us with an holy calling, not according to our works, but according to his own purpose and grace, which was given us in Christ Jesus before the world began,
1:9|WYC|that delivered us, and called with his holy calling, not after our works, but by his purpose and grace [that delivered us, and called with this holy calling, not after our works, but after his purpose and grace], that is given [to us] in Christ Jesus before worldly times;
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神救了我們，以聖召召了我們，不是按我們的行為，乃是按祂自己的定旨和恩典；這恩典是歷世之前，在基督耶穌裡賜給我們的，
1:10|ASV|but hath now been manifested by the appearing of our Saviour Christ Jesus, who abolished death, and brought life and immortality to light through the gospel,
1:10|Darby|but has been made manifest now by the appearing of our  Saviour Jesus Christ, who has annulled death, and brought to  light life and incorruptibility by the glad tidings;
1:10|KJV|But is now made manifest by the appearing of our Saviour Jesus Christ, who hath abolished death, and hath brought life and immortality to light through the gospel:
1:10|WYC|but now it is open by the lightening of our Saviour Jesus Christ, which destroyed death, and lightened life and uncorruption by the gospel. [now forsooth it is open by the lighting of our Saviour Jesus Christ, the which soothly destroyed death, forsooth lighted life and uncorruption by the gospel.]
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但如今藉著我們救主基督耶穌的顯現，纔顯明出來。祂已經把死廢掉，藉著福音將生命和不朽壞照耀出來；
1:11|ASV|whereunto I was appointed a preacher, and an apostle, and a teacher.
1:11|Darby|to which *I* have been appointed a herald and apostle and  teacher of [the] nations.
1:11|KJV|Whereunto I am appointed a preacher, and an apostle, and a teacher of the Gentiles.
1:11|WYC|In which I am set a preacher and apostle, and master of heathen men.
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我為這福音被派作傳揚者，作使徒，作教師。
1:12|ASV|For which cause I suffer also these things: yet I am not ashamed; for I know him whom I have believed, and I am persuaded that he is able to guard that which I have committed unto him against that day.
1:12|Darby|For which cause also I suffer these things; but I am not  ashamed; for I know whom I have believed, and am persuaded that  he is able to keep for that day the deposit I have entrusted to  him.
1:12|KJV|For the which cause I also suffer these things: nevertheless I am not ashamed: for I know whom I have believed, and am persuaded that he is able to keep that which I have committed unto him against that day.
1:12|WYC|For which cause also I suffer these things; but I am not confounded.  For I know to whom I have believed, and I am certain that he is mighty to keep that (which) is taken to my keeping into that day.
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|為這緣故，我也受這些苦難；然而我不以為恥，因為知道我所信的是誰，也深信祂能保守我所託付的，直到那日。
1:13|ASV|Hold the pattern of sound words which thou hast heard from me, in faith and love which is in Christ Jesus.
1:13|Darby|Have an outline of sound words, which [words] thou hast  heard of me, in faith and love which [are] in Christ Jesus.
1:13|KJV|Hold fast the form of sound words, which thou hast heard of me, in faith and love which is in Christ Jesus.
1:13|WYC|Have thou the form of wholesome words [Have thou the form of whole words], which thou heardest of me in faith and love in Christ Jesus.
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你從我聽的那健康話語的規範，要用基督耶穌裡的信和愛持守著。
1:14|ASV|That good thing which was committed unto thee guard through the Holy Spirit which dwelleth in us.
1:14|Darby|Keep, by the Holy Spirit which dwells in us, the good  deposit entrusted.
1:14|KJV|That good thing which was committed unto thee keep by the Holy Ghost which dwelleth in us.
1:14<version name="WYC">Keep thou the good [<i>thing</i>] taken to thy keeping by the Holy Ghost [Keep thou a good deposit, <i>or thing taken to thy keeping</i>, by the Holy Ghost], that dwelleth in us.</version>
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要藉著那住在我們裡面的聖靈，保守那美好的託付。
1:15|ASV|This thou knowest, that all that are in Asia turned away from me; of whom are Phygelus and Hermogenes.
1:15|Darby|Thou knowest this, that all who [are] in Asia, of whom is  Phygellus and Hermogenes, have turned away from me.
1:15|KJV|This thou knowest, that all they which are in Asia be turned away from me; of whom are Phygellus and Hermogenes.
1:15|WYC|Thou knowest this, that all that be in Asia be turned away from me, of which is Phygellus and Hermogenes [of whom is Phygellus and Hermogenes].
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你知道所有在亞西亞的人都離棄了我，其中有腓吉路和黑摩其尼。
1:16|ASV|The Lord grant mercy unto the house of Onesiphorus: for he oft refreshed me, and was not ashamed of my chain;
1:16|Darby|The Lord grant mercy to the house of Onesiphorus, for he  has often refreshed me, and has not been ashamed of my chain;
1:16|KJV|The Lord give mercy unto the house of Onesiphorus; for he oft refreshed me, and was not ashamed of my chain:
1:16|WYC|The Lord give mercy to the house of Onesiphorus, for oft he refreshed me, and shamed not my chain.
1:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願主憐憫阿尼色弗一家，因他屢次使我舒爽，且不以我的鎖鍊為恥；
1:17|ASV|but, when he was in Rome, he sought me diligently, and found me
1:17|Darby|but being in Rome sought me out very diligently, and found  [me] --
1:17|KJV|But, when he was in Rome, he sought me out very diligently, and found me.
1:17<version name="WYC">But when he came to Rome, he sought me busily, and found [<i>me</i>].</version>
1:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|反倒在羅馬的時候，殷勤的尋找我，並且找著了。
1:18<version name="ASV">(the Lord grant unto him to find mercy of the Lord in that day); and in how many things he ministered at Ephesus, thou knowest very well. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:18<version name="Darby">the Lord grant to him to find mercy from [the] Lord in that  day -- and how much service he rendered in Ephesus *thou*  knowest best. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:18<version name="KJV">The Lord grant unto him that he may find mercy of the Lord in that day: and in how many things he ministered unto me at Ephesus, thou knowest very well.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:18|WYC|The Lord give to him to find mercy of God in that day.  And how great things he ministered to me at Ephesus, thou knowest better.
1:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願主使他在那日從主得著憐憫。他在以弗所怎樣多方的服事我，你知道得最清楚。
2:1|ASV|Thou therefore, my child, be strengthened in the grace that is in Christ Jesus.
2:1|Darby|Thou therefore, my child, be strong in the grace which [is]  in Christ Jesus.
2:1|KJV|Thou therefore, my son, be strong in the grace that is in Christ Jesus.
2:1|WYC|Therefore thou, my son, be comforted in grace that is in Christ Jesus.
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，我的孩子，你要在基督耶穌裡的恩典上得著加力，
2:2|ASV|And the things which thou hast heard from me among many witnesses, the same commit thou to faithful men, who shall be able to teach others also.
2:2|Darby|And the things thou hast heard of me in the presence of many  witnesses, these entrust to faithful men, such as shall be  competent to instruct others also.
2:2|KJV|And the things that thou hast heard of me among many witnesses, the same commit thou to faithful men, who shall be able to teach others also.
2:2|WYC|And what things thou hast heard of me by many witnesses, betake thou these to faithful men, which shall be able also to teach other men.
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你在許多見證人面前從我所聽見的，要託付那忠信、能教導別人的人。
2:3|ASV|Suffer hardship with me, as a good soldier of Christ Jesus.
2:3|Darby|Take thy share in suffering as a good soldier of Jesus  Christ.
2:3|KJV|Thou therefore endure hardness, as a good soldier of Jesus Christ.
2:3|WYC|Travail thou as a good knight of Christ Jesus. [Travail thou as a good knight of Jesus Christ.]
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要和我同受苦難，好像基督耶穌的精兵。
2:4|ASV|No soldier on service entangleth himself in the affairs of this life; that he may please him who enrolled him as a soldier.
2:4|Darby|No one going as a soldier entangles himself with the affairs  of life, that he may please him who has enlisted him as a  soldier.
2:4|KJV|No man that warreth entangleth himself with the affairs of this life; that he may please him who hath chosen him to be a soldier.
2:4|WYC|No man holding knighthood to God, wrappeth himself [enwrappeth himself] with worldly needs, that he please to him, to whom he hath proved himself.
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡當兵的，不讓今生的事務纏身，好叫那招他入伍的人喜悅。
2:5|ASV|And if also a man contend in the games, he is not crowded, except he have contended lawfully.
2:5|Darby|And if also any one contend [in the games], he is not  crowned unless he contend lawfully.
2:5|KJV|And if a man also strive for masteries, yet is he not crowned, except he strive lawfully.
2:5|WYC|For he that fighteth in a battle [For why and he that striveth in a battle], shall not be crowned, but he fight lawfully.
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|競賽的人，非按規矩競賽，就不能得華冠。
2:6|ASV|The husbandmen that laboreth must be the first to partake of the fruits.
2:6|Darby|The husbandman must labour before partaking of the fruits.
2:6|KJV|The husbandman that laboureth must be first partaker of the fruits.
2:6|WYC|It behooveth an earth-tiller to receive first of the fruits.
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|勞力的農夫，理當先分享果實。
2:7|ASV|Consider what I say; for the Lord shall give thee understanding in all things.
2:7|Darby|Think of what I say, for the Lord will give thee  understanding in all things.
2:7|KJV|Consider what I say; and the Lord give thee understanding in all things.
2:7|WYC|Understand thou what things I say [Understand what things I say].  For the Lord shall give to thee understanding in all things.
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我所說的你要思想，因為凡事主必給你領悟力。
2:8|ASV|Remember Jesus Christ, risen from the dead, of the seed of David, according to my gospel:
2:8|Darby|Remember Jesus Christ raised from among [the] dead, of [the]  seed of David, according to my glad tidings,
2:8|KJV|Remember that Jesus Christ of the seed of David was raised from the dead according to my gospel:
2:8|WYC|Be thou mindful that the Lord Jesus Christ of the seed of David hath risen again from death [from dead], after my gospel,
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要記念那從死人中得復活的耶穌基督，祂是出於大衛的後裔，這正合乎我所傳的福音；
2:9|ASV|wherein I suffer hardship unto bonds, as a malefactor; but the word of God is not bound.
2:9|Darby|in which I suffer even unto bonds as an evil-doer: but the  word of God is not bound.
2:9|KJV|Wherein I suffer trouble, as an evil doer, even unto bonds; but the word of God is not bound.
2:9|WYC|in which I travail unto bonds, as working evil [as evil working], but the word of God is not bound.
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在這福音上受苦難，甚至被捆綁像犯人一樣，然而神的話卻不被捆綁。
2:10|ASV|Therefore I endure all things for the elect's sake, that they also may obtain the salvation which is in Christ Jesus with eternal glory.
2:10|Darby|For this cause I endure all things for the sake of the  elect, that *they* also may obtain the salvation which [is] in  Christ Jesus with eternal glory.
2:10|KJV|Therefore I endure all things for the elect's sakes, that they may also obtain the salvation which is in Christ Jesus with eternal glory.
2:10|WYC|Therefore I suffer all things [Therefore I sustain all things] for the chosen, that also they get the health, that is in Christ Jesus, with heavenly glory.
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我為選民凡事忍耐，叫他們也可以得著那在基督耶穌裡的救恩，同永遠的榮耀。
2:11|ASV|Faithful is the saying: For if we died with him, we shall also live with him:
2:11|Darby|The word [is] faithful; for if we have died together with  [him], we shall also live together;
2:11|KJV|It is a faithful saying: For if we be dead with him, we shall also live with him:
2:11<version name="WYC">A true word [<i>is this that I say</i>], that if we be dead together [<i>to the world</i>], also we shall live together [<i>in bliss</i>];</version>
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有可信的話說，我們若與基督同死，也必與祂同活；
2:12|ASV|if we endure, we shall also reign with him: if we shall deny him, he also will deny us:
2:12|Darby|if we endure, we shall also reign together; if we deny,  *he* also will deny us;
2:12|KJV|If we suffer, we shall also reign with him: if we deny him, he also will deny us:
2:12<version name="WYC">if we suffer, [and] we shall reign together [<i>with Christ</i>]; if we deny [<i>him</i>], [and] he shall deny us;</version>
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們如果忍耐，也必與祂一同作王；我們如果不認祂，祂也必不認我們；
2:13|ASV|if we are faithless, he abideth faithful; for he cannot deny himself.
2:13|Darby|if we are unfaithful, *he* abides faithful, for he cannot  deny himself.
2:13|KJV|If we believe not, yet he abideth faithful: he cannot deny himself.
2:13|WYC|if we believe not, he dwelleth faithful, he may not deny himself.
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們縱然失信，祂仍是可信的，因為祂不能否定自己。
2:14|ASV|Of these things put them in remembrance, charging them in the sight of the Lord, that they strive not about words, to no profit, to the subverting of them that hear.
2:14|Darby|Of these things put in remembrance, testifying earnestly  before the Lord not to have disputes of words, profitable for  nothing, to the subversion of the hearers.
2:14|KJV|Of these things put them in remembrance, charging them before the Lord that they strive not about words to no profit, but to the subverting of the hearers.
2:14|WYC|Teach thou these things [Forsooth these things I admonish], witnessing before God.  Do not thou strive in words; for to nothing it is profitable, but to the subverting of men that hear.
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要將這些事題醒眾人，在神面前鄭重的囑咐他們，不可為言辭爭辯，這是毫無用處的，只能敗壞聽見的人。
2:15|ASV|Give diligence to present thyself approved unto God, a workman that needeth not to be ashamed, handling aright the word of truth.
2:15|Darby|Strive diligently to present thyself approved to God, a  workman that has not to be ashamed, cutting in a straight line  the word of truth.
2:15|KJV|Study to shew thyself approved unto God, a workman that needeth not to be ashamed, rightly dividing the word of truth.
2:15<version name="WYC">Busily keep [Busily care, <i>or</i> <i>keep</i>,] to give thyself an approved, praiseable workman to God, without shame, rightly treating the word of truth.</version>
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你當竭力將自己呈獻神前，得蒙稱許，作無愧的工人，正直的分解真理的話。
2:16|ASV|But shun profane babblings: for they will proceed further in ungodliness,
2:16|Darby|But profane, vain babblings shun, for they will advance to  greater impiety,
2:16|KJV|But shun profane and vain babblings: for they will increase unto more ungodliness.
2:16|WYC|But eschew thou unholy and vain speeches, for why those profit much to unfaithfulness, [Forsooth shun thou unholy and vain speeches, soothly they profit much to unpiety,]
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但要遠避世俗的空談，因為這些空談必進而成為更不敬虔。
2:17|ASV|and their word will eat as doth a gangrene: or whom is Hymenaeus an Philetus;
2:17|Darby|and their word will spread as a gangrene; of whom is  Hymenaeus and Philetus;
2:17|KJV|And their word will eat as doth a canker: of whom is Hymenaeus and Philetus;
2:17|WYC|and the word of them creepeth as a canker.  Of whom Philetus is, and Hymenaeus,
2:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們的話必像毒瘡蔓衍；其中有許米乃和腓理徒，
2:18|ASV|men who concerning the truth have erred, saying that the resurrection is past already, and overthrow the faith of some.
2:18|Darby|[men] who as to the truth have gone astray, saying that the  resurrection has taken place already; and overthrow the faith  of some.
2:18|KJV|Who concerning the truth have erred, saying that the resurrection is past already; and overthrow the faith of some.
2:18|WYC|which felled down [the which fell down] from the truth, saying that the rising again is now done, and they subverted the faith of some men [and turned upside-down the faith of some men].
2:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們在真理上偏離了目標，說復活的事已過，就傾覆一些人的信心。
2:19|ASV|Howbeit the firm foundation of God standeth, having this seal, The Lord knoweth them that are his: and, Let every one that nameth the name of the Lord depart from unrighteousness.
2:19|Darby|Yet the firm foundation of God stands, having this seal,  [The] Lord knows those that are his; and, Let every one who  names the name of [the] Lord withdraw from iniquity.
2:19|KJV|Nevertheless the foundation of God standeth sure, having this seal, The Lord knoweth them that are his. And, let every one that nameth the name of Christ depart from iniquity.
2:19<version name="WYC">But the firm foundament of God standeth, having this mark [having this mark, <i>either signet</i>], The Lord knoweth which be his, and, Each man that nameth the name of the Lord, departeth from wickedness [depart from wickedness].</version>
2:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而，神堅固的根基立住了，上面有這印記說，主認識屬於祂的人。又說，凡稱呼主名的人，總要離開不義。
2:20|ASV|Now in a great house there are not only vessels of gold and of silver, but also of wood and of earth; and some unto honor, and some unto dishonor.
2:20|Darby|But in a great house there are not only gold and silver  vessels, but also wooden and earthen; and some to honour, and  some to dishonour.
2:20|KJV|But in a great house there are not only vessels of gold and of silver, but also of wood and of earth; and some to honour, and some to dishonour.
2:20<version name="WYC">But in a great house be not only vessels of gold and of silver, but also of tree and of earth; and so some <i>be</i> into honour, and some into despite.</version>
2:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但在大戶人家，不但有金器銀器，也有木器瓦器；有作為貴重的，也有作為卑賤的；
2:21|ASV|If a man therefore purge himself from these, he shall be a vessel unto honor, sanctified, meet for the master's use, prepared unto every good work.
2:21|Darby|If therefore one shall have purified himself from these,  [in separating himself from them], he shall be a vessel to  honour, sanctified, serviceable to the Master, prepared for  every good work.
2:21|KJV|If a man therefore purge himself from these, he shall be a vessel unto honour, sanctified, and meet for the master's use, and prepared unto every good work.
2:21|WYC|Therefore, if any man cleanseth himself from these [Therefore if any man shall cleanse himself from these], he shall be a vessel hallowed into honour, and profitable to the Lord, ready to all good work [ready into all good work].
2:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以人若潔淨自己，脫離這些卑賤的，就必成為貴重的器皿，分別為聖，合乎主人使用，豫備行各樣的善事。
2:22|ASV|after righteousness, faith, love, pace, with them that call on the Lord out of a pure heart.
2:22|Darby|But youthful lusts flee, and pursue righteousness, faith,  love, peace, with those that call upon the Lord out of a pure  heart.
2:22|KJV|Flee also youthful lusts: but follow righteousness, faith, charity, peace, with them that call on the Lord out of a pure heart.
2:22|WYC|And flee thou [the] desires of youth, but follow thou rightwiseness, faith, charity, peace, with them that inwardly call the Lord [that in-call the Lord] of a clean heart.
2:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要逃避青年人的私慾，同那清心呼求主的人，竭力追求公義、信、愛、和平。
2:23|ASV|But foolish and ignorant questionings refuse, knowing that they gender strifes.
2:23|Darby|But foolish and senseless questionings avoid, knowing that  they beget contentions.
2:23|KJV|But foolish and unlearned questions avoid, knowing that they do gender strifes.
2:23|WYC|And eschew thou foolish questions, and without knowing [Forsooth shun thou foolish questions, and without discipline], witting that those gender chidings.
2:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於愚拙無學問的辯論，總要棄絕，知道這些事是產生爭競的。
2:24|ASV|And the Lord's servant must not strive, but be gentle towards all, apt to teach, forbearing,
2:24|Darby|And a bondman of [the] Lord ought not to contend, but be  gentle towards all; apt to teach; forbearing;
2:24|KJV|And the servant of the Lord must not strive; but be gentle unto all men, apt to teach, patient,
2:24|WYC|But it behooveth the servant of the Lord to chide not [to not chide]; but to be mild to all men, able to teach, patient,
2:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但主的奴僕不該爭競，總要溫溫和和的待眾人，善於教導，忍受苦害，
2:25|ASV|in meekness correcting them that oppose themselves; if peradventure God may give them repentance unto the knowledge of the truth,
2:25|Darby|in meekness setting right those who oppose, if God perhaps  may sometime give them repentance to acknowledgment of [the]  truth,
2:25|KJV|In meekness instructing those that oppose themselves; if God peradventure will give them repentance to the acknowledging of the truth;
2:25|WYC|with temperance reproving them that against-stand the truth, that sometime God give to them repenting, that they know the truth [that sometime God give them penance to know the truth],
2:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|用溫柔規勸那些抵擋的人；或許神給他們悔改的心，得以認識真理；
2:26<version name="ASV">and they may recover themselves out of the snare of the devil, having been taken captive by him unto his will. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:26<version name="Darby">and that they may awake up out of the snare of the devil,  [who are] taken by him, for *his* will. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:26<version name="KJV">And that they may recover themselves out of the snare of the devil, who are taken captive by him at his will.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:26|WYC|and that they rise again from the snares of the devil, of whom they be held prisoners at his will [of whom they be holden captive at his will].
2:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們這些已被魔鬼活捉了去的，也可以醒悟過來，脫離他的網羅，歸於神的旨意。
3:1|ASV|But know this, that in the last days grievous times shall come.
3:1|Darby|But this know, that in [the] last days difficult times shall  be there;
3:1|KJV|This know also, that in the last days perilous times shall come.
3:1|WYC|But know thou this thing, that in the last days perilous times shall approach [shall nigh],
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但你要知道，末後的日子必有艱難的時期來到；
3:2|ASV|For men shall be lovers of self, lovers of money, boastful, haughty, railers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy,
3:2|Darby|for men shall be lovers of self, lovers of money, boastful,  arrogant, evil speakers, disobedient to parents, ungrateful,  profane,
3:2|KJV|For men shall be lovers of their own selves, covetous, boasters, proud, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy,
3:2|WYC|and men shall be loving themselves, covetous, high of bearing, proud, blasphemers, not obedient to father and mother, unkind, cursed,
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為那時人要成為愛自己者、愛錢財者、自誇者、狂傲的、毀謗者、違背父母的、忘恩負義的、不聖的、
3:3|ASV|without natural affection, implacable, slanderers, without self-control, fierce, no lovers of good,
3:3|Darby|without natural affection, implacable, slanderers, of  unsubdued passions, savage, having no love for what is good,
3:3|KJV|Without natural affection, trucebreakers, false accusers, incontinent, fierce, despisers of those that are good,
3:3<version name="WYC">without affection, without peace, false blamers, uncontinent, unmild, without benignity, <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22874a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|無親情的、不解怨的、好說讒言者、不能自約的、性情兇暴的、不愛良善者、
3:4|ASV|traitors, headstrong, puffed up, lovers of pleasure rather than lovers of God;
3:4|Darby|traitors, headlong, of vain pretensions, lovers of pleasure  rather than lovers of God;
3:4|KJV|Traitors, heady, highminded, lovers of pleasures more than lovers of God;
3:4<version name="WYC">traitors, over-thwart [froward], swollen <i>with proud thoughts </i>[blown], blind, lovers of lusts more than of God,</version>
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|賣主賣友者、鹵莽行事的、為高傲所蒙蔽的，寧願作愛宴樂者，不願作愛神者；
3:5|ASV|holding a form of godliness, but having denied the power therefore. From these also turn away.
3:5|Darby|having a form of piety but denying the power of it: and from  these turn away.
3:5|KJV|Having a form of godliness, but denying the power thereof: from such turn away.
3:5<version name="WYC">having the likeness of piety, but denying the virtue of it.  And eschew thou these <i>men</i>.</version>
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有敬虔的外形，卻否認了敬虔的能力；這等人你要躲開。
3:6|ASV|For of these are they that creep into houses, and take captive silly women laden with sins, led away by divers lusts,
3:6|Darby|For of these are they who are getting into houses, and  leading captive silly women, laden with sins, led by various  lusts,
3:6|KJV|For of this sort are they which creep into houses, and lead captive silly women laden with sins, led away with divers lusts,
3:6|WYC|Of these they be that pierce houses, and lead women captives [and lead little women captive] charged with sins, which be led with diverse desires,
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們中間有人偷進人家，牢籠無知的婦女；這些婦女為罪堆壓，被各樣私慾牽引，
3:7|ASV|ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth.
3:7|Darby|always learning, and never able to come to [the] knowledge  of [the] truth.
3:7|KJV|Ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth.
3:7|WYC|evermore learning, and never perfectly coming to the science of truth. [evermore learning, and never perfectly coming to the knowing of truth.]
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|常常學習，終久不能認識真理。
3:8|ASV|And even as Jannes and Jambres withstood Moses, so do these also withstand the truth. Men corrupted in mind, reprobate concerning the faith.
3:8|Darby|Now in the same manner in which Jannes and Jambres withstood  Moses, thus these also withstand the truth; men corrupted in  mind, found worthless as regards the faith.
3:8|KJV|Now as Jannes and Jambres withstood Moses, so do these also resist the truth: men of corrupt minds, reprobate concerning the faith.
3:8<version name="WYC">And as Jannes and Jambres against-stood Moses, so [and] these against-stand the truth, men corrupt in understanding [men corrupt in soul, <i>or</i> <i>understanding</i>], reproved about the faith.</version>
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|雅尼和佯庇曾用甚麼方法抵擋摩西，這等人也照樣抵擋真理；他們是心思敗壞了的人，在信仰上是不蒙稱許的。
3:9|ASV|But they shall proceed no further. For their folly shall be evident unto all men, as theirs also came to be.
3:9|Darby|But they shall not advance farther; for their folly shall be  completely manifest to all, as that of those also became.
3:9|KJV|But they shall proceed no further: for their folly shall be manifest unto all men, as their's also was.
3:9|WYC|But further they shall not profit, for the unwisdom of them shall be known to all men, as [and] theirs was.
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而他們不能再這樣下去，因為他們的無知，必在眾人面前完全顯露出來，像那二人一樣。
3:10|ASV|But thou didst follow my teaching, conduct, purpose, faith, longsuffering, love, patience,
3:10|Darby|But *thou* hast been thoroughly acquainted with my  teaching, conduct, purpose, faith, longsuffering, love,  endurance,
3:10|KJV|But thou hast fully known my doctrine, manner of life, purpose, faith, longsuffering, charity, patience,
3:10|WYC|But thou hast gotten my teaching [my doctrine], ordinance, purposing [purpose], faith, long abiding, love, patience,
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但你已經緊緊跟隨了我的教訓、品行、志向、信心、寬容、愛心、忍耐、
3:11|ASV|persecutions, sufferings. What things befell me at Antioch, at Iconium, at Lystra; what persecutions I endured. And out of them all the Lord delivered me.
3:11|Darby|persecutions, sufferings: what [sufferings] happened to me  in Antioch, in Iconium, in Lystra; what persecutions I endured;  and the Lord delivered me out of all.
3:11|KJV|Persecutions, afflictions, which came unto me at Antioch, at Iconium, at Lystra; what persecutions I endured: but out of them all the Lord delivered me.
3:11|WYC|persecutions, passions, which were made to me at Antioch, at Iconium, at Lystra, what manner persecutions I suffered, and the Lord hath delivered me of all [and the Lord delivered me of all].
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|逼迫、苦難，就是我在安提阿、以哥念、路司得所遭遇的；我所忍受的是何等的逼迫，但從這一切之中，主都把我救出來了。
3:12|ASV|Yea, and all that would live godly in Christ Jesus shall suffer persecution.
3:12|Darby|And all indeed who desire to live piously in Christ Jesus  will be persecuted.
3:12|KJV|Yea, and all that will live godly in Christ Jesus shall suffer persecution.
3:12<version name="WYC">And all men that will live faithfully in Christ Jesus [And all men that will live piously, <i>or faithfully</i>, in Christ Jesus], shall suffer persecution.</version>
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不但如此，凡立志在基督耶穌裡過敬虔生活的，也都要受逼迫。
3:13|ASV|But evil men and impostors shall wax worse and worse, deceiving and being deceived.
3:13|Darby|But wicked men and juggling impostors shall advance in  evil, leading and being led astray.
3:13|KJV|But evil men and seducers shall wax worse and worse, deceiving, and being deceived.
3:13<version name="WYC">But evil men and deceivers shall increase into worse, erring, and sending into error. [Forsooth evil men and deceivers shall profit into worse, erring <i>themselves</i>, and sending <i>others</i> into error.]</version>
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只是惡人和騙子，必進而變為更惡，他們迷惑人，也受人迷惑。
3:14|ASV|But abide thou in the things which thou hast learned and hast been assured of, knowing of whom thou hast learned them.
3:14|Darby|But *thou*, abide in those things which thou hast learned,  and [of which] thou hast been fully persuaded, knowing of whom  thou hast learned [them];
3:14|KJV|But continue thou in the things which thou hast learned and hast been assured of, knowing of whom thou hast learned them;
3:14|WYC|But dwell thou in these things that thou hast learned, and that be betaken to thee, witting of whom thou hast learned;
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但你所學習、所確信的，要活在其中，因為知道你是跟誰學的，
3:15|ASV|And that from a babe thou hast known the sacred writings which are able to make thee wise unto salvation through faith which is in Christ Jesus.
3:15|Darby|and that from a child thou hast known the sacred letters,  which are able to make thee wise unto salvation, through faith  which [is] in Christ Jesus.
3:15|KJV|And that from a child thou hast known the holy scriptures, which are able to make thee wise unto salvation through faith which is in Christ Jesus.
3:15<version name="WYC">for thou hast known holy letters from thy youth, which be able to learn thee to health [and for thou hast known holy letters from thy youth, <i>or childhood</i>, the which may inform thee to health], by faith that is in Christ Jesus.</version>
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且知道你是從小明白聖經；這聖經能使你藉著相信基督耶穌，有得救的智慧。
3:16|ASV|Every scripture inspired of God is also profitable for teaching, for reproof, for correction, for instruction which is in righteousness.
3:16|Darby|Every scripture [is] divinely inspired, and profitable for  teaching, for conviction, for correction, for instruction in  righteousness;
3:16|KJV|All scripture is given by inspiration of God, and is profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for instruction in righteousness:
3:16|WYC|For all scripture inspired of God is profitable to teach, to reprove, to chastise, [for] to learn in rightwiseness,
3:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|聖經都是神的呼出，對於教訓、督責、改正、在義上的教導，都是有益的，
3:17<version name="ASV">That the man of God may be complete, furnished completely unto every good work. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:17<version name="Darby">that the man of God may be complete, fully fitted to every  good work. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:17<version name="KJV">That the man of God may be perfect, thoroughly furnished unto all good works.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:17|WYC|that the man of God be perfect, learned to all good work [learned to all good works].
3:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|叫屬神的人得以完備，為著各樣的善工，裝備齊全。
4:1|ASV|I charge  thee in the sight of God, and of Christ Jesus, who shall judge the living and the dead, and by his appearing and his kingdom:
4:1|Darby|I testify before God and Christ Jesus, who is about to judge  living and dead, and by his appearing and his kingdom,
4:1|KJV|I charge thee therefore before God, and the Lord Jesus Christ, who shall judge the quick and the dead at his appearing and his kingdom;
4:1|WYC|I witness before God and Christ Jesus, that shall deem the quick and the dead, by the coming of him, and the kingdom of him,
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在神並那將要審判活人死人的基督耶穌面前，憑著祂的顯現和祂的國度，鄭重的囑咐你，
4:2|ASV|preach the word; be urgent in season, out of season; reprove, rebuke, exhort, with all longsuffering and teaching.
4:2|Darby|proclaim the word; be urgent in season [and] out of season,  convict, rebuke, encourage, with all longsuffering and  doctrine.
4:2|KJV|Preach the word; be instant in season, out of season; reprove, rebuke, exhort with all long suffering and doctrine.
4:2|WYC|preach the word, be thou busy suitably without rest, reprove thou, beseech thou, blame thou in all patience and doctrine. [preach the word, be thou busy to opportune and inopportune, reprove, beseech, blame in all patience and doctrine.]
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|務要傳道；無論得時不得時，都要豫備好，用全般的恆忍和教訓，叫人知罪自責，譴責人，勸勉人。
4:3|ASV|For the time will come when they will not endure the sound doctrine; but, having itching ears, will heap to themselves teachers after their own lusts;
4:3|Darby|For the time shall be when they will not bear sound  teaching; but according to their own lusts will heap up to  themselves teachers, having an itching ear;
4:3|KJV|For the time will come when they will not endure sound doctrine; but after their own lusts shall they heap to themselves teachers, having itching ears;
4:3<version name="WYC">For time shall be, when men shall not suffer wholesome teaching, but at their desires they shall gather together to themselves masters itching to the ears. [Forsooth time shall be, when men shall not sustain whole doctrine, but at their desires, they shall gather together to themselves masters itching, <i>or</i> <i>pleasing</i>, to the ears.]</version>
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為時候要到，那時人必容不下健康的教訓，反而耳朵發癢，隨著自己的情慾，給自己堆積起教師來；
4:4|ASV|and will turn away their ears from the truth, and turn aside unto fables.
4:4|Darby|and they will turn away their ear from the truth, and will  have turned aside to fables.
4:4|KJV|And they shall turn away their ears from the truth, and shall be turned unto fables.
4:4|WYC|And truly they shall turn away the hearing from truth, but to fables they shall turn. [And truly they shall turn away their hearing from truth, but to fables they shall be turned together.]
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且轉耳離棄真理，偏向虛構無稽之事。
4:5|ASV|But be thou sober in all things, suffer hardship, do the work of an evangelist, fulfil thy ministry.
4:5|Darby|But *thou*, be sober in all things, bear evils, do [the]  work of an evangelist, fill up the full measure of thy  ministry.
4:5|KJV|But watch thou in all things, endure afflictions, do the work of an evangelist, make full proof of thy ministry.
4:5<version name="WYC">But wake thou, in all things travail thou, do the work of an evangelist, fulfill thy service [fulfill thy service, <i>or</i> <i>office</i>], be thou sober.</version>
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你卻要凡事謹慎自守，忍受苦難，作傳福音者的工作，盡你的職事。
4:6|ASV|For I am already being offered, and the time of my departure is come.
4:6|Darby|For *I* am already being poured out, and the time of my  release is come.
4:6|KJV|For I am now ready to be offered, and the time of my departure is at hand.
4:6|WYC|For I am sacrificed now, and the time of my departing is nigh.
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我現在被澆奠，我離世的時候到了。
4:7|ASV|I have fought the good fight, I have finished the course, I have kept the faith:
4:7|Darby|I have combated the good combat, I have finished the race, I  have kept the faith.
4:7|KJV|I have fought a good fight, I have finished my course, I have kept the faith:
4:7|WYC|I have striven a good strife, I have ended the course, I have kept the faith.
4:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那美好的仗我已經打過了，當跑的賽程我已經跑盡了，當守的信仰我已經守住了；
4:8|ASV|henceforth there is laid up for me the crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous judge, shall give to me at that day; and not to me only, but also to all them that have loved his appearing.
4:8|Darby|Henceforth the crown of righteousness is laid up for me,  which the Lord, the righteous Judge, will render to me in that  day; but not only to me, but also to all who love his  appearing.
4:8|KJV|Henceforth there is laid up for me a crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous judge, shall give me at that day: and not to me only, but unto all them also that love his appearing.
4:8|WYC|In the tother time a crown of rightwiseness is kept to me, which the Lord, a just doomsman, shall yield to me in that day; and not only to me, but also to these that love his coming [but to them that love his coming].
4:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|從此以後，有公義的冠冕為我存留，就是主，那公義的審判者，在那日要賞賜我的；不但賞賜我，也賞賜凡愛祂顯現的人。
4:9|ASV|Give diligence to come shortly unto me:
4:9|Darby|Use diligence to come to me quickly;
4:9|KJV|Do thy diligence to come shortly unto me:
4:9|WYC|Hie thou to come to me soon.
4:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要儘快的到我這裡來；
4:10|ASV|for Demas forsook me, having loved this present world, and went to Thessalonica; Crescens to Galatia, Titus to Dalmatia.
4:10|Darby|for Demas has forsaken me, having loved the present age,  and is gone to Thessalonica; Crescens to Galatia, Titus to  Dalmatia.
4:10|KJV|For Demas hath forsaken me, having loved this present world, and is departed unto Thessalonica; Crescens to Galatia, Titus unto Dalmatia.
4:10|WYC|For Demas, loving this world, hath forsaken me [Forsooth Demas hath forsaken me, loving this world], and went to Thessalonica, Crescens into Galatia, Titus into Dalmatia;
4:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為底馬愛了現今的世代，就離棄我往帖撒羅尼迦去了；革勒士往加拉太去，提多往撻馬太去。
4:11|ASV|Only Luke is with me. Take Mark, and bring him with thee; for he is useful to me for ministering.
4:11|Darby|Luke alone is with me. Take Mark, and bring [him] with  thyself, for he is serviceable to me for ministry.
4:11|KJV|Only Luke is with me. Take Mark, and bring him with thee: for he is profitable to me for the ministry.
4:11|WYC|Luke alone is with me.  Take thou Mark [Take Mark], and bring with thee; for he is profitable to me into service.
4:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|獨有路加同我在一起。你要接得馬可，帶他同來，因為他在服事上對我有用處。
4:12|ASV|But Tychicus I sent to Ephesus.
4:12|Darby|But Tychicus I have sent to Ephesus.
4:12|KJV|And Tychicus have I sent to Ephesus.
4:12|WYC|Forsooth I sent Tychicus to Ephesus.
4:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我已經打發推基古往以弗所去。
4:13|ASV|The cloak that I left at Troas with Carpus, bring when thou comest, and the books, especially the parchments.
4:13|Darby|The cloak which I left behind [me] in Troas at Carpus's,  bring when thou comest, and the books, especially the  parchments.
4:13|KJV|The cloke that I left at Troas with Carpus, when thou comest, bring with thee, and the books, but especially the parchments.
4:13<version name="WYC">The cloak [<i>cloth</i>] which I left at Troas at Carpas, when thou comest, bring with thee, and the books, but most the parchments.</version>
4:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在特羅亞留於加布的那件外衣，你來的時候要帶來，還有那些書卷，尤其是那些皮卷。
4:14|ASV|Alexander the coppersmith did me much evil: the Lord will render to him according to his works:
4:14|Darby|Alexander the smith did many evil things against me. The  Lord will render to him according to his works.
4:14|KJV|Alexander the coppersmith did me much evil: the Lord reward him according to his works:
4:14|WYC|Alexander, the treasurer, showed to me much evil; the Lord shall yield to him after his works.
4:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|銅匠亞力山大多多的害我，主必照他所行的報應他。
4:15|ASV|of whom do thou also beware; for he greatly withstood our words.
4:15|Darby|Against whom be *thou* also on thy guard, for he has  greatly withstood our words.
4:15|KJV|Of whom be thou ware also; for he hath greatly withstood our words.
4:15|WYC|Whom also thou eschew; for he against-stood full greatly our words.
4:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你也要防備他，因為他極力抵擋我們的話。
4:16|ASV|At my first defence no one took my part, but all forsook me: may it not be laid to their account.
4:16|Darby|At my first defence no man stood with me, but all deserted  me. May it not be imputed to them.
4:16|KJV|At my first answer no man stood with me, but all men forsook me: I pray God that it may not be laid to their charge.
4:16|WYC|In my first defence no man helped me, but all forsook me; be it not areckoned to them. [In my first defence no man was to me, but all forsook me; be it not reckoned to them.]
4:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我初次申訴的時候，沒有人在旁支持我，眾人都離棄我；但願這罪不歸與他們。
4:17|ASV|But the Lord stood by me, and strengthened me; that through me the message might me fully proclaimed, and that all the Gentiles might hear: and I was delivered out of the mouth of the lion.
4:17|Darby|But the Lord stood with [me], and gave me power, that  through me the proclamation might be fully made, and all [those  of] the nations should hear; and I was delivered out of the  lion's mouth.
4:17|KJV|Notwithstanding the Lord stood with me, and strengthened me; that by me the preaching might be fully known, and that all the Gentiles might hear: and I was delivered out of the mouth of the lion.
4:17|WYC|But the Lord helped me, and comforted me, that the preaching be filled by me, and that all folks hear, that I am delivered from the mouth of the lion. [Forsooth the Lord stood nigh to me, and comforted me, that the preaching be full-filled by me, and that all folks hear, and I am delivered from the mouth of the lion.]
4:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|惟有主與我站在一起，加給我能力，使福音藉著我傳得完全，叫一切的外邦人都可聽見；我也從獅子口裡被救出來。
4:18|ASV|The Lord will deliver me from every evil work, and will save me unto his heavenly kingdom: to whom be the glory forever and ever. Amen.
4:18|Darby|The Lord shall deliver me from every wicked work, and shall  preserve [me] for his heavenly kingdom; to whom [be] glory for  the ages of ages. Amen.
4:18|KJV|And the Lord shall deliver me from every evil work, and will preserve me unto his heavenly kingdom: to whom be glory for ever and ever. Amen.
4:18<version name="WYC">And the Lord delivered me from all evil work, and shall make me safe into his heavenly kingdom, to whom <i>be</i> glory into worlds of worlds.  Amen.</version>
4:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主必救我脫離各樣兇惡的事，也必救我進入祂屬天的國。願榮耀歸與祂，直到永永遠遠。阿們。
4:19|ASV|Salute Prisca and Aquila, and the house of Onesiphorus.
4:19|Darby|Salute Prisca and Aquila, and the house of Onesiphorus.
4:19|KJV|Salute Prisca and Aquila, and the household of Onesiphorus.
4:19|WYC|Greet well Prisca, and Aquila, and the house of Onesiphorus.
4:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|問百基拉、亞居拉、和阿尼色弗一家的人安。
4:20|ASV|Erastus remained at Corinth: but Trophimus I left at Miletus sick.
4:20|Darby|Erastus remained in Corinth, but Trophimus I left behind in  Miletus sick.
4:20|KJV|Erastus abode at Corinth: but Trophimus have I left at Miletum sick.
4:20|WYC|Erastus left at Corinth [Forsooth Erastus dwelt at Corinth], and I left Trophimus sick at Miletum.
4:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以拉都在哥林多住下了。特羅非摩病了，我就留他在米利都。
4:21|ASV|Give diligence to come before winter. Eubulus saluteth thee, and Pudens, and Linus, and Claudia, and all the brethren.
4:21|Darby|Use diligence to come before winter. Eubulus salutes thee,  and Pudens, and Linus, and Claudia, and the brethren all.
4:21|KJV|Do thy diligence to come before winter. Eubulus greeteth thee, and Pudens, and Linus, and Claudia, and all the brethren.
4:21|WYC|Hie thou to come before winter.  Eubulus, and Pudens, and Linus, and Claudia, and all brethren, greet thee well.
4:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要趕緊在冬天以前來。友布羅、布田、利奴、革老底亞和眾弟兄，都問你安。
4:22<version name="ASV">The Lord be with thy spirit. Grace be with you. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:22<version name="Darby">The Lord Jesus Christ [be] with your spirit. Grace [be]  with you. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:22<version name="KJV">The Lord Jesus Christ be with thy spirit. Grace be with you. Amen.</p><p /><br /></version>
4:22<version name="WYC">Our Lord Jesus Christ <i>be</i> with thy spirit.  The grace of God <i>be</i> with you.  Amen.</version>
4:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願主與你的靈同在。願恩典與你同在。
