1:1|ASV|The words of Amos, who was among the herdsmen of Tekoa, which he saw concerning Israel in the days of Uzziah king of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam the son of Joash king of Israel, two years before the earthquake.
1:1|Darby|The words of Amos, who was among the herdmen of Tekoa, which  he saw concerning Israel in the days of Uzziah king of Judah,  and in the days of Jeroboam the son of Joash, king of Israel,  two years before the earthquake.
1:1|KJV|The words of Amos, who was among the herdmen of Tekoa, which he saw concerning Israel in the days of Uzziah king of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam the son of Joash king of Israel, two years before the earthquake.
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當猶大王烏西雅，以色列王約阿施的兒子耶羅波安在位的日子，大地震前二年，提哥亞牧羊人中的阿摩司得了論以色列的話。
1:2|ASV|And he said, Jehovah will roar from Zion, and utter his voice from Jerusalem; and the pastures of the shepherds shall mourn, and the top of Carmel shall wither.
1:2|Darby|And he said, Jehovah roareth from Zion, and uttereth his  voice from Jerusalem; and the pastures of the shepherds mourn,  and the top of Carmel withereth.
1:2|KJV|And he said, The LORD will roar from Zion, and utter his voice from Jerusalem; and the habitations of the shepherds shall mourn, and the top of Carmel shall wither.
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他說，耶和華必從錫安吼叫，從耶路撒冷發聲；牧人的草場要悲哀，迦密的山頂要枯乾。
1:3|ASV|Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Damascus, yea, for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because they have threshed Gilead with threshing instruments of iron:
1:3|Darby|Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Damascus,  and for four, I will not revoke [my sentence], because they  have threshed Gilead with threshing instruments of iron.
1:3|KJV|Thus saith the LORD; For three transgressions of Damascus, and for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because they have threshed Gilead with threshing instruments of iron:
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華如此說，因大馬色三番四次的犯罪，我必不免去他們的刑罰；因為他們以打糧食的尖利鐵器打過基列。
1:4|ASV|but I will send a fire into the house of Hazael, and it shall devour the palaces of Ben-hadad.
1:4|Darby|And I will send a fire into the house of Hazael, and it  shall devour the palaces of Ben-Hadad.
1:4|KJV|But I will send a fire into the house of Hazael, which shall devour the palaces of Benhadad.
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我卻要降火在哈薛的家中，燒滅便哈達的宮殿。
1:5|ASV|And I will break the bar of Damascus, and cut off the inhabitant from the valley of Aven, and him that holdeth the sceptre from the house of Eden; and the people of Syria shall go into captivity unto Kir, saith Jehovah.
1:5|Darby|And I will break the bar of Damascus, and cut off the  inhabitant from the valley of Aven, and him that holdeth the  sceptre from Beth-Eden; and the people of Syria shall go into  captivity unto Kir, saith Jehovah.
1:5|KJV|I will break also the bar of Damascus, and cut off the inhabitant from the plain of Aven, and him that holdeth the sceptre from the house of Eden: and the people of Syria shall go into captivity unto Kir, saith the LORD.
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必折斷大馬色的門閂，剪除亞文平原的居民和伯伊甸掌握權杖的；亞蘭人必被擄到吉珥，這是耶和華說的。
1:6|ASV|Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Gaza, yea, for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because they carried away captive the whole people, to deliver them up to Edom:
1:6|Darby|Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Gazah, and  for four, I will not revoke its sentence; because they carried  away captive the whole captivity, to deliver [them] up to Edom.
1:6|KJV|Thus saith the LORD; For three transgressions of Gaza, and for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because they carried away captive the whole captivity, to deliver them up to Edom:
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華如此說，因迦薩三番四次的犯罪，我必不免去他們的刑罰；因為他們將擄掠的眾民全然擄掠，交給以東。
1:7|ASV|but I will send a fire on the wall of Gaza, and it shall devour the palaces thereof.
1:7|Darby|And I will send a fire on the wall of Gazah, and it shall  devour the palaces thereof.
1:7|KJV|But I will send a fire on the wall of Gaza, which shall devour the palaces thereof:
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我卻要降火在迦薩的城牆，燒滅其中的宮殿。
1:8|ASV|And I will cut off the inhabitant from Ashdod, and him that holdeth the sceptre from Ashkelon; and I will turn my hand against Ekron; and the remnant of the Philistines shall perish, saith the Lord Jehovah.
1:8|Darby|And I will cut off the inhabitant from Ashdod, and him that  holdeth the sceptre from Ashkelon, and I will turn my hand  against Ekron; and the remnant of the Philistines shall perish,  saith the Lord Jehovah.
1:8|KJV|And I will cut off the inhabitant from Ashdod, and him that holdeth the sceptre from Ashkelon, and I will turn mine hand against Ekron: and the remnant of the Philistines shall perish, saith the Lord GOD.
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必剪除亞實突的居民，和亞實基倫掌握權杖的；也必反手攻擊以革倫；非利士人所餘剩的必都滅亡，這是主耶和華說的。
1:9|ASV|Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Tyre, yea, for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because they delivered up the whole people to Edom, and remembered not the brotherly covenant:
1:9|Darby|Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Tyre, and  for four, I will not revoke its sentence; because they  delivered up the whole captivity to Edom, and remembered not  the brotherly covenant.
1:9|KJV|Thus saith the LORD; For three transgressions of Tyrus, and for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because they delivered up the whole captivity to Edom, and remembered not the brotherly covenant:
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華如此說，因推羅三番四次的犯罪，我必不免去他們的刑罰；因為他們將擄掠的眾民全然擄掠，交給以東，並不記念弟兄之間的盟約。
1:10|ASV|but I will send a fire on the wall of Tyre, and it shall devour the palaces thereof.
1:10|Darby|And I will send a fire on the wall of Tyre, and it shall  devour the palaces thereof.
1:10|KJV|But I will send a fire on the wall of Tyrus, which shall devour the palaces thereof.
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我卻要降火在推羅的城牆，燒滅其中的宮殿。
1:11|ASV|Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Edom, yea, for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because he did pursue his brother with the sword, and did cast off all pity, and his anger did tear perpetually, and he kept his wrath for ever:
1:11|Darby|Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Edom, and  for four, I will not revoke its sentence; because he pursued  his brother with the sword, and cast off all pity; and his  anger did tear continually, and he kept his wrath for ever.
1:11|KJV|Thus saith the LORD; For three transgressions of Edom, and for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because he did pursue his brother with the sword, and did cast off all pity, and his anger did tear perpetually, and he kept his wrath for ever:
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華如此說，因以東三番四次的犯罪，我必不免去他的刑罰；因為他拿刀追趕兄弟，塞住憐恤，時常發怒撕裂，長懷忿怒。
1:12|ASV|but I will send a fire upon Teman, and it shall devour the palaces of Bozrah.
1:12|Darby|And I will send a fire upon Teman, and it shall devour the  palaces of Bozrah.
1:12|KJV|But I will send a fire upon Teman, which shall devour the palaces of Bozrah.
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我卻要降火在提幔，燒滅波斯拉的宮殿。
1:13|ASV|Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of the children of Ammon, yea, for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because they have ripped up the women with child of Gilead, that they may enlarge their border.
1:13|Darby|Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of the  children of Ammon, and for four, I will not revoke its  sentence; because they ripped up the women with child of  Gilead, that they might enlarge their border.
1:13|KJV|Thus saith the LORD; For three transgressions of the children of Ammon, and for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because they have ripped up the women with child of Gilead, that they might enlarge their border:
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華如此說，因亞捫人三番四次的犯罪，我必不免去他們的刑罰；因為他們剖開基列的孕婦，擴張自己的境界。
1:14|ASV|But I will kindle a fire in the wall of Rabbah, and it shall devour the palaces thereof, with shouting in the day of battle, with a tempest in the day of the whirlwind;
1:14|Darby|And I will kindle a fire in the wall of Rabbah, and it  shall devour the palaces thereof, with shouting in the day of  battle, with a tempest in the day of the whirlwind.
1:14|KJV|But I will kindle a fire in the wall of Rabbah, and it shall devour the palaces thereof, with shouting in the day of battle, with a tempest in the day of the whirlwind:
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我卻要在爭戰吶喊的日子，在暴風動盪的時候，點火在拉巴的城牆，燒滅其中的宮殿。
1:15<version name="ASV">and their king shall go into captivity, he and his princes together, saith Jehovah. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:15<version name="Darby">And their king shall go into captivity, he and his princes  together, saith Jehovah. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:15<version name="KJV">And their king shall go into captivity, he and his princes together, saith the LORD.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們的王和首領必一同被擄去，這是耶和華說的。
2:1|ASV|Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Moab, yea, for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because he burned the bones of the king of Edom into lime:
2:1|Darby|Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Moab, and  for four, I will not revoke its sentence; because he burned the  bones of the king of Edom into lime.
2:1|KJV|Thus saith the LORD; For three transgressions of Moab, and for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because he burned the bones of the king of Edom into lime:
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華如此說，因摩押三番四次的犯罪，我必不免去他的刑罰；因為他將以東王的骸骨焚燒成灰。
2:2|ASV|but I will send a fire upon Moab, and it shall devour the palaces of Kerioth; and Moab shall die with tumult, with shouting, and with the sound of the trumpet;
2:2|Darby|And I will send a fire upon Moab, and it shall devour the  palaces of Kerijoth; and Moab shall die with tumult, with  shouting, [and] with the sound of the trumpet.
2:2|KJV|But I will send a fire upon Moab, and it shall devour the palaces of Kirioth: and Moab shall die with tumult, with shouting, and with the sound of the trumpet:
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我卻要降火在摩押，燒滅加略的宮殿；摩押必在鬨嚷、吶喊、角聲中死亡。
2:3|ASV|and I will cut off the judge from the midst thereof, and will slay all the princes thereof with him, saith Jehovah.
2:3|Darby|And I will cut off the judge from the midst thereof, and  will slay all the princes thereof with him, saith Jehovah.
2:3|KJV|And I will cut off the judge from the midst thereof, and will slay all the princes thereof with him, saith the LORD.
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必剪除摩押中的審判者，將其中的一切首領，和他一同殺戮，這是耶和華說的。
2:4|ASV|Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Judah, yea, for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because they have rejected the law of Jehovah, and have not kept his statutes, and their lies have caused them to err, after which their fathers did walk:
2:4|Darby|Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Judah, and  for four, I will not revoke its sentence; because they have  despised the law of Jehovah, and have not kept his statutes;  and their lies have caused them to err, after which their  fathers walked.
2:4|KJV|Thus saith the LORD; For three transgressions of Judah, and for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because they have despised the law of the LORD, and have not kept his commandments, and their lies caused them to err, after the which their fathers have walked:
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華如此說，因猶大三番四次的犯罪，我必不免去他們的刑罰；因為他們厭棄耶和華的律法，不遵守祂的律例；他們列祖所隨從的虛假偶像使他們走迷了。
2:5|ASV|but I will send a fire upon Judah, and it shall devour the palaces of Jerusalem.
2:5|Darby|And I will send a fire upon Judah, and it shall devour the  palaces of Jerusalem.
2:5|KJV|But I will send a fire upon Judah, and it shall devour the palaces of Jerusalem.
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我卻要降火在猶大，燒滅耶路撒冷的宮殿。
2:6|ASV|Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Israel, yea, for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because they have sold the righteous for silver, and the needy for a pair of shoes-
2:6|Darby|Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Israel, and  for four, I will not revoke its sentence; because they have  sold the righteous for silver, and the needy for a pair of  shoes;
2:6|KJV|Thus saith the LORD; For three transgressions of Israel, and for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because they sold the righteous for silver, and the poor for a pair of shoes;
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華如此說，因以色列三番四次的犯罪，我必不免去他們的刑罰；因他們為銀子賣了義人，為一雙鞋賣了窮人。
2:7|ASV|they that pant after the dust of the earth on the head of the poor, and turn aside the way of the meek: and a man and his father go unto the same maiden, to profane my holy name:
2:7|Darby|panting after the dust of the earth on the head of the poor,  and turning aside the way of the meek; and a man and his father  will go in unto the [same] maid, to profane my holy name.
2:7|KJV|That pant after the dust of the earth on the head of the poor, and turn aside the way of the meek: and a man and his father will go in unto the same maid, to profane my holy name:
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們見窮人頭上所蒙的塵土也都垂涎，阻礙謙卑人的道路；父子同去親近一個少年女子，以致褻瀆我的聖名。
2:8|ASV|and they lay themselves down beside every altar upon clothes taken in pledge; and in the house of their God they drink the wine of such as have been fined.
2:8|Darby|And they lay [themselves] down by every altar upon clothes  taken in pledge, and they drink [in] the house of their God the  wine of the condemned.
2:8|KJV|And they lay themselves down upon clothes laid to pledge by every altar, and they drink the wine of the condemned in the house of their god.
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們在各壇旁鋪人所抵押的衣服，臥在其上；又在他們神的廟中，喝受罰之人的酒。
2:9|ASV|Yet destroyed I the Amorite before them, whose height was like the height of the cedars, and he was strong as the oaks; yet I destroyed his fruit from above, and his roots from beneath.
2:9|Darby|But I destroyed the Amorite before them, whose height was as  the height of the cedars, and he was strong as the oaks; but I  destroyed his fruit from above, and his roots from beneath.
2:9|KJV|Yet destroyed I the Amorite before them, whose height was like the height of the cedars, and he was strong as the oaks; yet I destroyed his fruit from above, and his roots from beneath.
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我從以色列人面前除滅亞摩利人；他雖高大如香柏樹，堅固如橡樹，我卻毀壞其上的果子，滅絕其下的根本。
2:10|ASV|Also I brought you up out of the land of Egypt, and led you forty years in the wilderness, to possess the land of the Amorite.
2:10|Darby|And I brought you up from the land of Egypt, and led you  forty years in the wilderness, to possess the land of the  Amorite.
2:10|KJV|Also I brought you up from the land of Egypt, and led you forty years through the wilderness, to possess the land of the Amorite.
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我也將你們從埃及地領上來，在曠野引導你們四十年，使你們得亞摩利人之地為業。
2:11|ASV|And I raised up of your sons for prophets, and of your young men for Nazirites. Is it not even thus, O ye children of Israel? saith Jehovah.
2:11|Darby|And I raised up of your sons for prophets, and of your  young men for Nazarites. Is it not even thus, ye children of  Israel? saith Jehovah.
2:11|KJV|And I raised up of your sons for prophets, and of your young men for Nazarites. Is it not even thus, O ye children of Israel? saith the LORD.
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我從你們子孫中興起申言者，又從你們少年人中興起拿細耳人。以色列人哪，不是這樣麼？這是耶和華說的。
2:12|ASV|But ye gave the Nazirites wine to drink, and commanded the prophets, saying, Prophesy not.
2:12|Darby|And ye gave the Nazarites wine to drink; and commanded the  prophets, saying, Prophesy not.
2:12|KJV|But ye gave the Nazarites wine to drink; and commanded the prophets, saying, Prophesy not.
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們卻給拿細耳人酒喝，囑咐申言者說，不要說豫言。
2:13|ASV|Behold, I will press you in your place, as a cart presseth that is full of sheaves.
2:13|Darby|Behold, I will press upon you, as a cart presseth that is  full of sheaves.
2:13|KJV|Behold, I am pressed under you, as a cart is pressed that is full of sheaves.
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|看哪，我必壓你們，如同裝滿禾捆的車壓物一樣。
2:14|ASV|And flight shall perish from the swift; and the strong shall not strengthen his force; neither shall the mighty deliver himself;
2:14|Darby|And flight shall perish from the swift, and the strong  shall not strengthen his force, neither shall the mighty  deliver his soul.
2:14|KJV|Therefore the flight shall perish from the swift, and the strong shall not strengthen his force, neither shall the mighty deliver himself:
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|快跑的不能逃走，強壯的不能加力，剛勇的也不能救自己；
2:15|ASV|neither shall he stand that handleth the bow; and he that is swift of foot shall not deliver himself; neither shall he that rideth the horse deliver himself;
2:15|Darby|Neither shall he stand that handleth the bow; and the swift  of foot shall not escape, and he that rideth the horse shall  not deliver his soul;
2:15|KJV|Neither shall he stand that handleth the bow; and he that is swift of foot shall not deliver himself: neither shall he that rideth the horse deliver himself.
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|拿弓的不能站立，腿快的不能逃脫，騎馬的也不能救自己。
2:16<version name="ASV">and he that is courageous among the mighty shall flee away naked in that day, saith Jehovah. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:16<version name="Darby">and he that is stout-hearted among the mighty shall flee  away naked in that day, saith Jehovah. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:16<version name="KJV">And he that is courageous among the mighty shall flee away naked in that day, saith the LORD.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|到那日，勇士中最有膽量的，必赤身逃跑，這是耶和華說的。
3:1|ASV|Hear this word that Jehovah hath spoken against you, O children of Israel, against the whole family which I brought up out of the land of Egypt, saying,
3:1|Darby|Hear this word that Jehovah hath spoken against you,  children of Israel, against the whole family that I brought up  from the land of Egypt, saying,
3:1|KJV|Hear this word that the LORD hath spoken against you, O children of Israel, against the whole family which I brought up from the land of Egypt, saying,
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列人哪，你們全族是我從埃及地領上來的，當聽耶和華攻擊你們的這話，說，
3:2|ASV|You only have I known of all the families of the earth: therefore I will visit upon you all your iniquities.
3:2|Darby|You only have I known of all the families of the earth;  therefore will I visit upon you all your iniquities.
3:2|KJV|You only have I known of all the families of the earth: therefore I will punish you for all your iniquities.
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在地上萬族中，我只認識你們；因此，我必追討你們的一切罪孽。
3:3|ASV|Shall two walk together, except they have agreed?
3:3|Darby|Shall two walk together except they be agreed?
3:3|KJV|Can two walk together, except they be agreed?
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|二人若不在約定的地方相會，豈能同行呢？
3:4|ASV|Will a lion roar in the forest, when he hath no prey? will a young lion cry out of his den, if he have taken nothing?
3:4|Darby|Will a lion roar in the forest when he hath no prey? Will a  young lion cry out of his den if he have taken nothing?
3:4|KJV|Will a lion roar in the forest, when he hath no prey? will a young lion cry out of his den, if he have taken nothing?
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|獅子若無獵物，豈會在林中咆哮麼？少壯獅子若無所得，豈會從洞中發聲麼？
3:5|ASV|Can a bird fall in a snare upon the earth, where no gin is set for him? shall a snare spring up from the ground, and have taken nothing at all?
3:5|Darby|Can a bird fall in a snare upon the earth when no gin [is  laid] for him? Will the snare spring up from the earth when  nothing at all hath been taken?
3:5|KJV|Can a bird fall in a snare upon the earth, where no gin is for him? shall one take up a snare from the earth, and have taken nothing at all?
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若沒有設網羅的，雀鳥豈會陷在地上的網羅婸礡H網羅若無所得，豈會從地上彈起麼？
3:6|ASV|Shall the trumpet be blown in a city, and the people not be afraid? shall evil befall a city, and Jehovah hath not done it?
3:6|Darby|Shall a trumpet be blown in the city, and the people not be  afraid? Shall there be evil in a city, and Jehovah not have  done [it]?
3:6|KJV|Shall a trumpet be blown in the city, and the people not be afraid? shall there be evil in a city, and the LORD hath not done it?
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|城中若吹角，百姓豈不驚恐麼？城中若有災禍，豈非耶和華所降的麼？
3:7|ASV|Surely the Lord Jehovah will do nothing, except he reveal his secret unto his servants the prophets.
3:7|Darby|But the Lord Jehovah will do nothing, but he revealeth his  secret unto his servants the prophets.
3:7|KJV|Surely the Lord GOD will do nothing, but he revealeth his secret unto his servants the prophets.
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主耶和華若不將祕密啟示祂的僕人眾申言者，就一無所行。
3:8|ASV|The lion hath roared; who will not fear? The Lord Jehovah hath spoken; who can but prophesy?
3:8|Darby|The lion hath roared, -- who will not fear? The Lord Jehovah  hath spoken, -- who can but prophesy?
3:8|KJV|The lion hath roared, who will not fear? the Lord GOD hath spoken, who can but prophesy?
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|獅子吼叫，誰不懼怕呢？主耶和華說了話，誰能不申言呢？
3:9|ASV|Publish ye in the palaces at Ashdod, and in the palaces in the land of Egypt, and say, Assemble yourselves upon the mountains of Samaria, and behold what great tumults are therein, and what oppressions in the midst thereof.
3:9|Darby|Publish in the palaces at Ashdod, and in the palaces in the  land of Egypt, and say, Assemble yourselves upon the mountains  of Samaria, and behold the great uproar in the midst thereof,  and the oppressions that are within her:
3:9|KJV|Publish in the palaces at Ashdod, and in the palaces in the land of Egypt, and say, Assemble yourselves upon the mountains of Samaria, and behold the great tumults in the midst thereof, and the oppressed in the midst thereof.
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|要在亞實突的宮殿中，和埃及地的宮殿堙A使人聽見，說，你們要聚集在撒瑪利亞的山上，就看見城中有何等大的擾亂，在城內有何等的欺壓；
3:10|ASV|For they know not to do right, saith Jehovah, who store up violence and robbery in their palaces.
3:10|Darby|and they know not to do right, saith Jehovah, who store up  violence and plunder in their palaces.
3:10|KJV|For they know not to do right, saith the LORD, who store up violence and robbery in their palaces.
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那些把強暴和殘害，積蓄在自己宮中的人，不知道行正直的事；這是耶和華說的。
3:11|ASV|Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: An adversary there shall be, even round about the land; and he shall bring down thy strength from thee, and thy palaces shall be plundered.
3:11|Darby|Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: An adversary! --  even round about the land! And he shall bring down thy strength  from thee, and thy palaces shall be pillaged.
3:11|KJV|Therefore thus saith the Lord GOD; An adversary there shall be even round about the land; and he shall bring down thy strength from thee, and thy palaces shall be spoiled.
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以主耶和華如此說，必有敵人包圍這地，使你的勢力衰微，搶掠你的宮殿。
3:12|ASV|Thus saith Jehovah: As the shepherd rescueth out of the mouth of the lion two legs, or a piece of an ear, so shall the children of Israel be rescued that sit in Samaria in the corner of a couch, and on the silken cushions of a bed.
3:12|Darby|Thus saith Jehovah: Like as the shepherd rescueth out of  the jaw of the lion two legs, or a piece of an ear; so shall  the children of Israel be rescued that sit in Samaria in the  corner of a couch, and upon the damask of a bed.
3:12|KJV|Thus saith the LORD; As the shepherd taketh out of the mouth of the lion two legs, or a piece of an ear; so shall the children of Israel be taken out that dwell in Samaria in the corner of a bed, and in Damascus in a couch.
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華如此說，牧人怎樣從獅子口中搶回兩條羊腿或一片耳朵，住撒瑪利亞的以色列人得救，也不過只剩床榻的一角，和一件鋪絲毯的床褥。
3:13|ASV|Hear ye, and testify against the house of Jacob, saith the Lord Jehovah, the God of hosts.
3:13|Darby|Hear ye, and testify in the house of Jacob, saith the Lord  Jehovah, the God of hosts,
3:13|KJV|Hear ye, and testify in the house of Jacob, saith the Lord GOD, the God of hosts,
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主耶和華萬軍之神說，當聽這話，作證警戒雅各家。
3:14|ASV|For in the day that I shall visit the transgressions of Israel upon him, I will also visit the altars of Beth-el; and the horns of the altar shall be cut off, and fall to the ground.
3:14|Darby|that in the day that I shall visit the transgressions of  Israel upon him, I will also punish the altars of Bethel; and  the horns of the altar shall be cut off, and fall to the  ground.
3:14|KJV|That in the day that I shall visit the transgressions of Israel upon him I will also visit the altars of Bethel: and the horns of the altar shall be cut off, and fall to the ground.
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我追討以色列罪的日子，也要追討伯特利祭壇的罪；壇角必被砍下，墜落於地。
3:15<version name="ASV">And I will smite the winter-house with the summer-house; and the houses of ivory shall perish, and the great houses shall have an end, saith Jehovah. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:15<version name="Darby">And I will smite the winter-house with the summer-house;  and the houses of ivory shall perish, and many houses shall  have an end, saith Jehovah. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:15<version name="KJV">And I will smite the winter house with the summer house; and the houses of ivory shall perish, and the great houses shall have an end, saith the LORD.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我要擊打過冬和過夏的房屋，象牙的房屋也必毀滅，許多房屋必歸無有，這是耶和華說的。
4:1|ASV|Hear this word, ye kine of Bashan, that are in the mountain of Samaria, that oppress the poor, that crush the needy, that say unto their lords, Bring, and let us drink.
4:1|Darby|Hear this word, ye kine of Bashan, that are in the mountain  of Samaria, that oppress the poor, that crush the needy, that  say to their lords, Bring, and let us drink:
4:1|KJV|Hear this word, ye kine of Bashan, that are in the mountain of Samaria, which oppress the poor, which crush the needy, which say to their masters, Bring, and let us drink.
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們在撒瑪利亞山上的巴珊母牛阿，當聽這話；你們欺負貧寒的，壓碎窮乏的，對他們的主人說，拿酒來，我們喝罷。
4:2|ASV|The Lord Jehovah hath sworn by his holiness, that, lo, the days shall come upon you, that they shall take you away with hooks, and your residue with fish-hooks.
4:2|Darby|the Lord Jehovah hath sworn by his holiness, that behold,  days shall come upon you, when he will take you away with  hooks, and your posterity with fish-hooks;
4:2|KJV|The Lord GOD hath sworn by his holiness, that, lo, the days shall come upon you, that he will take you away with hooks, and your posterity with fishhooks.
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主耶和華指著自己的聖別起誓，說，日子快要臨到你們，人必用鉤子將你們鉤去，用魚鉤將你們的後代鉤去。
4:3|ASV|And ye shall go out at the breaches, every one straight before her; and ye shall cast yourselves into Harmon, saith Jehovah.
4:3|Darby|and ye shall go out by the breaches, every one straight  before her, and ye shall be cast out to Harmon, saith Jehovah.
4:3|KJV|And ye shall go out at the breaches, every cow at that which is before her; and ye shall cast them into the palace, saith the LORD.
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們各人必從破口直往前行，投入哈門；這是耶和華說的。
4:4|ASV|Come to Beth-el, and transgress; to Gilgal, and multiply transgression; and bring your sacrifices every morning, and your tithes every three days;
4:4|Darby|Come to Bethel, and transgress; at Gilgal multiply  transgression; and bring your sacrifices in the morning, your  tithes every three days,
4:4|KJV|Come to Bethel, and transgress; at Gilgal multiply transgression; and bring your sacrifices every morning, and your tithes after three years:
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們往伯特利去犯罪，到吉甲加增罪過；每日早晨獻上你們的祭物，每三日奉上你們的十分之一。
4:5|ASV|and offer a sacrifice of thanksgiving of that which is leavened, and proclaim freewill-offerings and publish them: for this pleaseth you, O ye children of Israel, saith the Lord Jehovah.
4:5|Darby|and burn a thank-offering with leaven, and proclaim,  publish, voluntary offerings: for this pleaseth you, children  of Israel, saith the Lord Jehovah.
4:5|KJV|And offer a sacrifice of thanksgiving with leaven, and proclaim and publish the free offerings: for this liketh you, O ye children of Israel, saith the Lord GOD.
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列人哪，你們獻有酵的感謝祭，宣報甘心祭給眾人聽見；因為這些是你們所喜愛的，這是主耶和華說的。
4:6|ASV|And I also have given you cleanness of teeth in all your cities, and want of bread in all your places; yet have ye not returned unto me, saith Jehovah.
4:6|Darby|And I also have given you cleanness of teeth in all your  cities, and want of bread in all your places; yet ye have not  returned unto me, saith Jehovah.
4:6|KJV|And I also have given you cleanness of teeth in all your cities, and want of bread in all your places: yet have ye not returned unto me, saith the LORD.
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我也使你們在一切城中牙齒乾淨，在你們各處糧食缺乏。你們仍不歸向我；這是耶和華說的。
4:7|ASV|And I also have withholden the rain from you, when there were yet three months to the harvest; and I caused it to rain upon one city, and caused it not to rain upon another city: one piece was rained upon, and the piece whereupon it rained not withered.
4:7|Darby|And I also have withholden the rain from you, when there  were yet three months to the harvest; and I caused it to rain  upon one city, and caused it not to rain upon another city: one  piece [of land] was rained upon, and the piece whereupon it  rained not withered.
4:7|KJV|And also I have withholden the rain from you, when there were yet three months to the harvest: and I caused it to rain upon one city, and caused it not to rain upon another city: one piece was rained upon, and the piece whereupon it rained not withered.
4:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在收割的前三月，我使雨停止，不降給你們；我降雨在一座城，不降雨在另一座城；一塊地有雨，另一塊地無雨，就枯乾了。
4:8|ASV|So two or three cities wandered unto one city to drink water, and were not satisfied: yet have ye not returned unto me, saith Jehovah.
4:8|Darby|And two, three, cities wandered unto one city, to drink  water, and were not satisfied: yet have ye not returned unto  me, saith Jehovah.
4:8|KJV|So two or three cities wandered unto one city, to drink water; but they were not satisfied: yet have ye not returned unto me, saith the LORD.
4:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|兩三城的人湊到一城去喝水，卻喝不足。你們仍不歸向我；這是耶和華說的。
4:9|ASV|I have smitten you with blasting and mildew: the multitude of your gardens and your vineyards and your fig-trees and your olive-trees hath the palmer-worm devoured: yet have ye not returned unto me, saith Jehovah.
4:9|Darby|I have smitten you with blasting and mildew; the palmer-worm  hath devoured the multitude of your gardens, and your  vineyards, and your fig-trees and your olive-trees: yet have ye  not returned unto me, saith Jehovah.
4:9|KJV|I have smitten you with blasting and mildew: when your gardens and your vineyards and your fig trees and your olive trees increased, the palmerworm devoured them: yet have ye not returned unto me, saith the LORD.
4:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我以旱風、霉爛擊打你們；你們的許多園子和葡萄園，你們的無花果樹、橄欖樹，都被剪蝗吞喫；你們仍不歸向我；這是耶和華說的。
4:10|ASV|I have sent among you the pestilence after the manner of Egypt: your young men have I slain with the sword, and have carried away your horses; and I have made the stench of your camp to come up even into your nostrils: yet have ye not returned unto me, saith Jehovah.
4:10|Darby|I have sent among you the pestilence after the manner of  Egypt: your young men have I slain with the sword, taking away  captive your horses; and I made the stench of your camps to  come up, even into your nostrils: yet have ye not returned unto  me, saith Jehovah.
4:10|KJV|I have sent among you the pestilence after the manner of Egypt: your young men have I slain with the sword, and have taken away your horses; and I have made the stink of your camps to come up unto your nostrils: yet have ye not returned unto me, saith the LORD.
4:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我打發瘟疫到你們中間，像到埃及一樣；用刀殺戮你們的少年人，使你們的馬匹被擄掠；我使你們營中屍首的臭氣撲鼻；你們仍不歸向我；這是耶和華說的。
4:11|ASV|I have overthrown cities among you, as when God overthrew Sodom and Gomorrah, and ye were as a brand plucked out of the burning: yet have ye not returned unto me, saith Jehovah.
4:11|Darby|I have overthrown among you, like God's overthrow of Sodom  and Gomorrah, and ye were as a brand plucked out of the  burning; yet have ye not returned unto me, saith Jehovah.
4:11|KJV|I have overthrown some of you, as God overthrew Sodom and Gomorrah, and ye were as a firebrand plucked out of the burning: yet have ye not returned unto me, saith the LORD.
4:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我傾覆你們中間的城邑，如同神從前傾覆所多瑪、蛾摩拉一樣，使你們好像從火中抽出來的一根柴；你們仍不歸向我，這是耶和華說的。
4:12|ASV|Therefore thus will I do unto thee, O Israel; and because I will do this unto thee, prepare to meet thy God, O Israel.
4:12|Darby|Therefore thus will I do unto thee, O Israel: because I  will do this unto thee, prepare to meet thy God, O Israel.
4:12|KJV|Therefore thus will I do unto thee, O Israel: and because I will do this unto thee, prepare to meet thy God, O Israel.
4:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此，以色列阿，我必向你這樣行；以色列阿，我既必這樣行，你當豫備迎見你的神。
4:13<version name="ASV">For, lo, he that formeth the mountains, and createth the wind, and declareth unto man what is his thought; that maketh the morning darkness, and treadeth upon the high places of the Earth-jehovah, the God of hosts, is his name. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:13<version name="Darby">For behold, he who formeth the mountains, and createth the  wind, and declareth unto man what is his thought, who maketh  the morning darkness, and treadeth upon the high places of the  earth, -- Jehovah, the God of hosts, is his name. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:13<version name="KJV">For, lo, he that formeth the mountains, and createth the wind, and declareth unto man what is his thought, that maketh the morning darkness, and treadeth upon the high places of the earth, The LORD, The God of hosts, is his name.</p><p /><br /></version>
4:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那造山，創風，將祂的意念指示人，使晨光變為幽暗，腳踏在地之高處的，耶和華萬軍之神是祂的名！
5:1|ASV|Hear ye this word which I take up for a lamentation over you, O house of Israel.
5:1|Darby|Hear this word, a lamentation, which I take up against you,  O house of Israel.
5:1|KJV|Hear ye this word which I take up against you, even a lamentation, O house of Israel.
5:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列家阿，要聽這話，就是我為你們所作的哀歌。
5:2|ASV|The virgin of Israel is fallen; she shall no more rise: she is cast down upon her land; there is none to raise her up.
5:2|Darby|The virgin of Israel is fallen; she shall no more arise: she  is cast down upon her land; there is none to raise her up.
5:2|KJV|The virgin of Israel is fallen; she shall no more rise: she is forsaken upon her land; there is none to raise her up.
5:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列處女跌倒，不得再起；她被拋在自己地上，無人攙扶。
5:3|ASV|For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: The city that went forth a thousand shall have a hundred left, and that which went forth a hundred shall have ten left, to the house of Israel.
5:3|Darby|For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: The city that went forth a  thousand shall have a hundred left, and that which went forth a  hundred shall have ten left, for the house of Israel.
5:3|KJV|For thus saith the Lord GOD; The city that went out by a thousand shall leave an hundred, and that which went forth by an hundred shall leave ten, to the house of Israel.
5:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為主耶和華如此說，以色列家的城發出一千兵的，只剩一百；發出一百的，只剩十個。
5:4|ASV|For thus saith Jehovah unto the house of Israel, Seek ye me, and ye shall live;
5:4|Darby|For thus saith Jehovah unto the house of Israel: Seek ye me,  and ye shall live.
5:4|KJV|For thus saith the LORD unto the house of Israel, Seek ye me, and ye shall live:
5:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華向以色列家如此說，你們要尋求我，就必存活；
5:5|ASV|but seek not Beth-el, nor enter into Gilgal, and pass not to Beer-sheba: for Gilgal shall surely go into captivity, and Beth-el shall come to nought.
5:5|Darby|And seek not Bethel, neither go to Gilgal, and pass not to  Beer-sheba; for Gilgal shall surely go into captivity, and  Bethel shall come to nought.
5:5|KJV|But seek not Bethel, nor enter into Gilgal, and pass not to Beersheba: for Gilgal shall surely go into captivity, and Bethel shall come to nought.
5:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不要尋求伯特利，不要進入吉甲，不要過到別是巴；因為吉甲必被擄掠，伯特利也必歸於無有。
5:6|ASV|Seek Jehovah, and ye shall live; lest he break out like fire in the house of Joseph, and it devour, and there be none to quench it in Beth-el.
5:6|Darby|Seek Jehovah, and ye shall live; lest he break out like fire  in the house of Joseph, and devour [it], and there be none to  quench [it] in Bethel.
5:6|KJV|Seek the LORD, and ye shall live; lest he break out like fire in the house of Joseph, and devour it, and there be none to quench it in Bethel.
5:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|要尋求耶和華，就必存活；免得祂在約瑟家如火焚燒，將其吞滅；伯特利的火無人撲滅。
5:7|ASV|Ye who turn justice to wormwood, and cast down righteousness to the earth,
5:7|Darby|Ye who turn judgment to wormwood, and cast down  righteousness to the earth,
5:7|KJV|Ye who turn judgment to wormwood, and leave off righteousness in the earth,
5:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們使公平變為茵蔯，將公義丟棄於地。
5:8|ASV|seek him that maketh the Pleiades and Orion, and turneth the shadow of death into the morning, and maketh the day dark with night; that calleth for the waters of the sea, and poureth them out upon the face of the earth (Jehovah is his name);
5:8|Darby|[seek him] that made the Pleiades and Orion, and turneth the  shadow of death into the morning, and maketh the day dark with  night; that calleth for the waters of the sea, and poureth them  out upon the face of the earth: Jehovah is his name.
5:8|KJV|Seek him that maketh the seven stars and Orion, and turneth the shadow of death into the morning, and maketh the day dark with night: that calleth for the waters of the sea, and poureth them out upon the face of the earth: The LORD is his name:
5:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那造昴星和參星，使死蔭變為早晨，使白日變為黑夜，召喚海水傾倒在地面上的，耶和華是祂的名，
5:9|ASV|that bringeth sudden destruction upon the strong, so that destruction cometh upon the fortress.
5:9|Darby|He causeth destruction to break forth suddenly upon the  strong, and bringeth destruction upon the fortress.
5:9|KJV|That strengtheneth the spoiled against the strong, so that the spoiled shall come against the fortress.
5:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂使強壯的忽遭毀滅，以致保障遭遇毀壞。
5:10|ASV|They hate him that reproveth in the gate, and they abhor him that speaketh uprightly.
5:10|Darby|They hate him that reproveth in the gate, and they abhor  him that speaketh uprightly.
5:10|KJV|They hate him that rebuketh in the gate, and they abhor him that speaketh uprightly.
5:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們怨恨那在城門口責備人的，憎惡那說話純全的。
5:11|ASV|Forasmuch therefore as ye trample upon the poor, and take exactions from him of wheat: ye have built houses of hewn stone, but ye shall not dwell in them; ye have planted pleasant vineyards, but ye shall not drink the wine thereof.
5:11|Darby|Forasmuch, therefore, as ye trample upon the poor, and take  from him presents of wheat: ye have built houses of hewn stone,  but ye shall not dwell in them; ye have planted pleasant  vineyards, and ye shall not drink the wine of them.
5:11|KJV|Forasmuch therefore as your treading is upon the poor, and ye take from him burdens of wheat: ye have built houses of hewn stone, but ye shall not dwell in them; ye have planted pleasant vineyards, but ye shall not drink wine of them.
5:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為你們踐踏貧民，從他們強取麥子為禮物；所以你們用鑿過的石頭建造房屋，卻不得住在其內，栽種美好的葡萄園，卻不得喝所出的酒。
5:12|ASV|For I know how manifold are your transgressions, and how mighty are your sins-ye that afflict the just, that take a bribe, and that turn aside the needy in the gate from their right.
5:12|Darby|For I know how manifold are your transgressions and your  sins mighty: they afflict the just, they take a bribe, and they  turn aside [the right of] the needy in the gate.
5:12|KJV|For I know your manifold transgressions and your mighty sins: they afflict the just, they take a bribe, and they turn aside the poor in the gate from their right.
5:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我知道你們的過犯甚多，你們的罪極大；你們苦待義人，收受贖金，在城門口屈枉窮乏人。
5:13|ASV|Therefore he that is prudent shall keep silence in such a time; for it is an evil time.
5:13|Darby|Therefore the prudent shall keep silence in this time; for  it is an evil time.
5:13|KJV|Therefore the prudent shall keep silence in that time; for it is an evil time.
5:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以通達人在這時候，必靜默不言，因為時候邪惡。
5:14|ASV|Seek good, and not evil, that ye may live; and so Jehovah, the God of hosts, will be with you, as ye say.
5:14|Darby|Seek good, and not evil, that ye may live; and so Jehovah,  the God of hosts, shall be with you, as ye say.
5:14|KJV|Seek good, and not evil, that ye may live: and so the LORD, the God of hosts, shall be with you, as ye have spoken.
5:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要求善，不要求惡，就必存活；這樣，耶和華萬軍之神必照你們所說的，與你們同在。
5:15|ASV|Hate the evil, and love the good, and establish justice in the gate: it may be that Jehovah, the God of hosts, will be gracious unto the remnant of Joseph.
5:15|Darby|Hate evil, and love good, and establish judgment in the  gate: it may be that Jehovah, the God of hosts, will be  gracious unto the remnant of Joseph.
5:15|KJV|Hate the evil, and love the good, and establish judgment in the gate: it may be that the LORD God of hosts will be gracious unto the remnant of Joseph.
5:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|要恨惡邪惡，喜愛良善，在城門口建立公義；或者耶和華萬軍之神，向約瑟的餘民施恩。
5:16|ASV|Therefore thus saith Jehovah, the God of hosts, the Lord: Wailing shall be in all the broad ways; and they shall say in all the streets, Alas! Alas! and they shall call the husbandman to mourning, and such as are skilful in lamentation to wailing.
5:16|Darby|Therefore thus saith Jehovah, the God of hosts, the Lord:  Wailing shall be in all broadways; and they shall say in all  the streets, Alas! alas! And they shall call the husbandman to  mourning, and such as are skilful of lamentation to wailing.
5:16|KJV|Therefore the LORD, the God of hosts, the LORD, saith thus; Wailing shall be in all streets; and they shall say in all the highways, Alas! alas! and they shall call the husbandman to mourning, and such as are skilful of lamentation to wailing.
5:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此主耶和華萬軍之神如此說，在一切寬闊處必有哀號的聲音；在各街道上必有人說，哀哉！哀哉！又必叫農夫來哭號，叫善唱哀歌的來哀哭。
5:17|ASV|And in all vineyards shall be wailing; for I will pass through the midst of thee, saith Jehovah.
5:17|Darby|And in all vineyards shall be wailing; for I will pass  through the midst of thee, saith Jehovah.
5:17|KJV|And in all vineyards shall be wailing: for I will pass through thee, saith the LORD.
5:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在各葡萄園必有哀哭的聲音，因為我必從你中間經過；這是耶和華說的。
5:18|ASV|Woe unto you that desire the day of Jehovah! Wherefore would ye have the day of Jehovah? It is darkness, and not light.
5:18|Darby|Woe unto you that desire the day of Jehovah! To what end is  the day of Jehovah for you? It shall be darkness and not light:
5:18|KJV|Woe unto you that desire the day of the LORD! to what end is it for you? the day of the LORD is darkness, and not light.
5:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|想望耶和華日子來到的，有禍了！耶和華的日子與你們有甚麼好處呢？那日黑暗無光，
5:19|ASV|As if a man did flee from a lion, and a bear met him; or went into the house and leaned his hand on the wall, and a serpent bit him.
5:19|Darby|as if a man fled from a lion, and a bear met him; or went  into the house and leaned his hand on the wall, and a serpent  bit him.
5:19|KJV|As if a man did flee from a lion, and a bear met him; or went into the house, and leaned his hand on the wall, and a serpent bit him.
5:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|好像人躲避獅子，卻遇見熊，或是進房屋以手靠牆，就被蛇咬。
5:20|ASV|Shall not the day of Jehovah be darkness, and not light? even very dark, and no brightness in it?
5:20|Darby|Shall not the day of Jehovah be darkness, and not light?  even very dark, and no brightness in it?
5:20|KJV|Shall not the day of the LORD be darkness, and not light? even very dark, and no brightness in it?
5:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華的日子，不是黑暗無光麼？不是幽暗毫無光輝麼？
5:21|ASV|I hate, I despise your feasts, and I will take no delight in your solemn assemblies.
5:21|Darby|I hate, I despise your feasts, and I will not smell [a  sweet odour] in your solemn assemblies.
5:21|KJV|I hate, I despise your feast days, and I will not smell in your solemn assemblies.
5:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我恨惡厭棄你們的節期，也不喜悅你們的嚴肅會。
5:22|ASV|Yea, though ye offer me your burnt-offerings and meal-offerings, I will not accept them; neither will I regard the peace-offerings of your fat beasts.
5:22|Darby|For if ye offer up unto me burnt-offerings and your  oblations, I will not accept [them]; neither will I regard the  peace-offerings of your fatted beasts.
5:22|KJV|Though ye offer me burnt offerings and your meat offerings, I will not accept them: neither will I regard the peace offerings of your fat beasts.
5:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們雖然向我獻上燔祭和素祭，我卻不悅納；也不顧你們用肥畜所獻的平安祭。
5:23|ASV|Take thou away from me the noise of thy songs; for I will not hear the melody of thy viols.
5:23|Darby|Take away from me the noise of thy songs, and I will not  hear the melody of thy lutes;
5:23|KJV|Take thou away from me the noise of thy songs; for I will not hear the melody of thy viols.
5:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要使歌唱的聲音遠離我，因為我不聽你們彈琴的響聲。
5:24|ASV|But let justice roll down as waters, and righteousness as a mighty stream.
5:24|Darby|but let judgment roll down as waters, and righteousness as  an ever-flowing stream.
5:24|KJV|But let judgment run down as waters, and righteousness as a mighty stream.
5:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|惟願公平如大水滾滾，公義如江河滔滔。
5:25|ASV|Did ye bring unto me sacrifices and offerings in the wilderness forty years, O house of Israel?
5:25|Darby|Did ye bring unto me sacrifices and oblations in the  wilderness forty years, O house of Israel?
5:25|KJV|Have ye offered unto me sacrifices and offerings in the wilderness forty years, O house of Israel?
5:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列家阿，你們在曠野四十年，豈是將祭牲和素祭獻給我呢？
5:26|ASV|Yea, ye have borne the tabernacle of your king and the shrine of your images, the star of your god, which ye made to yourselves.
5:26|Darby|Yea, ye took up the tabernacle of your Moloch, and Chiun  your images, the star of your god, which ye had made to  yourselves;
5:26|KJV|But ye have borne the tabernacle of your Moloch and Chiun your images, the star of your god, which ye made to yourselves.
5:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們抬著你們的王索古特，並抬著你們的星神科完的像，就是你們為自己所造的。
5:27<version name="ASV">Therefore will I cause you to go into captivity beyond Damascus, saith Jehovah, whose name is the God of hosts. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:27<version name="Darby">and I will cause you to go into captivity beyond Damascus,  saith Jehovah, whose name is the God of hosts. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:27<version name="KJV">Therefore will I cause you to go into captivity beyond Damascus, saith the LORD, whose name is The God of hosts.</p><p /><br /></version>
5:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我要把你們擄到大馬色以外；這是耶和華說的；萬軍之神是祂的名。
6:1|ASV|Woe to them that are at ease in Zion, and to them that are secure in the mountain of Samaria, the notable men of the chief of the nations, to whom the house of Israel come!
6:1|Darby|Woe to them that are at ease in Zion and that are secure in  the mountain of Samaria, the renowned of the first of the  nations, to whom the house of Israel come.
6:1|KJV|Woe to them that are at ease in Zion, and trust in the mountain of Samaria, which are named chief of the nations, to whom the house of Israel came!
6:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在列國首領中著名，且為以色列家所歸向，在錫安安然無慮，在撒瑪利亞山自恃安穩的，有禍了！
6:2|ASV|Pass ye unto Calneh, and see; and from thence go ye to Hamath the great; then go down to Gath of the Philistines: are they better than these kingdoms? or is their border greater than your border?
6:2|Darby|Pass unto Calneh, and see; and from thence go to Hamath the  great; and go down to Gath of the Philistines: are they better  than these kingdoms? or their border greater than your border?
6:2|KJV|Pass ye unto Calneh, and see; and from thence go ye to Hamath the great: then go down to Gath of the Philistines: be they better than these kingdoms? or their border greater than your border?
6:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要過到甲尼察看，從那堜馱j城哈馬去，又下到非利士人的迦特。他們比這些國還強麼？他們的境界比你們的境界還大麼？
6:3|ASV|-ye that put far away the evil day, and cause the seat of violence to come near;
6:3|Darby|Ye that put far away the evil day, and cause the seat of  violence to come near;
6:3|KJV|Ye that put far away the evil day, and cause the seat of violence to come near;
6:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們推開降禍的日子，又使強暴的座位靠近，
6:4|ASV|that lie upon beds of ivory, and stretch themselves upon their couches, and eat the lambs out of the flock, and the calves out of the midst of the stall;
6:4|Darby|that lie upon beds of ivory, and stretch themselves upon  their couches, and eat the lambs out of the flock, and the  calves from the midst of the stall;
6:4|KJV|That lie upon beds of ivory, and stretch themselves upon their couches, and eat the lambs out of the flock, and the calves out of the midst of the stall;
6:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們躺臥在象牙床上，舒身在榻上，喫群中的羊羔和棚堛漱犢，
6:5|ASV|that sing idle songs to the sound of the viol; that invent for themselves instruments of music, like David;
6:5|Darby|that chant to the sound of the lute, [and] invent them  instruments of music, like David;
6:5|KJV|That chant to the sound of the viol, and invent to themselves instruments of musick, like David;
6:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在琴聲中閒談，為自己製造樂器，如同大衛所造的，
6:6|ASV|that drink wine in bowls, and anoint themselves with the chief oils; but they are not grieved for the affliction of Joseph.
6:6|Darby|that drink wine in bowls, and anoint themselves with the  chief ointments; but are not grieved for the breach of Joseph.
6:6|KJV|That drink wine in bowls, and anoint themselves with the chief ointments: but they are not grieved for the affliction of Joseph.
6:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以獻祭用的碗喝酒，用上等的油抹身；卻不為約瑟的毀壞憂傷。
6:7|ASV|Therefore shall they now go captive with the first that go captive; and the revelry of them that stretched themselves shall pass away.
6:7|Darby|Therefore shall they now go captive, with the first that go  captive, and the revelry of them that stretched themselves  shall pass away.
6:7|KJV|Therefore now shall they go captive with the first that go captive, and the banquet of them that stretched themselves shall be removed.
6:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以現在這些人必在被擄的人中首先被擄；舒身的人荒宴狂歡之聲必消滅了。
6:8|ASV|The Lord Jehovah hath sworn by himself, saith Jehovah, the God of hosts: I abhor the excellency of Jacob, and hate his palaces; therefore will I deliver up the city with all that is therein.
6:8|Darby|The Lord Jehovah hath sworn by himself, saith Jehovah, the  God of hosts, I abhor the pride of Jacob, and hate his palaces;  and I will deliver up the city with all that is therein.
6:8|KJV|The Lord GOD hath sworn by himself, saith the LORD the God of hosts, I abhor the excellency of Jacob, and hate his palaces: therefore will I deliver up the city with all that is therein.
6:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主耶和華萬軍之神指著自己起誓，說，我憎惡雅各的驕傲，厭恨他的宮殿；因此，我必將城和其中所充滿的，都交付敵人。
6:9|ASV|And it shall come to pass, if there remain ten men in one house, that they shall die.
6:9|Darby|And it shall come to pass, if there remain ten men in one  house, that they shall die.
6:9|KJV|And it shall come to pass, if there remain ten men in one house, that they shall die.
6:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時，若在一房之內剩下十個人，也都必死。
6:10|ASV|And when a man's uncle shall take him up, even he that burneth him, to bring out the bones out of the house, and shall say unto him that is in the innermost parts of the house, Is there yet any with thee? and he shall say, No; then shall he say, Hold thy peace; for we may not make mention of the name of Jehovah.
6:10|Darby|And a man's uncle, and he that should burn him, shall take  him up to bring out the bones from the house, and shall say  unto him that is in the inner parts of the house, Is there yet  [any] with thee? and he shall say, None. And he will say,  Silence! for we may not make mention of Jehovah's name.
6:10|KJV|And a man's uncle shall take him up, and he that burneth him, to bring out the bones out of the house, and shall say unto him that is by the sides of the house, Is there yet any with thee? and he shall say, No. Then shall he say, Hold thy tongue: for we may not make mention of the name of the LORD.
6:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|死人的親屬，就是燒他屍首的，要將骸骨搬到房外，對房屋內間的人說，你那媮晹酗H沒有？他必說，沒有；又說，不要作聲，因為不可題耶和華的名。
6:11|ASV|For, behold, Jehovah commandeth, and the great house shall be smitten with breaches, and the little house with clefts.
6:11|Darby|For behold, Jehovah commandeth, and he will smite the great  house with breaches, and the little house with clefts.
6:11|KJV|For, behold, the LORD commandeth, and he will smite the great house with breaches, and the little house with clefts.
6:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為耶和華出令，祂必將大房擊破，將小屋打碎。
6:12|ASV|Shall horses run upon the rock? will one plow there with oxen? that ye have turned justice into gall, and the fruit of righteousness into wormwood;
6:12|Darby|Shall horses run upon the rock? will [men] plough [thereon]  with oxen? For ye have turned judgment into gall, and the fruit  of righteousness into wormwood,
6:12|KJV|Shall horses run upon the rock? will one plow there with oxen? for ye have turned judgment into gall, and the fruit of righteousness into hemlock:
6:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|馬豈能在崖石上奔跑？人豈能在那堨峇耕種呢？你們卻使公理變為毒草，使公義的果子變為茵蔯，
6:13|ASV|ye that rejoice in a thing of nought, that say, Have we not taken to us horns by our own strength?
6:13|Darby|-- ye that rejoice in a thing of nought, that say, Have we  not taken to us power by our own strength?
6:13|KJV|Ye which rejoice in a thing of nought, which say, Have we not taken to us horns by our own strength?
6:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們喜愛虛無的事，你們說，我們不是憑自己的力量取得了角麼？
6:14<version name="ASV">For, behold, I will raise up against you a nation, O house of Israel, saith Jehovah, the God of hosts; and they shall afflict you from the entrance of Hamath unto the brook of the Arabah. </p><p /><br /></version>
6:14<version name="Darby">For behold, O house of Israel, saith Jehovah the God of  hosts, I will raise up against you a nation; and they shall  afflict you from the entering in of Hamath unto the torrent of  the Arabah. </p><p /><br /></version>
6:14<version name="KJV">But, behold, I will raise up against you a nation, O house of Israel, saith the LORD the God of hosts; and they shall afflict you from the entering in of Hemath unto the river of the wilderness.</p><p /><br /></version>
6:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華萬軍之神說，以色列家阿，我必興起一國攻擊你們；他們必欺壓你們，從哈馬口直到亞拉巴的河。
7:1|ASV|Thus the Lord Jehovah showed me: and, behold, he formed locusts in the beginning of the shooting up of the latter growth; and, lo, it was the latter growth after the king's mowings.
7:1|Darby|Thus did the Lord Jehovah shew unto me; and behold, he  formed locusts in the beginning of the shooting up of the  latter growth, and behold, it was the latter growth after the  king's mowings.
7:1|KJV|Thus hath the Lord GOD shewed unto me; and, behold, he formed grasshoppers in the beginning of the shooting up of the latter growth; and, lo, it was the latter growth after the king's mowings.
7:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主耶和華指給我看：在為王割草之後，春季作物剛開始生長時，主造了蝗蟲。
7:2|ASV|And it came to pass that, when they made an end of eating the grass of the land, then I said, O Lord Jehovah, forgive, I beseech thee: how shall Jacob stand? for he is small.
7:2|Darby|And it came to pass, when they had wholly eaten the grass of  the land, that I said, O Lord Jehovah, forgive, I beseech thee!  How shall Jacob arise? for he is small.
7:2|KJV|And it came to pass, that when they had made an end of eating the grass of the land, then I said, O Lord GOD, forgive, I beseech thee: by whom shall Jacob arise? for he is small.
7:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|蝗蟲喫盡那地的青物，我就說，主耶和華阿，求你赦免！因為雅各微小，他怎能站立得住呢？
7:3|ASV|Jehovah repented concerning this: It shall not be, saith Jehovah.
7:3|Darby|Jehovah repented for this: It shall not be, said Jehovah.
7:3|KJV|The LORD repented for this: It shall not be, saith the LORD.
7:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華就為此後悔：耶和華說，這災必不發生。
7:4|ASV|Thus the Lord Jehovah showed me: and, behold, the Lord Jehovah called to content by fire; and it devoured the great deep, and would have eaten up the land.
7:4|Darby|Thus did the Lord Jehovah shew unto me; and behold, the Lord  Jehovah called to contend by fire; and it devoured the great  deep, and ate up the inheritance.
7:4|KJV|Thus hath the Lord GOD shewed unto me: and, behold, the Lord GOD called to contend by fire, and it devoured the great deep, and did eat up a part.
7:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主耶和華又指給我看：主耶和華召來火的刑罰，火就吞滅深淵，燒滅那地。
7:5|ASV|Then said I, O Lord Jehovah, cease, I beseech thee: how shall Jacob stand? for he is small.
7:5|Darby|Then said I, O Lord Jehovah, cease, I beseech thee! How  shall Jacob arise? for he is small.
7:5|KJV|Then said I, O Lord GOD, cease, I beseech thee: by whom shall Jacob arise? for he is small.
7:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我就說，主耶和華阿，求你止息！因為雅各微小，他怎能站立得住呢？
7:6|ASV|Jehovah repented concerning this: this also shall not be, saith the Lord Jehovah.
7:6|Darby|Jehovah repented for this: This also shall not be, said the  Lord Jehovah.
7:6|KJV|The LORD repented for this: This also shall not be, saith the Lord GOD.
7:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華就為此後悔：主耶和華說，這災也必不發生。
7:7|ASV|Thus he showed me: and, behold, the Lord stood beside a wall made by a plumb-line, with a plumb-line in his hand.
7:7|Darby|Thus did he shew unto me; and behold, the Lord stood upon a  wall [made] by a plumb-line, with a plumb-line in his hand.
7:7|KJV|Thus he shewed me: and, behold, the LORD stood upon a wall made by a plumbline, with a plumbline in his hand.
7:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂又指給我看：主站在一道按準繩築好的牆上，祂手中拿著準繩。
7:8|ASV|And Jehovah said unto me, Amos, what seest thou? And I said, A plumb-line. Then said the Lord, Behold, I will set a plumb-line in the midst of my people Israel; I will not again pass by them any more;
7:8|Darby|And Jehovah said unto me, Amos, what seest thou? And I said,  A plumb-line. And the Lord said, Behold, I will set a  plumb-line in the midst of my people Israel: I will not again  pass by them any more.
7:8|KJV|And the LORD said unto me, Amos, what seest thou? And I said, A plumbline. Then said the LORD, Behold, I will set a plumbline in the midst of my people Israel: I will not again pass by them any more:
7:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華對我說，阿摩司阿，你看見甚麼？我說，一條準繩。主說，我要安放準繩在我民以色列中；我必不再放過他們。
7:9|ASV|and the high places of Isaac shall be desolate, and the sanctuaries of Israel shall be laid waste; and I will rise against the house of Jeroboam with the sword.
7:9|Darby|And the high places of Isaac shall be desolated, and the  sanctuaries of Israel shall be laid waste; and I will arise  against the house of Jeroboam with the sword.
7:9|KJV|And the high places of Isaac shall be desolate, and the sanctuaries of Israel shall be laid waste; and I will rise against the house of Jeroboam with the sword.
7:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以撒的邱壇必然荒廢，以色列的聖所必成荒場；我必興起，用刀攻擊耶羅波安的家。
7:10|ASV|Then Amaziah the priest of Beth-el sent to Jeroboam king of Israel, saying, Amos hath conspired against thee in the midst of the house of Israel: the land is not able to bear all his words.
7:10|Darby|Then Amaziah the priest of Bethel sent to Jeroboam king of  Israel, saying, Amos hath conspired against thee in the midst  of the house of Israel: the land is not able to bear all his  words.
7:10|KJV|Then Amaziah the priest of Bethel sent to Jeroboam king of Israel, saying, Amos hath conspired against thee in the midst of the house of Israel: the land is not able to bear all his words.
7:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|伯特利的祭司亞瑪謝打發人到以色列王耶羅波安那堙A說，阿摩司在以色列家中，圖謀背叛你；他所說的一切話，這地擔當不起。
7:11|ASV|For thus Amos saith, Jeroboam shall die by the sword, and Israel shall surely be led away captive out of his land.
7:11|Darby|For thus Amos saith: Jeroboam shall die by the sword, and  Israel shall certainly go into captivity out of his land.
7:11|KJV|For thus Amos saith, Jeroboam shall die by the sword, and Israel shall surely be led away captive out of their own land.
7:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為阿摩司如此說，耶羅波安必被刀殺，以色列民定被擄去，離開本地。
7:12|ASV|Also Amaziah said unto Amos, O thou seer, go, flee thou away into the land of Judah, and there eat bread, and prophesy there:
7:12|Darby|And Amaziah said unto Amos, [Thou] seer, go, flee away into  the land of Judah, and eat bread there, and prophesy there.
7:12|KJV|Also Amaziah said unto Amos, O thou seer, go, flee thee away into the land of Judah, and there eat bread, and prophesy there:
7:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞瑪謝又對阿摩司說，你這先見哪，要逃往猶大地去，在那崶M口，在那婸▼搢央F
7:13|ASV|but prophesy not again any more at Beth-el; for it is the king's sanctuary, and it is a royal house.
7:13|Darby|But prophesy not again any more at Bethel; for it is the  king's sanctuary, and it is the house of the kingdom.
7:13|KJV|But prophesy not again any more at Bethel: for it is the king's chapel, and it is the king's court.
7:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|卻不要在伯特利再說豫言，因為這堿O王的聖所，是王的宮殿。
7:14|ASV|Then answered Amos, and said to Amaziah, I was no prophet, neither was I a prophet's son; but I was a herdsman, and a dresser of sycomore-trees:
7:14|Darby|And Amos answered and said to Amaziah, I was no prophet,  neither was I a prophet's son; but I was a herdman, and a  gatherer of sycamore fruit.
7:14|KJV|Then answered Amos, and said to Amaziah, I was no prophet, neither was I a prophet's son; but I was an herdman, and a gatherer of sycomore fruit:
7:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|阿摩司回答亞瑪謝說，我原不是申言者，也不是申言者的兒子；我是牧人，又是修剪桑樹的。
7:15|ASV|and Jehovah took me from following the flock, and Jehovah said unto me, Go, prophesy unto my people Israel.
7:15|Darby|And Jehovah took me as I followed the flock, and Jehovah  said unto me, Go, prophesy unto my people Israel.
7:15|KJV|And the LORD took me as I followed the flock, and the LORD said unto me, Go, prophesy unto my people Israel.
7:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華選召我，使我不跟從羊群，對我說，你去向我民以色列說豫言。
7:16|ASV|Now therefore hear thou the word of Jehovah: Thou sayest, Prophesy not against Israel, and drop not thy word against the house of Isaac;
7:16|Darby|And now hear thou the word of Jehovah: Thou sayest,  Prophesy not against Israel, and utter not [words] against the  house of Isaac.
7:16|KJV|Now therefore hear thou the word of the LORD: Thou sayest, Prophesy not against Israel, and drop not thy word against the house of Isaac.
7:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞瑪謝阿，現在你要聽耶和華的話；你說，不要說豫言攻擊以色列，也不要說話攻擊以撒家。
7:17<version name="ASV">therefore thus saith Jehovah: Thy wife shall be a harlot in the city, and thy sons and thy daughters shall fall by the sword, and thy land shall be divided by line; and thou thyself shalt die in a land that is unclean, and Israel shall surely be led away captive out of his land. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:17<version name="Darby">Therefore thus saith Jehovah: Thy wife shall be a harlot in  the city, and thy sons and thy daughters shall fall by the  sword, and thy land shall be divided with the line; and thou  shalt die in a land that is unclean; and Israel shall certainly  go into captivity, out of his land. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:17<version name="KJV">Therefore thus saith the LORD; Thy wife shall be an harlot in the city, and thy sons and thy daughters shall fall by the sword, and thy land shall be divided by line; and thou shalt die in a polluted land: and Israel shall surely go into captivity forth of his land.</p><p /><br /></version>
7:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以耶和華如此說，你的妻子必在城中作妓女，你的兒女必倒在刀下，你的地必有人用繩子量了分取，你自己必死在污穢之地；以色列民定被擄去離開本地。
8:1|ASV|Thus the Lord Jehovah showed me: and, behold, a basket of summer fruit.
8:1|Darby|Thus did Jehovah shew unto me; and behold, a basket of  summer-fruit.
8:1|KJV|Thus hath the Lord GOD shewed unto me: and behold a basket of summer fruit.
8:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主耶和華又指給我看：有一筐夏天的果子。
8:2|ASV|And he said, Amos, what seest thou? And I said, A basket of summer fruit. Then said Jehovah unto me, The end is come upon my people Israel; I will not again pass by them any more.
8:2|Darby|And he said, Amos, what seest thou? And I said, A basket of  summer-fruit. And Jehovah said unto me, The end is come upon my  people Israel: I will not again pass by them any more.
8:2|KJV|And he said, Amos, what seest thou? And I said, A basket of summer fruit. Then said the LORD unto me, The end is come upon my people of Israel; I will not again pass by them any more.
8:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂說，阿摩司阿，你看見甚麼？我說，一筐夏天的果子。耶和華對我說，我民以色列的結局到了；我必不再放過他們。
8:3|ASV|And the songs of the temple shall be wailings in that day, saith the Lord Jehovah: the dead bodies shall be many: in every place shall they cast them forth with silence.
8:3|Darby|And the songs of the palace shall be howlings in that day,  saith the Lord Jehovah. The dead bodies shall be many; in every  place they shall be cast forth. Silence!
8:3|KJV|And the songs of the temple shall be howlings in that day, saith the Lord GOD: there shall be many dead bodies in every place; they shall cast them forth with silence.
8:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主耶和華說，那日殿中的詩歌必變為哀號。必有許多屍首在各處被人拋棄。你們不要作聲！
8:4|ASV|Hear this, O ye that would swallow up the needy, and cause the poor of the land to fail,
8:4|Darby|Hear this, ye that pant after the needy, even to cause to  fail the poor of the land,
8:4|KJV|Hear this, O ye that swallow up the needy, even to make the poor of the land to fail,
8:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們這些渴求奪取窮乏人，要除滅地上困苦人的，當聽這話。
8:5|ASV|saying, When will the new moon be gone, that we may sell grain? and the sabbath, that we may set forth wheat, making the ephah small, and the shekel great, and dealing falsely with balances of deceit;
8:5|Darby|saying, When will the new moon be gone, that we may sell  corn? and the sabbath, that we may set forth wheat? making the  ephah small and the shekel great, and falsifying the balances  for deceit:
8:5|KJV|Saying, When will the new moon be gone, that we may sell corn? and the sabbath, that we may set forth wheat, making the ephah small, and the shekel great, and falsifying the balances by deceit?
8:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們說，月朔幾時過去，我們好賣糧？安息日幾時過去，我們好擺開麥子，好把賣出用的量器弄小，把收銀用的法碼弄大，用詭詐的天平欺哄人；
8:6|ASV|that we may buy the poor for silver, and the needy for a pair of shoes, and sell the refuse of the wheat?
8:6|Darby|that we may buy the poor for silver, and the needy for a  pair of shoes; and that we may sell the refuse of the wheat.
8:6|KJV|That we may buy the poor for silver, and the needy for a pair of shoes; yea, and sell the refuse of the wheat?
8:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|好用銀子買貧寒人，用一雙鞋換窮乏人，將壞了的麥子賣給人。
8:7|ASV|Jehovah hath sworn by the excellency of Jacob, Surely I will never forget any of their works.
8:7|Darby|Jehovah hath sworn by the glory of Jacob, Certainly I will  never forget any of their works.
8:7|KJV|The LORD hath sworn by the excellency of Jacob, Surely I will never forget any of their works.
8:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華指著雅各的超絕起誓，說，他們的一切行為，我必永遠不忘。
8:8|ASV|Shall not the land tremble for this, and every one mourn that dwelleth therein? yea, it shall rise up wholly like the River; and it shall be troubled and sink again, like the River of Egypt.
8:8|Darby|Shall not the land tremble for this, and every one mourn  that dwelleth therein? And it shall wholly rise up like the  Nile; and it shall surge and sink down, as the river of Egypt.
8:8|KJV|Shall not the land tremble for this, and every one mourn that dwelleth therein? and it shall rise up wholly as a flood; and it shall be cast out and drowned, as by the flood of Egypt.
8:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|地豈不因這事震動，住在其上的不也都悲哀麼？地必全然像尼羅河漲起，如同埃及河湧上落下。
8:9|ASV|And it shall come to pass in that day, saith the Lord Jehovah, that I will cause the sun to go down at noon, and I will darken the earth in the clear day.
8:9|Darby|And it shall come to pass in that day, saith the Lord  Jehovah, that I will cause the sun to go down at noon, and I  will darken the land in the clear day.
8:9|KJV|And it shall come to pass in that day, saith the Lord GOD, that I will cause the sun to go down at noon, and I will darken the earth in the clear day:
8:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主耶和華說，到那日，我必使日頭在午間落下，使地在白日的光中變暗。
8:10|ASV|And I will turn your feasts into mourning, and all your songs into lamentation; and I will bring sackcloth upon all loins, and baldness upon every head; and I will make it as the mourning for an only son, and the end thereof as a bitter day.
8:10|Darby|And I will turn your feasts into mourning, and all your  songs into lamentation; and I will bring up sackcloth upon all  loins, and baldness upon every head; and I will make it as the  mourning for an only [son], and the end thereof as a bitter  day.
8:10|KJV|And I will turn your feasts into mourning, and all your songs into lamentation; and I will bring up sackcloth upon all loins, and baldness upon every head; and I will make it as the mourning of an only son, and the end thereof as a bitter day.
8:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必使你們的節期變為悲哀，一切歌曲變為哀歌；我必使眾人腰束麻布，頭上光禿；也必使這場悲哀如喪獨生子，至終如痛苦的日子一樣。
8:11|ASV|Behold, the days come, saith the Lord Jehovah, that I will send a famine in the land, not a famine of bread, nor a thirst for water, but of hearing the words of Jehovah.
8:11|Darby|Behold, days come, saith the Lord Jehovah, when I will send  a famine in the land; not a famine of bread, nor a thirst for  water, but of hearing the words of Jehovah.
8:11|KJV|Behold, the days come, saith the Lord GOD, that I will send a famine in the land, not a famine of bread, nor a thirst for water, but of hearing the words of the LORD:
8:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主耶和華說，日子將到，我必打發饑荒臨到這地；人飢餓非因無餅，乾渴非因無水，乃因聽不見耶和華的話。
8:12|ASV|And they shall wander from sea to sea, and from the north even to the east; they shall run to and fro to seek the word of Jehovah, and shall not find it.
8:12|Darby|And they shall wander from sea to sea, and from the north  to the east; they shall run to and fro to seek the word of  Jehovah, and shall not find it.
8:12|KJV|And they shall wander from sea to sea, and from the north even to the east, they shall run to and fro to seek the word of the LORD, and shall not find it.
8:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們必飄流，從這海到那海，從北邊到東邊；往來奔跑尋求耶和華的話，卻尋不著。
8:13|ASV|In that day shall the fair virgins and the young men faint for thirst.
8:13|Darby|In that day shall the fair virgins and the young men faint  for thirst;
8:13|KJV|In that day shall the fair virgins and young men faint for thirst.
8:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當那日，美貌的處女和少年的男子，必因乾渴發昏。
8:14<version name="ASV">They that swear by the sin of Samaria, and say, As thy god, O Dan, liveth; and, As the way of Beer-sheba liveth; they shall fall, and never rise up again. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:14<version name="Darby">they that swear by the sin of Samaria, and say, [As] thy  god, O Dan, liveth! and, [As] the way of Beer-sheba liveth!  even they shall fall, and never rise up again. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:14<version name="KJV">They that swear by the sin of Samaria, and say, Thy god, O Dan, liveth; and, The manner of Beersheba liveth; even they shall fall, and never rise up again.</p><p /><br /></version>
8:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那指著撒瑪利亞罪愆起誓的，說，但哪，我們指著你那堨穫〞滲城_誓！又說，我們指著別是巴永活的道起誓；這些人都必仆倒，不再起來。
9:1|ASV|I saw the Lord standing beside the altar: and he said, Smite the capitals, that the thresholds may shake; and break them in pieces on the head of all of them; and I will slay the last of them with the sword: there shall not one of them flee away, and there shall not one of them escape.
9:1|Darby|I saw the Lord standing upon the altar; and he said, Smite  the chapiter that the thresholds may shake; and break all of  them in pieces, in the head; and I will slay the last of them  with the sword: he that fleeth of them shall not get away by  flight, and he that escapeth of them shall not be delivered.
9:1|KJV|I saw the LORD standing upon the altar: and he said, Smite the lintel of the door, that the posts may shake: and cut them in the head, all of them; and I will slay the last of them with the sword: he that fleeth of them shall not flee away, and he that escapeth of them shall not be delivered.
9:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我看見主站在祭壇上面；祂說，你要擊打柱頂，使門檻震動，打碎柱頂落在眾人頭上，所剩下的人我必用刀殺戮；無一人能逃避，無一人能逃脫。
9:2|ASV|Though they dig into Sheol, thence shall my hand take them; and though they climb up to heaven, thence will I bring them down.
9:2|Darby|Though they dig into Sheol, thence shall my hand take them;  and though they climb up to the heavens, thence will I bring  them down;
9:2|KJV|Though they dig into hell, thence shall mine hand take them; though they climb up to heaven, thence will I bring them down:
9:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們雖然挖進陰間，我的手必從那堥出他們來；雖然爬上天去，我必從那堮酗U他們來。
9:3|ASV|And though they hide themselves in the top of Carmel, I will search and take them out thence; and though they be hid from my sight in the bottom of the sea, thence will I command the serpent, and it shall bite them.
9:3|Darby|and though they hide themselves on the top of Carmel, I will  search and take them out thence; and though they be hid from my  sight in the bottom of the sea, there will I command the  serpent, and it shall bite them;
9:3|KJV|And though they hide themselves in the top of Carmel, I will search and take them out thence; and though they be hid from my sight in the bottom of the sea, thence will I command the serpent, and he shall bite them:
9:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|雖然藏在迦密山頂，我必從那媟j尋捉出他們來；雖然從我眼前藏在海底，我必在那堜R蛇咬他們。
9:4|ASV|And though they go into captivity before their enemies, thence will I command the sword, and it shall slay them: and I will set mine eyes upon them for evil, and not for good.
9:4|Darby|and though they go into captivity before their enemies,  there will I command the sword, and it shall slay them: and I  will set mine eyes upon them for evil, and not for good.
9:4|KJV|And though they go into captivity before their enemies, thence will I command the sword, and it shall slay them: and I will set mine eyes upon them for evil, and not for good.
9:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|雖然被仇敵擄去，我必在那堜R刀劍殺戮他們；我必向他們定住眼目，降禍不降福。
9:5|ASV|For the Lord, Jehovah of hosts,  is he that toucheth the land and it melteth, and all that dwell therein shall mourn; and it shall rise up wholly like the River, and shall sink again, like the River of Egypt;
9:5|Darby|And the Lord Jehovah of hosts is he that toucheth the land,  and it melteth, and all that dwell therein shall mourn; and it  shall wholly rise up like the Nile, and sink down as the river  of Egypt.
9:5|KJV|And the Lord GOD of hosts is he that toucheth the land, and it shall melt, and all that dwell therein shall mourn: and it shall rise up wholly like a flood; and shall be drowned, as by the flood of Egypt.
9:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主萬軍之耶和華摸地，地就鎔化，凡住在其中的都必悲哀；地必全然像尼羅河漲起，如同埃及河落下。
9:6|ASV|it is he that buildeth his chambers in the heavens, and hath founded his vault upon the earth; he that calleth for the waters of the sea, and poureth them out upon the face of the earth; Jehovah is his name.
9:6|Darby|It is he that buildeth his upper chambers in the heavens,  and hath founded his vault upon the earth; he that calleth for  the waters of the sea, and poureth them out upon the face of  the earth: Jehovah is his name.
9:6|KJV|It is he that buildeth his stories in the heaven, and hath founded his troop in the earth; he that calleth for the waters of the sea, and poureth them out upon the face of the earth: The LORD is his name.
9:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那在天上建造樓閣，在地上立定穹蒼，召喚海水傾倒在地面的，耶和華是祂的名。
9:7|ASV|Are ye not as the children of the Ethiopians unto me, O children of Israel? saith Jehovah. Have not I brought up Israel out of the land of Egypt, and the Philistines from Caphtor, and the Syrians from Kir?
9:7|Darby|Are ye not as children of the Ethiopians unto me, O children  of Israel? saith Jehovah. Have not I brought up Israel out of  the land of Egypt? and the Philistines from Caphtor, and the  Syrians from Kir?
9:7|KJV|Are ye not as children of the Ethiopians unto me, O children of Israel? saith the LORD. Have not I brought up Israel out of the land of Egypt? and the Philistines from Caphtor, and the Syrians from Kir?
9:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華說，以色列人哪，我豈不看你們如古實人麼？我豈不是領以色列人從埃及地上來，領非利士人從迦斐託出來，領亞蘭人從吉珥出來麼？
9:8|ASV|Behold, the eyes of the Lord Jehovah are upon the sinful kingdom, and I will destroy it from off the face of the earth; save that I will not utterly destroy the house of Jacob, saith Jehovah.
9:8|Darby|Behold, the eyes of the Lord Jehovah are upon the sinful  kingdom, and I will destroy it from off the face of the earth:  only that I will not utterly destroy the house of Jacob, saith  Jehovah.
9:8|KJV|Behold, the eyes of the Lord GOD are upon the sinful kingdom, and I will destroy it from off the face of the earth; saving that I will not utterly destroy the house of Jacob, saith the LORD.
9:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主耶和華的眼目察看這有罪的國，必將這國從地面上除滅，卻不將雅各家滅絕淨盡，這是耶和華說的。
9:9|ASV|For, lo, I will command, and I will sift the house of Israel among all the nations, like as grain is sifted in a sieve, yet shall not the least kernel fall upon the earth.
9:9|Darby|For behold, I command, and I will shake the house of Israel  to and fro among all the nations, like as one shaketh [corn] in  a sieve; yet shall not the least grain fall upon the earth.
9:9|KJV|For, lo, I will command, and I will sift the house of Israel among all nations, like as corn is sifted in a sieve, yet shall not the least grain fall upon the earth.
9:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我必出令，將以色列家篩在列國中，好像穀粒用篩子篩過，然而連一粒也不落在地上。
9:10|ASV|All the sinners of my people shall die by the sword, who say, The evil shall not overtake nor meet us.
9:10|Darby|All the sinners of my people shall die by the sword, who  say, Evil shall not overtake nor befall us.
9:10|KJV|All the sinners of my people shall die by the sword, which say, The evil shall not overtake nor prevent us.
9:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我民中的一切罪人必死在刀下，他們說，災禍必追不上我們，也不四面臨到我們。
9:11|ASV|In that day will I raise up the tabernacle of David that is fallen, and close up the breaches thereof; and I will raise up its ruins, and I will build it as in the days of old;
9:11|Darby|In that day will I raise up the tabernacle of David which  is fallen, and close up the breaches thereof; and I will raise  up its ruins, and I will build it as in the days of old:
9:11|KJV|In that day will I raise up the tabernacle of David that is fallen, and close up the breaches thereof; and I will raise up his ruins, and I will build it as in the days of old:
9:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|到那日，我必建立大衛倒塌的帳幕，堵住其中的破口，把那毀壞的建立起來，重新修造，像古時一樣；
9:12|ASV|that they may possess the remnant of Edom, and all the nations that are called by my name, saith Jehovah that doeth this.
9:12|Darby|that they may possess the remnant of Edom, and all the  nations upon whom my name is called, saith Jehovah who doeth  this.
9:12|KJV|That they may possess the remnant of Edom, and of all the heathen, which are called by my name, saith the LORD that doeth this.
9:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|使以色列人得以東所餘剩的，和所有稱為我名下的國；這是行這事的耶和華說的。
9:13|ASV|Behold, the days come, saith Jehovah, that the plowman shall overtake the reaper, and the treader of grapes him that soweth seed; and the mountains shall drop sweet wine, and all the hills shall melt.
9:13|Darby|Behold, the days come, saith Jehovah, when the ploughman  shall overtake the reaper, and the treader of grapes him that  soweth seed; and the mountains shall drop new wine, and all the  hills shall melt.
9:13|KJV|Behold, the days come, saith the LORD, that the plowman shall overtake the reaper, and the treader of grapes him that soweth seed; and the mountains shall drop sweet wine, and all the hills shall melt.
9:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華說，日子將到，耕種的必追上收割的，踹葡萄的必追上撒種的；大山要滴下甜酒，小山都必鎔化。
9:14|ASV|And I will bring back the captivity of my people Israel, and they shall build the waste cities, and inhabit them; and they shall plant vineyards, and drink the wine thereof; they shall also make gardens, and eat the fruit of them.
9:14|Darby|And I will turn again the captivity of my people Israel,  and they shall build the waste cities, and inhabit them; and  they shall plant vineyards, and drink the wine thereof; and  they shall make gardens, and eat the fruit of them.
9:14|KJV|And I will bring again the captivity of my people of Israel, and they shall build the waste cities, and inhabit them; and they shall plant vineyards, and drink the wine thereof; they shall also make gardens, and eat the fruit of them.
9:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必使我民以色列被擄的歸回，他們必修建荒廢的城邑居住，栽種葡萄園，喝其中所出的酒，修造園子，喫其中的果子。
9:15<version name="ASV">And I will plant them upon their land, and they shall no more be plucked up out of their land which I have given them, saith Jehovah thy God. </p><p /><br /></version>
9:15<version name="Darby">And I will plant them upon their land, and they shall no  more be plucked up out of their land which I have given them,  saith Jehovah thy God. </p><p /><br /></version>
9:15<version name="KJV">And I will plant them upon their land, and they shall no more be pulled up out of their land which I have given them, saith the LORD thy God.</p><p /><br /></version>
9:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我要將他們栽於本地，他們不再從我所賜給他們的地上拔出來；這是耶和華你的神說的。
