1:1|ASV|Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus through the will of God, and Timothy our brother,
1:1|Darby|Paul, apostle of Christ Jesus, by God's will, and Timotheus  the brother,
1:1|KJV|Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God, and Timotheus our brother,
1:1|WYC|Paul, apostle of Jesus Christ, by the will of God, and Timothy, brother,
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|憑神旨意，作基督耶穌使徒的保羅，和弟兄提摩太，
1:2|ASV|To the saints and faithful brethren in Christ that are at Colossae: Grace to you and peace from God our Father.
1:2|Darby|to the holy and faithful brethren in Christ which [are] in  Colosse. Grace to you and peace from God our Father [and Lord  Jesus Christ].
1:2|KJV|To the saints and faithful brethren in Christ which are at Colosse: Grace be unto you, and peace, from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.
1:2|WYC|to them that be at Colosse, holy and faithful brethren in Christ Jesus, grace and peace to you of God our Father [grace to you and peace of God our Father] and of the Lord Jesus Christ.
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|寫信給在歌羅西的聖徒，就是在基督裡忠信的弟兄：願恩典與平安，從神我們的父歸與你們。
1:3|ASV|We give thanks to God the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, praying always for you,
1:3|Darby|We give thanks to the God and Father of our Lord Jesus  Christ continually [when] praying for you,
1:3|KJV|We give thanks to God and the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, praying always for you,
1:3|WYC|We do thankings to God, and to the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ [and the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ], evermore praying for you,
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們感謝神，我們主耶穌基督的父，常常為你們禱告，
1:4|ASV|having heard of your faith in Christ Jesus, and of the love which ye have toward all the saints,
1:4|Darby|having heard of your faith in Christ Jesus, and the love  which ye have towards all the saints,
1:4|KJV|Since we heard of your faith in Christ Jesus, and of the love which ye have to all the saints,
1:4<version name="WYC">[<i>we</i>] hearing your faith in Christ Jesus, and the love that ye have to all holy men,</version>
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因聽見你們對基督耶穌的信，並對眾聖徒的愛，
1:5|ASV|because of the hope which is laid up for you in the heavens, whereof ye heard before in the word of the truth of the gospel,
1:5|Darby|on account of the hope which [is] laid up for you in the  heavens; of which ye heard before in the word of the truth of  the glad tidings,
1:5|KJV|For the hope which is laid up for you in heaven, whereof ye heard before in the word of the truth of the gospel;
1:5|WYC|for the hope that is kept to you in heavens.  Which ye heard in the word of truth of the gospel,
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|是因那給你們存在諸天之上的盼望，就是你們從前在福音真理的話上所聽見的；
1:6|ASV|which is come unto you; even as it is also in all the world bearing fruit and increasing, as it doth in you also, since the day ye heard and knew the grace of God in truth;
1:6|Darby|which are come to you, as [they are] in all the world, [and]  are bearing fruit and growing, even as also among you, from the  day ye heard [them] and knew indeed the grace of God, in truth:
1:6|KJV|Which is come unto you, as it is in all the world; and bringeth forth fruit, as it doth also in you, since the day ye heard of it, and knew the grace of God in truth:
1:6|WYC|that came to you, as also it is in all the world, and maketh fruit, and waxeth, as [it is] in you, from that day in which ye heard and knew the grace of God in truth.
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這福音傳到你們那裡，也傳到全世界，一直結果增長，正如在你們中間，自從你們聽見，並在真實中認識神恩典的日子一樣；
1:7|ASV|even as ye learned of Epaphras our beloved fellow-servant, who is a faithful minister of Christ on our behalf,
1:7|Darby|even as ye learned from Epaphras our beloved fellow-bondman,  who is a faithful minister of Christ for you,
1:7|KJV|As ye also learned of Epaphras our dear fellowservant, who is for you a faithful minister of Christ;
1:7|WYC|As ye learned of Epaphras, our fellow most dear-worthy [our even-servant most dear-worthy], which is a true minister of Jesus Christ for you;
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|正如你們從我們所親愛，一同作奴僕的以巴弗所學的，他為你們作了基督忠信的執事，
1:8|ASV|who also declared unto us your love in the Spirit.
1:8|Darby|who has also manifested to us your love in [the] Spirit.
1:8|KJV|Who also declared unto us your love in the Spirit.
1:8|WYC|which also showed to us your loving in Spirit.
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|也把你們在那靈裡的愛告訴了我們。
1:9|ASV|For this cause we also, since the day we heard it, do not cease to pray and make request for you, that ye may be filled with the knowledge of his will in all spiritual wisdom and understanding,
1:9|Darby|For this reason *we* also, from the day we heard [of your  faith and love], do not cease praying and asking for you, to  the end that ye may be filled with the full knowledge of his  will, in all wisdom and spiritual understanding,
1:9|KJV|For this cause we also, since the day we heard it, do not cease to pray for you, and to desire that ye might be filled with the knowledge of his will in all wisdom and spiritual understanding;
1:9|WYC|And therefore we from the day in which we heard, cease not to pray for you, and to ask, that ye be filled with the knowing of his will in all wisdom and ghostly understanding;
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，我們自從聽見的日子，也就為你們不住的禱告祈求，願你們在一切屬靈的智慧和悟性上，充分認識神的旨意，
1:10|ASV|to walk worthily of the Lord unto all pleasing, bearing fruit in every good work, and increasing in the knowledge of God;
1:10|Darby|[so as] to walk worthily of the Lord unto all  well-pleasing, bearing fruit in every good work, and growing by  the true knowledge of God;
1:10|KJV|That ye might walk worthy of the Lord unto all pleasing, being fruitful in every good work, and increasing in the knowledge of God;
1:10|WYC|that ye walk worthily to God pleasing by all things, and make fruit in all good work, and wax in the science of God, [that ye walk worthily to God pleasing by all things, making fruit in all good work, and waxing in the science of God,]
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|行事為人配得過主，以致凡事蒙祂喜悅，在一切善工上結果子，藉著認識神而長大，
1:11|ASV|strengthened with all power, according to the might of his glory, unto all patience and longsuffering with joy;
1:11|Darby|strengthened with all power according to the might of his  glory unto all endurance and longsuffering with joy;
1:11|KJV|Strengthened with all might, according to his glorious power, unto all patience and longsuffering with joyfulness;
1:11|WYC|and be comforted in all virtue by the might of his clearness [after the might of his clearness], in all patience and long abiding with joy,
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|照祂榮耀的權能，得以在各樣的力上加力，使你們凡事歡歡喜喜的忍耐寬容，
1:12|ASV|giving thanks unto the Father, who made us meet to be partakers of the inheritance of the saints in light;
1:12|Darby|giving thanks to the Father, who has made us fit for  sharing the portion of the saints in light,
1:12|KJV|Giving thanks unto the Father, which hath made us meet to be partakers of the inheritance of the saints in light:
1:12<version name="WYC">that ye do thankings to God and to the Father, which made you worthy into the part of heritage of holy men in light. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22495a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|感謝父，叫你們彀資格在光中同得所分給眾聖徒的分；
1:13|ASV|who delivered us out of the power of darkness, and translated us into the kingdom of the Son of his love;
1:13|Darby|who has delivered us from the authority of darkness, and  translated [us] into the kingdom of the Son of his love:
1:13|KJV|Who hath delivered us from the power of darkness, and hath translated us into the kingdom of his dear Son:
1:13<version name="WYC">Which delivered us from the power of darknesses [The which delivered us from the power of darkness], and translated [<i>us</i>] into the kingdom of the Son of his loving,</version>
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂拯救了我們脫離黑暗的權勢，把我們遷入祂愛子的國裡；
1:14|ASV|in whom we have our redemption, the forgiveness of our sins:
1:14|Darby|in whom we have redemption, the forgiveness of sins;
1:14|KJV|In whom we have redemption through his blood, even the forgiveness of sins:
1:14|WYC|in whom we have again-buying and remission of sins.
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們在愛子裡得蒙救贖，就是罪得赦免。
1:15|ASV|who is the image of the invisible God, the firstborn of all creation;
1:15|Darby|who is image of the invisible God, firstborn of all  creation;
1:15|KJV|Who is the image of the invisible God, the firstborn of every creature:
1:15|WYC|Which is the image of God invisible, the first begotten of each creature.
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|愛子是那不能看見之神的像，是一切受造之物的首生者。
1:16|ASV|for in him were all things created, in the heavens and upon the earth, things visible and things invisible, whether thrones or dominions or principalities or powers; all things have been created through him, and unto him;
1:16|Darby|because by him were created all things, the things in the  heavens and the things upon the earth, the visible and the  invisible, whether thrones, or lordships, or principalities, or  authorities: all things have been created by him and for him.
1:16|KJV|For by him were all things created, that are in heaven, and that are in earth, visible and invisible, whether they be thrones, or dominions, or principalities, or powers: all things were created by him, and for him:
1:16|WYC|For in him all things be made, in heavens and in earth, visible and invisible, either thrones, either dominations, either princehoods, either powers, all things be made of nought by him, and in him,
1:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為萬有，無論是在諸天之上的、在地上的、能看見的、不能看見的、或是有位的、主治的、執政的、掌權的，都是在祂裡面造的；萬有都是藉著祂並為著祂造的；
1:17|ASV|and he is before all things, and in him all things consist.
1:17|Darby|And *he* is before all, and all things subsist together by  him.
1:17|KJV|And he is before all things, and by him all things consist.
1:17|WYC|and he is before all, and all things be in him.
1:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂在萬有之先，萬有也在祂裡面得以維繫；
1:18|ASV|And he is the head of the body, the church: who is the beginning, the firstborn from the dead; that in all things he might have the preeminence.
1:18|Darby|And *he* is the head of the body, the assembly; who is  [the] beginning, firstborn from among the dead, that *he* might  have the first place in all things:
1:18|KJV|And he is the head of the body, the church: who is the beginning, the firstborn from the dead; that in all things he might have the preeminence.
1:18<version name="WYC">And he is head of the body of the church; which is the beginning and the first begotten of dead <i>men</i>, that he hold the first dignity in all things <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22501b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup>.</version>
1:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂也是召會身體的頭；祂是元始，是從死人中復活的首生者，使祂可以在萬有中居首位；
1:19|ASV|For it was the good pleasure of the Father that in him should all the fulness dwell;
1:19|Darby|for in him all the fulness [of the Godhead] was pleased to  dwell,
1:19|KJV|For it pleased the Father that in him should all fulness dwell;
1:19|WYC|For in him it pleased all plenty to inhabit,
1:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為一切的豐滿，樂意居住在祂裡面，
1:20|ASV|and through him to reconcile all things unto himself, having made peace through the blood of his cross; through him, I say, whether things upon the earth, or things in the heavens.
1:20|Darby|and by him to reconcile all things to itself, having made  peace by the blood of his cross -- by him, whether the things  on the earth or the things in the heavens.
1:20|KJV|And, having made peace through the blood of his cross, by him to reconcile all things unto himself; by him, I say, whether they be things in earth, or things in heaven.
1:20|WYC|and by him all things to be reconciled into him, and made peace by the blood of his cross, those things that be in earth's, either that be in heavens [either those things that be in earth's, or that be in heavens].
1:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且既藉著祂在十字架上的血，成就了和平，便藉著祂叫萬有，無論是在地上的、或是在諸天之上的，都與自己和好了。
1:21|ASV|And you, being in time past alienated and enemies in your mind in your evil works,
1:21|Darby|And you, who once were alienated and enemies in mind by  wicked works, yet now has it reconciled
1:21|KJV|And you, that were sometime alienated and enemies in your mind by wicked works, yet now hath he reconciled
1:21<version name="WYC">And when ye were sometime aliened, and enemies by wit in evil works, now he hath reconciled <i>you</i></version>
1:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們從前是隔絕的，因著惡行心思裡與祂為敵，
1:22|ASV|yet now hath he reconciled in the body of his flesh through death, to present you holy and without blemish and unreproveable before him:
1:22|Darby|in the body of his flesh through death; to present you holy  and unblamable and irreproachable before it,
1:22|KJV|In the body of his flesh through death, to present you holy and unblameable and unreproveable in his sight:
1:22|WYC|in the body of his flesh by death, to have you holy, and unwemmed, and without reproof before him.
1:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但如今祂在基督肉體的身體裡，藉著死，叫你們與自己和好了，把你們聖別、沒有瑕疵、無可責備的呈獻在自己面前；
1:23|ASV|if so be that ye continue in the faith, grounded and stedfast, and not moved away from the hope of the gospel which ye heard, which was preached in all creation under heaven; whereof I Paul was made a minister.
1:23|Darby|if indeed ye abide in the faith founded and firm, and not  moved away from the hope of the glad tidings, which ye have  heard, which have been proclaimed in the whole creation which  [is] under heaven, of which *I* Paul became minister.
1:23|KJV|If ye continue in the faith grounded and settled, and be not moved away from the hope of the gospel, which ye have heard, and which was preached to every creature which is under heaven; whereof I Paul am made a minister;
1:23|WYC|If nevertheless ye dwell in the faith, founded, and stable [founded, and stabled], and unmoveable from the hope of the gospel that ye have heard, which is preached in all creature that is under heaven.  Of which I Paul am made a minister,
1:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只要你們一直留於信仰中，根基立定，堅定不移，不被移動離開福音的盼望；這福音就是你們所聽過，傳與天下一切受造之物的，我保羅也作了這福音的執事。
1:24|ASV|Now I rejoice in my sufferings for your sake, and fill up on my part that which is lacking of the afflictions of Christ in my flesh for his body's sake, which is the church;
1:24|Darby|Now, I rejoice in sufferings for you, and I fill up that  which is behind of the tribulations of Christ in my flesh, for  his body, which is the assembly;
1:24|KJV|Who now rejoice in my sufferings for you, and fill up that which is behind of the afflictions of Christ in my flesh for his body's sake, which is the church:
1:24|WYC|and now I have joy in passion for you, and I fill those things that fail of the passions of Christ in my flesh, for his body, that is the church. [the which now I have joy in passions for you, and full-fill those things that fail of the passions of Christ in my flesh, for his body, that is the church.]
1:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現在我因著為你們所受的苦難喜樂，並且為基督的身體，就是為召會，在我一面，在我肉身上補滿基督患難的缺欠；
1:25|ASV|whereof I was made a minister, according to the dispensation of God which was given me to you-ward, to fulfil the word of God,
1:25|Darby|of which *I* became minister, according to the dispensation  of God which [is] given me towards you to complete the word of  God,
1:25|KJV|Whereof I am made a minister, according to the dispensation of God which is given to me for you, to fulfil the word of God;
1:25<version name="WYC">Of which I Paul am made [a] minister by the dispensation of God, that is given to me in you, that I fill the word of God, <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22508c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup></version>
1:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我照神為你們所賜我的管家職分，作了召會的執事，要完成神的話，
1:26|ASV|even the mystery which hath been hid for ages and generations: but now hath it been manifested to his saints,
1:26|Darby|the mystery which [has been] hidden from ages and from  generations, but has now been made manifest to his saints;
1:26|KJV|Even the mystery which hath been hid from ages and from generations, but now is made manifest to his saints:
1:26<version name="WYC">the private [the mystery, <i>or private</i>], that was hid from worlds and generations.  But now it is showed to his saints,</version>
1:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就是歷世歷代以來所隱藏的奧祕，但如今向祂的聖徒顯明了；
1:27|ASV|to whom God was pleased to make known what is the riches of the glory of this mystery among the Gentiles, which is Christ in you, the hope of glory:
1:27|Darby|to whom God would make known what are the riches of the  glory of this mystery among the nations, which is Christ in you  the hope of glory:
1:27|KJV|To whom God would make known what is the riches of the glory of this mystery among the Gentiles; which is Christ in you, the hope of glory:
1:27|WYC|to whom God would make known the riches of the glory of this sacrament in heathen men, which is Christ in you, the hope of glory.
1:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神願意叫他們知道，這奧祕的榮耀在外邦人中是何等的豐富，就是基督在你們裡面成了榮耀的盼望；
1:28|ASV|whom we proclaim, admonishing every man and teaching every man in all wisdom, that we may present every man perfect in Christ;
1:28|Darby|whom *we* announce, admonishing every man, and teaching  every man, in all wisdom, to the end that we may present every  man perfect in Christ.
1:28|KJV|Whom we preach, warning every man, and teaching every man in all wisdom; that we may present every man perfect in Christ Jesus:
1:28|WYC|Whom we show, reproving each man, and teaching each man in all wisdom, that we offer each man perfect in Christ Jesus.
1:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們宣揚祂，是用全般的智慧警戒各人，教導各人，好將各人在基督裡成熟的獻上；
1:29<version name="ASV">whereunto I labor also, striving according to his working, which worketh in me mightily. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:29<version name="Darby">Whereunto also I toil, combating according to his working,  which works in me in power. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:29<version name="KJV">Whereunto I also labour, striving according to his working, which worketh in me mightily.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:29|WYC|In which thing also I travail, in striving by the working of him [In which thing and I travail, striving after the working of him], that he worketh in me in virtue.
1:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我也為此勞苦，照著祂在我裡面大能的運行，竭力奮鬥。
2:1|ASV|For I would have you know how greatly I strive for you, and for them at Laodicea, and for as many as have not seen my face in the flesh;
2:1|Darby|For I would have you know what combat I have for you, and  those in Laodicea, and as many as have not seen my face in  flesh;
2:1|KJV|For I would that ye knew what great conflict I have for you, and for them at Laodicea, and for as many as have not seen my face in the flesh;
2:1|WYC|But I will that ye know, what busyness I have for you, and for them that be at Laodicea, and whichever saw not my face in flesh,
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我願意你們曉得，我為你們和那些在老底嘉，甚至所有在肉身上沒有見過我面的人，是何等竭力奮鬥，
2:2|ASV|that their hearts may be comforted, they being knit together in love, and unto all riches of the full assurance of understanding, that they may know the mystery of God, even Christ,
2:2|Darby|to the end that their hearts may be encouraged, being united  together in love, and unto all riches of the full assurance of  understanding, to [the] full knowledge of the mystery of God;
2:2|KJV|That their hearts might be comforted, being knit together in love, and unto all riches of the full assurance of understanding, to the acknowledgement of the mystery of God, and of the Father, and of Christ;
2:2<version name="WYC">that their hearts be comforted, and they <i>be</i> taught in charity, into all the riches of the plenty of understanding [that the hearts of them be comforted, taught in charity, and into all riches of plenty of understanding], into the knowing of [the] mystery of God, the Father of Jesus Christ,</version>
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|要叫他們的心得安慰，在愛裡結合一起，以致豐豐富富的在悟性上有充分的確信，能以完全認識神的奧祕，就是基督；
2:3|ASV|in whom are all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge hidden.
2:3|Darby|in which are hid all the treasures of wisdom and of  knowledge.
2:3|KJV|In whom are hid all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge.
2:3|WYC|in whom all the treasures of wisdom and of science be hid. [in whom be all the treasures of wisdom and knowing hid.]
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|一切智慧和知識的寶藏，都藏在祂裡面。
2:4|ASV|This I say, that no one may delude you with persuasiveness of speech.
2:4|Darby|And I say this to the end that no one may delude you by  persuasive speech.
2:4|KJV|And this I say, lest any man should beguile you with enticing words.
2:4|WYC|For this thing I say, that no man deceive you in height of words.
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我說這話，免得有人用花言巧語欺騙你們。
2:5|ASV|For though I am absent in the flesh, yet am I with you in the spirit, joying and beholding your order, and the stedfastness of your faith in Christ.
2:5|Darby|For if indeed in the flesh I am absent, yet I am with you in  spirit, rejoicing and seeing your order, and the firmness of  your faith in Christ.
2:5|KJV|For though I be absent in the flesh, yet am I with you in the spirit, joying and beholding your order, and the stedfastness of your faith in Christ.
2:5|WYC|For though I be absent in body, [but] by spirit I am with you, joying and seeing your order and the firmness of your belief that is in Christ.
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在肉身裡雖然離開，在靈裡卻與你們同在，歡喜看見你們整齊有序，並堅定的信入基督。
2:6|ASV|As therefore ye received Christ Jesus the Lord, so walk in him,
2:6|Darby|As therefore ye have received the Christ, Jesus the Lord,  walk in him,
2:6|KJV|As ye have therefore received Christ Jesus the Lord, so walk ye in him:
2:6|WYC|Therefore as ye have taken Jesus Christ our Lord, walk ye in him,
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們既然接受了基督，就是主耶穌，
2:7|ASV|rooted and builded up in him, and established in your faith, even as ye were taught, abounding in thanksgiving.
2:7|Darby|rooted and built up in him, and assured in the faith, even  as ye have been taught, abounding in it with thanksgiving.
2:7|KJV|Rooted and built up in him, and stablished in the faith, as ye have been taught, abounding therein with thanksgiving.
2:7|WYC|and be ye rooted and builded above in him [rooted and built above in Christ], and confirmed in the belief, as ye have learned, abounding in him in doing of thankings.
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在祂裡面已經生根，並正被建造，且照著你們所受的教導，在信心上得以堅固，洋溢著感謝，就要在祂裡面行事為人。
2:8|ASV|Take heed lest there shall be any one that maketh spoil of you through his philosophy and vain deceit, after the tradition of men, after the rudiments of the world, and not after Christ:
2:8|Darby|See that there be no one who shall lead *you* away as a prey  through philosophy and vain deceit, according to the teaching  of men, according to the elements of the world, and not  according to Christ.
2:8|KJV|Beware lest any man spoil you through philosophy and vain deceit, after the tradition of men, after the rudiments of the world, and not after Christ.
2:8|WYC|See ye that no man deceive you by philosophy and vain fallacy, after the tradition of men, after the elements of the world, and not after Christ.
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要謹慎，恐怕有人用他的哲學，和虛空的欺騙，照著人的傳統，照著世上的蒙學，不照著基督，把你們擄去；
2:9|ASV|for in him dwelleth all the fulness of the Godhead bodily,
2:9|Darby|For in him dwells all the fulness of the Godhead bodily;
2:9|KJV|For in him dwelleth all the fulness of the Godhead bodily.
2:9|WYC|For in him dwelleth body-like all the fullness of the Godhead.
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神格一切的豐滿，都有形有體的居住在基督裡面，
2:10|ASV|and in him ye are made full, who is the head of all principality and power:
2:10|Darby|and ye are complete in him, who is the head of all  principality and authority,
2:10|KJV|And ye are complete in him, which is the head of all principality and power:
2:10|WYC|And ye be filled in him [And ye be fulfilled in him], that is head of all principat and power.
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們在祂裡面也得了豐滿。祂是一切執政掌權者的元首；
2:11|ASV|in whom ye were also circumcised with a circumcision not made with hands, in the putting off of the body of the flesh, in the circumcision of Christ;
2:11|Darby|in whom also ye have been circumcised with circumcision not  done by hand, in the putting off of the body of the flesh, in  the circumcision of the Christ;
2:11|KJV|In whom also ye are circumcised with the circumcision made without hands, in putting off the body of the sins of the flesh by the circumcision of Christ:
2:11|WYC|In whom also ye be circumcised in circumcision not made with hand, in despoiling of the body of flesh [in nakedness of the body of flesh], but in circumcision of Christ;
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們在祂裡面也受了非人手所行的割禮，乃是在基督的割禮裡，脫去了肉體的身體，
2:12|ASV|having been buried with him in baptism, wherein ye were also raised with him through faith in the working of God, who raised him from the dead.
2:12|Darby|buried with him in baptism, in which ye have been also  raised with [him] through faith of the working of God who  raised him from among the dead.
2:12|KJV|Buried with him in baptism, wherein also ye are risen with him through the faith of the operation of God, who hath raised him from the dead.
2:12<version name="WYC">and ye be buried together with him in baptism, in whom also ye have risen again by faith of the working of God, that raised him from death. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22524a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在受浸中與祂一同埋葬，也在受浸中，藉著那叫祂從死人中復活之神所運行的信心，與祂一同復活。
2:13|ASV|And you, being dead through your trespasses and the uncircumcision of your flesh, you, I say, did he make alive together with him, having forgiven us all our trespasses;
2:13|Darby|And you, being dead in offences and in the uncircumcision  of your flesh, he has quickened together with him, having  forgiven us all the offences;
2:13|KJV|And you, being dead in your sins and the uncircumcision of your flesh, hath he quickened together with him, having forgiven you all trespasses;
2:13<version name="WYC">And when ye were dead in your guilts, and in the prepuce of your flesh, he quickened together <i>you</i> with him; forgiving to you all guilts [all guilts, <i>or</i> <i>trespasses</i>],</version>
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們從前在過犯，和未受割禮的肉體中死了，神赦免了你們一切的過犯，叫你們一同與基督活過來；
2:14|ASV|having blotted out the bond written in ordinances that was against us, which was contrary to us: and he hath taken it out that way, nailing it to the cross;
2:14|Darby|having effaced the handwriting in ordinances which [stood  out] against us, which was contrary to us, he has taken it also  out of the way, having nailed it to the cross;
2:14|KJV|Blotting out the handwriting of ordinances that was against us, which was contrary to us, and took it out of the way, nailing it to his cross;
2:14|WYC|doing away that writing of decree that was against us, that was contrary to us; and he took away that from the middle, pitching it on the cross [pitching it to the cross];
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|塗抹了規條上所寫，攻擊我們，反對我們的字據，並且把牠撤去，釘在十字架上。
2:15|ASV|having despoiled the principalities and the powers, he made a show of them openly, triumphing over them in it.
2:15|Darby|having spoiled principalities and authorities, he made a  show of them publicly, leading them in triumph by it.
2:15|KJV|And having spoiled principalities and powers, he made a shew of them openly, triumphing over them in it.
2:15|WYC|and he spoiled principats and powers, and led out trustily, openly overcoming them in himself.
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|既將執政的和掌權的脫下，神就把他們公然示眾，仗著十字架在凱旋中向他們誇勝。
2:16|ASV|Let no man therefore judge you in meat, or in drink, or in respect of a feast day or a new moon or a sabbath day:
2:16|Darby|Let none therefore judge you in meat or in drink, or in  matter of feast, or new moon, or sabbaths,
2:16|KJV|Let no man therefore judge you in meat, or in drink, or in respect of an holyday, or of the new moon, or of the sabbath days:
2:16|WYC|Therefore no man judge you in meat, or in drink, or in part of feast day, or of new moon, or of sabbaths,
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以不拘在飲食上、或在節期、月朔、或安息日方面，都不可讓人論斷你們，
2:17|ASV|which are a shadow of the things to come; but the body is Christ's.
2:17|Darby|which are a shadow of things to come; but the body [is] of  Christ.
2:17|KJV|Which are a shadow of things to come; but the body is of Christ.
2:17<version name="WYC">which be shadow of things to coming [which be shadow of things to come]; for the body <i>is </i>of Christ.</version>
2:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些原是要來之事的影兒，那實體卻屬於基督。
2:18|ASV|Let no man rob you of your prize by a voluntary humility and worshipping of the angels, dwelling in the things which he hath seen, vainly puffed up by his fleshly mind,
2:18|Darby|Let no one fraudulently deprive you of your prize, doing  his own will in humility and worship of angels, entering into  things which he has not seen, vainly puffed up by the mind of  his flesh,
2:18|KJV|Let no man beguile you of your reward in a voluntary humility and worshipping of angels, intruding into those things which he hath not seen, vainly puffed up by his fleshly mind,
2:18<version name="WYC">No man deceive you, willing <i>to</i> <i>teach</i> in meekness, and [the] religion of angels, those things which he hath not seen, walking vainly, swollen with wit of his flesh [in-blown with wit of his flesh],</version>
2:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不可讓人憑故意卑微，並敬拜天使，所作反對你們的判斷，騙取你們的獎賞；這等人留戀於所見過的，隨著自己肉體的心思，徒然自高自大，
2:19|ASV|and not holding fast the Head, from whom all the body, being supplied and knit together through the joints and bands, increasing with the increase of God.
2:19|Darby|and not holding fast the head, from whom all the body,  ministered to and united together by the joints and bands,  increases with the increase of God.
2:19|KJV|And not holding the Head, from which all the body by joints and bands having nourishment ministered, and knit together, increaseth with the increase of God.
2:19|WYC|and not holding the head, of which all the body, by bands and joinings together [by bonds and joinings together] under-ministered and made, waxeth into [the] increasing of God.
2:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不持定元首；本於祂，全身藉著節和筋，得了豐富的供應，並結合一起，就以神的增長而長大。
2:20|ASV|If ye died with Christ from the rudiments of the world, why, as though living in the world, do ye subject yourselves to ordinances,
2:20|Darby|If ye have died with Christ from the elements of the world,  why as [if] alive in [the] world do ye subject yourselves to  ordinances?
2:20|KJV|Wherefore if ye be dead with Christ from the rudiments of the world, why, as though living in the world, are ye subject to ordinances,
2:20|WYC|For if ye be dead with Christ from the elements of the world, what yet as men living to the world deem ye?
2:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|20-21
2:21|ASV|Handle not, nor taste, nor touch
2:21|Darby|Do not handle, do not taste, do not touch,
2:21|KJV|(Touch not; taste not; handle not;
2:21|WYC|That ye touch not, neither taste, neither treat with hands those things, [Neither ye shall touch, neither taste, neither treat with hands,]
2:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們若是與基督同死，脫離了世上的蒙學，為甚麼仍像在世界中活著，服從那不可拿，不可嘗，不可摸等類的規條？
2:22|ASV|(all which things are to perish with the using), after the precepts and doctrines of men?
2:22|Darby|(things which are all for destruction in the using [of  them]:) according to the injunctions and teachings of men,
2:22|KJV|Which all are to perish with the using;) after the commandments and doctrines of men?
2:22|WYC|which all be into death by that use, after the commandments and teachings of men;
2:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些都是照著人的吩咐和教導，一經使用，就都敗壞了。
2:23<version name="ASV">Which things have indeed a show of wisdom in will-worship, and humility, and severity to the body; but are not of any value against the indulgence of the flesh. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:23<version name="Darby">(which have indeed an appearance of wisdom in voluntary  worship, and humility, and harsh treatment of the body, not in  a certain honour,) to [the] satisfaction of the flesh. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:23<version name="KJV">Which things have indeed a shew of wisdom in will worship, and humility, and neglecting of the body: not in any honour to the satisfying of the flesh.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:23<version name="WYC">which have a reason of wisdom in vain religion and meekness [which be soothly having reason of wisdom in superstition, <i>or vain religion, </i>and meekness], and not to spare the body, not in any honour to the fulfilling of the flesh.</version>
2:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些事在私意敬拜，自表卑微和苦待己身上，確有智慧之名，但在克制肉體的放縱上，卻是毫無價值。
3:1|ASV|If then ye were raised together with Christ, seek the things that are above, where Christ is, seated on the right hand of God.
3:1|Darby|If therefore ye have been raised with the Christ, seek the  things [which are] above, where the Christ is, sitting at [the]  right hand of God:
3:1|KJV|If ye then be risen with Christ, seek those things which are above, where Christ sitteth on the right hand of God.
3:1|WYC|Therefore if ye have risen together with Christ, seek ye those things that be above, where Christ is sitting on the right half of God.
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以你們若與基督一同復活，就當尋求在上面的事，那裡有基督坐在神的右邊。
3:2|ASV|Set your mind on the things that are above, not on the things that are upon the earth.
3:2|Darby|have your mind on the things [that are] above, not on the  things [that are] on the earth;
3:2|KJV|Set your affection on things above, not on things on the earth.
3:2<version name="WYC">Savour ye those things, that be above [Savour,<i> or understand</i>, ye those things that be above], not those that <i>be</i> on the earth.</version>
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要思念在上面的事，不要思念在地上的事。
3:3|ASV|For ye died, and your life is hid with Christ in God.
3:3|Darby|for ye have died, and your life is hid with the Christ in  God.
3:3|KJV|For ye are dead, and your life is hid with Christ in God.
3:3|WYC|For ye be dead, and your life is hid with Christ in God.
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為你們已經死了，你們的生命與基督一同藏在神裡面。
3:4|ASV|When Christ, who is our life, shall be manifested, then shall ye also with him be manifested in glory.
3:4|Darby|When the Christ is manifested who [is] our life, then shall  *ye* also be manifested with him in glory.
3:4|KJV|When Christ, who is our life, shall appear, then shall ye also appear with him in glory.
3:4|WYC|For when Christ shall appear, your life, then also ye shall appear with him in glory.
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|基督是我們的生命，祂顯現的時候，你們也要與祂一同顯現在榮耀裡。
3:5|ASV|Put to death therefore your members which are upon the earth: fornication, uncleanness, passion, evil desire, and covetousness, which is idolatry;
3:5|Darby|Put to death therefore your members which [are] upon the  earth, fornication, uncleanness, vile passions, evil lust, and  unbridled desire, which is idolatry.
3:5|KJV|Mortify therefore your members which are upon the earth; fornication, uncleanness, inordinate affection, evil concupiscence, and covetousness, which is idolatry:
3:5|WYC|Therefore slay ye your members [Therefore slay your members], which be on the earth, fornication, uncleanness, lechery, evil covetousness, and avarice, which is service of maumets [which is service of simulacra];
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以要治死你們在地上的肢體，就是淫亂、污穢、邪情、惡慾和貪婪，貪婪就是拜偶像，
3:6|ASV|for which things' sake cometh the wrath of God upon the sons of disobedience:
3:6|Darby|On account of which things the wrath of God comes upon the  sons of disobedience.
3:6|KJV|For which things' sake the wrath of God cometh on the children of disobedience:
3:6|WYC|for which things the wrath of God came on the sons of unbelief;
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因這些事，神的忿怒正臨到那悖逆之子。
3:7|ASV|wherein ye also once walked, when ye lived in these things;
3:7|Darby|In which *ye* also once walked when ye lived in these  things.
3:7|KJV|In the which ye also walked some time, when ye lived in them.
3:7|WYC|in which also ye walked some time, when ye lived in them.
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當你們在這些事中活著的時候，也曾在其間行事為人過。
3:8|ASV|but now do ye also put them all away: anger, wrath, malice, railing, shameful speaking out of your mouth:
3:8|Darby|But now, put off, *ye* also, all [these] things, wrath,  anger, malice, blasphemy, vile language out of your mouth.
3:8|KJV|But now ye also put off all these; anger, wrath, malice, blasphemy, filthy communication out of your mouth.
3:8|WYC|But now put ye away all things, wrath, indignation, malice, blasphemy and foul words of your mouth. [But now and ye put away all things, wrath, indignation, malice, blasphemy, foul word of your mouth.]
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但現在你們要脫去這一切的事，就是忿怒、惱恨、惡毒、毀謗，並你們口中所出可恥的穢語。
3:9|ASV|lie not one to another; seeing that ye have put off the old man with his doings,
3:9|Darby|Do not lie to one another, having put off the old man with  his deeds,
3:9|KJV|Lie not one to another, seeing that ye have put off the old man with his deeds;
3:9<version name="WYC">Do not ye lie together; despoil ye you from the old man with his deeds, [Do not ye lie, <i>or gab</i>, together, spoiling the old man with his deeds,]</version>
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不要彼此說謊，因你們已經脫去舊人，同舊人的行為，
3:10|ASV|and have put on the new man, that is being renewed unto knowledge after the image of him that created him:
3:10|Darby|and having put on the new, renewed into full knowledge  according to [the] image of him that has created him;
3:10|KJV|And have put on the new man, which is renewed in knowledge after the image of him that created him:
3:10|WYC|and clothe ye the new man [and clothing the new man], that is made new again into the knowing of God, after the image of him that made him;
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且穿上了新人；這新人照著創造他者的形像漸漸更新，以致有充足的知識；
3:11|ASV|where there cannot be Greek and Jew, circumcision and uncircumcision, barbarian, Scythian, bondman, freeman; but Christ is all, and in all.
3:11|Darby|wherein there is not Greek and Jew, circumcision and  uncircumcision, barbarian, Scythian, bondman, freeman; but  Christ [is] everything, and in all.
3:11|KJV|Where there is neither Greek nor Jew, circumcision nor uncircumcision, Barbarian, Scythian, bond nor free: but Christ is all, and in all.
3:11|WYC|where is not male and female, heathen man and Jew, circumcision and prepuce, barbarous and Scythian, bondman and free, but all things and in all things Christ.
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在此並沒有希利尼人和猶太人、受割禮的和未受割禮的、化外人、西古提人、為奴的、自主的，惟有基督是一切，又在一切之內。
3:12|ASV|Put on therefore, as God's elect, holy and beloved, a heart of compassion, kindness, lowliness, meekness, longsuffering;
3:12|Darby|Put on therefore, as [the] elect of God, holy and beloved,  bowels of compassion, kindness, lowliness, meekness,  longsuffering;
3:12|KJV|Put on therefore, as the elect of God, holy and beloved, bowels of mercies, kindness, humbleness of mind, meekness, longsuffering;
3:12|WYC|Therefore ye, as the chosen of God, holy and loved, clothe you with the entrails of mercy, benignity, and meekness, temperance, patience; [Therefore clothe ye you, as the chosen of God, holy, and loved, with the entrails of mercy, benignity, and meekness, temperance, patience;]
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以你們既是神的選民，聖別蒙愛的人，就要穿上憐恤的心腸、恩慈、卑微、溫柔、恆忍。
3:13|ASV|forbearing one another, and forgiving each other, if any man have a complaint against any; even as the Lord forgave you, so also do ye:
3:13|Darby|forbearing one another, and forgiving one another, if any  should have a complaint against any; even as the Christ has  forgiven you, so also [do] *ye*.
3:13|KJV|Forbearing one another, and forgiving one another, if any man have a quarrel against any: even as Christ forgave you, so also do ye.
3:13<version name="WYC">and support ye each one (the) other, and forgive to yourselves, if any man against any hath a quarrel; as the Lord forgave to you, so also ye. [supporting, <i>or bearing up together</i>, and forgiving to yourselves, if any man against any hath quarrel, <i>or plaint</i>, as and the Lord Christ forgave to you, so and ye.]</version>
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|倘若這人與那人有嫌隙，總要彼此容忍，彼此饒恕；主怎樣饒恕了你們，你們也要怎樣饒恕人。
3:14|ASV|and above all these things put on love, which is the bond of perfectness.
3:14|Darby|And to all these [add] love, which is the bond of  perfectness.
3:14|KJV|And above all these things put on charity, which is the bond of perfectness.
3:14|WYC|And upon all these things have ye charity, that is the bond of perfectness [that is the bond of perfection].
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在這一切之上，還要穿上愛，愛是全德的聯索。
3:15|ASV|And let the peace of Christ rule in your hearts, to the which also ye were called in one body; and be ye thankful.
3:15|Darby|And let the peace of Christ preside in your hearts, to  which also ye have been called in one body, and be thankful.
3:15|KJV|And let the peace of God rule in your hearts, to the which also ye are called in one body; and be ye thankful.
3:15|WYC|And the peace of Christ enjoy in your hearts, in which ye be called in one body, and be ye kind.
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又要讓基督的平安在你們心裡作仲裁，你們在一個身體裡蒙召，也是為了這平安；且要感恩。
3:16|ASV|Let the word of Christ dwell in you richly; in all wisdom teaching and admonishing one another with psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing with grace in your hearts unto God.
3:16|Darby|Let the word of the Christ dwell in you richly, in all  wisdom teaching and admonishing one another, in psalms, hymns,  spiritual songs, singing with grace in your hearts to God.
3:16|KJV|Let the word of Christ dwell in you richly in all wisdom; teaching and admonishing one another in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing with grace in your hearts to the Lord.
3:16|WYC|The word of Christ dwell in you plenteously, in all wisdom; and teach and admonish yourselves in psalms [teaching and admonishing yourselves in psalms], and hymns, and spiritual songs, in grace singing in your hearts to the Lord.
3:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當用各樣的智慧，讓基督的話豐豐富富的住在你們裡面，用詩章、頌辭、靈歌，彼此教導，互相勸戒，心被恩感歌頌神；
3:17|ASV|And whatsoever ye do, in word or in deed, do all in the name of the Lord Jesus, giving thanks to God the Father through him.
3:17|Darby|And everything, whatever ye may do in word or in deed, [do]  all things in [the] name of [the] Lord Jesus, giving thanks to  God the Father by him.
3:17|KJV|And whatsoever ye do in word or deed, do all in the name of the Lord Jesus, giving thanks to God and the Father by him.
3:17|WYC|All thing, whatever thing ye do, in word or in deed, all things in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, doing thankings to God and to the Father by him. [All thing, whatever ye do, in word or deed, all things in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ, doing thankings to God the Father by him.]
3:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡你們所作的，無論是甚麼，或說話，或行事，都要在主耶穌的名裡，藉著祂感謝父神。
3:18|ASV|Wives, be in subjection to your husbands, as is fitting in the Lord.
3:18|Darby|Wives, be subject to [your] husbands, as is fitting in  [the] Lord.
3:18|KJV|Wives, submit yourselves unto your own husbands, as it is fit in the Lord.
3:18|WYC|Women, be ye subject to your husbands, as it behooveth in the Lord.
3:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|作妻子的，要服從丈夫，這在主裡是相宜的。
3:19|ASV|Husbands, love your wives, and be not bitter against them.
3:19|Darby|Husbands, love your wives, and be not bitter against them.
3:19|KJV|Husbands, love your wives, and be not bitter against them.
3:19|WYC|Men, love ye your wives, and do not ye be bitter to them.
3:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|作丈夫的，要愛妻子，不可苦待她們。
3:20|ASV|Children, obey your parents in all things, for this is well-pleasing in the Lord.
3:20|Darby|Children, obey your parents in all things, for this is  well-pleasing in [the] Lord.
3:20|KJV|Children, obey your parents in all things: for this is well pleasing unto the Lord.
3:20<version name="WYC">Sons, obey ye to your father and mother by all things; for this is well pleasing in the Lord. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22555a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
3:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|作兒女的，要凡事順從父母，因為這在主裡是可喜悅的。
3:21|ASV|Fathers, provoke not your children, that they be not discouraged.
3:21|Darby|Fathers, do not vex your children, to the end that they be  not disheartened.
3:21|KJV|Fathers, provoke not your children to anger, lest they be discouraged.
3:21|WYC|Fathers, do not ye provoke your sons to indignation, that they be not made feeble-hearted.
3:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|作父親的，不要惹你們兒女的氣，免得他們灰心喪志。
3:22|ASV|Servants, obey in all things them that are your masters according to the flesh; not with eye-service, as men-pleasers, but in singleness of heart, fearing the Lord:
3:22|Darby|Bondmen, obey in all things your masters according to  flesh; not with eye-services, as men-pleasers, but in  simplicity of heart, fearing the Lord.
3:22|KJV|Servants, obey in all things your masters according to the flesh; not with eyeservice, as menpleasers; but in singleness of heart, fearing God;
3:22<version name="WYC">Servants, obey ye by all things to fleshly lords, not serving at the eye [not serving at eye], as pleasing to men, but in simpleness of heart, dreading the Lord [dreading the Lord <i>God</i>].</version>
3:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|作奴僕的，要凡事順從肉身的主人，不要只在眼前事奉，像是討人喜歡的，乃要憑心中的單純敬畏主。
3:23|ASV|whatsoever ye do, work heartily, as unto the Lord, and not unto men;
3:23|Darby|Whatsoever ye do, labour at it heartily, as [doing it] to  the Lord, and not to men;
3:23|KJV|And whatsoever ye do, do it heartily, as to the Lord, and not unto men;
3:23|WYC|Whatever ye do, work ye of will, as to the Lord and not to men;
3:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們無論作甚麼，都要從心裡作，像是給主作的，不是給人作的，
3:24|ASV|knowing that from the Lord ye shall receive the recompense of the inheritance: ye serve the Lord Christ.
3:24|Darby|knowing that of [the] Lord ye shall receive the recompense  of the inheritance; ye serve the Lord Christ.
3:24|KJV|Knowing that of the Lord ye shall receive the reward of the inheritance: for ye serve the Lord Christ.
3:24|WYC|witting that of the Lord ye shall take yielding of heritage [witting that of the Lord ye shall take reward of heritage].  Serve ye to the Lord Christ.
3:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|知道你們從主那裡必得著基業為賞報；你們所事奉的乃是主基督。
3:25<version name="ASV">For he that doeth wrong shall receive again for the wrong that he hath done: and there is no respect of persons. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:25<version name="Darby">For he that does a wrong shall receive the wrong he has  done, and there is no respect of persons. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:25<version name="KJV">But he that doeth wrong shall receive for the wrong which he hath done: and there is no respect of persons.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:25<version name="WYC">For he that doeth injury, shall receive that that he did evil; and acception of persons is not with God. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22560b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
3:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那行不義的，必受不義的報應，並沒有偏待人的事。
4:1|ASV|Masters, render unto your servants that which is just and equal; knowing that ye also have a Master in heaven.
4:1|Darby|Masters, give to bondmen what is just and fair, knowing that  *ye* also have a Master in [the] heavens.
4:1|KJV|Masters, give unto your servants that which is just and equal; knowing that ye also have a Master in heaven.
4:1|WYC|Lords, give ye to servants that that is just and even, witting that also ye have a Lord in heaven.
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|作主人的，要公公平平的對待奴僕，知道你們也有一位主在天上。
4:2|ASV|Continue stedfastly in prayer, watching therein with thanksgiving;
4:2|Darby|Persevere in prayer, watching in it with thanksgiving;
4:2|KJV|Continue in prayer, and watch in the same with thanksgiving;
4:2|WYC|Be ye busy in prayer, and wake in it, in doing of thankings;
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要堅定持續的禱告，在此儆醒感恩，
4:3|ASV|withal praying for us also, that God may open unto us a door for the word, to speak the mystery of Christ, for which I am also in bonds;
4:3|Darby|praying at the same time for us also, that God may open to  us a door of the word to speak the mystery of Christ, on  account of which also I am bound,
4:3|KJV|Withal praying also for us, that God would open unto us a door of utterance, to speak the mystery of Christ, for which I am also in bonds:
4:3|WYC|and pray each for other, and for us [praying together and for us], that God open to us the door of word, to speak the mystery of Christ; for which also I am bound,
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|同時也要為我們禱告，求神給我們開傳道的門，能以講說基督的奧祕，（我也為此被捆鎖，）
4:4|ASV|that I may make it manifest, as I ought to speak.
4:4|Darby|to the end that I may make it manifest as I ought to speak.
4:4|KJV|That I may make it manifest, as I ought to speak.
4:4|WYC|that I show it, so as it behooveth me to speak.
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|叫我按著所當說的，將這奧祕顯明出來。
4:5|ASV|Walk in wisdom toward them that are without, redeeming the time.
4:5|Darby|Walk in wisdom towards those without, redeeming  opportunities.
4:5|KJV|Walk in wisdom toward them that are without, redeeming the time. Let your speech be always with grace, seasoned with salt, that ye may know how ye ought to answer every man.
4:5|WYC|Walk ye in wisdom to them that be withoutforth, again-buying time.
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們對於外人要憑智慧行事，要贖回光陰。
4:6|ASV|Let your speech be always with grace, seasoned with salt, that ye may know how ye ought to answer each one.
4:6|Darby|[Let] your word [be] always with grace, seasoned with salt,  [so as] to know how ye ought to answer each one.
4:6|WYC|Your word be savoured with salt evermore in grace; that ye know, how it behooveth you to answer to each man.
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們的言語總要帶著恩典，好像用鹽調和，就可知道你們應當怎樣回答各人。
4:7|ASV|All my affairs shall Tychicus make known unto you, the beloved brother and faithful minister and fellow-servant in the Lord:
4:7|Darby|Tychicus, the beloved brother and faithful minister and  fellow-bondman in [the] Lord, will make known to you all that  concerns me;
4:7|KJV|All my state shall Tychicus declare unto you, who is a beloved brother, and a faithful minister and fellowservant in the Lord:
4:7|WYC|Tychicus, most dear brother, and faithful minister, and my fellow in the Lord [and even-servant in the Lord], shall make all things known to you, that be about me.
4:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|一切關於我的事，有親愛的弟兄，忠信的執事，在主裡同作奴僕的推基古，要告訴你們。
4:8|ASV|whom I have sent you for this very purpose, that ye may know our state, and that he may comfort your hearts;
4:8|Darby|whom I have sent to you for this very purpose, that he might  know your state, and that he might encourage your hearts:
4:8|KJV|Whom I have sent unto you for the same purpose, that he might know your estate, and comfort your hearts;
4:8|WYC|Whom I sent to you to this same thing [Whom I sent to you to the same thing], that he know what things be about you, and comfort your hearts,
4:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我為這事打發他到你們那裡去，好叫你們知道關於我們的事，又叫他安慰你們的心；
4:9|ASV|together with Onesimus, the faithful and beloved brother, who is one of you. They shall make known unto you all things that are done here.
4:9|Darby|with Onesimus, the faithful and beloved brother, who is  [one] of you. They shall make known to you everything here.
4:9|KJV|With Onesimus, a faithful and beloved brother, who is one of you. They shall make known unto you all things which are done here.
4:9|WYC|with Onesimus, most dear and faithful brother, which is of you; which shall make all things that be done here [that shall make all things that be done here], known to you.
4:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|還有忠信親愛的弟兄歐尼西母同去，他是你們那裡的人。他們要把這裡一切的事都告訴你們。
4:10|ASV|Aristarchus my fellow-prisoner saluteth you, and Mark, the cousin of Barnabas (touching whom ye received commandments; if he come unto you, receive him),
4:10|Darby|Aristarchus my fellow-captive salutes you, and Mark,  Barnabas's cousin, concerning whom ye have received orders, (if  he come to you, receive him,)
4:10|KJV|Aristarchus my fellowprisoner saluteth you, and Marcus, sister's son to Barnabas, (touching whom ye received commandments: if he come unto you, receive him;)
4:10<version name="WYC">Aristarchus, prisoner with me [mine even-captive, <i>or prisoner with me</i>], greeteth you well, and Marcus, the cousin of Barnabas, of whom ye have taken commandments; if he come to you, receive ye him;</version>
4:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|與我一同坐監的亞里達古問你們安。巴拿巴的表弟馬可也問你們安。（說到這馬可，你們已經受了吩咐，他若到了你們那裡，你們就接待他。）
4:11|ASV|and Jesus that is called Justus, who are of the circumcision: these only are my fellow-workers unto the kingdom of God, men that have been a comfort unto me.
4:11|Darby|and Jesus called Justus, who are of the circumcision. These  [are the] only fellow-workers for the kingdom of God who have  been a consolation to me.
4:11|KJV|And Jesus, which is called Justus, who are of the circumcision. These only are my fellowworkers unto the kingdom of God, which have been a comfort unto me.
4:11|WYC|and Jesus, that is said Justus; which be of circumcision; they alone be mine helpers in the kingdom of God, that were to me in solace.
4:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那稱為猶士都的耶數，也問你們安；奉割禮的人中，只有這些人是為神的國作我的同工，他們也成了我的安慰。
4:12|ASV|Epaphras, who is one of you, a servant of Christ Jesus, saluteth you, always striving for you in his prayers, that ye may stand perfect and fully assured in all the will of God.
4:12|Darby|Epaphras, who is [one] of you, [the] bondman of Christ  Jesus, salutes you, always combating earnestly for you in  prayers, to the end that ye may stand perfect and complete in  all [the] will of God.
4:12|KJV|Epaphras, who is one of you, a servant of Christ, saluteth you, always labouring fervently for you in prayers, that ye may stand perfect and complete in all the will of God.
4:12|WYC|Epaphras, that is of you, the servant of Jesus Christ, greeteth you well; ever busy for you in prayers, that ye stand perfect and full in all the will of God.
4:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有你們那裡的人，作基督耶穌奴僕的以巴弗問你們安；他在禱告中常為你們竭力奮鬥，要你們得以成熟，站立得住，在神一切的旨意上滿有確信。
4:13|ASV|For I bear him witness, that he hath much labor for you, and for them in Laodicea, and for them in Hierapolis.
4:13|Darby|For I bear him witness that he labours much for you, and  them in Laodicea, and them in Hierapolis.
4:13|KJV|For I bear him record, that he hath a great zeal for you, and them that are in Laodicea, and them in Hierapolis.
4:13|WYC|And I bear witnessing to him, that he hath much travail for you, and for them that be at Laodicea, and that be at Hierapolis.
4:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我可以給他作見證，他為你們和那些在老底嘉，並在希拉波立的人，多多的辛勞。
4:14|ASV|Luke, the beloved physician, and Demas salute you.
4:14|Darby|Luke, the beloved physician, salutes you, and Demas.
4:14|KJV|Luke, the beloved physician, and Demas, greet you.
4:14|WYC|Luke, the physician most dear [the leech most dear], and Demas, greet you well.
4:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|親愛的醫生路加，和底馬問你們安。
4:15|ASV|Salute the brethren that are in Laodicea, and Nymphas, and the church that is in their house.
4:15|Darby|Salute the brethren in Laodicea, and Nymphas, and the  assembly which [is] in his house.
4:15|KJV|Salute the brethren which are in Laodicea, and Nymphas, and the church which is in his house.
4:15<version name="WYC">Greet ye well the brethren that be at Laodicea, and <i>the woman</i> Nymphas, and the church that is in her house [and Nymphas, and the church that is in his house].</version>
4:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|請問在老底嘉的弟兄和寧法，並他家裡的召會安。
4:16|ASV|And when this epistle hath been read among you, cause that it be read also in the church of the Laodiceans; and that ye also read the epistle from Laodicea.
4:16|Darby|And when the letter has been read among you, cause that it  be read also in the assembly of Laodiceans, and that *ye* also  read that from Laodicea.
4:16|KJV|And when this epistle is read among you, cause that it be read also in the church of the Laodiceans; and that ye likewise read the epistle from Laodicea.
4:16<version name="WYC">And when this epistle is read among you, do ye, that it be read in the church of Laodiceans; and read ye that <i>epistle</i> that is of Laodiceans.</version>
4:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這書信在你們中間念了之後，務要叫在老底嘉的召會也念，你們也要念從老底嘉來的書信。
4:17|ASV|And say to Archippus, Take heed to the ministry which thou hast received in the Lord, that thou fulfil it.
4:17|Darby|And say to Archippus, Take heed to the ministry which thou  hast received in [the] Lord, to the end that thou fulfil it.
4:17|KJV|And say to Archippus, Take heed to the ministry which thou hast received in the Lord, that thou fulfil it.
4:17|WYC|And say ye to Archippus, See the ministry, that thou hast taken in the Lord, that thou fill it [that thou fulfill it].
4:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|要告訴亞基布：務要留心你在主裡所領受的職事，好盡這職事。
4:18<version name="ASV">The salutation of me Paul with mine own hand. Remember my bonds. Grace be with you. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:18<version name="Darby">The salutation by the hand of me Paul. Remember my bonds.  Grace [be] with you. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:18<version name="KJV">The salutation by the hand of me Paul. Remember my bonds. Grace be with you. Amen.</p><p /><br /></version>
4:18|WYC|My salutation, by the hand of Paul.  Be ye mindful of my bonds.  The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you.  Amen.
4:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我保羅親筆問安。你們要記念我的捆鎖。願恩典與你們同在。
