1:1|Darby|In the third year of the reign of Jehoiakim king of Judah  came Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon unto Jerusalem, and  besieged it.
1:1|KJV|In the third year of the reign of Jehoiakim king of Judah came Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon unto Jerusalem, and besieged it.
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|猶大王約雅敬在位第三年，巴比倫王尼布甲尼撒來到耶路撒冷，將城圍困。
1:2|Darby|And the Lord gave Jehoiakim king of Judah into his hand, and  a part of the vessels of the house of God; and he carried them  into the land of Shinar, to the house of his god; and he  brought the vessels into the treasure-house of his god.
1:2|KJV|And the Lord gave Jehoiakim king of Judah into his hand, with part of the vessels of the house of God: which he carried into the land of Shinar to the house of his god; and he brought the vessels into the treasure house of his god.
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主將猶大王約雅敬，並神殿中的一些器皿交付他手，他就把這些器皿帶到示拿地，他神的廟堙A帶進他神的庫中。
1:3|Darby|And the king spoke unto Ashpenaz the chief of his eunuchs,  that he should bring of the children of Israel, both of the  royal seed and of the nobles,
1:3|KJV|And the king spake unto Ashpenaz the master of his eunuchs, that he should bring certain of the children of Israel, and of the king's seed, and of the princes;
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王吩咐太監長亞施毘拿，從以色列人中，從王室後裔和貴冑中，帶進幾個人來，
1:4|Darby|youths in whom was no blemish, and of goodly countenance,  and skilful in all wisdom, and acquainted with knowledge, and  understanding science, and such as had ability in them to stand  in the king's palace, and whom they might teach the learning  and the language of the Chaldeans.
1:4|KJV|Children in whom was no blemish, but well favoured, and skilful in all wisdom, and cunning in knowledge, and understanding science, and such as had ability in them to stand in the king's palace, and whom they might teach the learning and the tongue of the Chaldeans.
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就是年少沒有殘疾，相貌俊美，通曉各樣智慧，知識通達，思想敏捷，足能侍立在王宮堛滿A要教他們迦勒底人的學問和語言。
1:5|Darby|And the king appointed unto them a daily provision of the  king's delicate food, and of the wine that he drank, to nourish  them three years, that at the end thereof they might stand  before the king.
1:5|KJV|And the king appointed them a daily provision of the king's meat, and of the wine which he drank: so nourishing them three years, that at the end thereof they might stand before the king.
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王派定將自己所用的膳和所飲的酒，每日賜他們一分，養他們三年；好叫他們在期滿以後可以在王面前侍立。
1:6|Darby|Now among these were of the children of Judah, Daniel,  Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah.
1:6|KJV|Now among these were of the children of Judah, Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah:
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們中間有猶大族的人，但以理、哈拿尼雅、米沙利、亞撒利雅；
1:7|Darby|And the prince of the eunuchs gave them names: to Daniel he  gave [the name] Belteshazzar, and to Hananiah, Shadrach, and to  Mishael, Meshach, and to Azariah, Abed-nego.
1:7|KJV|Unto whom the prince of the eunuchs gave names: for he gave unto Daniel the name of Belteshazzar; and to Hananiah, of Shadrach; and to Mishael, of Meshach; and to Azariah, of Abednego.
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|太監長給他們起名，稱但以理為伯提沙撒，稱哈拿尼雅為沙得拉，稱米沙利為米煞，稱亞撒利雅為亞伯尼歌。
1:8|Darby|And Daniel purposed in his heart that he would not pollute  himself with the king's delicate food, nor with the wine which  he drank; and he requested of the prince of the eunuchs that he  might not have to pollute himself.
1:8|KJV|But Daniel purposed in his heart that he would not defile himself with the portion of the king's meat, nor with the wine which he drank: therefore he requested of the prince of the eunuchs that he might not defile himself.
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但以理卻立定心意，不以王的膳和王所飲的酒玷污自己，所以求太監長容他不玷污自己。
1:9|Darby|And God granted Daniel favour and mercy before the prince of  the eunuchs.
1:9|KJV|Now God had brought Daniel into favour and tender love with the prince of the eunuchs.
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神使但以理在太監長眼前蒙恩惠，受憐恤；
1:10|Darby|And the prince of the eunuchs said unto Daniel, I fear my  lord the king who hath appointed your food and your drink; for  why should he see your faces worse liking than the youths who  are of your age? and ye would endanger my head with the king.
1:10|KJV|And the prince of the eunuchs said unto Daniel, I fear my lord the king, who hath appointed your meat and your drink: for why should he see your faces worse liking than the children which are of your sort? then shall ye make me endanger my head to the king.
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|太監長對但以理說，我懼怕我主我王，他已經派定你們的飲食；為何叫他看見你們的面貌，比你們同歲的少年人瘦弱難看呢？這樣，你們就使我的頭在王那媄曮O。
1:11|Darby|And Daniel said to the steward, whom the prince of the  eunuchs had set over Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah,
1:11|KJV|Then said Daniel to Melzar, whom the prince of the eunuchs had set over Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah,
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但以理對太監長所派管理但以理、哈拿尼雅、米沙利、亞撒利雅的委辦說，
1:12|Darby|Prove thy servants, I beseech thee, ten days; and let them  give us pulse to eat, and water to drink;
1:12|KJV|Prove thy servants, I beseech thee, ten days; and let them give us pulse to eat, and water to drink.
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|求你試試僕人們十天，給我們蔬菜喫，白水喝，
1:13|Darby|then let our countenances be looked upon before thee, and  the countenance of the youths that eat of the king's delicate  food: and as thou shalt see, deal with thy servants.
1:13|KJV|Then let our countenances be looked upon before thee, and the countenance of the children that eat of the portion of the king's meat: and as thou seest, deal with thy servants.
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然後當面察看我們的面貌，和用王膳那些少年人的面貌；就照你所看的待僕人罷。
1:14|Darby|And he hearkened unto them in this matter, and proved them  ten days.
1:14|KJV|So he consented to them in this matter, and proved them ten days.
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|委辦便允准他們這件事，試看他們十天。
1:15|Darby|And at the end of ten days their countenances appeared  fairer and were fatter in flesh than all the youths that ate of  the king's delicate food.
1:15|KJV|And at the end of ten days their countenances appeared fairer and fatter in flesh than all the children which did eat the portion of the king's meat.
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|過了十天，見他們的面貌更顯俊美，比用王膳的一切少年人更加健壯；
1:16|Darby|So the steward took away their delicate food, and the wine  that they should drink; and gave them pulse.
1:16|KJV|Thus Melzar took away the portion of their meat, and the wine that they should drink; and gave them pulse.
1:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是委辦撤去派定他們用的膳、飲的酒，只給他們蔬菜喫。
1:17|Darby|As for these four youths, God gave them knowledge and skill  in all learning and wisdom; and Daniel had understanding in all  visions and dreams.
1:17|KJV|As for these four children, God gave them knowledge and skill in all learning and wisdom: and Daniel had understanding in all visions and dreams.
1:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這四個少年人，神在各樣學問、智慧上，賜給他們知識聰明；但以理又明白各樣的異象和夢兆。
1:18|Darby|And at the end of the days that the king had said he should  bring them in, the prince of the eunuchs brought them in before  Nebuchadnezzar.
1:18|KJV|Now at the end of the days that the king had said he should bring them in, then the prince of the eunuchs brought them in before Nebuchadnezzar.
1:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|尼布甲尼撒王吩咐帶進少年人來的日期到了，太監長就把他們帶到王面前。
1:19|Darby|And the king spoke with them; and among them all was found  none like Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah: and they  stood before the king.
1:19|KJV|And the king communed with them; and among them all was found none like Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah: therefore stood they before the king.
1:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王與他們談論，見少年人中，無一人能比但以理、哈拿尼雅、米沙利、亞撒利雅；於是他們就在王面前侍立。
1:20|Darby|And in all matters of judicious wisdom, as to which the  king enquired of them, he found them ten times better than all  the scribes [and] magicians that were in all his realm.
1:20|KJV|And in all matters of wisdom and understanding, that the king enquired of them, he found them ten times better than all the magicians and astrologers that were in all his realm.
1:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王考問他們一切智慧、學問的事，見他們比通國的術士和用法術的，勝過十倍。
1:21<version name="Darby">And Daniel continued unto the first year of king Cyrus. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:21<version name="KJV">And Daniel continued even unto the first year of king Cyrus.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|直到古列王元年，但以理還在。
2:1|Darby|And in the second year of the reign of Nebuchadnezzar,  Nebuchadnezzar dreamed dreams, and his spirit was troubled, and  his sleep went from him.
2:1|KJV|And in the second year of the reign of Nebuchadnezzar Nebuchadnezzar dreamed dreams, wherewith his spirit was troubled, and his sleep brake from him.
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|尼布甲尼撒在位第二年，他作了夢，靈媟迠獺A不能睡覺。
2:2|Darby|And the king commanded to call the scribes, and the  magicians, and the sorcerers, and the Chaldeans, to shew the  king his dreams; and they came and stood before the king.
2:2|KJV|Then the king commanded to call the magicians, and the astrologers, and the sorcerers, and the Chaldeans, for to shew the king his dreams. So they came and stood before the king.
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王吩咐人將術士、用法術的、行邪術的、和迦勒底人召來，要他們將王的夢告訴王；他們就來站在王前。
2:3|Darby|And the king said unto them, I have dreamed a dream, and my  spirit is troubled to know the dream.
2:3|KJV|And the king said unto them, I have dreamed a dream, and my spirit was troubled to know the dream.
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王對他們說，我作了一個夢，靈媟迠獺A要知道這夢是甚麼。
2:4|Darby|And the Chaldeans spoke to the king in Aramaic, O king, live  for ever! tell thy servants the dream, and we will shew the  interpretation.
2:4|KJV|Then spake the Chaldeans to the king in Syriack, O king, live for ever: tell thy servants the dream, and we will shew the interpretation.
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|迦勒底人用亞蘭語對王說，願王萬歲！請將那夢告訴僕人，僕人就可以講解說明。
2:5|Darby|The king answered and said to the Chaldeans, The command is  gone forth from me: If ye do not make known unto me the dream,  and its interpretation, ye shall be cut in pieces, and your  houses shall be made a dunghill.
2:5|KJV|The king answered and said to the Chaldeans, The thing is gone from me: if ye will not make known unto me the dream, with the interpretation thereof, ye shall be cut in pieces, and your houses shall be made a dunghill.
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王回答迦勒底人說，我已發出命令，你們若不將夢和夢的講解告訴我，就必被凌遲，你們的房屋必成為糞堆；
2:6|Darby|But if ye shew the dream and its interpretation, ye shall  receive of me gifts and rewards and great honour; therefore  shew me the dream and its interpretation.
2:6|KJV|But if ye shew the dream, and the interpretation thereof, ye shall receive of me gifts and rewards and great honour: therefore shew me the dream, and the interpretation thereof.
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們若將夢和夢的講解告訴我，就必從我這堭o贈品、賞賜、和大尊榮。現在你們要將夢和夢的講解告訴我。
2:7|Darby|They answered the second time and said, Let the king tell  his servants the dream, and we will shew the interpretation.
2:7|KJV|They answered again and said, Let the king tell his servants the dream, and we will shew the interpretation of it.
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們第二次回答王，說，請王將夢告訴僕人，僕人就可以講解說明。
2:8|Darby|The king answered and said, I know of a certainty that ye  would gain time, because ye see the word is gone forth from me;
2:8|KJV|The king answered and said, I know of certainty that ye would gain the time, because ye see the thing is gone from me.
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王回答說，我準知道你們是在拖延時間，因為你們看見我已發出命令；
2:9|Darby|but if ye do not make known unto me the dream, there is but  one decree for you; for ye have prepared lying and corrupt  words to speak before me, till the time be changed: therefore  tell me the dream, and I shall know that ye can shew me its  interpretation.
2:9|KJV|But if ye will not make known unto me the dream, there is but one decree for you: for ye have prepared lying and corrupt words to speak before me, till the time be changed: therefore tell me the dream, and I shall know that ye can shew me the interpretation thereof.
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們若不將夢告訴我，只有一條法令對待你們，因為你們在我面前協同說虛謊敗壞的話，要等候時勢改變。所以你們要將夢告訴我，我就知道你們能將夢的講解告訴我。
2:10|Darby|The Chaldeans answered before the king and said, There is  not a man upon the earth that can shew the king's matter;  therefore there is no king, however great and powerful, that  hath asked such a thing of any scribe, or magician, or  Chaldean.
2:10|KJV|The Chaldeans answered before the king, and said, There is not a man upon the earth that can shew the king's matter: therefore there is no king, lord, nor ruler, that asked such things at any magician, or astrologer, or Chaldean.
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|迦勒底人在王面前回答說，地上沒有人能將王所問的事說出來，因為沒有大君王或掌權者，向術士、用法術的、或迦勒底人，問過這樣的事。
2:11|Darby|For the thing that the king demandeth is extraordinary, and  there is none other that can shew it before the king, except  the gods, whose dwelling is not with flesh.
2:11|KJV|And it is a rare thing that the king requireth, and there is none other that can shew it before the king, except the gods, whose dwelling is not with flesh.
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王所問的事甚難，除了不與血肉之人同居的神明，沒有人能在王面前說出來。
2:12|Darby|For this cause the king was irritated and very wroth, and  commanded to destroy all the wise men of Babylon.
2:12|KJV|For this cause the king was angry and very furious, and commanded to destroy all the wise men of Babylon.
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王為此生氣，大發烈怒，吩咐滅絕巴比倫所有的哲士。
2:13|Darby|And the decree went forth that the wise men were to be  slain; and they sought Daniel and his companions to slay them.
2:13|KJV|And the decree went forth that the wise men should be slain; and they sought Daniel and his fellows to be slain.
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是命令發出，哲士將要被殺；人就尋找但以理和他的同伴，要殺他們。
2:14|Darby|Then Daniel answered with counsel and prudence to Arioch  the chief of the king's bodyguard, who had gone forth to slay  the wise men of Babylon:
2:14|KJV|Then Daniel answered with counsel and wisdom to Arioch the captain of the king's guard, which was gone forth to slay the wise men of Babylon:
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王的護衛長亞略出來，要殺巴比倫的哲士，但以理就用機智、審慎的話回答他，
2:15|Darby|he answered and said to Arioch the king's captain, Why is  the decree so rigorous from the king? Then Arioch made the  thing known to Daniel.
2:15|KJV|He answered and said to Arioch the king's captain, Why is the decree so hasty from the king? Then Arioch made the thing known to Daniel.
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|向王的軍長亞略說，從王發出的命令為何這樣嚴厲呢？亞略就將情節告訴但以理。
2:16|Darby|And Daniel went in, and requested of the king that he would  give him time, that he might shew the king the interpretation.
2:16|KJV|Then Daniel went in, and desired of the king that he would give him time, and that he would shew the king the interpretation.
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但以理遂進去求王寬限，就可以將夢的講解告訴王。
2:17|Darby|Then Daniel went to his house, and made the thing known to  Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah, his companions;
2:17|KJV|Then Daniel went to his house, and made the thing known to Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah, his companions:
2:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但以理回到他的家，將這事告訴他的同伴哈拿尼雅、米沙利、亞撒利雅，
2:18|Darby|that they would desire mercies of the God of the heavens  concerning this secret; that Daniel and his companions should  not perish with the rest of the wise men of Babylon.
2:18|KJV|That they would desire mercies of the God of heaven concerning this secret; that Daniel and his fellows should not perish with the rest of the wise men of Babylon.
2:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|要他們為這奧祕的事，在天上的神面前求憐恤，免得但以理和他的同伴，與巴比倫其餘的哲士一同滅亡。
2:19|Darby|Then was the secret revealed unto Daniel in a night vision.  Then Daniel blessed the God of the heavens.
2:19|KJV|Then was the secret revealed unto Daniel in a night vision. Then Daniel blessed the God of heaven.
2:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這奧祕的事，就在夜間異象中，啟示給但以理。但以理便頌讚天上的神。
2:20|Darby|Daniel answered and said, Blessed be the name of God for  ever and ever; For wisdom and might are his.
2:20|KJV|Daniel answered and said, Blessed be the name of God for ever and ever: for wisdom and might are his:
2:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但以理說，從亙古直到永遠，神的名是當受頌讚的，因為智慧、能力都屬乎祂。
2:21|Darby|And it is he that changeth times and seasons; He deposeth  kings, and setteth up kings; He giveth wisdom to the wise, And  knowledge to them that know understanding.
2:21|KJV|And he changeth the times and the seasons: he removeth kings, and setteth up kings: he giveth wisdom unto the wise, and knowledge to them that know understanding:
2:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂改變時候和時期；廢王、立王，將智慧賜與智慧人，將知識賜與通達人。
2:22|Darby|It is he that revealeth the deep and secret things; He  knoweth what is in the darkness, and the light dwelleth with  him.
2:22|KJV|He revealeth the deep and secret things: he knoweth what is in the darkness, and the light dwelleth with him.
2:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂啟示深奧隱祕的事，知道暗中所含的，光也與祂同居。
2:23|Darby|I thank thee, and I praise thee, O God of my fathers, Who  hast given me wisdom and might, And hast made known unto me  already what we desired of thee; For thou hast made known unto  us the king's matter.
2:23|KJV|I thank thee, and praise thee, O thou God of my fathers, who hast given me wisdom and might, and hast made known unto me now what we desired of thee: for thou hast now made known unto us the king's matter.
2:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我列祖的神阿，我感謝你，讚美你，因你將智慧、能力賜給了我；如今你已使我知道我們向你所求的，把王的事指示我們。
2:24|Darby|Therefore Daniel went in unto Arioch, whom the king had  appointed to destroy the wise men of Babylon; he went and said  thus unto him: Destroy not the wise men of Babylon; bring me in  before the king, and I will shew unto the king the  interpretation.
2:24|KJV|Therefore Daniel went in unto Arioch, whom the king had ordained to destroy the wise men of Babylon: he went and said thus unto him; Destroy not the wise men of Babylon: bring me in before the king, and I will shew unto the king the interpretation.
2:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是但以理進去見亞略，就是王所派滅絕巴比倫哲士的，對他說，不要滅絕巴比倫的哲士，求你領我到王面前，我要將夢的講解告訴王。
2:25|Darby|Then Arioch brought in Daniel before the king in haste, and  said thus unto him: I have found a man of the sons of the  captivity of Judah that will make known unto the king the  interpretation.
2:25|KJV|Then Arioch brought in Daniel before the king in haste, and said thus unto him, I have found a man of the captives of Judah, that will make known unto the king the interpretation.
2:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞略就急忙將但以理領到王面前，對王說，我在被擄的猶大人中遇見一人，他要將夢的講解告訴王。
2:26|Darby|The king answered and said unto Daniel, whose name was  Belteshazzar, Art thou able to make known unto me the dream  that I have seen, and its interpretation?
2:26|KJV|The king answered and said to Daniel, whose name was Belteshazzar, Art thou able to make known unto me the dream which I have seen, and the interpretation thereof?
2:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王對稱為伯提沙撒的但以理說，你能將我所作的夢和夢的講解，告訴我麼？
2:27|Darby|Daniel answered in the presence of the king and said, The  secret that the king hath demanded cannot the wise men, the  magicians, the scribes, the astrologers, shew unto the king;
2:27|KJV|Daniel answered in the presence of the king, and said, The secret which the king hath demanded cannot the wise men, the astrologers, the magicians, the soothsayers, shew unto the king;
2:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但以理在王面前回答說，王所問的那奧祕事，哲士、用法術的、術士、觀兆的，都不能告訴王；
2:28|Darby|but there is a God in the heavens, who revealeth secrets,  and maketh known to king Nebuchadnezzar what shall be at the  end of days. Thy dream, and the visions of thy head upon thy  bed are these:
2:28|KJV|But there is a God in heaven that revealeth secrets, and maketh known to the king Nebuchadnezzar what shall be in the latter days. Thy dream, and the visions of thy head upon thy bed, are these;
2:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只有一位在天上的神，能啟示奧祕的事，祂已將末後日子必發生的事，指示尼布甲尼撒王。你的夢，就是你在床上腦中的異象，乃是這樣。
2:29|Darby|-- as for thee, O king, thy thoughts arose upon thy bed,  what should come to pass hereafter; and he that revealeth  secrets hath made known to thee what shall come to pass.
2:29|KJV|As for thee, O king, thy thoughts came into thy mind upon thy bed, what should come to pass hereafter: and he that revealeth secrets maketh known to thee what shall come to pass.
2:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王阿，你在床上想到後來要發生的事，那啟示奧祕事的主，就把將來必發生的事指示你。
2:30|Darby|And as for me, this secret is revealed to me, not by [any]  wisdom that I have more than any living, but to the intent that  the interpretation should be made known to the king, and that  thou mightest know the thoughts of thy heart.
2:30|KJV|But as for me, this secret is not revealed to me for any wisdom that I have more than any living, but for their sakes that shall make known the interpretation to the king, and that thou mightest know the thoughts of thy heart.
2:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於我，這奧祕的事啟示給我，並非因我的智慧勝過一切活人，乃為使王知道夢的講解，並使王知道心堛澈銎嚏C
2:31|Darby|Thou, O king, sawest, and behold, a great image. This image  was mighty and its brightness excellent; it stood before thee,  and its appearance was terrible.
2:31|KJV|Thou, O king, sawest, and behold a great image. This great image, whose brightness was excellent, stood before thee; and the form thereof was terrible.
2:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王阿，你觀看，看見一個大像。這像巨大，極其光耀，站在你面前，樣子甚是可怕。
2:32|Darby|This image's head was of fine gold, its breast and its arms  of silver, its belly and its thighs of brass,
2:32|KJV|This image's head was of fine gold, his breast and his arms of silver, his belly and his thighs of brass,
2:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這像的頭是精金的，胸膛和膀臂是銀的，肚腹和腰是銅的，
2:33|Darby|its legs of iron, its feet part of iron and part of clay.
2:33|KJV|His legs of iron, his feet part of iron and part of clay.
2:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|腿是鐵的，腳是半鐵半泥的。
2:34|Darby|Thou sawest till a stone was cut out without hands; and it  smote the image upon its feet of iron and clay, and broke them  to pieces.
2:34|KJV|Thou sawest till that a stone was cut out without hands, which smote the image upon his feet that were of iron and clay, and brake them to pieces.
2:34|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你觀看，見有一塊非人手鑿出來的石頭，打在這像半鐵半泥的腳上，把腳砸碎。
2:35|Darby|Then was the iron, the clay, the brass, the silver, and the  gold broken in pieces together, and they became like the chaff  of the summer threshing-floors; and the wind carried them away,  and no place was found for them. And the stone that smote the  image became a great mountain, and filled the whole earth.
2:35|KJV|Then was the iron, the clay, the brass, the silver, and the gold, broken to pieces together, and became like the chaff of the summer threshingfloors; and the wind carried them away, that no place was found for them: and the stone that smote the image became a great mountain, and filled the whole earth.
2:35|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是鐵、泥、銅、銀、金，都一同砸得粉碎，成如夏天禾場上的糠秕，被風吹散，無處可尋。打碎這像的石頭，變成一座大山，充滿全地。
2:36|Darby|This is the dream; and we will tell the interpretation of  it before the king.
2:36|KJV|This is the dream; and we will tell the interpretation thereof before the king.
2:36|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這就是那夢；我們在王面前要講解那夢。
2:37|Darby|Thou, O king, art a king of kings, unto whom the God of the  heavens hath given the kingdom, the power, and the strength,  and the glory;
2:37|KJV|Thou, O king, art a king of kings: for the God of heaven hath given thee a kingdom, power, and strength, and glory.
2:37|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王阿，你是諸王之王，天上的神已將國度、權能、力量、榮耀，都賜給了你；
2:38|Darby|and wheresoever the children of men, the beasts of the  field, and the fowl of the heavens dwell, he hath given them  into thy hand, and hath made thee ruler over them all: thou art  this head of gold.
2:38|KJV|And wheresoever the children of men dwell, the beasts of the field and the fowls of the heaven hath he given into thine hand, and hath made thee ruler over them all. Thou art this head of gold.
2:38|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|無論住在何處的世人、田野的走獸、並天空的飛鳥，祂都已交付你手，使你掌管這一切。你就是那金頭。
2:39|Darby|And after thee shall arise another kingdom inferior to  thee; then another third kingdom of brass, which shall bear  rule over all the earth.
2:39|KJV|And after thee shall arise another kingdom inferior to thee, and another third kingdom of brass, which shall bear rule over all the earth.
2:39|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在你以後必另有一國興起，不及於你；又有第三國，就是銅的，必掌管全地。
2:40|Darby|And the fourth kingdom shall be strong as iron: forasmuch  as iron breaketh in pieces and subdueth everything, and as iron  that breaketh all these, so shall it break in pieces and  bruise.
2:40|KJV|And the fourth kingdom shall be strong as iron: forasmuch as iron breaketh in pieces and subdueth all things: and as iron that breaketh all these, shall it break in pieces and bruise.
2:40|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|必有第四國，堅強如鐵，像鐵一樣能打碎剋制百物；鐵怎樣能壓碎一切，那國也必照樣打碎壓制列國。
2:41|Darby|And whereas thou sawest the feet and toes, part of potter's  clay, and part of iron, the kingdom shall be divided; but there  shall be in it of the strength of the iron, forasmuch as thou  sawest the iron mixed with miry clay.
2:41|KJV|And whereas thou sawest the feet and toes, part of potters' clay, and part of iron, the kingdom shall be divided; but there shall be in it of the strength of the iron, forasmuch as thou sawest the iron mixed with miry clay.
2:41|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你既看見那像的腳和腳指頭，一半是窯匠的泥，一半是鐵，那國將來也必是混雜的；你既看見鐵與陶泥攙雜，那國也必有鐵的堅硬；
2:42|Darby|And [as] the toes of the feet were part of iron and part of  clay, the kingdom shall be partly strong and partly fragile.
2:42|KJV|And as the toes of the feet were part of iron, and part of clay, so the kingdom shall be partly strong, and partly broken.
2:42|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那些腳指頭，既是半鐵半泥，那國也必半強半弱；
2:43|Darby|And whereas thou sawest the iron mixed with miry clay, they  shall mingle themselves with the seed of men; but they shall  not cleave one to another, even as iron doth not mingle with  clay.
2:43|KJV|And whereas thou sawest iron mixed with miry clay, they shall mingle themselves with the seed of men: but they shall not cleave one to another, even as iron is not mixed with clay.
2:43|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你既看見鐵與陶泥攙雜，那國的民也必人種攙雜，卻不能彼此相合，正如鐵與泥不能攙合一樣。
2:44|Darby|And in the days of these kings shall the God of the heavens  set up a kingdom which shall never be destroyed; and the  sovereignty thereof shall not be left to another people: it  shall break in pieces and consume all these kingdoms, but  itself shall stand for ever.
2:44|KJV|And in the days of these kings shall the God of heaven set up a kingdom, which shall never be destroyed: and the kingdom shall not be left to other people, but it shall break in pieces and consume all these kingdoms, and it shall stand for ever.
2:44|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當那列王在位的日子，天上的神必興起一國，永不敗滅，國權也不留歸別民，卻要打碎滅絕那一切國；這國必存到永遠。
2:45|Darby|Forasmuch as thou sawest that a stone was cut out of the  mountain without hands, and that it broke in pieces the iron,  the brass, the clay, the silver, and the gold, -- the great God  hath made known to the king what shall come to pass hereafter.  And the dream is certain, and the interpretation of it sure.
2:45|KJV|Forasmuch as thou sawest that the stone was cut out of the mountain without hands, and that it brake in pieces the iron, the brass, the clay, the silver, and the gold; the great God hath made known to the king what shall come to pass hereafter: and the dream is certain, and the interpretation thereof sure.
2:45|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你既看見非人手鑿出來的一塊石頭，從山而出，打碎鐵、銅、泥、銀、金，那就是至大的神把後來必發生的事給王指明。這夢準是這樣，這講解也是可信的。
2:46|Darby|Then king Nebuchadnezzar fell on his face and worshipped  Daniel, and commanded that they should offer an oblation and  sweet odours unto him.
2:46|KJV|Then the king Nebuchadnezzar fell upon his face, and worshipped Daniel, and commanded that they should offer an oblation and sweet odours unto him.
2:46|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當時尼布甲尼撒王面伏於地，向但以理下拜，並且吩咐人給他奉上供物和香。
2:47|Darby|The king answered Daniel and said, Of a truth it is that  your God is the God of gods, and the Lord of kings, and a  revealer of secrets, because thou wast able to reveal this  secret.
2:47|KJV|The king answered unto Daniel, and said, Of a truth it is, that your God is a God of gods, and a Lord of kings, and a revealer of secrets, seeing thou couldest reveal this secret.
2:47|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王對但以理說，你既能將這奧祕的事啟示出來，你們的神誠然是萬神之神，萬王之主，又是奧祕事的啟示者。
2:48|Darby|Then the king made Daniel great, and gave him many great  gifts, and made him ruler over the whole province of Babylon,  and chief of the governors over all the wise men of Babylon.
2:48|KJV|Then the king made Daniel a great man, and gave him many great gifts, and made him ruler over the whole province of Babylon, and chief of the governors over all the wise men of Babylon.
2:48|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是王使但以理尊大，賞賜他許多貴重禮物，派他管理巴比倫全省，又立他為總長，掌管巴比倫的一切哲士。
2:49<version name="Darby">And Daniel requested of the king, and he appointed  Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego over the administration of the  province of Babylon. And Daniel was in the gate of the king. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:49<version name="KJV">Then Daniel requested of the king, and he set Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, over the affairs of the province of Babylon: but Daniel sat in the gate of the king.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:49|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但以理求王，王就派沙得拉、米煞、亞伯尼歌管理巴比倫省的事務；只是但以理常在王的朝廷中。
3:1|Darby|Nebuchadnezzar the king made an image of gold, whose height  was sixty cubits, [and] its breadth six cubits; he set it up in  the plain of Dura, in the province of Babylon.
3:1|KJV|Nebuchadnezzar the king made an image of gold, whose height was threescore cubits, and the breadth thereof six cubits: he set it up in the plain of Dura, in the province of Babylon.
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|尼布甲尼撒王造了一個金像，高六十肘，寬六肘，立在巴比倫省的杜拉平原。
3:2|Darby|And Nebuchadnezzar the king sent to gather together the  satraps, the prefects, and the governors, the judges, the  treasurers, the counsellors, the justices, and all the rulers  of the provinces, to come to the dedication of the image that  Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up.
3:2|KJV|Then Nebuchadnezzar the king sent to gather together the princes, the governors, and the captains, the judges, the treasurers, the counsellors, the sheriffs, and all the rulers of the provinces, to come to the dedication of the image which Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up.
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|尼布甲尼撒王差人將總督、司令、省長、審判長、財政官員、司法官員、審判官、和各省的官員，都招聚來，為尼布甲尼撒王所立的像，行開光之禮。
3:3|Darby|Then the satraps, the prefects, and the governors, the  judges, the treasurers, the counsellors, the justices, and all  the rulers of the provinces, were gathered together unto the  dedication of the image that Nebuchadnezzar the king had set  up; and they stood before the image that Nebuchadnezzar had set  up.
3:3|KJV|Then the princes, the governors, and captains, the judges, the treasurers, the counsellors, the sheriffs, and all the rulers of the provinces, were gathered together unto the dedication of the image that Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up; and they stood before the image that Nebuchadnezzar had set up.
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是總督、司令、省長、審判長、財政官員、司法官員、審判官、和各省的官員，都聚集了來，要為尼布甲尼撒王所立的像，行開光之禮，就站在尼布甲尼撒所立的像前。
3:4|Darby|And the herald cried aloud, To you it is commanded, [O]  peoples, nations, and languages,
3:4|KJV|Then an herald cried aloud, To you it is commanded, O people, nations, and languages,
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時傳令的，大聲呼叫說，各族、各國、各方言的人哪，有令傳與你們。
3:5|Darby|that at what time ye hear the sound of the cornet, pipe,  lute, sambuca, psaltery, bagpipe, and all kinds of music, ye  fall down and worship the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the  king hath set up;
3:5|KJV|That at what time ye hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, dulcimer, and all kinds of musick, ye fall down and worship the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the king hath set up:
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們一聽見角、笛、七絃琴、三角琴、瑟、風笛、和各樣樂器的聲音，就當俯伏敬拜尼布甲尼撒王所立的金像；
3:6|Darby|and whosoever doth not fall down and worship shall that same  hour be cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace.
3:6|KJV|And whoso falleth not down and worshippeth shall the same hour be cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace.
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡不俯伏敬拜的，必立時扔在烈火的窯中。
3:7|Darby|Therefore at that time when all the peoples heard the sound  of the cornet, pipe, lute, sambuca, psaltery, and all kinds of  music, all the peoples, the nations, and the languages fell  down [and] worshipped the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the  king had set up.
3:7|KJV|Therefore at that time, when all the people heard the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, and all kinds of musick, all the people, the nations, and the languages, fell down and worshipped the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up.
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此各族、各國、各方言的人，一聽見角、笛、七絃琴、三角琴、瑟、風笛、和各樣樂器的聲音，就都俯伏敬拜尼布甲尼撒王所立的金像。
3:8|Darby|Whereupon at that time certain Chaldeans came near, and  accused the Jews.
3:8|KJV|Wherefore at that time certain Chaldeans came near, and accused the Jews.
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時有幾個迦勒底人，為此進前來控告猶大人。
3:9|Darby|They spoke and said to the king Nebuchadnezzar, O king, live  for ever!
3:9|KJV|They spake and said to the king Nebuchadnezzar, O king, live for ever.
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們對尼布甲尼撒王說，願王萬歲！
3:10|Darby|Thou, O king, hast made a decree, that every man that shall  hear the sound of the cornet, pipe, lute, sambuca, psaltery,  and bagpipe, and all kinds of music, shall fall down and  worship the golden image;
3:10|KJV|Thou, O king, hast made a decree, that every man that shall hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, and dulcimer, and all kinds of musick, shall fall down and worship the golden image:
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王阿，你曾降旨說，凡聽見角、笛、七絃琴、三角琴、瑟、風笛、和各樣樂器聲音的人，都當俯伏敬拜金像；
3:11|Darby|and [that] whosoever doth not fall down and worship, shall  be cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace.
3:11|KJV|And whoso falleth not down and worshippeth, that he should be cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace.
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡不俯伏敬拜的，必扔在烈火的窯中。
3:12|Darby|There are certain Jews whom thou hast appointed over the  administration of the province of Babylon: Shadrach, Meshach,  and Abed-nego: these men, O king, regard thee not; they serve  not thy gods, nor worship the golden image that thou hast set  up.
3:12|KJV|There are certain Jews whom thou hast set over the affairs of the province of Babylon, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego; these men, O king, have not regarded thee: they serve not thy gods, nor worship the golden image which thou hast set up.
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現在有幾個猶大人，就是王所派管理巴比倫省事務的沙得拉、米煞、亞伯尼歌，王阿，這些人不尊重你，不事奉你的神，也不敬拜你所立的金像。
3:13|Darby|Then Nebuchadnezzar in rage and fury commanded to bring  Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego. Then were these men brought  before the king.
3:13|KJV|Then Nebuchadnezzar in his rage and fury commanded to bring Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. Then they brought these men before the king.
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當時尼布甲尼撒大發烈怒，吩咐人把沙得拉、米煞、亞伯尼歌帶過來；他們就把那些人帶到王面前。
3:14|Darby|Nebuchadnezzar spoke and said unto them, Is it of purpose,  Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, that ye serve not my god, nor  worship the golden image that I have set up?
3:14|KJV|Nebuchadnezzar spake and said unto them, Is it true, O Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, do not ye serve my gods, nor worship the golden image which I have set up?
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|尼布甲尼撒問他們說，沙得拉、米煞、亞伯尼歌，你們不事奉我的神，也不敬拜我所立的金像，是故意的麼？
3:15|Darby|Now if ye be ready at the time that ye hear the sound of  the cornet, pipe, lute, sambuca, psaltery, and bagpipe, and all  kinds of music, to fall down and worship the image that I have  made, [well]: but if ye worship not, ye shall be cast that same  hour into the midst of a burning fiery furnace: and who is the  God that shall deliver you out of my hands?
3:15|KJV|Now if ye be ready that at what time ye hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, and dulcimer, and all kinds of musick, ye fall down and worship the image which I have made; well: but if ye worship not, ye shall be cast the same hour into the midst of a burning fiery furnace; and who is that God that shall deliver you out of my hands?
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|如今你們一聽見角、笛、七絃琴、三角琴、瑟、風笛、和各樣樂器的聲音，若立即俯伏敬拜我所造的像，卻還可以；若不敬拜，必立時扔在烈火的窯中，誰是那能救你們脫離我手的神呢？
3:16|Darby|Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego answered and said to the  king, O Nebuchadnezzar, we have no need to answer thee in this  matter.
3:16|KJV|Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, answered and said to the king, O Nebuchadnezzar, we are not careful to answer thee in this matter.
3:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|沙得拉、米煞、亞伯尼歌回答王說，尼布甲尼撒阿，這件事我們不必回答你。
3:17|Darby|If it be [so], our God whom we serve is able to deliver us  from the burning fiery furnace, and he will deliver [us] out of  thy hand, O king.
3:17|KJV|If it be so, our God whom we serve is able to deliver us from the burning fiery furnace, and he will deliver us out of thine hand, O king.
3:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|即便如此，我們所事奉的神，也能將我們從烈火的窯中救出來；王阿，祂必救我們脫離你的手。
3:18|Darby|But if not, be it known unto thee, O king, that we will not  serve thy gods, nor worship the golden image that thou hast set  up.
3:18|KJV|But if not, be it known unto thee, O king, that we will not serve thy gods, nor worship the golden image which thou hast set up.
3:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|即或不然，王阿，你當知道，我們決不事奉你的神，也不敬拜你所立的金像。
3:19|Darby|Then was Nebuchadnezzar full of fury, and the form of his  visage was changed against Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego. He  spoke, and commanded that they should heat the furnace seven  times more than it was wont to be heated.
3:19|KJV|Then was Nebuchadnezzar full of fury, and the form of his visage was changed against Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego: therefore he spake, and commanded that they should heat the furnace one seven times more than it was wont to be heated.
3:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當時尼布甲尼撒怒氣填胸，向沙得拉、米煞、亞伯尼歌變了臉色，吩咐人把窯燒熱，比平常更熱七倍。
3:20|Darby|And he commanded the most mighty men that were in his army  to bind Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, and cast them into  the burning fiery furnace.
3:20|KJV|And he commanded the most mighty men that were in his army to bind Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, and to cast them into the burning fiery furnace.
3:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又吩咐他軍中的幾個壯士，將沙得拉、米煞、亞伯尼歌捆起來，扔在烈火的窯中。
3:21|Darby|Then these men were bound in their hosen, their tunics, and  their cloaks, and their garments, and were cast into the midst  of the burning fiery furnace.
3:21|KJV|Then these men were bound in their coats, their hosen, and their hats, and their other garments, and were cast into the midst of the burning fiery furnace.
3:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當時這三個人是穿著襯衣、內袍、外衣、和別的衣服，被捆起來扔在烈火的窯中。
3:22|Darby|Forasmuch as the king's commandment was rigorous, and the  furnace exceeding hot, the flame of the fire slew those men  that had taken up Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego.
3:22|KJV|Therefore because the king's commandment was urgent, and the furnace exceeding hot, the flames of the fire slew those men that took up Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego.
3:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為王命嚴厲，窯又燒得極熱，那抬沙得拉、米煞、亞伯尼歌的人，都被火焰燒死。
3:23|Darby|And these three men, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, fell  down bound into the midst of the burning fiery furnace.
3:23|KJV|And these three men, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, fell down bound into the midst of the burning fiery furnace.
3:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|沙得拉、米煞、亞伯尼歌這三個人，都被捆著落在烈火的窯中。
3:24|Darby|Then Nebuchadnezzar the king was astonied, and rose up in  haste; he spoke and said unto his counsellors, Did not we cast  three men bound into the midst of the fire? They answered and  said to the king, True, O king.
3:24|KJV|Then Nebuchadnezzar the king was astonished, and rose up in haste, and spake, and said unto his counsellors, Did not we cast three men bound into the midst of the fire? They answered and said unto the king, True, O king.
3:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時尼布甲尼撒王驚奇，急忙起來，對謀士說，我們豈不是把三個人捆起來扔在火婸礡H他們回答王說，王阿，確實是的。
3:25|Darby|He answered and said, Lo, I see four men loose, walking in  the midst of the fire, and they have no hurt; and the  appearance of the fourth is like a son of God.
3:25|KJV|He answered and said, Lo, I see four men loose, walking in the midst of the fire, and they have no hurt; and the form of the fourth is like the Son of God.
3:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王說，看哪，我見有四個人，並沒有捆綁，在火中行走，也沒有受傷；那第四個的相貌，好像神子。
3:26|Darby|Then Nebuchadnezzar came near to the opening of the burning  fiery furnace; he spoke and said, Shadrach, Meshach, and  Abed-nego, ye servants of the Most High God, come forth, and  come [hither]. Then Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego came forth  from the midst of the fire.
3:26|KJV|Then Nebuchadnezzar came near to the mouth of the burning fiery furnace, and spake, and said, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, ye servants of the most high God, come forth, and come hither. Then Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, came forth of the midst of the fire.
3:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是尼布甲尼撒就近烈火窯門，說，至高神的僕人沙得拉、米煞、亞伯尼歌出來，到這堥蚑}。沙得拉、米煞、亞伯尼歌就從火中出來了。
3:27|Darby|And the satraps, the prefects, and the governors, and the  king's counsellors, being gathered together, saw these men,  upon whose bodies the fire had had no power, nor was the hair  of their head singed, neither were their hosen changed, nor had  the smell of fire passed on them.
3:27|KJV|And the princes, governors, and captains, and the king's counsellors, being gathered together, saw these men, upon whose bodies the fire had no power, nor was an hair of their head singed, neither were their coats changed, nor the smell of fire had passed on them.
3:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那些總督、司令、省長、和王的謀士，一同聚集看這三個人，見火無力傷及他們的身體，他們的頭髮沒有燒焦，衣裳沒有變色，身上也沒有火燎的氣味。
3:28|Darby|Nebuchadnezzar spoke and said, Blessed be the God of  Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, who hath sent his angel, and  delivered his servants who trusted in him, and who changed the  king's word, and yielded their bodies, that they might not  serve nor worship any god, except their own God!
3:28|KJV|Then Nebuchadnezzar spake, and said, Blessed be the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, who hath sent his angel, and delivered his servants that trusted in him, and have changed the king's word, and yielded their bodies, that they might not serve nor worship any god, except their own God.
3:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|尼布甲尼撒說，沙得拉、米煞、亞伯尼歌的神是當受頌讚的，祂差遣使者救護祂的僕人，他們信靠祂，不遵王言，寧捨己身，在他們神以外不肯事奉敬拜別神；
3:29|Darby|Therefore I make a decree, that in every people, nation,  and language, he who shall speak anything amiss against the God  of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, shall be cut in pieces,  and his house shall be made a dunghill: because there is no  other God that is able to deliver after this sort.
3:29|KJV|Therefore I make a decree, That every people, nation, and language, which speak any thing amiss against the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, shall be cut in pieces, and their houses shall be made a dunghill: because there is no other God that can deliver after this sort.
3:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現在我降旨，無論何族、何國、何方言的人，謗讟沙得拉、米煞、亞伯尼歌之神的，必被凌遲，他的房屋必成糞堆，因為沒有別神能這樣施行拯救。
3:30<version name="Darby">Then the king promoted Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego in  the province of Babylon. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:30<version name="KJV">Then the king promoted Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, in the province of Babylon.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時王使沙得拉、米煞、亞伯尼歌在巴比倫省得亨通。
4:1|Darby|Nebuchadnezzar the king unto all the peoples, nations, and  languages, that dwell in all the earth: Peace be multiplied  unto you.
4:1|KJV|Nebuchadnezzar the king, unto all people, nations, and languages, that dwell in all the earth; Peace be multiplied unto you.
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|尼布甲尼撒王曉諭住在全地各族、各國、各方言的人，說，願你們大享平安。
4:2|Darby|It hath seemed good unto me to declare the signs and wonders  that the Most High God hath wrought toward me.
4:2|KJV|I thought it good to shew the signs and wonders that the high God hath wrought toward me.
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我樂意將至高的神向我所行的神蹟奇事，宣揚出來。
4:3|Darby|How great are his signs! and how mighty are his wonders! His  kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and his dominion is from  generation to generation.
4:3|KJV|How great are his signs! and how mighty are his wonders! his kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and his dominion is from generation to generation.
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂的神蹟何其偉大，祂的奇事何其有能！祂的國是永遠的國，祂的權柄存到萬代。
4:4|Darby|I Nebuchadnezzar was at rest in my house, and flourishing in  my palace.
4:4|KJV|I Nebuchadnezzar was at rest in mine house, and flourishing in my palace:
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我尼布甲尼撒在宮中處安逸，在殿內享昌隆。
4:5|Darby|I saw a dream which made me afraid, and the thoughts upon my  bed and the visions of my head troubled me.
4:5|KJV|I saw a dream which made me afraid, and the thoughts upon my bed and the visions of my head troubled me.
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我作了一個夢使我懼怕，我在床上的思念並腦中的異象使我驚惶；
4:6|Darby|And I made a decree to bring in all the wise men of Babylon  before me, that they might make known unto me the  interpretation of the dream.
4:6|KJV|Therefore made I a decree to bring in all the wise men of Babylon before me, that they might make known unto me the interpretation of the dream.
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我降旨召巴比倫的一切哲士到我面前，叫他們把夢的講解告訴我。
4:7|Darby|Then came in the scribes, the magicians, the Chaldeans, and  the astrologers; and I told the dream before them; but they did  not make known unto me the interpretation of it.
4:7|KJV|Then came in the magicians, the astrologers, the Chaldeans, and the soothsayers: and I told the dream before them; but they did not make known unto me the interpretation thereof.
4:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是那些術士、用法術的、迦勒底人、觀兆的都進來，我將那夢告訴了他們，他們卻不能把夢的講解告訴我。
4:8|Darby|But at the last Daniel came in before me, whose name is  Belteshazzar, according to the name of my god, and in whom is  the spirit of the holy gods; and before him I told the dream:
4:8|KJV|But at the last Daniel came in before me, whose name was Belteshazzar, according to the name of my God, and in whom is the spirit of the holy gods: and before him I told the dream, saying,
4:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|末後那照我神的名稱為伯提沙撒，媕Y有聖神明之靈的但以理，來到我面前；我將夢告訴他，說，
4:9|Darby|O Belteshazzar, master of the scribes, because I know that  the spirit of the holy gods is in thee, and no secret is too  hard for thee, tell me the visions of my dream which I have  seen, and the interpretation of it.
4:9|KJV|O Belteshazzar, master of the magicians, because I know that the spirit of the holy gods is in thee, and no secret troubleth thee, tell me the visions of my dream that I have seen, and the interpretation thereof.
4:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|術士的領袖伯提沙撒阿，因我知道你媕Y有聖神明的靈，沒有甚麼奧祕的事能使你為難；這是我夢中所見的異象，你要把講解告訴我。
4:10|Darby|Thus were the visions of my head upon my bed: I saw, and  behold a tree in the midst of the earth, and its height was  great.
4:10|KJV|Thus were the visions of mine head in my bed; I saw, and behold a tree in the midst of the earth, and the height thereof was great.
4:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在床上腦中的異象是這樣：我觀看，見地當中有一棵樹，極其高大。
4:11|Darby|The tree grew, and was strong, and its height reached unto  the heavens, and the sight thereof to the end of all the earth.
4:11|KJV|The tree grew, and was strong, and the height thereof reached unto heaven, and the sight thereof to the end of all the earth:
4:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那樹漸漸長大，而且堅固，高達於天，從地極都能看見。
4:12|Darby|Its leaves were beautiful, and its fruit abundant, and in  it was food for all: the beasts of the field found shade under  it, and the birds of the heavens dwelt in its branches, and all  flesh was fed from it.
4:12|KJV|The leaves thereof were fair, and the fruit thereof much, and in it was meat for all: the beasts of the field had shadow under it, and the fowls of the heaven dwelt in the boughs thereof, and all flesh was fed of it.
4:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|樹的葉子華美，果子甚多，可作眾生的食物。野地的走獸臥在蔭下，天空的飛鳥宿在枝上，凡有血肉的，都從這樹得食。
4:13|Darby|I saw in the visions of my head upon my bed, and behold, a  watcher and a holy one came down from the heavens;
4:13|KJV|I saw in the visions of my head upon my bed, and, behold, a watcher and an holy one came down from heaven;
4:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在床上腦中的異象堙A正觀看時，見有一位守望者，就是聖者，從天而降。
4:14|Darby|he cried aloud, and said thus: Hew down the tree, and cut  off its branches, shake off its leaves, and scatter its fruit;  let the beasts get away from under it, and the birds from its  branches.
4:14|KJV|He cried aloud, and said thus, Hew down the tree, and cut off his branches, shake off his leaves, and scatter his fruit: let the beasts get away from under it, and the fowls from his branches:
4:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他大聲呼叫說，伐倒這樹，砍下枝子，搖掉葉子，拋散果子，使走獸逃開樹下，飛鳥逃離樹枝。
4:15|Darby|Nevertheless leave the stump of its roots in the earth,  even with a band of iron and brass, in the tender grass of the  field; and let it be bathed with the dew of heaven, and let his  portion be with the beasts in the grass of the earth.
4:15|KJV|Nevertheless leave the stump of his roots in the earth, even with a band of iron and brass, in the tender grass of the field; and let it be wet with the dew of heaven, and let his portion be with the beasts in the grass of the earth:
4:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|樹根的不卻要留在地內，用鐵圈和銅圈箍住，在野地的青草中；讓他被天露沾濕，且與走獸同分，喫地上的草；
4:16|Darby|Let his heart be changed from man's, and let a beast's  heart be given unto him; and let seven times pass over him.
4:16|KJV|Let his heart be changed from man's, and let a beast's heart be given unto him; and let seven times pass over him.
4:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|使他的心變得不是人心，給他一個獸心，使他經過七個時期。
4:17|Darby|This sentence is by the decree of the watchers, and the  decision by the word of the holy ones: that the living may know  that the Most High ruleth over the kingdom of men, and giveth  it to whomsoever he will, and setteth up over it the basest of  men.
4:17|KJV|This matter is by the decree of the watchers, and the demand by the word of the holy ones: to the intent that the living may know that the most High ruleth in the kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomsoever he will, and setteth up over it the basest of men.
4:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這乃是眾守望者的命令，這決定乃是眾聖者的吩咐，好叫活人知道，至高者纔是人國的掌權者，要將國賜與誰，就賜與誰；祂立極卑微的人掌權。
4:18|Darby|This dream I, king Nebuchadnezzar, have seen; and thou,  Belteshazzar, tell the interpretation, forasmuch as all the  wise men of my kingdom are not able to make known unto me the  interpretation; but thou art able, for the spirit of the holy  gods is in thee.
4:18|KJV|This dream I king Nebuchadnezzar have seen. Now thou, O Belteshazzar, declare the interpretation thereof, forasmuch as all the wise men of my kingdom are not able to make known unto me the interpretation: but thou art able; for the spirit of the holy gods is in thee.
4:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這是我尼布甲尼撒王所作的夢，伯提沙撒阿，你要說出這夢的講解，因為我國中的一切哲士，都不能將夢的講解告訴我；惟獨你能，因你媕Y有聖神明的靈。
4:19|Darby|Then Daniel, whose name is Belteshazzar, was astonied for  one hour, and his thoughts troubled him. The king spoke and  said, Belteshazzar, let not the dream, nor its interpretation,  trouble thee. Belteshazzar answered and said, My lord, the  dream be to them that hate thee, and its interpretation to  thine enemies!
4:19|KJV|Then Daniel, whose name was Belteshazzar, was astonied for one hour, and his thoughts troubled him. The king spake, and said, Belteshazzar, let not the dream, or the interpretation thereof, trouble thee. Belteshazzar answered and said, My lord, the dream be to them that hate thee, and the interpretation thereof to thine enemies.
4:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時，稱為伯提沙撒的但以理，驚訝片刻，心意驚惶。王說，伯提沙撒阿，不要因夢和夢的講解驚惶。伯提沙撒回答說，我主阿，願這夢歸與恨你的人，講解歸與你的敵人！
4:20|Darby|The tree that thou sawest, which grew and was strong, whose  height reached unto the heavens, and the sight of it to all the  earth;
4:20|KJV|The tree that thou sawest, which grew, and was strong, whose height reached unto the heaven, and the sight thereof to all the earth;
4:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你所見的樹漸漸長大，而且堅固，高達於天，從地極都能看見；
4:21|Darby|whose leaves were beautiful, and its fruit abundant, and in  it was food for all; under which the beasts of the field dwelt,  and in whose branches the birds of the heavens had their  habitation:
4:21|KJV|Whose leaves were fair, and the fruit thereof much, and in it was meat for all; under which the beasts of the field dwelt, and upon whose branches the fowls of the heaven had their habitation:
4:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|樹的葉子華美，果子甚多，可作眾生的食物，野地的走獸住在其下，天空的飛鳥宿在枝上；
4:22|Darby|it is thou, O king, who art grown and become strong; for  thy greatness is grown, and reacheth unto the heavens, and thy  dominion to the end of the earth.
4:22|KJV|It is thou, O king, that art grown and become strong: for thy greatness is grown, and reacheth unto heaven, and thy dominion to the end of the earth.
4:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王阿，這長大又堅固的樹就是你，因為你的威勢漸長及天，你的權柄達到地極。
4:23|Darby|And whereas the king saw a watcher and a holy one coming  down from the heavens, and saying, Hew the tree down, and  destroy it; nevertheless leave the stump of its roots in the  earth, even with a band of iron and brass, in the tender grass  of the field; and let it be bathed with the dew of heaven, and  let his portion be with the beasts of the field, till seven  times pass over him:
4:23|KJV|And whereas the king saw a watcher and an holy one coming down from heaven, and saying, Hew the tree down, and destroy it; yet leave the stump of the roots thereof in the earth, even with a band of iron and brass, in the tender grass of the field; and let it be wet with the dew of heaven, and let his portion be with the beasts of the field, till seven times pass over him;
4:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王既看見一位守望者，就是聖者從天而降，說，將這樹砍伐毀壞，樹根的不卻要留在地內，用鐵圈和銅圈箍住，在野地的青草中；讓他被天露沾濕，且與走獸同分，直到經過七個時期。
4:24|Darby|this is the interpretation, O king, and it is the decree of  the Most High, which cometh upon my lord the king:
4:24|KJV|This is the interpretation, O king, and this is the decree of the most High, which is come upon my lord the king:
4:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王阿，這就是講解；臨到我主我王的事，乃是至高者的命令：
4:25|Darby|They shall drive thee from men, and thy dwelling shall be  with the beasts of the field, and they shall make thee to eat  grass as oxen, and thou shalt be bathed with the dew of heaven;  and seven times shall pass over thee, till thou know that the  Most High ruleth over the kingdom of men, and giveth it to  whomsoever he will.
4:25|KJV|That they shall drive thee from men, and thy dwelling shall be with the beasts of the field, and they shall make thee to eat grass as oxen, and they shall wet thee with the dew of heaven, and seven times shall pass over thee, till thou know that the most High ruleth in the kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomsoever he will.
4:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你必被趕出離開人類，與野地的獸同住；你必喫草如牛，被天露沾濕，且要經過七個時期，等你知道至高者纔是人國的掌權者，要將國賜與誰，就賜與誰。
4:26|Darby|And whereas it was commanded to leave the stump of the  roots of the tree; thy kingdom shall remain unto thee, after  that thou shalt know that the heavens do rule.
4:26|KJV|And whereas they commanded to leave the stump of the tree roots; thy kingdom shall be sure unto thee, after that thou shalt have known that the heavens do rule.
4:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|守望者既吩咐存留樹根的不，等你知道諸天掌權，以後你的國必定歸你。
4:27|Darby|Therefore, O king, let my counsel be acceptable unto thee,  and break off thy sins by righteousness, and thine iniquities  by shewing mercy to the poor; if it may be a lengthening of thy  tranquillity.
4:27|KJV|Wherefore, O king, let my counsel be acceptable unto thee, and break off thy sins by righteousness, and thine iniquities by shewing mercy to the poor; if it may be a lengthening of thy tranquillity.
4:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以王阿，求你悅納我的諫言：以行義斷絕罪過，以憐憫窮人除掉罪孽，或者你的榮華可以延長。
4:28|Darby|All this came upon king Nebuchadnezzar.
4:28|KJV|All this came upon the king Nebuchadnezzar.
4:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這一切都臨到尼布甲尼撒王。
4:29|Darby|At the end of twelve months he was walking upon the royal  palace of Babylon:
4:29|KJV|At the end of twelve months he walked in the palace of the kingdom of Babylon.
4:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|過了十二個月，他在巴比倫王宮頂上行走。
4:30|Darby|the king spoke and said, Is not this great Babylon, that I  have built for the house of the kingdom by the might of my  power and for the glory of my majesty?
4:30|KJV|The king spake, and said, Is not this great Babylon, that I have built for the house of the kingdom by the might of my power, and for the honour of my majesty?
4:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他說，這大巴比倫不是我用自己權能的力量建為王家，要顯我威嚴的榮耀麼？
4:31|Darby|While the word was in the king's mouth, there fell a voice  from the heavens: King Nebuchadnezzar, to thee it is spoken:  The kingdom is departed from thee;
4:31|KJV|While the word was in the king's mouth, there fell a voice from heaven, saying, O king Nebuchadnezzar, to thee it is spoken; The kingdom is departed from thee.
4:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這話在王口中尚未說完，有聲音從天降下，說，尼布甲尼撒王阿，有話對你說，你的國位離開你了；
4:32|Darby|and they shall drive thee from men, and thy dwelling shall  be with the beasts of the field; they shall make thee to eat  grass as oxen, and seven times shall pass over thee, until thou  know that the Most High ruleth over the kingdom of men, and  giveth it to whomsoever he will.
4:32|KJV|And they shall drive thee from men, and thy dwelling shall be with the beasts of the field: they shall make thee to eat grass as oxen, and seven times shall pass over thee, until thou know that the most High ruleth in the kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomsoever he will.
4:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你必被趕出離開人類，與野地的獸同住；你必喫草如牛，且要經過七個時期，等你知道至高者纔是人國的掌權者，要將國賜與誰，就賜與誰。
4:33|Darby|The same hour was the word fulfilled upon Nebuchadnezzar;  and he was driven from men, and ate grass as oxen; and his body  was bathed with the dew of heaven, till his hair grew like  eagles' [feathers], and his nails like birds' [claws].
4:33|KJV|The same hour was the thing fulfilled upon Nebuchadnezzar: and he was driven from men, and did eat grass as oxen, and his body was wet with the dew of heaven, till his hairs were grown like eagles' feathers, and his nails like birds' claws.
4:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當時這話就應驗在尼布甲尼撒的身上，他被趕出離開人類，喫草如牛，身被天露沾濕，直到頭髮長長好像鷹毛，指甲長長如同鳥爪。
4:34|Darby|And at the end of the days I Nebuchadnezzar lifted up mine  eyes unto the heavens, and mine understanding returned unto me,  and I blessed the Most High, and I praised and honoured him  that liveth for ever, whose dominion is an everlasting  dominion, and his kingdom is from generation to generation.
4:34|KJV|And at the end of the days I Nebuchadnezzar lifted up mine eyes unto heaven, and mine understanding returned unto me, and I blessed the most High, and I praised and honoured him that liveth for ever, whose dominion is an everlasting dominion, and his kingdom is from generation to generation:
4:34|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那些日子過後，我尼布甲尼撒舉目望天，我的理性復歸於我，我便頌讚至高者，讚美尊敬那永活者；因為祂的權柄是永遠的權柄，祂的國存到萬代。
4:35|Darby|And all the inhabitants of the earth are reputed as  nothing; and he doeth according to his will in the army of the  heavens, and among the inhabitants of the earth; and none can  stay his hand, or say unto him, What doest thou?
4:35|KJV|And all the inhabitants of the earth are reputed as nothing: and he doeth according to his will in the army of heaven, and among the inhabitants of the earth: and none can stay his hand, or say unto him, What doest thou?
4:35|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|地上所有的居民，都算為虛無；但在天上的萬軍和地上的居民中，祂照自己的意旨行事；無人能攔住祂的手，或對祂說，你作甚麼呢？
4:36|Darby|At the same time mine understanding returned unto me; and  for the glory of my kingdom, my majesty and brightness returned  unto me; and my counsellors and my nobles sought me; and I was  established in my kingdom, and excellent greatness was added  unto me.
4:36|KJV|At the same time my reason returned unto me; and for the glory of my kingdom, mine honour and brightness returned unto me; and my counsellors and my lords sought unto me; and I was established in my kingdom, and excellent majesty was added unto me.
4:36|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時，我的理性復歸於我；為了我國的榮耀，威嚴和光耀也都復歸於我；我的謀士和大臣也來求見我，我又得堅立在國位上，超越的尊大加增於我。
4:37<version name="Darby">Now I Nebuchadnezzar praise and extol and honour the King  of the heavens, all whose works are truth, and his paths  judgment: and those that walk in pride he is able to abase. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:37<version name="KJV">Now I Nebuchadnezzar praise and extol and honour the King of heaven, all whose works are truth, and his ways judgment: and those that walk in pride he is able to abase.</p><p /><br /></version>
4:37|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現在我尼布甲尼撒讚美、高舉、尊敬天上的王，因為祂一切的作為全是真的，祂的道路是公平的，因為祂能使那行動驕傲的降為卑。
5:1|Darby|Belshazzar the king made a great feast to a thousand of his  nobles, and drank wine before the thousand.
5:1|KJV|Belshazzar the king made a great feast to a thousand of his lords, and drank wine before the thousand.
5:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|伯沙撒王為他的一千大臣設擺盛筵，與這一千人對面飲酒。
5:2|Darby|Belshazzar, while he tasted the wine, commanded to bring the  golden and silver vessels that Nebuchadnezzar his father had  taken out of the temple which was in Jerusalem; that the king  and his nobles, his wives and his concubines, might drink in  them.
5:2|KJV|Belshazzar, whiles he tasted the wine, commanded to bring the golden and silver vessels which his father Nebuchadnezzar had taken out of the temple which was in Jerusalem; that the king, and his princes, his wives, and his concubines, might drink therein.
5:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|伯沙撒飲酒歡暢時，吩咐人將他先祖尼布甲尼撒從耶路撒冷殿中所掠的金銀器皿拿來，王與大臣、皇后、妃嬪好用這些器皿飲酒。
5:3|Darby|Then they brought the golden vessels that were taken out of  the temple of the house of God which was at Jerusalem; and the  king and his nobles, his wives and his concubines, drank in  them.
5:3|KJV|Then they brought the golden vessels that were taken out of the temple of the house of God which was at Jerusalem; and the king, and his princes, his wives, and his concubines, drank in them.
5:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是他們把耶路撒冷殿中，就是神家中所掠的金器皿拿來，王和大臣、皇后、妃嬪就用這些器皿飲酒。
5:4|Darby|They drank wine, and praised the gods of gold and of silver,  of brass, of iron, of wood, and of stone.
5:4|KJV|They drank wine, and praised the gods of gold, and of silver, of brass, of iron, of wood, and of stone.
5:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們飲酒，讚美那用金、銀、銅、鐵、木、石所造的神。
5:5|Darby|In the same hour came forth fingers of a man's hand, and  wrote over against the candlestick upon the plaster of the wall  of the king's palace: and the king saw the part of the hand  that wrote.
5:5|KJV|In the same hour came forth fingers of a man's hand, and wrote over against the candlestick upon the plaister of the wall of the king's palace: and the king saw the part of the hand that wrote.
5:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當時有人手的指頭顯出來，在王宮媬O臺對面的粉牆上寫字；王看見寫字的手指頭，
5:6|Darby|Then the king's countenance was changed, and his thoughts  troubled him, and the joints of his loins were loosed, and his  knees smote one against another.
5:6|KJV|Then the king's countenance was changed, and his thoughts troubled him, so that the joints of his loins were loosed, and his knees smote one against another.
5:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就變了臉色，心意驚惶，腰骨好像脫節，雙膝彼此相碰。
5:7|Darby|The king cried aloud to bring in the magicians, the  Chaldeans, and the astrologers. The king spoke and said to the  wise men of Babylon, Whosoever shall read this writing, and  shew me the interpretation thereof, shall be clothed with  purple, and have a chain of gold about his neck, and shall be  the third ruler in the kingdom.
5:7|KJV|The king cried aloud to bring in the astrologers, the Chaldeans, and the soothsayers. And the king spake, and said to the wise men of Babylon, Whosoever shall read this writing, and shew me the interpretation thereof, shall be clothed with scarlet, and have a chain of gold about his neck, and shall be the third ruler in the kingdom.
5:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王大聲吩咐將用法術的、迦勒底人、並觀兆的領進來；王對巴比倫的哲士說，甚麼人能讀這文字，把講解告訴我，他必身穿紫袍，項戴金鍊，在我國中掌權，位列第三。
5:8|Darby|Then came in all the king's wise men, but they could not  read the writing, nor make known to the king the  interpretation.
5:8|KJV|Then came in all the king's wise men: but they could not read the writing, nor make known to the king the interpretation thereof.
5:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是王的一切哲士都進來，卻不能讀那文字，也不能把講解告訴王。
5:9|Darby|Then was king Belshazzar greatly troubled, and his  countenance was changed in him, and his nobles were confounded.
5:9|KJV|Then was king Belshazzar greatly troubled, and his countenance was changed in him, and his lords were astonied.
5:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|伯沙撒王就極其驚惶，臉色更為改變，他的大臣也都驚奇。
5:10|Darby|-- The queen, by reason of the words of the king and his  nobles, came into the banquet-house. The queen spoke and said,  O king, live for ever! let not thy thoughts trouble thee,  neither let thy countenance be changed.
5:10|KJV|Now the queen by reason of the words of the king and his lords came into the banquet house: and the queen spake and said, O king, live for ever: let not thy thoughts trouble thee, nor let thy countenance be changed:
5:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|太后因王和他大臣所說的話，就進入宴宮，說，願王萬歲！你的心意不要驚惶，臉色不要改變。
5:11|Darby|There is a man in thy kingdom in whom is the spirit of the  holy gods; and in the days of thy father, light and  understanding and wisdom, like the wisdom of the gods was found  in him; and the king Nebuchadnezzar thy father, [even] the king  thy father, made him master of the scribes, magicians,  Chaldeans, [and] astrologers;
5:11|KJV|There is a man in thy kingdom, in whom is the spirit of the holy gods; and in the days of thy father light and understanding and wisdom, like the wisdom of the gods, was found in him; whom the king Nebuchadnezzar thy father, the king, I say, thy father, made master of the magicians, astrologers, Chaldeans, and soothsayers;
5:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在你國中有一個人，他媕Y有聖神明的靈，你先祖在世的日子，見這人媕Y有光，又有聰明智慧，好像神明的智慧；你先祖尼布甲尼撒王，就是王的先祖，立他為術士、用法術的、迦勒底人、並觀兆者的領袖；
5:12|Darby|forasmuch as an excellent spirit, and knowledge, and  understanding, interpreting of dreams, and shewing of hard  sentences, and solving of problems, were found in the same  Daniel, whom the king named Belteshazzar. Now let Daniel be  called, and he will shew the interpretation.
5:12|KJV|Forasmuch as an excellent spirit, and knowledge, and understanding, interpreting of dreams, and shewing of hard sentences, and dissolving of doubts, were found in the same Daniel, whom the king named Belteshazzar: now let Daniel be called, and he will shew the interpretation.
5:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為在他媕Y有美好的靈，又有知識聰明，能圓夢，釋謎語，解難題，這人名叫但以理，尼布甲尼撒王稱他為伯提沙撒；現在可以把但以理召來，他必講解說明。
5:13|Darby|Then was Daniel brought in before the king. The king spoke  and said unto Daniel, Art thou that Daniel, of the children of  the captivity of Judah, whom the king my father brought out of  Judah?
5:13|KJV|Then was Daniel brought in before the king. And the king spake and said unto Daniel, Art thou that Daniel, which art of the children of the captivity of Judah, whom the king my father brought out of Jewry?
5:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是但以理被領到王前；王問但以理說，你是被擄之猶大人中的但以理麼？就是我的先祖王從猶大帶來的麼？
5:14|Darby|And I have heard of thee, that the spirit of the gods is in  thee, and [that] light and understanding and excellent wisdom  is found in thee.
5:14|KJV|I have even heard of thee, that the spirit of the gods is in thee, and that light and understanding and excellent wisdom is found in thee.
5:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我聽說你媕Y有神明的靈，並且有光，又有聰明和超越的智慧。
5:15|Darby|And now the wise men, the magicians, have been brought in  before me, that they should read this writing, and make known  unto me the interpretation thereof; but they could not shew the  interpretation of the thing.
5:15|KJV|And now the wise men, the astrologers, have been brought in before me, that they should read this writing, and make known unto me the interpretation thereof: but they could not shew the interpretation of the thing:
5:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現在哲士和用法術的，都被領到我面前，為叫他們讀這文字，把講解告訴我，但他們都不能講解說明。
5:16|Darby|But I have heard of thee, that thou canst give  interpretations, and solve problems. Now if thou canst read the  writing, and make known to me the interpretation thereof, thou  shalt be clothed with purple, and have a chain of gold about  thy neck, and shalt be the third ruler in the kingdom.
5:16|KJV|And I have heard of thee, that thou canst make interpretations, and dissolve doubts: now if thou canst read the writing, and make known to me the interpretation thereof, thou shalt be clothed with scarlet, and have a chain of gold about thy neck, and shalt be the third ruler in the kingdom.
5:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我聽說你善於講解，能解難題；現在你若能讀這文字，把講解告訴我，就必身穿紫袍，項戴金鍊，在我國中掌權，位列第三。
5:17|Darby|Then Daniel answered and said before the king, Let thy  gifts be to thyself, and give thy rewards to another; yet will  I read the writing to the king, and make known to him the  interpretation.
5:17|KJV|Then Daniel answered and said before the king, Let thy gifts be to thyself, and give thy rewards to another; yet I will read the writing unto the king, and make known to him the interpretation.
5:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但以理在王面前回答說，你的贈品可以歸你自己；你的賞賜可以賜給別人；我卻要為王讀這文字，把講解告訴王。
5:18|Darby|O thou king, the Most High God gave Nebuchadnezzar thy  father the kingdom, and greatness, and glory, and majesty;
5:18|KJV|O thou king, the most high God gave Nebuchadnezzar thy father a kingdom, and majesty, and glory, and honour:
5:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王阿，至高的神曾將國度、尊大、榮耀、威嚴，賜與你的先祖尼布甲尼撒。
5:19|Darby|and for the greatness that he gave him, all peoples,  nations, and languages, trembled and feared before him: whom he  would he slew, and whom he would he kept alive; and whom he  would he exalted, and whom he would he humbled.
5:19|KJV|And for the majesty that he gave him, all people, nations, and languages, trembled and feared before him: whom he would he slew; and whom he would he kept alive; and whom he would he set up; and whom he would he put down.
5:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因神所賜他的尊大，各族、各國、各方言的人，都在他面前戰兢恐懼，他可以隨意生殺，隨意升降。
5:20|Darby|But when his heart was lifted up, and his spirit hardened  unto presumption, he was deposed from the throne of his  kingdom, and they took his glory from him;
5:20|KJV|But when his heart was lifted up, and his mind hardened in pride, he was deposed from his kingly throne, and they took his glory from him:
5:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但他的心高傲，靈也剛愎，甚至行事狂傲，就被革去王位，奪去榮耀。
5:21|Darby|and he was driven from the sons of men, and his heart was  made like the beasts, and his dwelling was with the wild asses;  they fed him with grass like oxen, and his body was bathed with  the dew of heaven; till he knew that the Most High God ruleth  over the kingdom of men, and that he appointeth over it  whomsoever he will.
5:21|KJV|And he was driven from the sons of men; and his heart was made like the beasts, and his dwelling was with the wild asses: they fed him with grass like oxen, and his body was wet with the dew of heaven; till he knew that the most high God ruled in the kingdom of men, and that he appointeth over it whomsoever he will.
5:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他被趕出離開世人，他的心變如獸心，與野驢同住；他喫草如牛，身被天露沾濕，等他知道至高的神纔是人國的掌權者，隨自己的意旨立人治國。
5:22|Darby|And thou, Belshazzar, his son, hast not humbled thy heart,  although thou knewest all this;
5:22|KJV|And thou his son, O Belshazzar, hast not humbled thine heart, though thou knewest all this;
5:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|伯沙撒阿，你是他的子孫，你雖知道這一切，你的心仍不謙卑，
5:23|Darby|but hast lifted up thyself against the Lord of the heavens;  and they have brought the vessels of his house before thee, and  thou and thy nobles, thy wives and thy concubines, have drunk  wine in them; and thou hast praised the gods of silver and  gold, of brass, iron, wood, and stone, which see not, nor hear,  nor know; and the God in whose hand thy breath is, and whose  are all thy ways, hast thou not glorified:
5:23|KJV|But hast lifted up thyself against the Lord of heaven; and they have brought the vessels of his house before thee, and thou, and thy lords, thy wives, and thy concubines, have drunk wine in them; and thou hast praised the gods of silver, and gold, of brass, iron, wood, and stone, which see not, nor hear, nor know: and the God in whose hand thy breath is, and whose are all thy ways, hast thou not glorified:
5:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|竟向天上的主自高，使人將祂殿中的器皿拿到你面前，你和大臣、皇后、妃嬪用這些器皿飲酒；你又讚美那不能看、不能聽，無知無識，用金、銀、銅、鐵、木、石所造的神；卻沒有將尊榮歸與那手中有你氣息，管理你一切道路的神；
5:24|Darby|then from before him was sent the part of the hand, and  this writing hath been written.
5:24|KJV|Then was the part of the hand sent from him; and this writing was written.
5:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此從神面前差出手指頭來，寫這文字。
5:25|Darby|And this is the writing that is written: MENE, MENE, TEKEL,  UPHARSIN.
5:25|KJV|And this is the writing that was written, MENE, MENE, TEKEL, UPHARSIN.
5:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所寫的文字是：彌尼，彌尼，提客勒，烏法珥新。
5:26|Darby|This is the interpretation of the thing: MENE, God hath  numbered thy kingdom, and finished it;
5:26|KJV|This is the interpretation of the thing: MENE; God hath numbered thy kingdom, and finished it.
5:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這話的講解是這樣。彌尼，就是神已經數算你國的年日，使其終止；
5:27|Darby|TEKEL, Thou art weighed in the balances, and art found  wanting;
5:27|KJV|TEKEL; Thou art weighed in the balances, and art found wanting.
5:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|提客勒，就是你被稱在天平堙A顯出你的虧欠；
5:28|Darby|PERES, Thy kingdom is divided, and given to the Medes and  Persians.
5:28|KJV|PERES; Thy kingdom is divided, and given to the Medes and Persians.
5:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|毘勒斯，就是你的國分裂，歸與瑪代人和波斯人。
5:29|Darby|Then Belshazzar commanded, and they clothed Daniel with  purple, and [put] a chain of gold about his neck, and made  proclamation concerning him that he should be the third ruler  in the kingdom.
5:29|KJV|Then commanded Belshazzar, and they clothed Daniel with scarlet, and put a chain of gold about his neck, and made a proclamation concerning him, that he should be the third ruler in the kingdom.
5:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|伯沙撒下令，人就把紫袍給但以理穿上，把金鍊給他戴在頸項上，又傳令使他在國中掌權，位列第三。
5:30|Darby|In that night was Belshazzar the king of the Chaldeans  slain.
5:30|KJV|In that night was Belshazzar the king of the Chaldeans slain.
5:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當夜迦勒底王伯沙撒被殺；
5:31<version name="Darby">And Darius the Mede received the kingdom, [being] about  sixty-two years old. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:31<version name="KJV">And Darius the Median took the kingdom, being about threescore and two years old.</p><p /><br /></version>
5:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|瑪代人大利烏，約六十二歲，取了迦勒底國。
6:1|Darby|It pleased Darius to set over the kingdom a hundred and  twenty satraps, who should be in all the kingdom;
6:1|KJV|It pleased Darius to set over the kingdom an hundred and twenty princes, which should be over the whole kingdom;
6:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|大利烏隨心所願，在全國立了一百二十個總督，治理通國；
6:2|Darby|and over these, three presidents -- of whom Daniel was one  -- to whom these satraps should render account, and that the  king should suffer no loss.
6:2|KJV|And over these three presidents; of whom Daniel was first: that the princes might give accounts unto them, and the king should have no damage.
6:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又在他們以上立總長三人，（但以理為其中之一，）使這些總督向他們三人呈報，免得王受虧損。
6:3|Darby|Now this Daniel surpassed the presidents and the satraps,  because an excellent spirit was in him; and the king thought to  appoint him over the whole realm.
6:3|KJV|Then this Daniel was preferred above the presidents and princes, because an excellent spirit was in him; and the king thought to set him over the whole realm.
6:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因這但以理有美好的靈，所以顯然超乎其餘的總長和總督，王又想立他治理通國。
6:4|Darby|Then the presidents and the satraps sought to find a pretext  against Daniel with respect to the kingdom; but they could not  find any pretext or fault; inasmuch as he was faithful, neither  was there any error or fault found in him.
6:4|KJV|Then the presidents and princes sought to find occasion against Daniel concerning the kingdom; but they could find none occasion nor fault; forasmuch as he was faithful, neither was there any error or fault found in him.
6:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時總長和總督，在國事上尋找但以理的把柄，為要告他，只是找不著他的把柄和過失；因他忠信可靠，在他身上找不到任何疏忽和過失。
6:5|Darby|Then said these men, We shall not find any pretext against  this Daniel, unless we find [it] against him touching the law  of his God.
6:5|KJV|Then said these men, We shall not find any occasion against this Daniel, except we find it against him concerning the law of his God.
6:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那些人便說，我們要找控告這但以理的把柄，除非在與他神的律法有關的事上去找，就尋不著。
6:6|Darby|Then these presidents and satraps came in a body to the  king, and said thus unto him: King Darius, live for ever!
6:6|KJV|Then these presidents and princes assembled together to the king, and said thus unto him, King Darius, live for ever.
6:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是總長和總督紛紛聚集來見王，說，願大利烏王萬歲！
6:7|Darby|All the presidents of the kingdom, the prefects, and the  satraps, the counsellors, and the governors have consulted  together to establish a royal statute, and to make a firm  decree, that whosoever shall ask a petition of any god or man  for thirty days, except of thee, O king, he shall be cast into  the den of lions.
6:7|KJV|All the presidents of the kingdom, the governors, and the princes, the counsellors, and the captains, have consulted together to establish a royal statute, and to make a firm decree, that whosoever shall ask a petition of any God or man for thirty days, save of thee, O king, he shall be cast into the den of lions.
6:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|國中的總長、司令、總督、謀士和省長，彼此商議，要王堅立一條律例，嚴定一道禁令，三十日內不拘何人，若在王以外向任何神明或任何人求甚麼，就必扔在獅子坑中。
6:8|Darby|Now, O king, establish the decree, and sign the writing,  that it be not changed, according to the law of the Medes and  Persians, which may not be revoked.
6:8|KJV|Now, O king, establish the decree, and sign the writing, that it be not changed, according to the law of the Medes and Persians, which altereth not.
6:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王阿，現在求你立這禁令，簽署這文書，使禁令絕不更改，照瑪代人和波斯人的法例，是不可廢除的。
6:9|Darby|Therefore king Darius signed the writing and the decree.
6:9|KJV|Wherefore king Darius signed the writing and the decree.
6:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是大利烏王簽署了這禁令的文書。
6:10|Darby|And when Daniel knew that the writing was signed, he went  into his house; and, his windows being open in his upper  chamber toward Jerusalem, he kneeled on his knees three times a  day, and prayed and gave thanks before his God, as he did  aforetime.
6:10|KJV|Now when Daniel knew that the writing was signed, he went into his house; and his windows being open in his chamber toward Jerusalem, he kneeled upon his knees three times a day, and prayed, and gave thanks before his God, as he did aforetime.
6:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但以理知道這文書已經簽署了，就到自己家堙A（他樓上的窗戶，開向耶路撒冷，）一日三次，雙膝跪下，在他神面前禱告感謝，因他素常就是這樣行。
6:11|Darby|But those men came in a body, and found Daniel praying and  making supplication before his God.
6:11|KJV|Then these men assembled, and found Daniel praying and making supplication before his God.
6:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那些人就紛紛聚集，見但以理在他神面前祈禱懇求。
6:12|Darby|Then they came near, and spoke before the king concerning  the king's decree: Hast thou not signed a decree, that every  man that shall ask [anything] of any god or man within thirty  days, except of thee, O king, shall be cast into the den of  lions? The king answered and said, The thing is true, according  to the law of the Medes and Persians, which may not be revoked.
6:12|KJV|Then they came near, and spake before the king concerning the king's decree; Hast thou not signed a decree, that every man that shall ask a petition of any God or man within thirty days, save of thee, O king, shall be cast into the den of lions? The king answered and said, The thing is true, according to the law of the Medes and Persians, which altereth not.
6:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們便進到王前，題王的禁令，說，王阿，三十日內不拘何人，若在王以外向任何神明或任何人求甚麼，必扔在獅子坑中，王不是簽署了這條禁令麼？王回答說，實有這事，照瑪代人和波斯人的法例，是不可廢除的。
6:13|Darby|Then they answered and said before the king, That Daniel,  who is of the children of the captivity of Judah, regardeth not  thee, O king, nor the decree that thou hast signed, but maketh  his petition three times a day.
6:13|KJV|Then answered they and said before the king, That Daniel, which is of the children of the captivity of Judah, regardeth not thee, O king, nor the decree that thou hast signed, but maketh his petition three times a day.
6:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們便對王說，王阿，那被擄之猶大人中的但以理不尊重你，也不尊重你所簽署的禁令，竟一日三次祈禱。
6:14|Darby|Then the king, when he heard these words, was sore  distressed thereby, and set his heart on Daniel to save him;  and he laboured till the going down of the sun to deliver him.
6:14|KJV|Then the king, when he heard these words, was sore displeased with himself, and set his heart on Daniel to deliver him: and he laboured till the going down of the sun to deliver him.
6:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王聽見這話，就甚愁煩，一心要救但以理，竭力要解救他，直到日落的時候。
6:15|Darby|Then these men came in a body unto the king, and said unto  the king, Know, O king, that the law of the Medes and Persians  is, That no decree nor statute which the king establisheth may  be changed.
6:15|KJV|Then these men assembled unto the king, and said unto the king, Know, O king, that the law of the Medes and Persians is, That no decree nor statute which the king establisheth may be changed.
6:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那些人紛紛聚集來見王，說，王阿，當知道瑪代人和波斯人有法例，凡王所立的禁令和律例，都不可更改。
6:16|Darby|Then the king commanded, and they brought Daniel, and cast  [him] into the den of lions. The king spoke and said unto  Daniel, Thy God whom thou servest continually, he will save  thee.
6:16|KJV|Then the king commanded, and they brought Daniel, and cast him into the den of lions. Now the king spake and said unto Daniel, Thy God whom thou servest continually, he will deliver thee.
6:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是王下令，人就把但以理帶來，扔在獅子坑中。王對但以理說，你所常事奉的神，祂必救你。
6:17|Darby|And a stone was brought, and laid upon the mouth of the  den; and the king sealed it with his own signet, and with the  signet of his nobles, that the purpose might not be changed  concerning Daniel.
6:17|KJV|And a stone was brought, and laid upon the mouth of the den; and the king sealed it with his own signet, and with the signet of his lords; that the purpose might not be changed concerning Daniel.
6:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有人搬一塊石頭放在坑口，王用自己戒指的印，和各大臣戒指的印，封閉那坑，使關於但以理的事，毫無更改。
6:18|Darby|Then the king went to his palace, and passed the night  fasting; neither were concubines brought before him; and his  sleep fled from him.
6:18|KJV|Then the king went to his palace, and passed the night fasting: neither were instruments of musick brought before him: and his sleep went from him.
6:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王回宮，終夜不食，無人拿樂器到他面前；並且睡不著覺。
6:19|Darby|Then the king arose with the light at break of day, and  went in haste unto the den of lions.
6:19|KJV|Then the king arose very early in the morning, and went in haste unto the den of lions.
6:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|次日黎明，天一亮王就起來，急忙往獅子坑那堨h。
6:20|Darby|And when he came near unto the den, he cried with a  mournful voice unto Daniel: the king spoke and said unto  Daniel, O Daniel, servant of the living God, hath thy God whom  thou servest continually been able to save thee from the lions?
6:20|KJV|And when he came to the den, he cried with a lamentable voice unto Daniel: and the king spake and said to Daniel, O Daniel, servant of the living God, is thy God, whom thou servest continually, able to deliver thee from the lions?
6:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他臨近坑邊，哀聲呼叫但以理，對但以理說，活神的僕人但以理阿，你所常事奉的神能救你脫離獅子麼？
6:21|Darby|Then Daniel spoke unto the king, O king, live for ever!
6:21|KJV|Then said Daniel unto the king, O king, live for ever.
6:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但以理對王說，願王萬歲！
6:22|Darby|My God hath sent his angel, and hath shut the lions'  mouths, that they have not hurt me; forasmuch as before him  innocence was found in me; and also before thee, O king, have I  done no hurt.
6:22|KJV|My God hath sent his angel, and hath shut the lions' mouths, that they have not hurt me: forasmuch as before him innocency was found in me; and also before thee, O king, have I done no hurt.
6:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的神差遣使者，封住獅子的口，叫獅子不傷我，因我在神面前顯為無辜，我在王面前也沒有行過害人的事。
6:23|Darby|Thereupon was the king exceeding glad, and commanded that  they should take Daniel up out of the den. So Daniel was taken  up out of the den, and no manner of hurt was found upon him,  because he believed in his God.
6:23|KJV|Then was the king exceedingly glad for him, and commanded that they should take Daniel up out of the den. So Daniel was taken up out of the den, and no manner of hurt was found upon him, because he believed in his God.
6:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王就甚為喜樂，吩咐人將但以理從坑媄握W來；於是但以理從坑堻Q繫上來；身上不見任何傷損，因為他信靠他的神。
6:24|Darby|And the king commanded, and they brought those men who had  accused Daniel, and cast them into the den of lions, them,  their children, and their wives; and the lions had the mastery  of them, and broke all their bones in pieces ere they came to  the bottom of the den.
6:24|KJV|And the king commanded, and they brought those men which had accused Daniel, and they cast them into the den of lions, them, their children, and their wives; and the lions had the mastery of them, and brake all their bones in pieces or ever they came at the bottom of the den.
6:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王下令，人就把那些控告但以理的人，連他們的兒女和妻子都帶來，扔在獅子坑中；他們還沒有到坑底，獅子就抓住他們，咬碎他們的骨頭。
6:25|Darby|Then king Darius wrote unto all peoples, nations, and  languages, that dwell in all the earth: Peace be multiplied  unto you.
6:25|KJV|Then king Darius wrote unto all people, nations, and languages, that dwell in all the earth; Peace be multiplied unto you.
6:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時大利烏王致書給住在全地，各族、各國、各方言的人，說，願你們大享平安！
6:26|Darby|I make a decree, That in every dominion of my kingdom men  tremble and fear before the God of Daniel; for he is the living  God, and steadfast for ever, and his kingdom [that] which shall  not be destroyed, and his dominion shall be even unto the end.
6:26|KJV|I make a decree, That in every dominion of my kingdom men tremble and fear before the God of Daniel: for he is the living God, and stedfast for ever, and his kingdom that which shall not be destroyed, and his dominion shall be even unto the end.
6:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現在我下令，在我所統轄的國內，人都要在但以理的神面前戰兢恐懼；因為祂是活神，永遠長存；祂的國永不敗壞，祂的權柄永存無終。
6:27|Darby|He saveth and delivereth, and he worketh signs and wonders  in the heavens and on the earth: who hath saved Daniel from the  power of the lions.
6:27|KJV|He delivereth and rescueth, and he worketh signs and wonders in heaven and in earth, who hath delivered Daniel from the power of the lions.
6:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂解救人，搭救人，在天上地上施行神蹟奇事，救了但以理脫離獅子的爪。
6:28<version name="Darby">And this Daniel prospered in the reign of Darius, and in  the reign of Cyrus the Persian. </p><p /><br /></version>
6:28<version name="KJV">So this Daniel prospered in the reign of Darius, and in the reign of Cyrus the Persian.</p><p /><br /></version>
6:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這但以理，當大利烏王在位的時候，和波斯王古列在位的時候，都得享亨通。
7:1|Darby|In the first year of Belshazzar king of Babylon, Daniel saw  a dream and visions of his head upon his bed: then he wrote the  dream; he told the sum of the matters.
7:1|KJV|In the first year of Belshazzar king of Babylon Daniel had a dream and visions of his head upon his bed: then he wrote the dream, and told the sum of the matters.
7:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|巴比倫王伯沙撒元年，但以理在床上作夢，見了腦中的異象。他就記錄這夢，述說事情的大意。
7:2|Darby|Daniel spoke and said, I saw in my vision by night, and  behold, the four winds of the heavens broke forth upon the  great sea.
7:2|KJV|Daniel spake and said, I saw in my vision by night, and, behold, the four winds of the heaven strove upon the great sea.
7:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但以理說，我夜間在異象中觀看，見天的四風陡起，颳在大海之上。
7:3|Darby|And four great beasts came up from the sea, different one  from another.
7:3|KJV|And four great beasts came up from the sea, diverse one from another.
7:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有四個大獸從海中上來，彼此各不相同。
7:4|Darby|The first was like a lion, and had eagle's wings: I beheld  till its wings were plucked; and it was lifted up from the  earth, and made to stand upon two feet as a man, and a man's  heart was given to it.
7:4|KJV|The first was like a lion, and had eagle's wings: I beheld till the wings thereof were plucked, and it was lifted up from the earth, and made stand upon the feet as a man, and a man's heart was given to it.
7:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|頭一個像獅子，有鷹的翅膀。我正觀看的時候，獸的翅膀被拔去，獸從地上被拉起來，用兩腳站立，像人一樣，又有人心給了牠。
7:5|Darby|And behold, another beast, a second, like unto a bear, and  it raised up itself on one side; and [it had] three ribs in its  mouth between its teeth; and they said thus unto it: Arise,  devour much flesh.
7:5|KJV|And behold another beast, a second, like to a bear, and it raised up itself on one side, and it had three ribs in the mouth of it between the teeth of it: and they said thus unto it, Arise, devour much flesh.
7:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又有一獸如熊，就是第二獸，挺起身體一邊，口齒間啣著三根肋骨；有人對牠說，起來吞喫多肉。
7:6|Darby|After this I saw, and behold, another, like a leopard, and  it had four wings of a bird upon its back; and the beast had  four heads; and dominion was given to it.
7:6|KJV|After this I beheld, and lo another, like a leopard, which had upon the back of it four wings of a fowl; the beast had also four heads; and dominion was given to it.
7:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|此後我觀看，又有一獸如豹，背上有鳥的四個翅膀；這獸有四個頭，又有權柄給了牠。
7:7|Darby|After this I saw in the night visions, and behold, a fourth  beast, dreadful and terrible, and exceeding strong; and it had  great iron teeth: it devoured and broke in pieces, and stamped  the rest with its feet; and it was different from all the  beasts that were before it; and it had ten horns.
7:7|KJV|After this I saw in the night visions, and behold a fourth beast, dreadful and terrible, and strong exceedingly; and it had great iron teeth: it devoured and brake in pieces, and stamped the residue with the feet of it: and it was diverse from all the beasts that were before it; and it had ten horns.
7:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其後我在夜間的異象中觀看，見第四獸甚是可怕可懼，極其強壯；這獸有大鐵牙，吞喫嚼碎，所剩下的用腳踐踏；這獸與前三獸不同，頭有十角；
7:8|Darby|I considered the horns, and behold, there came up among them  another, a little horn, before which three of the first horns  were plucked up by the roots; and behold, in this horn were  eyes like the eyes of a man, and a mouth speaking great things.
7:8|KJV|I considered the horns, and, behold, there came up among them another little horn, before whom there were three of the first horns plucked up by the roots: and, behold, in this horn were eyes like the eyes of man, and a mouth speaking great things.
7:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我正注意這些角，見其中又長起一個小角；先前的角中，有三角在這角前連根被拔出來。這角有眼像人的眼，有口說誇大的話。
7:9|Darby|I beheld till thrones were set, and the Ancient of days did  sit: his raiment was white as snow, and the hair of his head  like pure wool; his throne was flames of fire, [and] its wheels  burning fire.
7:9|KJV|I beheld till the thrones were cast down, and the Ancient of days did sit, whose garment was white as snow, and the hair of his head like the pure wool: his throne was like the fiery flame, and his wheels as burning fire.
7:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我觀看，見有些寶座設立，那亙古常在者坐下了。祂的衣服潔白如雪，頭髮如純淨的羊毛；祂的寶座乃是火焰，其輪乃是烈火。
7:10|Darby|A stream of fire issued and came forth from before him;  thousand thousands ministered unto him, and ten thousand times  ten thousand stood before him: the judgment was set, and the  books were opened.
7:10|KJV|A fiery stream issued and came forth from before him: thousand thousands ministered unto him, and ten thousand times ten thousand stood before him: the judgment was set, and the books were opened.
7:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|從祂面前有火河流出。事奉祂的有千千，侍立在祂面前的有萬萬。審判者已經坐庭，案卷都展開了。
7:11|Darby|I beheld therefore, because of the voice of the great words  that the horn spoke; I beheld till the beast was slain, and its  body destroyed, and it was given up to be burned with fire.
7:11|KJV|I beheld then because of the voice of the great words which the horn spake: I beheld even till the beast was slain, and his body destroyed, and given to the burning flame.
7:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時因那小角說誇大話的聲音，我就觀看，見那獸被殺，身體毀壞，扔在火中焚燒。
7:12|Darby|As for the rest of the beasts, their dominion was taken  away; but their lives were prolonged for a season and a time.
7:12|KJV|As concerning the rest of the beasts, they had their dominion taken away: yet their lives were prolonged for a season and time.
7:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於其餘的獸，權柄都被奪去，生命卻仍存留，直到所定的時期和時候。
7:13|Darby|I saw in the night visions, and behold, there came with the  clouds of heaven [one] like a son of man, and he came up even  to the Ancient of days, and they brought him near before him.
7:13|KJV|I saw in the night visions, and, behold, one like the Son of man came with the clouds of heaven, and came to the Ancient of days, and they brought him near before him.
7:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在夜間的異象中觀看，見有一位像人子的，駕著天雲而來；祂來到亙古常在者那堙A被領近祂面前。
7:14|Darby|And there was given him dominion, and glory, and a kingdom,  that all peoples, nations, and languages should serve him: his  dominion is an everlasting dominion, which shall not pass away,  and his kingdom [that] which shall not be destroyed.
7:14|KJV|And there was given him dominion, and glory, and a kingdom, that all people, nations, and languages, should serve him: his dominion is an everlasting dominion, which shall not pass away, and his kingdom that which shall not be destroyed.
7:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|權柄、榮耀、國度都給了祂，使各族、各國、各方言的人都事奉祂。祂的權柄是永遠的權柄，不能廢去，祂的國必不毀壞。
7:15|Darby|As for me Daniel, my spirit was grieved in the midst of my  body, and the visions of my head troubled me.
7:15|KJV|I Daniel was grieved in my spirit in the midst of my body, and the visions of my head troubled me.
7:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於我但以理，我的靈在我堶捧T煩，我腦中的異象使我驚惶。
7:16|Darby|I came near unto one of them that stood by, and asked him  the certainty of all this. And he told me, and made me know the  interpretation of the things:
7:16|KJV|I came near unto one of them that stood by, and asked him the truth of all this. So he told me, and made me know the interpretation of the things.
7:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我就近一位侍立者，問他這一切的準確意義；他就告訴我，將這些事的講解給我說明：
7:17|Darby|These great beasts, which are four, are four kings, [that]  shall arise out of the earth.
7:17|KJV|These great beasts, which are four, are four kings, which shall arise out of the earth.
7:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這四個大獸就是將要在地上興起的四王。
7:18|Darby|But the saints of the most high [places] shall receive the  kingdom, and they shall possess the kingdom for ever, even to  the ages of ages.
7:18|KJV|But the saints of the most High shall take the kingdom, and possess the kingdom for ever, even for ever and ever.
7:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而至高者的聖民，必領受國度，擁有國度，直到永永遠遠。
7:19|Darby|Then I desired to know the certainty concerning the fourth  beast, which was different from them all, exceeding dreadful,  whose teeth were of iron, and its nails of brass; which  devoured, broke in pieces, and stamped the rest with its feet;
7:19|KJV|Then I would know the truth of the fourth beast, which was diverse from all the others, exceeding dreadful, whose teeth were of iron, and his nails of brass; which devoured, brake in pieces, and stamped the residue with his feet;
7:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時我願知道第四獸的準確意義，牠為何與那三獸不同，甚是可怕，有鐵牙銅爪，吞喫嚼碎，所餘剩的用腳踐踏，
7:20|Darby|and concerning the ten horns that were in its head, and the  other that came up, and before which three fell: even that horn  that had eyes, and a mouth speaking great things, and whose  look was more imposing than its fellows.
7:20|KJV|And of the ten horns that were in his head, and of the other which came up, and before whom three fell; even of that horn that had eyes, and a mouth that spake very great things, whose look was more stout than his fellows.
7:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|牠頭上有十角和那另長的一角，在這角前有三角傾倒；這角有眼，有說誇大話的口，形狀強大，過於牠的同伴。
7:21|Darby|I beheld, and that horn made war with the saints, and  prevailed over them;
7:21|KJV|I beheld, and the same horn made war with the saints, and prevailed against them;
7:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我觀看，見這角與聖民爭戰，勝了他們，
7:22|Darby|until the Ancient of days came, and judgment was given to  the saints of the most high [places]; and the appointed time  arrived, and the saints possessed the kingdom.
7:22|KJV|Until the Ancient of days came, and judgment was given to the saints of the most High; and the time came that the saints possessed the kingdom.
7:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|直到亙古常在者來臨，為至高者的聖民伸冤，聖民得著國度的時候就到了。
7:23|Darby|He said thus: The fourth beast shall be a fourth kingdom  upon the earth, which shall be different from all the kingdoms,  and shall devour the whole earth, and shall tread it down, and  break it in pieces.
7:23|KJV|Thus he said, The fourth beast shall be the fourth kingdom upon earth, which shall be diverse from all kingdoms, and shall devour the whole earth, and shall tread it down, and break it in pieces.
7:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那侍立者這樣說，第四獸就是地上必有的第四國，與一切國不同，必吞喫全地，並且踐踏嚼碎。
7:24|Darby|And as to the ten horns, out of this kingdom shall arise  ten kings; and another shall arise after them; and he shall be  different from the former, and he shall subdue three kings.
7:24|KJV|And the ten horns out of this kingdom are ten kings that shall arise: and another shall rise after them; and he shall be diverse from the first, and he shall subdue three kings.
7:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於那十角，就是從這國中必興起的十王，後來又興起一王，與先前的不同，他必制伏三王。
7:25|Darby|And he shall speak words against the Most High, and shall  wear out the saints of the most high [places], and think to  change seasons and the law; and they shall be given into his  hand until a time and times and a half time.
7:25|KJV|And he shall speak great words against the most High, and shall wear out the saints of the most High, and think to change times and laws: and they shall be given into his hand until a time and times and the dividing of time.
7:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他必向至高者說頂撞的話，並折磨至高者的聖民；他想要改變節期和律法；聖民必交付在他手中一年、二年、半年。
7:26|Darby|And the judgment shall sit, and they shall take away his  dominion, to consume and to destroy it unto the end.
7:26|KJV|But the judgment shall sit, and they shall take away his dominion, to consume and to destroy it unto the end.
7:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而審判者必坐庭，他的權柄必被奪去，以致毀壞、滅絕，一直到底。
7:27|Darby|But the kingdom and the dominion, and the greatness of the  kingdoms under the whole heavens, shall be given to the people  of the saints of the most high [places]. His kingdom is an  everlasting kingdom, and all dominions shall serve and obey  him.
7:27|KJV|And the kingdom and dominion, and the greatness of the kingdom under the whole heaven, shall be given to the people of the saints of the most High, whose kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and all dominions shall serve and obey him.
7:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|國度、權柄、和天下諸國的尊大，必賜給至高者的聖民；祂的國是永遠的國，一切掌權的都必事奉祂，順從祂。
7:28<version name="Darby">So far is the end of the matter. As for me Daniel, my  thoughts much troubled me, and my countenance was changed in  me; but I kept the matter in my heart. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:28<version name="KJV">Hitherto is the end of the matter. As for me Daniel, my cogitations much troubled me, and my countenance changed in me: but I kept the matter in my heart.</p><p /><br /></version>
7:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那事至此完畢。至於我但以理，我的心意甚為驚惶，臉色也改變了，卻將那事存記在心。
8:1|Darby|In the third year of the reign of Belshazzar the king, a  vision appeared unto me, [even] to me Daniel, after that which  appeared unto me at the first.
8:1|KJV|In the third year of the reign of king Belshazzar a vision appeared unto me, even unto me Daniel, after that which appeared unto me at the first.
8:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|伯沙撒王在位第三年，有異象顯與我但以理，是在起初所顯與我的異象之後。
8:2|Darby|And I saw in the vision; and it came to pass, when I saw,  that I was in the fortress of Shushan, which is in the province  of Elam. And I saw in the vision, and I was by the river Ulai.
8:2|KJV|And I saw in a vision; and it came to pass, when I saw, that I was at Shushan in the palace, which is in the province of Elam; and I saw in a vision, and I was by the river of Ulai.
8:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在異象中觀看，正觀看時，我在以攔省書珊城中；在異象中正觀看時，我在烏萊河邊。
8:3|Darby|And I lifted up mine eyes and saw, and behold, there stood  before the river a ram which had two horns; and the two horns  were high; and one was higher than the other, and the higher  came up last.
8:3|KJV|Then I lifted up mine eyes, and saw, and, behold, there stood before the river a ram which had two horns: and the two horns were high; but one was higher than the other, and the higher came up last.
8:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我舉目觀看，見有一隻雙角的公綿羊面向河站著，兩角都高，這角高過那角，更高的是後長的。
8:4|Darby|I saw the ram pushing westward, and northward, and  southward, and no beast could stand before him, neither was  there any that could deliver out of his hand; and he did  according to his will, and became great.
8:4|KJV|I saw the ram pushing westward, and northward, and southward; so that no beasts might stand before him, neither was there any that could deliver out of his hand; but he did according to his will, and became great.
8:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我見那公綿羊往西、往北、往南牴觸；獸在他面前都站立不住，也沒有能救護脫離他手的，但他任意而行，漸漸強大。
8:5|Darby|And as I was considering, behold, a he-goat came from the  west over the face of the whole earth, and touched not the  ground: and the goat had a notable horn between his eyes.
8:5|KJV|And as I was considering, behold, an he goat came from the west on the face of the whole earth, and touched not the ground: and the goat had a notable horn between his eyes.
8:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我正思想的時候，見有一隻公山羊從西而來，遍行全地，腳不觸地；這山羊兩眼之間，有一顯著的角。
8:6|Darby|And he came to the ram that had the two horns, which I had  seen standing before the river, and ran upon him in the fury of  his power.
8:6|KJV|And he came to the ram that had two horns, which I had seen standing before the river, and ran unto him in the fury of his power.
8:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他往我所看見面向河站著，有雙角的公綿羊那堨h，大發忿怒，向他直闖。
8:7|Darby|And I saw him come close to the ram, and he was enraged with  him, and smote the ram, and broke his two horns; and there was  no power in the ram to stand before him; and he cast him down  to the ground, and trampled upon him; and there was none that  could deliver the ram out of his hand.
8:7|KJV|And I saw him come close unto the ram, and he was moved with choler against him, and smote the ram, and brake his two horns: and there was no power in the ram to stand before him, but he cast him down to the ground, and stamped upon him: and there was none that could deliver the ram out of his hand.
8:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我見公山羊就近公綿羊，向他發烈怒，衝撞他，折斷他的兩角；綿羊無力抵擋他，被他撞倒在地，用腳踐踏；沒有能救綿羊脫離他手的。
8:8|Darby|And the he-goat became exceeding great; but when he was  become strong, the great horn was broken; and in its stead came  up four notable ones toward the four winds of the heavens.
8:8|KJV|Therefore the he goat waxed very great: and when he was strong, the great horn was broken; and for it came up four notable ones toward the four winds of heaven.
8:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這山羊成為極其強大，正強盛的時候，那大角折斷了，在角根上向天的四方，長出四個顯著的角來。
8:9|Darby|And out of one of them came forth a little horn, which  became exceeding great, toward the south, and toward the east,  and toward the beauty [of the earth].
8:9|KJV|And out of one of them came forth a little horn, which waxed exceeding great, toward the south, and toward the east, and toward the pleasant land.
8:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|四角之中，有一角長出一個小角，向南、向東、向榮美之地，漸漸極其強大。
8:10|Darby|And it became great, even to the host of heaven; and it  cast down [some] of the host and of the stars to the ground,  and trampled upon them.
8:10|KJV|And it waxed great, even to the host of heaven; and it cast down some of the host and of the stars to the ground, and stamped upon them.
8:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他漸漸強大，高及天象，將些天象和星宿拋落在地，用腳踐踏。
8:11|Darby|(And he magnified [himself] even to the prince of the host,  and from him the continual [sacrifice] was taken away, and the  place of his sanctuary was cast down.
8:11|KJV|Yea, he magnified himself even to the prince of the host, and by him the daily sacrifice was taken away, and the place of the sanctuary was cast down.
8:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且他漸漸強大，以為高及天象之君；祂日常的祭祀從祂除掉，祂的聖所被毀壞。
8:12|Darby|And a time of trial was appointed unto the continual  [sacrifice] by reason of transgression.) And it cast down the  truth to the ground; and it practised and prospered.
8:12|KJV|And an host was given him against the daily sacrifice by reason of transgression, and it cast down the truth to the ground; and it practised, and prospered.
8:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因過犯的緣故，有軍兵和日常的祭祀交付與他；他將真理拋在地上，行事無不順利。
8:13|Darby|And I heard one saint speaking, and another saint said unto  that one who spoke, How long shall be the vision of the  continual [sacrifice] and of the transgression that maketh  desolate, to give both the sanctuary and the host to be trodden  down under foot?
8:13|KJV|Then I heard one saint speaking, and another saint said unto that certain saint which spake, How long shall be the vision concerning the daily sacrifice, and the transgression of desolation, to give both the sanctuary and the host to be trodden under foot?
8:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我聽見有一位聖者說話，又有一位聖者問那說話的聖者，說，這除掉日常祭祀，和造成荒涼的過犯，以致聖所與軍兵遭踐踏的異象，要持續多久呢？
8:14|Darby|And he said unto me, Until two thousand and three hundred  evenings [and] mornings: then shall the sanctuary be  vindicated.
8:14|KJV|And he said unto me, Unto two thousand and three hundred days; then shall the sanctuary be cleansed.
8:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他對我說，到二千三百個日夜，聖所就必得潔淨。
8:15|Darby|And it came to pass, when I Daniel had seen the vision, I  sought for the understanding of it, and behold, there stood  before me as the appearance of a man.
8:15|KJV|And it came to pass, when I, even I Daniel, had seen the vision, and sought for the meaning, then, behold, there stood before me as the appearance of a man.
8:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我但以理見了這異象，尋求明白其中的意思，忽有一位樣子像人的，站在我面前。
8:16|Darby|And I heard a man's voice between [the banks of] the Ulai;  and he called and said, Gabriel, make this [man] to understand  the vision.
8:16|KJV|And I heard a man's voice between the banks of Ulai, which called, and said, Gabriel, make this man to understand the vision.
8:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我又聽見烏萊河兩岸間有人聲呼叫說，加百列阿，要使此人明白這異象。
8:17|Darby|And he came near where I stood; and when he came, I was  afraid, and fell on my face; and he said unto me, Understand,  son of man; for the vision is for the time of the end.
8:17|KJV|So he came near where I stood: and when he came, I was afraid, and fell upon my face: but he said unto me, Understand, O son of man: for at the time of the end shall be the vision.
8:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他便來到我所站的地方；他一來，我就驚慌，面伏於地；他對我說，人子阿，你要明白，這異象是關於末期的。
8:18|Darby|Now, as he was speaking with me, I was in a deep stupor,  with my face toward the ground. And he touched me, and set me  up where I had stood.
8:18|KJV|Now as he was speaking with me, I was in a deep sleep on my face toward the ground: but he touched me, and set me upright.
8:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他與我說話的時候，我面伏在地沉睡了；但他摸我，扶我站在原地。
8:19|Darby|And he said, Behold, I will make thee know what shall be at  the end of the indignation: for at the set time the end shall  be.
8:19|KJV|And he said, Behold, I will make thee know what shall be in the last end of the indignation: for at the time appointed the end shall be.
8:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他說，我要使你知道惱怒末期必發生的事，因為這是關於末後的定期。
8:20|Darby|The ram that thou sawest having the two horns: they are the  kings of Media and Persia.
8:20|KJV|The ram which thou sawest having two horns are the kings of Media and Persia.
8:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你所看見雙角的公綿羊，就是瑪代和波斯王。
8:21|Darby|And the rough goat is the king of Greece; and the great  horn that was between his eyes is the first king.
8:21|KJV|And the rough goat is the king of Grecia: and the great horn that is between his eyes is the first king.
8:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那多毛的公山羊，就是雅完王；牠兩眼之間的大角，就是頭一王。
8:22|Darby|Now that being broken, whereas four stood up in its stead,  four kingdoms shall stand up out of the nation, but not with  his power.
8:22|KJV|Now that being broken, whereas four stood up for it, four kingdoms shall stand up out of the nation, but not in his power.
8:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於那折斷了的角，及其根上長出的四角，乃是從這國媬陸_來的四國，只是力量都不及他。
8:23|Darby|And at the latter time of their kingdom, when the  transgressors shall have come to the full, a king of bold  countenance, and understanding riddles, shall stand up.
8:23|KJV|And in the latter time of their kingdom, when the transgressors are come to the full, a king of fierce countenance, and understanding dark sentences, shall stand up.
8:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在這四國末期，犯法的人罪惡滿盈，必有一王興起，面貌兇惡，善用雙關的詐語。
8:24|Darby|And his power shall be mighty, but not by his own power;  and he shall destroy marvellously, and shall prosper, and shall  practise, and shall destroy the mighty ones, and the people of  the saints.
8:24|KJV|And his power shall be mighty, but not by his own power: and he shall destroy wonderfully, and shall prosper, and practise, and shall destroy the mighty and the holy people.
8:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他的力量必強大，卻不是因自己的力量，他必行非常的毀滅，並且行事順利；又必毀滅有能力者和聖民。
8:25|Darby|And through his cunning shall he cause craft to prosper in  his hand; and he will magnify [himself] in his heart, and by  prosperity will corrupt many; and he will stand up against the  Prince of princes: but he shall be broken without hand.
8:25|KJV|And through his policy also he shall cause craft to prosper in his hand; and he shall magnify himself in his heart, and by peace shall destroy many: he shall also stand up against the Prince of princes; but he shall be broken without hand.
8:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他用權術使手中的詭計亨通；他心埵菾爬菑j，在人坦然安定的時候，毀滅多人；又要站起來攻擊萬君之君，至終卻非因人手而被滅。
8:26|Darby|And the vision of the evening and the morning which hath  been told is true; but close thou up the vision, for it is for  many days [to come].
8:26|KJV|And the vision of the evening and the morning which was told is true: wherefore shut thou up the vision; for it shall be for many days.
8:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所說二千三百日夜的異象是真的，但你要將這異象封住，因為那是關於許多日子以後的事。
8:27<version name="Darby">And I Daniel fainted, and was sick [certain] days: then I  rose up, and did the king's business. And I was astonished at  the vision, but none understood [it]. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:27<version name="KJV">And I Daniel fainted, and was sick certain days; afterward I rose up, and did the king's business; and I was astonished at the vision, but none understood it.</p><p /><br /></version>
8:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是我但以理疲憊力竭，病了數日，然後起來辦理王的事務；我因這異象驚奇，卻無人能解釋其中的意思。
9:1|Darby|In the first year of Darius the son of Ahasuerus, of the  seed of the Medes, who was made king over the realm of the  Chaldeans,
9:1|KJV|In the first year of Darius the son of Ahasuerus, of the seed of the Medes, which was made king over the realm of the Chaldeans;
9:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|瑪代族，亞哈隨魯的兒子大利烏，立為迦勒底國的王元年，
9:2|Darby|in the first year of his reign, I Daniel understood by the  books that the number of the years, whereof the word of Jehovah  came to Jeremiah the prophet, for the accomplishment of the  desolations of Jerusalem, was seventy years.
9:2|KJV|In the first year of his reign I Daniel understood by books the number of the years, whereof the word of the LORD came to Jeremiah the prophet, that he would accomplish seventy years in the desolations of Jerusalem.
9:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就是他在位第一年，
9:3|Darby|And I set my face unto the Lord God, to seek by prayer and  supplications, with fasting, and sackcloth, and ashes;
9:3|KJV|And I set my face unto the Lord God, to seek by prayer and supplications, with fasting, and sackcloth, and ashes:
9:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我便禁食，披麻蒙灰，面向主神尋求，禱告、懇求。
9:4|Darby|and I prayed unto Jehovah my God, and made my confession,  and said, Alas Lord! the great and terrible ???’???’?????????God, keeping  covenant and loving-kindness with them that love him, and that  keep his commandments:
9:4|KJV|And I prayed unto the LORD my God, and made my confession, and said, O Lord, the great and dreadful God, keeping the covenant and mercy to them that love him, and to them that keep his commandments;
9:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我向耶和華我的神禱告、認罪，說，哎，主阿，大而可畏的神，向愛祂守祂誡命的人，守約並施慈愛。
9:5|Darby|we have sinned, and have committed iniquity, and have done  wickedly, and have rebelled, even turning aside from thy  commandments and from thine ordinances.
9:5|KJV|We have sinned, and have committed iniquity, and have done wickedly, and have rebelled, even by departing from thy precepts and from thy judgments:
9:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們犯罪作孽，行惡悖逆，偏離你的誡命典章。
9:6|Darby|And we have not hearkened unto thy servants the prophets,  who spoke in thy name to our kings, our princes, and our  fathers, and to all the people of the land.
9:6|KJV|Neither have we hearkened unto thy servants the prophets, which spake in thy name to our kings, our princes, and our fathers, and to all the people of the land.
9:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|沒有聽從你僕人眾申言者，在你名埵V我們君王、首領、列祖、和那地一切百姓所說的話。
9:7|Darby|Thine, O Lord, is the righteousness, but unto us confusion  of face, as at this day, to the men of Judah, and to the  inhabitants of Jerusalem, and unto all Israel, that are near,  and that are far off, in all the countries whither thou hast  driven them, because of their unfaithfulness in which they have  been unfaithful against thee.
9:7|KJV|O LORD, righteousness belongeth unto thee, but unto us confusion of faces, as at this day; to the men of Judah, and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and unto all Israel, that are near, and that are far off, through all the countries whither thou hast driven them, because of their trespass that they have trespassed against thee.
9:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主阿，公義歸於你，滿面羞愧歸於我們，正如今日一樣，就是歸於猶大人和耶路撒冷的居民、並以色列眾人，或在近處，或在遠處，被你趕到各地的人，因為他們犯了對你不忠信的罪。
9:8|Darby|O Lord, unto us is confusion of face, to our kings, to our  princes, and to our fathers, because we have sinned against  thee.
9:8|KJV|O Lord, to us belongeth confusion of face, to our kings, to our princes, and to our fathers, because we have sinned against thee.
9:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華阿，滿面羞愧歸於我們，就是歸於我們的君王、首領、列祖，因為我們得罪了你。
9:9|Darby|With the Lord our God are mercies and pardons, for we have  rebelled against him;
9:9|KJV|To the Lord our God belong mercies and forgivenesses, though we have rebelled against him;
9:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|憐恤和饒恕歸於主我們的神，因為我們悖逆了祂；
9:10|Darby|and we have not hearkened unto the voice of Jehovah our  God, to walk in his laws, which he set before us through his  servants the prophets.
9:10|KJV|Neither have we obeyed the voice of the LORD our God, to walk in his laws, which he set before us by his servants the prophets.
9:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們沒有聽從耶和華我們神的話，沒有遵行祂藉僕人眾申言者擺在我們面前的訓誨。
9:11|Darby|And all Israel have transgressed thy law, even turning  aside so as not to listen unto thy voice. And the curse hath  been poured out upon us, and the oath that is written in the  law of Moses the servant of God: for we have sinned against  him.
9:11|KJV|Yea, all Israel have transgressed thy law, even by departing, that they might not obey thy voice; therefore the curse is poured upon us, and the oath that is written in the law of Moses the servant of God, because we have sinned against him.
9:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列眾人都犯了你的律法，甚至偏離，不聽從你的話；因此，在你僕人摩西律法上所寫的咒詛和誓言，都傾倒在我們身上，因為我們得罪了神。
9:12|Darby|And he hath performed his words, which he spoke against us,  and against our judges that judged us, by bringing upon us a  great evil; so that there hath not been done under the whole  heaven as hath been done upon Jerusalem.
9:12|KJV|And he hath confirmed his words, which he spake against us, and against our judges that judged us, by bringing upon us a great evil: for under the whole heaven hath not been done as hath been done upon Jerusalem.
9:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂使大災禍臨到我們，證實了祂警戒我們的話，和祂警戒那些審判我們之審判官的話；原來在普天之下，未曾行過像在耶路撒冷所行的。
9:13|Darby|As it is written in the law of Moses, all this evil is come  upon us; yet we besought not Jehovah our God, that we might  turn from our iniquities, and understand thy truth.
9:13|KJV|As it is written in the law of Moses, all this evil is come upon us: yet made we not our prayer before the LORD our God, that we might turn from our iniquities, and understand thy truth.
9:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這一切災禍臨到我們身上，是照摩西律法上所寫的；我們卻沒有求耶和華我們神的恩惠，使我們回頭離開罪孽，留心你的真理。
9:14|Darby|And Jehovah hath watched over the evil, and brought it upon  us; for Jehovah our God is righteous in all his works which he  hath done; and we have not hearkened unto his voice.
9:14|KJV|Therefore hath the LORD watched upon the evil, and brought it upon us: for the LORD our God is righteous in all his works which he doeth: for we obeyed not his voice.
9:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以耶和華留意使這災禍臨到我們身上，因為耶和華我們的神在祂所行的事上，都是公義的；我們並沒有聽從祂的話。
9:15|Darby|-- And now, O Lord our God, who broughtest thy people forth  out of the land of Egypt with a strong hand, and hast made thee  a name, as it is this day, -- we have sinned, we have done  wickedly.
9:15|KJV|And now, O Lord our God, that hast brought thy people forth out of the land of Egypt with a mighty hand, and hast gotten thee renown, as at this day; we have sinned, we have done wickedly.
9:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主我們的神阿，你曾用大能的手領你的子民出埃及地，使自己得了名，正如今日一樣；我們犯了罪，作了惡。
9:16|Darby|Lord, according to all thy righteousnesses, I beseech thee,  let thine anger and thy fury be turned away from thy city  Jerusalem, thy holy mountain; for because of our sins, and  because of the iniquities of our fathers, Jerusalem and thy  people [are become] a reproach to all round about us.
9:16|KJV|O LORD, according to all thy righteousness, I beseech thee, let thine anger and thy fury be turned away from thy city Jerusalem, thy holy mountain: because for our sins, and for the iniquities of our fathers, Jerusalem and thy people are become a reproach to all that are about us.
9:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主阿，求你按著你所顯明的一切公義，使你的怒氣和忿怒轉離你的城耶路撒冷，就是你的聖山；耶路撒冷和你的子民，因我們的罪和我們列祖的罪孽，被四圍的人羞辱。
9:17|Darby|And now, our God, hearken to the prayer of thy servant, and  to his supplications, and cause thy face to shine upon thy  sanctuary that is desolate, for the Lord's sake.
9:17|KJV|Now therefore, O our God, hear the prayer of thy servant, and his supplications, and cause thy face to shine upon thy sanctuary that is desolate, for the Lord's sake.
9:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們的神阿，現在垂聽你僕人的禱告懇求，為主的緣故使你的臉光照你荒涼的聖所。
9:18|Darby|Incline thine ear, O my God, and hear; open thine eyes and  behold our desolations, and the city that is called by thy  name: for we do not present our supplications before thee  because of our righteousnesses, but because of thy manifold  mercies.
9:18|KJV|O my God, incline thine ear, and hear; open thine eyes, and behold our desolations, and the city which is called by thy name: for we do not present our supplications before thee for our righteousnesses, but for thy great mercies.
9:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的神阿，求你側耳聽；睜眼看我們的荒涼，和稱為你名下的城；我們在你面前懇求，原不是靠自己所行的義，乃是靠你的大憐恤。
9:19|Darby|Lord, hear! Lord, forgive! Lord, hearken and do! defer not,  for thine own sake, O my God! for thy city and thy people are  called by thy name.
9:19|KJV|O Lord, hear; O Lord, forgive; O Lord, hearken and do; defer not, for thine own sake, O my God: for thy city and thy people are called by thy name.
9:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主阿，求你垂聽！主阿，求你赦免！主阿，求你傾聽並行事！我的神阿，為你自己的緣故，求你不要遲延；因你的城和你的民，都是稱為你名下的。
9:20|Darby|And whilst I was speaking, and praying, and confessing my  sin and the sin of my people Israel, and presenting my  supplication before Jehovah my God for the holy mountain of my  God;
9:20|KJV|And whiles I was speaking, and praying, and confessing my sin and the sin of my people Israel, and presenting my supplication before the LORD my God for the holy mountain of my God;
9:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當我還在說話、禱告，承認我的罪，和我本民以色列的罪，為我神的聖山，在耶和華我神面前懇求；
9:21|Darby|whilst I was yet speaking in prayer, the man Gabriel, whom  I had seen in the vision at the beginning, flying swiftly,  touched me about the time of the evening oblation.
9:21|KJV|Yea, whiles I was speaking in prayer, even the man Gabriel, whom I had seen in the vision at the beginning, being caused to fly swiftly, touched me about the time of the evening oblation.
9:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|正當我禱告說話的時候，起初在異象中所見的那人加百列，在我精疲力竭時，約在獻晚祭的時候就近我。
9:22|Darby|And he informed [me], and talked with me, and said, Daniel,  I am now come forth to make thee skilful of understanding.
9:22|KJV|And he informed me, and talked with me, and said, O Daniel, I am now come forth to give thee skill and understanding.
9:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他指教我，對我說，但以理阿，現在我出來要使你有見識，有聰明。
9:23|Darby|At the beginning of thy supplications the word went forth,  and I am come to declare [it]; for thou art one greatly  beloved. Therefore consider the word, and have understanding in  the vision:
9:23|KJV|At the beginning of thy supplications the commandment came forth, and I am come to shew thee; for thou art greatly beloved: therefore understand the matter, and consider the vision.
9:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你初懇求的時候，就有命令發出，我來告訴你，因你是大蒙眷愛的；所以你要明白這事，思想這異象。
9:24|Darby|Seventy weeks are apportioned out upon thy people and upon  thy holy city, to close the transgression, and to make an end  of sins, and to make expiation for iniquity, and to bring in  the righteousness of the ages, and to seal the vision and  prophet, and to anoint the holy of holies.
9:24|KJV|Seventy weeks are determined upon thy people and upon thy holy city, to finish the transgression, and to make an end of sins, and to make reconciliation for iniquity, and to bring in everlasting righteousness, and to seal up the vision and prophecy, and to anoint the most Holy.
9:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|為你本國之民和你的聖城，已經截定了七十個七，要終止過犯，了結罪惡，為罪孽成就平息，帶進永遠的義，封住異象和豫言，並膏至聖所。
9:25|Darby|Know therefore and understand: From the going forth of the  word to restore and to build Jerusalem unto Messiah, the  Prince, are seven weeks, and sixty-two weeks. The street and  the moat shall be built again, even in troublous times.
9:25|KJV|Know therefore and understand, that from the going forth of the commandment to restore and to build Jerusalem unto the Messiah the Prince shall be seven weeks, and threescore and two weeks: the street shall be built again, and the wall, even in troublous times.
9:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以你當知道，當明白：從出令重新修建耶路撒冷，直到彌賽亞君的時候，必有七個七和六十二個七；即使在艱難的時候，耶路撒冷城也必連街帶濠，重新建造。
9:26|Darby|And after the sixty-two weeks shall Messiah be cut off, and  shall have nothing; and the people of the prince that shall  come shall destroy the city and the sanctuary; and the end  thereof shall be with an overflow, and unto the end, war, --  the desolations determined.
9:26|KJV|And after threescore and two weeks shall Messiah be cut off, but not for himself: and the people of the prince that shall come shall destroy the city and the sanctuary; and the end thereof shall be with a flood, and unto the end of the war desolations are determined.
9:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|過了六十二個七，彌賽亞必被剪除，一無所有；必有一王的民來毀滅這城和聖所；結局必有洪水，並一直到底的爭戰；荒涼的事已經定了。
9:27<version name="Darby">And he shall confirm a covenant with the many [for] one  week; and in the midst of the week he shall cause the sacrifice  and the oblation to cease, and because of the protection of  abominations [there shall be] a desolator, even until that the  consumption and what is determined shall be poured out upon the  desolate. </p><p /><br /></version>
9:27<version name="KJV">And he shall confirm the covenant with many for one week: and in the midst of the week he shall cause the sacrifice and the oblation to cease, and for the overspreading of abominations he shall make it desolate, even until the consummation, and that determined shall be poured upon the desolate.</p><p /><br /></version>
9:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他必與許多人堅定一個七的盟約；到一七之半，他必使祭祀和供獻止息，並且以那造成荒涼者的可憎之物代替祭祀和供獻，直到所定之完全的毀壞傾倒在那造成荒涼者的身上。
10:1|Darby|In the third year of Cyrus king of Persia a thing was  revealed unto Daniel, whose name was called Belteshazzar; and  the thing is true, but the appointed time of trial is long; and  he understood the thing, and had understanding of the vision.
10:1|KJV|In the third year of Cyrus king of Persia a thing was revealed unto Daniel, whose name was called Belteshazzar; and the thing was true, but the time appointed was long: and he understood the thing, and had understanding of the vision.
10:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|波斯王古列第三年，有話啟示給稱為伯提沙撒的但以理；
10:2|Darby|In those days I Daniel was mourning three full weeks:
10:2|KJV|In those days I Daniel was mourning three full weeks.
10:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當那些日子，我但以理悲傷了三個七日。
10:3|Darby|I ate no pleasant bread, neither came flesh nor wine into  my mouth, neither did I anoint myself at all, till three full  weeks were fulfilled.
10:3|KJV|I ate no pleasant bread, neither came flesh nor wine in my mouth, neither did I anoint myself at all, till three whole weeks were fulfilled.
10:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|美食我沒有喫，酒肉沒有入我的口，也沒有用油抹我的身，直到滿了三個七日。
10:4|Darby|And on the four-and-twentieth day of the first month, I was  by the side of the great river, which is Hiddekel:
10:4|KJV|And in the four and twentieth day of the first month, as I was by the side of the great river, which is Hiddekel;
10:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|正月二十四日，我在希底結大河邊，
10:5|Darby|and I lifted up mine eyes and looked, and behold, a certain  man clothed in linen, and his loins were girded with pure gold  of Uphaz;
10:5|KJV|Then I lifted up mine eyes, and looked, and behold a certain man clothed in linen, whose loins were girded with fine gold of Uphaz:
10:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|舉目觀看，見有一人身穿細麻衣，腰束烏法精金帶。
10:6|Darby|and his body was like a chrysolite, and his face as the  appearance of lightning, and his eyes as torches of fire, and  his arms and his feet as the look of burnished brass, and the  voice of his words like the voice of a multitude.
10:6|KJV|His body also was like the beryl, and his face as the appearance of lightning, and his eyes as lamps of fire, and his arms and his feet like in colour to polished brass, and the voice of his words like the voice of a multitude.
10:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂身體如水蒼玉，面貌如閃電，眼目如火把，手和腳如閃耀發亮的銅，說話的聲音如大眾的聲音。
10:7|Darby|And I Daniel alone saw the vision; and the men that were  with me saw not the vision, but a great quaking fell on them,  and they fled to hide themselves.
10:7|KJV|And I Daniel alone saw the vision: for the men that were with me saw not the vision; but a great quaking fell upon them, so that they fled to hide themselves.
10:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這異象惟有我但以理一人看見，同著我的人沒有看見；他們卻大大戰兢，逃跑隱藏，
10:8|Darby|And I was left alone, and saw this great vision, and there  remained no strength in me; and my comeliness was turned in me  into corruption, and I retained no strength.
10:8|KJV|Therefore I was left alone, and saw this great vision, and there remained no strength in me: for my comeliness was turned in me into corruption, and I retained no strength.
10:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只剩下我一人；我見了這大異象，便渾身無力，面色死灰，毫無力氣。
10:9|Darby|And I heard the voice of his words; and when I heard the  voice of his words, I fell into a deep stupor on my face, and  my face to the ground.
10:9|KJV|Yet heard I the voice of his words: and when I heard the voice of his words, then was I in a deep sleep on my face, and my face toward the ground.
10:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我卻聽見祂說話的聲音；我一聽見祂說話的聲音，就面伏在地沉睡了。
10:10|Darby|And behold, a hand touched me, which set me upon my knees  and the palms of my hands.
10:10|KJV|And, behold, an hand touched me, which set me upon my knees and upon the palms of my hands.
10:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|忽然有一隻手摸我，使我用膝和手掌，戰抖著支起來。
10:11|Darby|And he said unto me, O Daniel, man greatly beloved,  understand the words which I speak unto thee, and stand  upright; for unto thee am I now sent. And as he spoke this word  unto me, I stood trembling.
10:11|KJV|And he said unto me, O Daniel, a man greatly beloved, understand the words that I speak unto thee, and stand upright: for unto thee am I now sent. And when he had spoken this word unto me, I stood trembling.
10:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他對我說，大蒙眷愛的但以理阿，要明白我與你所說的話，只管在原地站起，因為我現在奉差遣來到你這堙F他對我說這話，我便戰戰兢兢的立起來。
10:12|Darby|And he said unto me, Fear not, Daniel; for from the first  day that thou didst set thy heart to understand, and to humble  thyself before thy God, thy words were heard, and I am come  because of thy words.
10:12|KJV|Then said he unto me, Fear not, Daniel: for from the first day that thou didst set thine heart to understand, and to chasten thyself before thy God, thy words were heard, and I am come for thy words.
10:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他說，但以理阿，不要懼怕，因為從你第一日專心求明白這事，又在你神面前刻苦自己，你的言語已蒙垂聽；我是因你的言語而來。
10:13|Darby|But the prince of the kingdom of Persia withstood me one  and twenty days; and behold, Michael, one of the chief princes,  came to help me; and I remained there with the kings of Persia.
10:13|KJV|But the prince of the kingdom of Persia withstood me one and twenty days: but, lo, Michael, one of the chief princes, came to help me; and I remained there with the kings of Persia.
10:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但波斯國的魔君，攔阻我二十一日；然而大君中的一位米迦勒來幫助我，因我單獨滯留在波斯諸王那堙C
10:14|Darby|And I am come to make thee understand what shall befall  thy people at the end of the days: for the vision is yet for  [many] days.
10:14|KJV|Now I am come to make thee understand what shall befall thy people in the latter days: for yet the vision is for many days.
10:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現在我來要使你明白你的民在末後日子必遭遇的事，而這異象是關於許多日子以後的事。
10:15|Darby|And as he was speaking with me according to these words, I  set my face toward the ground, and I became dumb.
10:15|KJV|And when he had spoken such words unto me, I set my face toward the ground, and I became dumb.
10:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他向我說這些話時，我臉面朝地，啞口無聲。
10:16|Darby|And behold, one after the likeness of the sons of men  touched my lips; and I opened my mouth and spoke, and said unto  him that stood before me, My lord, by reason of the vision my  pains are turned upon me, and I retain no strength.
10:16|KJV|And, behold, one like the similitude of the sons of men touched my lips: then I opened my mouth, and spake, and said unto him that stood before me, O my lord, by the vision my sorrows are turned upon me, and I have retained no strength.
10:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不料，有一位像人子的，摸我的嘴脣；我便開口說話，向那站在我面前的說，我主阿，因這景象，我大受痛苦，毫無力氣。
10:17|Darby|And how can the servant of this my lord talk with this my  lord? for as for me, straightway there remaineth no strength in  me, neither is there breath left in me.
10:17|KJV|For how can the servant of this my lord talk with this my lord? for as for me, straightway there remained no strength in me, neither is there breath left in me.
10:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我主的僕人怎能與我主說話呢？至於我，現今我渾身無力，毫無氣息。
10:18|Darby|Then there touched me again one like the appearance of a  man, and he strengthened me;
10:18|KJV|Then there came again and touched me one like the appearance of a man, and he strengthened me,
10:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有一位樣子像人的，又摸我使我有力量；
10:19|Darby|and he said, Fear not, man greatly beloved; peace be unto  thee, be strong, yea, be strong. And as he was speaking with me  I was strengthened, and I said, Let my lord speak; for thou  hast strengthened me.
10:19|KJV|And said, O man greatly beloved, fear not: peace be unto thee, be strong, yea, be strong. And when he had spoken unto me, I was strengthened, and said, Let my lord speak; for thou hast strengthened me.
10:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他說，大蒙眷愛的人哪，不要懼怕，願你平安。你要剛強，要剛強；他一向我說話，我便覺得有力量，說，我主請說，因你使我有了力量。
10:20|Darby|And he said, Knowest thou wherefore I am come unto thee?  And now I return to fight with the prince of Persia; and when I  go forth, behold, the prince of Greece shall come.
10:20|KJV|Then said he, Knowest thou wherefore I come unto thee? and now will I return to fight with the prince of Persia: and when I am gone forth, lo, the prince of Grecia shall come.
10:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他就說，你知道我為何來見你麼？現在我要回去與波斯的魔君爭戰，我出去後雅完的魔君必來。
10:21<version name="Darby">However, I will declare unto thee that which is set down  in the scripture of truth; and there is not one that sheweth  himself strong with me against these, but Michael your prince. </p><p /><br /></version>
10:21<version name="KJV">But I will shew thee that which is noted in the scripture of truth: and there is none that holdeth with me in these things, but Michael your prince.</p><p /><br /></version>
10:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但我要將那記錄在真理書上的事告訴你。除了你們的君米迦勒之外，沒有剛強幫助我抵擋這兩魔君的。
11:1|Darby|And I, in the first year of Darius the Mede, I stood to  confirm and to strengthen him.
11:1|KJV|Also I in the first year of Darius the Mede, even I, stood to confirm and to strengthen him.
11:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在瑪代王大利烏元年，曾起來扶助他，使他堅強。
11:2|Darby|And now will I declare unto thee the truth. Behold, there  shall stand up yet three kings in Persia; and the fourth shall  enrich himself with great riches more than all; and when he  hath become strong through his riches, he shall stir up all  against the realm of Greece.
11:2|KJV|And now will I shew thee the truth. Behold, there shall stand up yet three kings in Persia; and the fourth shall be far richer than they all: and by his strength through his riches he shall stir up all against the realm of Grecia.
11:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現在我將真情告訴你。波斯還有三王要興起，第四王必取得財富，遠勝諸王，他因富足成為強盛，就必激動全國攻擊雅完國。
11:3|Darby|And a mighty king shall stand up that shall rule with great  dominion, and do according to his will.
11:3|KJV|And a mighty king shall stand up, that shall rule with great dominion, and do according to his will.
11:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|必有一個有能力的王興起，執掌大權，隨意而行。
11:4|Darby|And when he shall stand up, his kingdom shall be broken,  and shall be divided toward the four winds of the heavens; but  not to his posterity, nor according to his dominion wherewith  he ruled; for his kingdom shall be plucked up, even for others  beside these.
11:4|KJV|And when he shall stand up, his kingdom shall be broken, and shall be divided toward the four winds of heaven; and not to his posterity, nor according to his dominion which he ruled: for his kingdom shall be plucked up, even for others beside those.
11:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但他一興起，他的國就破裂，向天的四方分開，卻不歸他的後裔，治國的權勢也都不及他；因為他的國必被拔出，歸與他後裔之外的人。
11:5|Darby|And the king of the south, who is one of his princes, shall  be strong; but [another] shall be stronger than he, and have  dominion: his dominion shall be a great dominion.
11:5|KJV|And the king of the south shall be strong, and one of his princes; and he shall be strong above him, and have dominion; his dominion shall be a great dominion.
11:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|南方的王必強盛，他將帥中必有一個權勢漸漸超過他，並要執掌權柄，他的權柄甚大。
11:6|Darby|And after the course of years they shall join affinity; and  the king's daughter of the south shall come to the king of the  north to make equitable conditions: but she shall not retain  the strength of her arm; neither shall he stand, nor his arm;  and she shall be given up, she and they that brought her, and  he that begat her, and he that strengthened her in [those]  times.
11:6|KJV|And in the end of years they shall join themselves together; for the king's daughter of the south shall come to the king of the north to make an agreement: but she shall not retain the power of the arm; neither shall he stand, nor his arm: but she shall be given up, and they that brought her, and he that begat her, and he that strengthened her in these times.
11:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|過些年後，他們必互相聯合。南方王的女兒，必就了北方王來立盟約；但這女子的勢力存留不住，王和他的勢力，也不能存立；這女子和引導她來聯盟的，並生她的，以及當時扶助她的，都必交與死地。
11:7|Darby|But out of a shoot from her roots shall one stand up in his  place, who shall come to the army, and shall enter into the  fortress of the king of the north, and shall deal against them,  and shew himself mighty.
11:7|KJV|But out of a branch of her roots shall one stand up in his estate, which shall come with an army, and shall enter into the fortress of the king of the north, and shall deal against them, and shall prevail:
11:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但這女子的根必另興起一嫩枝繼續王位，他必攻擊北方王的軍隊，進入北方王的保障，攻打他們，而且得勝。
11:8|Darby|He shall also carry captive into Egypt their gods, with  their princes, and their precious vessels of silver and of  gold; and he shall subsist for more years than the king of the  north;
11:8|KJV|And shall also carry captives into Egypt their gods, with their princes, and with their precious vessels of silver and of gold; and he shall continue more years than the king of the north.
11:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他要將他們的神像、鑄成的像、與金銀的寶器，掠到埃及去；數年之內，他不去攻擊北方王。
11:9|Darby|and [the same] shall come into the realm of the king of the  south, but shall return into his own land.
11:9|KJV|So the king of the south shall come into his kingdom, and shall return into his own land.
11:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|北方王必進入南方王的國，卻要仍回本地。
11:10|Darby|And his sons shall be stirred up, and shall assemble a  multitude of great forces; and one shall certainly come, and  overflow, and pass through; and he shall return and carry the  war even to his fortress.
11:10|KJV|But his sons shall be stirred up, and shall assemble a multitude of great forces: and one shall certainly come, and overflow, and pass through: then shall he return, and be stirred up, even to his fortress.
11:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他的二子必動干戈，招聚許多軍兵；這一軍兵必兇猛前來，如洪水沖沒氾濫，又必再去爭戰，直到南方王的保障。
11:11|Darby|And the king of the south shall be enraged, and shall come  forth and fight with him, with the king of the north, who shall  set forth a great multitude, but the multitude shall be given  into his hand.
11:11|KJV|And the king of the south shall be moved with choler, and shall come forth and fight with him, even with the king of the north: and he shall set forth a great multitude; but the multitude shall be given into his hand.
11:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|南方王必發烈怒，出來與北方王爭戰，北方王必興舉大軍，但他的軍眾必交付南方王的手。
11:12|Darby|And when the multitude shall have been taken away, his  heart shall be exalted; and he shall cast down myriads; but he  shall not prevail.
11:12|KJV|And when he hath taken away the multitude, his heart shall be lifted up; and he shall cast down many ten thousands: but he shall not be strengthened by it.
11:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他的軍眾被擄去，南方王的心也必高傲，他雖使數萬人仆倒，卻不能得勝。
11:13|Darby|For the king of the north shall return, and shall set  forth a multitude greater than the former; and shall certainly  come at the end of the times of years with a great army and  with much substance.
11:13|KJV|For the king of the north shall return, and shall set forth a multitude greater than the former, and shall certainly come after certain years with a great army and with much riches.
11:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|北方王必回來，他必興舉大軍，比先前的更多；過了數年，他必率領大軍，帶著極多的輜重，兇猛而來。
11:14|Darby|And in those times shall many stand up against the king of  the south; and the violent of thy people will exalt themselves  to establish the vision; but they shall fall.
11:14|KJV|And in those times there shall many stand up against the king of the south: also the robbers of thy people shall exalt themselves to establish the vision; but they shall fall.
11:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時必有許多人起來攻擊南方王，並且你本民中的強暴人必高抬自己，成就那異象，他們卻要敗亡。
11:15|Darby|And the king of the north shall come, and cast up a mound,  and take the well-fenced city; and the arms of the south shall  not withstand, neither his chosen people, for there shall be no  strength to withstand.
11:15|KJV|So the king of the north shall come, and cast up a mount, and take the most fenced cities: and the arms of the south shall not withstand, neither his chosen people, neither shall there be any strength to withstand.
11:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|北方王必來，築壘攻取堅固城；南方的軍兵必站立不住，就是精選的人也無力站住。
11:16|Darby|And he that cometh against him shall do according to his  own will, and none shall stand before him; and he shall stand  in the land of beauty, and destruction shall be in his hand.
11:16|KJV|But he that cometh against him shall do according to his own will, and none shall stand before him: and he shall stand in the glorious land, which by his hand shall be consumed.
11:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|來攻擊南方王的，必任意而行，無人在北方王面前站立得住。他必站在榮美之地，用手施行毀滅。
11:17|Darby|And he shall set his face to come with the strength of his  whole kingdom, and upright ones with him; and he shall  practise; and he shall give him the daughter of women, to  corrupt her; but she shall not stand, neither shall she be for  him.
11:17|KJV|He shall also set his face to enter with the strength of his whole kingdom, and upright ones with him; thus shall he do: and he shall give him the daughter of women, corrupting her: but she shall not stand on his side, neither be for him.
11:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他必定意用全國之力而來，與南方王立和平的約，並要照約而行，將年少的女子給南方王為妻，想要敗壞他的國。女子卻不能為他站立，對他毫無用處。
11:18|Darby|And he shall turn his face unto the isles, and shall take  many; but a captain for his own behalf shall cause the reproach  offered by him to cease: he shall turn it upon him, without  reproach for himself.
11:18|KJV|After this shall he turn his face unto the isles, and shall take many: but a prince for his own behalf shall cause the reproach offered by him to cease; without his own reproach he shall cause it to turn upon him.
11:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其後他必轉回，面向眾海島，奪取許多島嶼。但有一首領必為自己使他造成的羞辱止息，並且使這羞辱歸他本身。
11:19|Darby|And he shall turn his face toward the fortresses of his  own land; and he shall stumble and fall, and not be found.
11:19|KJV|Then he shall turn his face toward the fort of his own land: but he shall stumble and fall, and not be found.
11:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|北方王就必轉回，面向本地的保障，卻要絆跌仆倒，歸於無有。
11:20|Darby|And in his place shall one stand up who shall cause the  exactor to pass through the glory of the kingdom; but in a few  days he shall be broken, neither in anger nor in battle.
11:20|KJV|Then shall stand up in his estate a raiser of taxes in the glory of the kingdom: but within few days he shall be destroyed, neither in anger, nor in battle.
11:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時必有一人興起接續他的王位，使一暴虐的人通行國中的榮美地；這王不多日就必破滅，卻不是因忿怒，也不是因爭戰。
11:21|Darby|And in his place shall stand up a vile person, to whom  they shall not give the honour of the kingdom; but he shall  come in peaceably and obtain the kingdom by flatteries.
11:21|KJV|And in his estate shall stand up a vile person, to whom they shall not give the honour of the kingdom: but he shall come in peaceably, and obtain the kingdom by flatteries.
11:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|必有一個卑鄙的人興起接續他的王位，人必不將國的尊榮給他，他卻趁人安穩的時候，用狡猾奸詐的言語行動奪了國。
11:22|Darby|And the overflowing forces shall be overflowed from before  him, and shall be broken: yea, also the prince of the covenant.
11:22|KJV|And with the arms of a flood shall they be overflown from before him, and shall be broken; yea, also the prince of the covenant.
11:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|勢如洪水氾濫的軍兵，必在他面前被沖沒、敗壞，連與他同盟的君也必如此。
11:23|Darby|And after the league made with him he shall work  deceitfully, and he shall come up, and shall become strong with  a small people.
11:23|KJV|And after the league made with him he shall work deceitfully: for he shall come up, and shall become strong with a small people.
11:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他與那君結盟之後，必行詭詐；他必上來，以微小的民成為強盛。
11:24|Darby|In time of peace shall he enter even into the fattest  places of the province; and he shall do that which his fathers  have not done, nor his fathers' fathers: he shall scatter among  them prey, and spoil, and substance, and he shall plan his  devices against the fortified places, even for a time.
11:24|KJV|He shall enter peaceably even upon the fattest places of the province; and he shall do that which his fathers have not done, nor his fathers' fathers; he shall scatter among them the prey, and spoil, and riches: yea, and he shall forecast his devices against the strong holds, even for a time.
11:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他趁人安穩的時候，必進到國中極肥美之地，行他列祖和他列祖之祖所未曾行的；他必將擄物、掠物和財寶，散給眾人；又設計攻打保障，然而這都是暫時的。
11:25|Darby|And he shall stir up his power and his courage against the  king of the south with a great army; and the king of the south  shall engage in battle with an exceeding great and mighty army;  but he shall not stand, for they shall plan devices against  him.
11:25|KJV|And he shall stir up his power and his courage against the king of the south with a great army; and the king of the south shall be stirred up to battle with a very great and mighty army; but he shall not stand: for they shall forecast devices against him.
11:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他必奮力鼓勇，率領大軍攻擊南方王；南方王也必以極大極強的軍兵與他爭戰，卻站立不住，因為有人設計謀害南方王。
11:26|Darby|And they that eat of his delicate food shall break him,  and his army shall be dissolved; and many shall fall down  slain.
11:26|KJV|Yea, they that feed of the portion of his meat shall destroy him, and his army shall overflow: and many shall fall down slain.
11:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那些喫王膳食的，必毀壞他；他的軍隊必如洪水氾濫，多人必被殺仆倒。
11:27|Darby|And both these kings' hearts [shall meditate] mischief,  and they shall speak lies at one table; but it shall not  prosper; for yet the end shall be at the time appointed.
11:27|KJV|And both of these kings' hearts shall be to do mischief, and they shall speak lies at one table; but it shall not prosper: for yet the end shall be at the time appointed.
11:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於這二王，他們心懷邪惡，同席說謊；但所行的必不成功，因為到了定期，結局纔來到。
11:28|Darby|And he shall return into his land with great substance;  and his heart shall be against the holy covenant; and he shall  practise, and return to his own land.
11:28|KJV|Then shall he return into his land with great riches; and his heart shall be against the holy covenant; and he shall do exploits, and return to his own land.
11:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|北方王必帶許多財寶回往本地；他的心卻反對聖約，任意而行，回到本地。
11:29|Darby|At the set time he shall return, and come towards the  south; but not as the former time shall be the latter;
11:29|KJV|At the time appointed he shall return, and come toward the south; but it shall not be as the former, or as the latter.
11:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|到了定期，他必返回，來攻南方；但這後一次，卻不如前一次，
11:30|Darby|for ships of Chittim shall come against him; and he shall  be grieved, and return, and have indignation against the holy  covenant; and will practise; and he shall return and direct his  attention to those that forsake the holy covenant.
11:30|KJV|For the ships of Chittim shall come against him: therefore he shall be grieved, and return, and have indignation against the holy covenant: so shall he do; he shall even return, and have intelligence with them that forsake the holy covenant.
11:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為基提戰船必來攻擊他，他就喪膽而回；又要惱恨聖約，任意而行；他必回來，特別留意背棄聖約的人。
11:31|Darby|And forces shall stand on his part, and they shall profane  the sanctuary, the fortress, and shall take away the continual  [sacrifice], and they shall place the abomination that maketh  desolate.
11:31|KJV|And arms shall stand on his part, and they shall pollute the sanctuary of strength, and shall take away the daily sacrifice, and they shall place the abomination that maketh desolate.
11:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他必起兵褻瀆聖所，就是保障，且要除掉日常的獻祭；他們必設立那造成荒涼的可憎之物。
11:32|Darby|And such as do wickedly against the covenant shall he  pervert by flatteries; but the people that know their God shall  be strong, and shall act.
11:32|KJV|And such as do wickedly against the covenant shall he corrupt by flatteries: but the people that do know their God shall be strong, and do exploits.
11:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|作惡違背聖約的人，他必用花言巧語使他們被玷污；惟獨認識神的子民，必剛強行事。
11:33|Darby|And they that are wise among the people shall instruct the  many; and they shall fall by the sword, and by flame, by  captivity, and by spoil, [many] days.
11:33|KJV|And they that understand among the people shall instruct many: yet they shall fall by the sword, and by flame, by captivity, and by spoil, many days.
11:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|民間的通達人，必訓誨多人，然而他們多日必倒在刀下，或被火燒，或被擄掠搶奪。
11:34|Darby|And when they fall, they shall be helped with a little  help; but many shall cleave to them with flatteries.
11:34|KJV|Now when they shall fall, they shall be holpen with a little help: but many shall cleave to them with flatteries.
11:34|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們跌倒的時候，稍得扶助；有許多人只用諂媚的話依附他們。
11:35|Darby|And [some] of the wise shall fall, to try them, and to  purge and to make them white, to the time of the end: for it  shall yet be for the time appointed.
11:35|KJV|And some of them of understanding shall fall, to try them, and to purge, and to make them white, even to the time of the end: because it is yet for a time appointed.
11:35|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|通達人中有些跌倒的，為要熬煉百姓，使他們純淨潔白，直到末時，因為到了定期，結局纔來到。
11:36|Darby|And the king shall do according to his will; and he shall  exalt himself, and magnify himself above every ???’???’?????????god, and speak  monstrous things against the ???’???’?????????God of ???’???’?????????gods; and he shall  prosper until the indignation be accomplished: for that which  is determined shall be done.
11:36|KJV|And the king shall do according to his will; and he shall exalt himself, and magnify himself above every god, and shall speak marvellous things against the God of gods, and shall prosper till the indignation be accomplished: for that that is determined shall be done.
11:36|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王必任意行事，自高自大，超過所有的神，又用奇異的話攻擊萬神之神；他必行事亨通，直到忿怒完畢，因為所定的事，必然成就。
11:37|Darby|And he will not regard the God of his fathers, nor the  desire of women; nor regard any +god: for he will magnify  himself above all.
11:37|KJV|Neither shall he regard the God of his fathers, nor the desire of women, nor regard any god: for he shall magnify himself above all.
11:37|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他必不顧他列祖的神，也不顧婦女所羨慕的神，無論何神他都不顧，因為他必自大，高過一切。
11:38|Darby|And in his place will he honour the +god of fortresses;  and a +god whom his fathers knew not will he honour with gold  and silver, and with precious stones and pleasant things.
11:38|KJV|But in his estate shall he honour the God of forces: and a god whom his fathers knew not shall he honour with gold, and silver, and with precious stones, and pleasant things.
11:38|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他倒要尊崇保障的神，用金銀寶石和珍寶，敬奉他列祖所不認識的神。
11:39|Darby|And he will practise in the strongholds of fortresses with  a strange +god: whoso acknowledgeth him will he increase with  glory; and he shall cause them to rule over the many, and shall  divide the land [to them] for a reward.
11:39|KJV|Thus shall he do in the most strong holds with a strange god, whom he shall acknowledge and increase with glory: and he shall cause them to rule over many, and shall divide the land for gain.
11:39|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他必靠外邦神明的幫助，攻擊最堅固的保障；凡承認他的，他必將榮耀加給他們，使他們管轄許多人，又分地賞給他們。
11:40|Darby|And at the time of the end shall the king of the south  push at him; and the king of the north shall come against him  like a whirlwind, with chariots, and with horsemen, and with  many ships; and he shall enter into the countries, and overflow  and pass through.
11:40|KJV|And at the time of the end shall the king of the south push at him: and the king of the north shall come against him like a whirlwind, with chariots, and with horsemen, and with many ships; and he shall enter into the countries, and shall overflow and pass over.
11:40|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|到了末時，南方王要與他交戰，北方王必用戰車、馬兵、和許多戰船，勢如暴風來攻擊他，也必進入列國，如洪水沖沒氾濫；
11:41|Darby|And he shall enter into the land of beauty, and many  [countries] shall be overthrown; but these shall escape out of  his hand: Edom, and Moab, and the chief of the children of  Ammon.
11:41|KJV|He shall enter also into the glorious land, and many countries shall be overthrown: but these shall escape out of his hand, even Edom, and Moab, and the chief of the children of Ammon.
11:41|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又必進入榮美之地，有許多國就被傾覆；但以東人、摩押人、和亞捫人中為首的，必脫離他的手。
11:42|Darby|And he shall stretch forth his hand upon the countries;  and the land of Egypt shall not escape.
11:42|KJV|He shall stretch forth his hand also upon the countries: and the land of Egypt shall not escape.
11:42|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他必伸手攻擊列國；埃及地也不得逃脫。
11:43|Darby|And he shall have power over the treasures of gold and of  silver, and over all the precious things of Egypt; and the  Libyans and the Ethiopians shall be at his steps.
11:43|KJV|But he shall have power over the treasures of gold and of silver, and over all the precious things of Egypt: and the Libyans and the Ethiopians shall be at his steps.
11:43|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他必把持埃及人隱藏的金銀財寶，和各樣的寶物；呂彼亞人和古實人，都必跟從他的腳步。
11:44|Darby|But tidings out of the east and out of the north shall  trouble him; and he shall go forth with great fury to  exterminate, and utterly to destroy many.
11:44|KJV|But tidings out of the east and out of the north shall trouble him: therefore he shall go forth with great fury to destroy, and utterly to make away many.
11:44|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但從東方和北方必有消息擾亂他，他就大發烈怒出去，將多人殺滅淨盡。
11:45<version name="Darby">And he shall plant the tents of his palace between the sea  and the mountain of holy beauty; and he shall come to his end,  and there shall be none to help him. </p><p /><br /></version>
11:45<version name="KJV">And he shall plant the tabernacles of his palace between the seas in the glorious holy mountain; yet he shall come to his end, and none shall help him.</p><p /><br /></version>
11:45|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他必在海和榮美的聖山之間，支搭他如宮殿的帳幕；然而到了他的結局，必無人幫助他。
12:1|Darby|And at that time shall Michael stand up, the great prince  who standeth for the children of thy people; and there shall be  a time of distress, such as never was since there was a nation  until that time. And at that time thy people shall be  delivered, every one that is found written in the book.
12:1|KJV|And at that time shall Michael stand up, the great prince which standeth for the children of thy people: and there shall be a time of trouble, such as never was since there was a nation even to that same time: and at that time thy people shall be delivered, every one that shall be found written in the book.
12:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時保護你本民的大君米迦勒必起來；並且必有困苦的時期，是從有國以來直到那時未曾發生過的；那時，你本民中凡記錄在冊上的，必得拯救。
12:2|Darby|And many of them that sleep in the dust of the earth shall  awake, some to everlasting life, and some to shame, to  everlasting contempt.
12:2|KJV|And many of them that sleep in the dust of the earth shall awake, some to everlasting life, and some to shame and everlasting contempt.
12:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|睡在塵埃中的，必有多人醒起；其中有歸到永遠生命的，有歸到羞辱，永遠蒙羞的。
12:3|Darby|And they that are wise shall shine as the brightness of the  expanse; and they that turn the many to righteousness as the  stars, for ever and ever.
12:3|KJV|And they that be wise shall shine as the brightness of the firmament; and they that turn many to righteousness as the stars for ever and ever.
12:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|通達人必發光，如同穹蒼的光輝；那使多人歸義的，必發光如星，直到永永遠遠。
12:4|Darby|And thou, Daniel, close the words, and seal the book, till  the time of the end. Many shall run to and fro, and knowledge  shall be increased.
12:4|KJV|But thou, O Daniel, shut up the words, and seal the book, even to the time of the end: many shall run to and fro, and knowledge shall be increased.
12:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但以理阿，你要隱藏這話，封閉這書，直到末時；必有多人來往奔跑，知識就必增多。
12:5|Darby|And I Daniel looked, and behold, there stood other two, the  one on this side, on the bank of the river, and the other on  that side, on the bank of the river.
12:5|KJV|Then I Daniel looked, and, behold, there stood other two, the one on this side of the bank of the river, and the other on that side of the bank of the river.
12:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我但以理觀看，見另有兩位站立，一位在河這邊，一位在河那邊。
12:6|Darby|And he said to the man clothed in linen, who was above the  waters of the river, How long [is it to] the end of these  wonders?
12:6|KJV|And one said to the man clothed in linen, which was upon the waters of the river, How long shall it be to the end of these wonders?
12:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有一位問那在河水以上，穿細麻衣的，說，這些奇事的結局，還有多久纔到呢？
12:7|Darby|And I heard the man clothed in linen, who was above the  waters of the river; and he held up his right hand and his left  hand unto the heavens, and swore by him that liveth for ever  that it is for a time, times, and a half; and when the  scattering of the power of the holy people shall be  accomplished, all these things shall be finished.
12:7|KJV|And I heard the man clothed in linen, which was upon the waters of the river, when he held up his right hand and his left hand unto heaven, and sware by him that liveth for ever that it shall be for a time, times, and an half; and when he shall have accomplished to scatter the power of the holy people, all these things shall be finished.
12:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我聽見那在河水以上，穿細麻衣的，向天舉起左右手，憑著那永遠活著的主起誓，說，要到一年、二年、半年，打破聖民權力完成的時候，這一切事就都完成了！
12:8|Darby|And I heard, but I understood not. And I said, My lord,  what shall be the end of these things?
12:8|KJV|And I heard, but I understood not: then said I, O my Lord, what shall be the end of these things?
12:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我聽見這話，卻不明白，就說，我主阿，這些事末後的結局是怎樣呢？
12:9|Darby|And he said, Go thy way, Daniel; for these words are closed  and sealed till the time of the end.
12:9|KJV|And he said, Go thy way, Daniel: for the words are closed up and sealed till the time of the end.
12:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂說，但以理阿，你只管去，因為這些話已經隱藏封閉，直到末時。
12:10|Darby|Many shall be purified, and be made white, and be refined;  but the wicked shall do wickedly: and none of the wicked shall  understand; but the wise shall understand.
12:10|KJV|Many shall be purified, and made white, and tried; but the wicked shall do wickedly: and none of the wicked shall understand; but the wise shall understand.
12:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|許多人必得潔淨，成為潔白，且被煉淨，但惡人仍必行惡；一切惡人都不明白，惟獨通達人能明白。
12:11|Darby|And from the time that the continual [sacrifice] is taken  away, and the abomination that maketh desolate set up, [there  shall be] a thousand, two hundred, and ninety days.
12:11|KJV|And from the time that the daily sacrifice shall be taken away, and the abomination that maketh desolate set up, there shall be a thousand two hundred and ninety days.
12:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|從除掉日常獻的祭，並設立那造成荒涼的可憎之物的時候，必有一千二百九十日。
12:12|Darby|Blessed is he that waiteth, and cometh to the thousand  three hundred and thirty-five days!
12:12|KJV|Blessed is he that waiteth, and cometh to the thousand three hundred and five and thirty days.
12:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡等到一千三百三十五日的，那人便為有福。
12:13<version name="Darby">But do thou go thy way until the end; and thou shalt rest,  and stand in thy lot at the end of the days. </p><p /><br /></version>
12:13<version name="KJV">But go thou thy way till the end be: for thou shalt rest, and stand in thy lot at the end of the days.</p><p /><br /></version>
12:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你且去等候結局，你必安歇；到末了的日子，你必起來，享受你的業分。
