1:1|ASV|The words of the Preacher, the son of David, king in Jerusalem.
1:1|Darby|The words of the Preacher, the son of David, king in  Jerusalem.
1:1|KJV|The words of the Preacher, the son of David, king in Jerusalem.
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在耶路撒冷作王，大衛的兒子，傳道者的言語。
1:2|ASV|Vanity of vanities, saith the Preacher; vanity of vanities, all is vanity.
1:2|Darby|Vanity of vanities, saith the Preacher, vanity of vanities!  all is vanity.
1:2|KJV|Vanity of vanities, saith the Preacher, vanity of vanities; all is vanity.
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|傳道者說，虛空的虛空，虛空的虛空，凡事都是虛空。
1:3|ASV|What profit hath man of all his labor wherein he laboreth under the sun?
1:3|Darby|What profit hath man of all his labour wherewith he  laboureth under the sun?
1:3|KJV|What profit hath a man of all his labour which he taketh under the sun?
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人一切的勞碌，就是他在日光之下的勞碌，有甚麼益處呢？
1:4|ASV|One generation goeth, and another generation cometh; but the earth abideth for ever.
1:4|Darby|[One] generation passeth away, and [another] generation  cometh, but the earth standeth for ever.
1:4|KJV|One generation passeth away, and another generation cometh: but the earth abideth for ever.
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|一代過去，一代又來，地卻永遠存立。
1:5|ASV|The sun also ariseth, and the sun goeth down, and hasteth to its place where it ariseth.
1:5|Darby|The sun also riseth, and the sun goeth down, and hasteth to  its place where it ariseth.
1:5|KJV|The sun also ariseth, and the sun goeth down, and hasteth to his place where he arose.
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|日頭升起，日頭落下，急歸升起之處。
1:6|ASV|The wind goeth toward the south, and turneth about unto the north; it turneth about continually in its course, and the wind returneth again to its circuits.
1:6|Darby|The wind goeth towards the south, and turneth about towards  the north: it turneth about continually, and the wind returneth  again to its circuits.
1:6|KJV|The wind goeth toward the south, and turneth about unto the north; it whirleth about continually, and the wind returneth again according to his circuits.
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|風往南颳，又向北轉，不住的旋轉，而且返回轉行原道。
1:7|ASV|All the rivers run into the sea, yet the sea is not full; unto the place whither the rivers go, thither they go again.
1:7|Darby|All the rivers run into the sea, yet the sea is not full:  unto the place whither the rivers go, thither they go again.
1:7|KJV|All the rivers run into the sea; yet the sea is not full; unto the place from whence the rivers come, thither they return again.
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|江河都往海堿y，海卻不滿；江河往何處流，仍再流往何處。
1:8|ASV|All things are full of weariness; man cannot utter it: the eye is not satisfied with seeing, nor the ear filled with hearing.
1:8|Darby|All things are full of toil; none can express it. The eye is  not satisfied with seeing, nor the ear filled with hearing.
1:8|KJV|All things are full of labour; man cannot utter it: the eye is not satisfied with seeing, nor the ear filled with hearing.
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬事令人厭煩，人不能說盡。眼看，看不飽；耳聽，聽不足。
1:9|ASV|That which hath been is that which shall be; and that which hath been done is that which shall be done: and there is no new thing under the sun.
1:9|Darby|That which hath been is that which shall be; and that which  hath been done is that which will be done: and there is nothing  new under the sun.
1:9|KJV|The thing that hath been, it is that which shall be; and that which is done is that which shall be done: and there is no new thing under the sun.
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|已有的事，後必再有；已作的事，後必再作。日光之下並無新事。
1:10|ASV|Is there a thing whereof it may be said, See, this is new? it hath been long ago, in the ages which were before us.
1:10|Darby|Is there a thing whereof it may be said, See, this is new?  It hath been already in the ages which were before us.
1:10|KJV|Is there any thing whereof it may be said, See, this is new? it hath been already of old time, which was before us.
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|豈有一件事人能指著說，這是新的？那知，在我們以前的世代早已有了。
1:11|ASV|There is no remembrance of the former generations ; neither shall there be any remembrance of the latter generations that are to come, among those that shall come after.
1:11|Darby|There is no remembrance of former things; neither shall  there be remembrance of things that are to come with those who  shall live afterwards.
1:11|KJV|There is no remembrance of former things; neither shall there be any remembrance of things that are to come with those that shall come after.
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|已過的世代，無人記念；將來的世代，後來的人也不記念。
1:12|ASV|I the Preacher was king over Israel in Jerusalem.
1:12|Darby|I, the Preacher, was king over Israel in Jerusalem.
1:12|KJV|I the Preacher was king over Israel in Jerusalem.
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我傳道者在耶路撒冷作過以色列的王。
1:13|ASV|And I applied my heart to seek and to search out by wisdom concerning all that is done under heaven: it is a sore travail that God hath given to the sons of men to be exercised therewith.
1:13|Darby|And I applied my heart to seek and search out by wisdom  concerning all that is done under the heavens: this grievous  occupation hath God given to the children of men to weary  themselves therewith.
1:13|KJV|And I gave my heart to seek and search out by wisdom concerning all things that are done under heaven: this sore travail hath God given to the sons of man to be exercised therewith.
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我專心用智慧尋求、查究天下所作的一切；乃知神叫世人所操勞的，是極重的辛勞。
1:14|ASV|I have seen all the works that are done under the sun; and, behold, all is vanity and a striving after wind.
1:14|Darby|I have seen all the works that are done under the sun, and  behold, all is vanity and pursuit of the wind.
1:14|KJV|I have seen all the works that are done under the sun; and, behold, all is vanity and vexation of spirit.
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我見日光之下所作的一切工，看哪，都是虛空，都是捕風。
1:15|ASV|That which is crooked cannot be made straight; and that which is wanting cannot be numbered.
1:15|Darby|That which is crooked cannot be made straight; and that  which is wanting cannot be numbered.
1:15|KJV|That which is crooked cannot be made straight: and that which is wanting cannot be numbered.
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|彎曲的不能變直，缺少的不能足數。
1:16|ASV|I communed with mine own hear, saying, Lo, I have gotten me great wisdom above all that were before me in Jerusalem; yea, my heart hath had great experience of wisdom and knowledge.
1:16|Darby|I communed with mine own heart, saying, Lo, I have become  great and have acquired wisdom more than all they that have  been before me over Jerusalem; and my heart hath seen much of  wisdom and knowledge.
1:16|KJV|I communed with mine own heart, saying, Lo, I am come to great estate, and have gotten more wisdom than all they that have been before me in Jerusalem: yea, my heart had great experience of wisdom and knowledge.
1:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我自己心婸﹛A我得了大智慧，勝過以前所有治理耶路撒冷的人，我的心也見識了許多智慧和知識的事。
1:17|ASV|And I applied my heart to know wisdom, and to know madness and folly: I perceived that this also was a striving after wind.
1:17|Darby|And I applied my heart to the knowledge of wisdom, and to  the knowledge of madness and folly: I perceived that this also  is a striving after the wind.
1:17|KJV|And I gave my heart to know wisdom, and to know madness and folly: I perceived that this also is vexation of spirit.
1:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我又專心要明白智慧，並要明白狂妄和愚昧，乃知這也是捕風。
1:18<version name="ASV">For in much wisdom is much grief; and he that increaseth knowledge increaseth sorrow. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:18<version name="Darby">For in much wisdom is much vexation, and he that increaseth  knowledge increaseth sorrow. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:18<version name="KJV">For in much wisdom is much grief: and he that increaseth knowledge increaseth sorrow.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為多有智慧，就多有愁煩；加增知識的，就加增憂傷。
2:1|ASV|I said in my heart, Come now, I will prove thee with mirth; therefore enjoy pleasure: and, behold, this also was vanity.
2:1|Darby|I said in my heart, Come now, I will try thee with mirth,  therefore enjoy pleasure. But behold, this also is vanity.
2:1|KJV|I said in mine heart, Go to now, I will prove thee with mirth, therefore enjoy pleasure: and, behold, this also is vanity.
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我心婸﹛A來罷，我要試一試享樂，好享美福！誰知，這也是虛空。
2:2|ASV|I said of laughter, It is mad; and of mirth, What doeth it?
2:2|Darby|I said of laughter, Madness! and of mirth, What availeth it?
2:2|KJV|I said of laughter, It is mad: and of mirth, What doeth it?
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我指嬉笑說，這是狂妄；論享樂說，這有何功效呢？
2:3|ASV|I searched in my heart how to cheer my flesh with wine, my heart yet guiding me with wisdom, and how to lay hold on folly, till I might see what it was good for the sons of men that they should do under heaven all the days of their life.
2:3|Darby|I searched in my heart how to cherish my flesh with wine,  while practising my heart with wisdom; and how to lay hold on  folly, till I should see what was that good for the children of  men which they should do under the heavens all the days of  their life.
2:3|KJV|I sought in mine heart to give myself unto wine, yet acquainting mine heart with wisdom; and to lay hold on folly, till I might see what was that good for the sons of men, which they should do under the heaven all the days of their life.
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我心堿d究，如何用酒使我肉體舒暢，我心卻仍以智慧引導我；又如何持住愚昧，等我看明，世人在天下一生有數的日子中所作的，有何好處。
2:4|ASV|I made me great works; I builded me houses; I planted me vineyards;
2:4|Darby|I made me great works; I builded me houses; I planted me  vineyards;
2:4|KJV|I made me great works; I builded me houses; I planted me vineyards:
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我為自己動大工程，建造房屋，栽種葡萄園，
2:5|ASV|I made me gardens and parks, and I planted trees in them of all kinds of fruit;
2:5|Darby|I made me gardens and parks, and I planted trees in them of  every kind of fruit;
2:5|KJV|I made me gardens and orchards, and I planted trees in them of all kind of fruits:
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|修造園囿，在其中栽種各樣果樹；
2:6|ASV|I made me pools of water, to water therefrom the forest where trees were reared;
2:6|Darby|I made me ponds of water, to water therewith the wood, where  the trees are reared.
2:6|KJV|I made me pools of water, to water therewith the wood that bringeth forth trees:
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|挖造水池，用以澆灌生長的林木。
2:7|ASV|I bought men-servants and maid-servants, and had servants born in my house; also I had great possessions of herds and flocks, above all that were before me in Jerusalem;
2:7|Darby|I acquired servants and maidens, and had servants born in my  house; also I had great possessions of herds and flocks, above  all that had been in Jerusalem before me.
2:7|KJV|I got me servants and maidens, and had servants born in my house; also I had great possessions of great and small cattle above all that were in Jerusalem before me:
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我買了僕婢，也有生在家中的奴僕；又擁有許多的牛群羊群，勝過以前在耶路撒冷的眾人。
2:8|ASV|I gathered me also silver and gold, and the treasure of kings and of the provinces; I gat me men-singers and women-singers, and the delights of the sons of men, musical instruments, and that of all sorts.
2:8|Darby|I gathered me also silver and gold, and the peculiar  treasure of kings and of the provinces; I got me men-singers  and women-singers, and the delights of the children of men, a  wife and concubines.
2:8|KJV|I gathered me also silver and gold, and the peculiar treasure of kings and of the provinces: I gat me men singers and women singers, and the delights of the sons of men, as musical instruments, and that of all sorts.
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我又為自己積蓄金銀，和君王並各省的財寶；又得唱歌的男女，和世人所喜愛的物，並許多的妃嬪。
2:9|ASV|So I was great, and increased more than all that were before me in Jerusalem: also my wisdom remained with me.
2:9|Darby|And I became great, and increased more than all that had  been before me in Jerusalem: also my wisdom remained with me.
2:9|KJV|So I was great, and increased more than all that were before me in Jerusalem: also my wisdom remained with me.
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我就日見昌大，勝過以前在耶路撒冷的眾人；我的智慧仍然存留。
2:10|ASV|And whatsoever mine eyes desired I kept not from them; I withheld not my heart from any joy; for my heart rejoiced because of all my labor; and this was my portion from all my labor.
2:10|Darby|And whatsoever mine eyes desired I kept not from them: I  withheld not my heart from any joy; for my heart rejoiced in  all my labour, and this was my portion from all my labour.
2:10|KJV|And whatsoever mine eyes desired I kept not from them, I withheld not my heart from any joy; for my heart rejoiced in all my labour: and this was my portion of all my labour.
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡我眼所要的，我沒有不給的；我不禁止我的心有任何的享樂；因我的心在我一切勞碌中得了快樂，這就是我從一切勞碌中所得的分。
2:11|ASV|Then I looked on all the works that my hands had wrought, and on the labor that I had labored to do; and, behold, all was vanity and a striving after wind, and there was no profit under the sun.
2:11|Darby|Then I looked on all the works that my hands had wrought,  and on the labour that it had cost me to do [them]; and behold,  all was vanity and pursuit of the wind, and there was no profit  under the sun.
2:11|KJV|Then I looked on all the works that my hands had wrought, and on the labour that I had laboured to do: and, behold, all was vanity and vexation of spirit, and there was no profit under the sun.
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|後來，我轉看我手所作的一切工，和我工作中的勞碌；誰知都是虛空，都是捕風；在日光之下毫無益處。
2:12|ASV|And I turned myself to behold wisdom, and madness, and folly: for what can the man do that cometh after the king?  even that which hath been done long ago.
2:12|Darby|And I turned myself to behold wisdom, and madness, and  folly; for what shall the man [do] that cometh after the king?  -- that which hath already been done.
2:12|KJV|And I turned myself to behold wisdom, and madness, and folly: for what can the man do that cometh after the king? even that which hath been already done.
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我轉看智慧、狂妄和愚昧。在王以後來的人還能作甚麼呢？也不過作早先所作的就是了。
2:13|ASV|Then I saw that wisdom excelleth folly, as far as light excelleth darkness.
2:13|Darby|And I saw that wisdom excelleth folly, as light excelleth  darkness.
2:13|KJV|Then I saw that wisdom excelleth folly, as far as light excelleth darkness.
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我便看出智慧勝過愚昧，如同光明勝過黑暗。
2:14|ASV|The wise man's eyes are in his head, and the fool walketh in darkness: and yet I perceived that one event happeneth to them all.
2:14|Darby|The wise man's eyes are in his head, and the fool walketh  in darkness; but I myself also perceived that one event  happeneth to them all.
2:14|KJV|The wise man's eyes are in his head; but the fool walketh in darkness: and I myself perceived also that one event happeneth to them all.
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|智慧人的眼目光明，愚昧人在黑暗埵獢F但我也看明，這兩等人所遭遇的都是一樣。
2:15|ASV|Then said I in my heart, As it happeneth to the fool, so will it happen even to me; and why was I then more wise? Then said I in my heart, that this also is vanity.
2:15|Darby|And I said in my heart, As it happeneth to the fool so will  it happen even to me; and why was I then so wise? Then I said  in my heart that this also is vanity.
2:15|KJV|Then said I in my heart, As it happeneth to the fool, so it happeneth even to me; and why was I then more wise? Then I said in my heart, that this also is vanity.
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我就心婸﹛A愚昧人所遭遇的，我也必遭遇。既是這樣，我為何更有智慧呢？我心婸﹛A這也是虛空。
2:16|ASV|For of the wise man, even as of the fool, there is no remembrance for ever; seeing that in the days to come all will have been long forgotten. And how doth the wise man die even as the fool!
2:16|Darby|For there shall be no remembrance of the wise more than of  the fool for ever; because everything is already forgotten in  the days which come. And how dieth the wise even as the fool?
2:16|KJV|For there is no remembrance of the wise more than of the fool for ever; seeing that which now is in the days to come shall all be forgotten. And how dieth the wise man? as the fool.
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|智慧人和愚昧人一樣，永遠無人記念，因為日後都要被遺忘；可歎智慧人死亡，與愚昧人無異！
2:17|ASV|So I hated life, because the work that is wrought under the sun was grievous unto me; for all is vanity and a striving after wind.
2:17|Darby|And I hated life; for the work that is wrought under the  sun was grievous unto me; for all is vanity and pursuit of the  wind.
2:17|KJV|Therefore I hated life; because the work that is wrought under the sun is grievous unto me: for all is vanity and vexation of spirit.
2:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我恨惡生命，因為在日光之下所作的工，我都以為煩惱；一切都是虛空，都是捕風。
2:18|ASV|And I hated all my labor wherein I labored under the sun, seeing that I must leave it unto the man that shall be after me.
2:18|Darby|And I hated all my labour wherewith I had been toiling  under the sun, because I should leave it unto the man that  shall be after me.
2:18|KJV|Yea, I hated all my labour which I had taken under the sun: because I should leave it unto the man that shall be after me.
2:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我恨惡一切的勞碌，就是我在日光之下的勞碌，因為我所得的都必留給我以後的人。
2:19|ASV|And who knoweth whether he will be a wise man or a fool? yet will he have rule over all my labor wherein I have labored, and wherein I have showed myself wise under the sun. This also is vanity.
2:19|Darby|And who knoweth whether he will be a wise [man] or a fool?  yet shall he have rule over all my labour at which I have  laboured, and wherein I have been wise under the sun. This also  is vanity.
2:19|KJV|And who knoweth whether he shall be a wise man or a fool? yet shall he have rule over all my labour wherein I have laboured, and wherein I have shewed myself wise under the sun. This is also vanity.
2:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那人是智慧是愚昧，誰能知道？他竟要管理我勞碌所得的一切，就是我在日光之下用智慧所得的。這也是虛空。
2:20|ASV|Therefore I turned about to cause my heart to despair concerning all the labor wherein I had labored under the sun.
2:20|Darby|Then I went about to cause my heart to despair of all the  labour wherewith I had laboured under the sun.
2:20|KJV|Therefore I went about to cause my heart to despair of all the labour which I took under the sun.
2:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|故此，我轉想我在日光之下勞碌所得的一切，心便絕望。
2:21|ASV|For there is a man whose labor is with wisdom, and with knowledge, and with skilfulness; yet to a man that hath not labored therein shall he leave it for his portion. This also is vanity and a great evil.
2:21|Darby|For there is a man whose labour hath been with wisdom, and  with knowledge, and with skill, and who leaveth it to a man  that hath not laboured therein, to be his portion. This also is  vanity and a great evil.
2:21|KJV|For there is a man whose labour is in wisdom, and in knowledge, and in equity; yet to a man that hath not laboured therein shall he leave it for his portion. This also is vanity and a great evil.
2:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為有人用智慧、知識、技能所勞碌得來的，卻要留給未曾勞碌的人為分。這也是虛空，也是大患。
2:22|ASV|For what hath a man of all his labor, and of the striving of his heart, wherein he laboreth under the sun?
2:22|Darby|For what will man have of all his labour and of the  striving of his heart, wherewith he hath wearied himself under  the sun?
2:22|KJV|For what hath man of all his labour, and of the vexation of his heart, wherein he hath laboured under the sun?
2:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人在日光之下勞碌操心，在他一切的勞碌上得著甚麼呢？
2:23|ASV|For all his days are but sorrows, and his travail is grief; yea, even in the night his heart taketh no rest. This also is vanity.
2:23|Darby|For all his days are sorrows, and his travail vexation:  even in the night his heart taketh no rest. This also is  vanity.
2:23|KJV|For all his days are sorrows, and his travail grief; yea, his heart taketh not rest in the night. This is also vanity.
2:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為他一生的日子都是憂傷，他的辛勞成為愁煩，連夜間心也不安息。這也是虛空。
2:24|ASV|There is nothing better for a man than that he should eat and drink, and make his soul enjoy good in his labor. This also I saw, that it is from the hand of God.
2:24|Darby|There is nothing good for man, but that he should eat and  drink, and that he should make his soul enjoy good in his  labour. This also I saw, that it was from the hand of God.
2:24|KJV|There is nothing better for a man, than that he should eat and drink, and that he should make his soul enjoy good in his labour. This also I saw, that it was from the hand of God.
2:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人莫強如喫喝，且讓自己在勞碌中享美福。我看這也是出於神的手。
2:25|ASV|For who can eat, or who can have enjoyment, more than I?
2:25|Darby|For who can eat, or who be eager, more than I?
2:25|KJV|For who can eat, or who else can hasten hereunto, more than I?
2:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為離了祂，誰能喫用、享受呢？
2:26<version name="ASV">For to the man that pleaseth him God giveth wisdom, and knowledge, and joy; but to the sinner he giveth travail, to gather and to heap up, that he may give to him that pleaseth God. This also is vanity and a striving after wind. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:26<version name="Darby">For he giveth to a man that is good in his sight wisdom,  and knowledge, and joy; but to the sinner he giveth travail to  gather and to heap up, that he may give to him that is good in  God's sight. This also is vanity and pursuit of the wind. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:26<version name="KJV">For God giveth to a man that is good in his sight wisdom, and knowledge, and joy: but to the sinner he giveth travail, to gather and to heap up, that he may give to him that is good before God. This also is vanity and vexation of spirit.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神看誰為好，就給誰智慧、知識和喜樂；卻將辛勞給罪人，叫他將所收聚的、所堆積的，歸給神看為好的人。這也是虛空，也是捕風。
3:1|ASV|For everything there is a season, and a time for every purpose under heaven:
3:1|Darby|To everything there is a season, and a time to every purpose  under the heavens:
3:1|KJV|To every thing there is a season, and a time to every purpose under the heaven:
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡事都有定期，天下各樣事務都有定時。
3:2|ASV|a time to be born, and a time to die; a time to plant, and a time to pluck up that which is planted;
3:2|Darby|A time to be born, and a time to die; A time to plant, and a  time to pluck up that which is planted;
3:2|KJV|A time to be born, and a time to die; a time to plant, and a time to pluck up that which is planted;
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|生有時，死有時；栽種有時，拔出所栽種的也有時；
3:3|ASV|a time to kill, and a time to heal; a time to break down, and a time to build up;
3:3|Darby|A time to kill, and a time to heal; A time to break down,  and a time to build up;
3:3|KJV|A time to kill, and a time to heal; a time to break down, and a time to build up;
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|殺戮有時，醫治有時；拆毀有時，建造有時；
3:4|ASV|a time to weep, and a time to laugh; a time to mourn, and a time to dance;
3:4|Darby|A time to weep, and a time to laugh; A time to mourn, and a  time to dance;
3:4|KJV|A time to weep, and a time to laugh; a time to mourn, and a time to dance;
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哭有時，笑有時；哀慟有時，跳舞有時；
3:5|ASV|a time to cast away stones, and a time to gather stones together; a time to embrace, and a time to refrain from embracing;
3:5|Darby|A time to cast away stones, and a time to gather stones  together; A time to embrace, and a time to refrain from  embracing;
3:5|KJV|A time to cast away stones, and a time to gather stones together; a time to embrace, and a time to refrain from embracing;
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|拋擲石頭有時，堆聚石頭有時；擁抱有時，不擁抱有時；
3:6|ASV|a time to seek, and a time to lose; a time to keep, and a time to cast away;
3:6|Darby|A time to seek, and a time to lose; A time to keep, and a  time to cast away;
3:6|KJV|A time to get, and a time to lose; a time to keep, and a time to cast away;
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|尋找有時，失落有時；保守有時，捨棄有時；
3:7|ASV|a time to rend, and a time to sew; a time to keep silence, and a time to speak;
3:7|Darby|A time to rend, and a time to sew; A time to keep silence,  and a time to speak;
3:7|KJV|A time to rend, and a time to sew; a time to keep silence, and a time to speak;
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|撕裂有時，縫補有時；靜默有時，說話有時；
3:8|ASV|a time to love, and a time to hate; a time for war, and a time for peace.
3:8|Darby|A time to love, and a time to hate; A time of war, and a  time of peace.
3:8|KJV|A time to love, and a time to hate; a time of war, and a time of peace.
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|愛有時，恨有時；戰爭有時，和平有時。
3:9|ASV|What profit hath he that worketh in that wherein he laboreth?
3:9|Darby|What profit hath he that worketh from that wherein he  laboureth?
3:9|KJV|What profit hath he that worketh in that wherein he laboureth?
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣看來，作事的人在他的勞碌上有甚麼益處呢？
3:10|ASV|I have seen the travail which God hath given to the sons of men to be exercised therewith.
3:10|Darby|I have seen the travail that God hath given to the sons of  men to toil in.
3:10|KJV|I have seen the travail, which God hath given to the sons of men to be exercised in it.
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我見神將辛勞給世人，使他們在其中操勞。
3:11|ASV|He hath made everything beautiful in its time: also he hath set eternity in their heart, yet so that man cannot find out the work that God hath done from the beginning even to the end.
3:11|Darby|He hath made everything beautiful in its time; also he hath  set the world in their heart, so that man findeth not out from  the beginning to the end the work that God doeth.
3:11|KJV|He hath made every thing beautiful in his time: also he hath set the world in their heart, so that no man can find out the work that God maketh from the beginning to the end.
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神造萬物，各按其時成為美好，又將永遠安置在世人心堙C雖是這樣，人並不能參透神從始至終的作為。
3:12|ASV|I know that there is nothing better for them, than to rejoice, and to do good so long as they live.
3:12|Darby|I know that there is nothing good for them but to rejoice  and to do well in their life;
3:12|KJV|I know that there is no good in them, but for a man to rejoice, and to do good in his life.
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我知道人莫強如一生喜樂行善；
3:13|ASV|And also that every man should eat and drink, and enjoy good in all his labor, is the gift of God.
3:13|Darby|yea also that every man should eat and drink, and enjoy  good in all his labour, it is the gift of God.
3:13|KJV|And also that every man should eat and drink, and enjoy the good of all his labour, it is the gift of God.
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且人人喫喝，在他一切勞碌中享美福，這乃是神的恩賜。
3:14|ASV|I know that, whatsoever God doeth, it shall be for ever: nothing can be put to it, nor anything taken from it; and God hath done it, that men should fear before him.
3:14|Darby|I know that whatever God doeth, it shall be for ever; there  is nothing to be added to it, nor anything to be taken from it;  and God doeth [it], that [men] should fear before him.
3:14|KJV|I know that, whatsoever God doeth, it shall be for ever: nothing can be put to it, nor any thing taken from it: and God doeth it, that men should fear before him.
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我知道神一切所作的都必永存；無可增添，無可減少。神這樣行，是要人在祂面前敬畏祂。
3:15|ASV|That which is hath been long ago; and that which is to be hath long ago been: and God seeketh again that which is passed away.
3:15|Darby|That which is was long ago, and that which is to be hath  already been; and God bringeth back again that which is past.
3:15|KJV|That which hath been is now; and that which is to be hath already been; and God requireth that which is past.
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現今的事早先就有了，將來的事早已也有了，並且神使已過的事重新再來。
3:16|ASV|And moreover I saw under the sun, in the place of justice, that wickedness was there; and in the place of righteousness, that wickedness was there.
3:16|Darby|And moreover I saw under the sun, that in the place of  judgment, wickedness was there; and in the place of  righteousness, wickedness was there.
3:16|KJV|And moreover I saw under the sun the place of judgment, that wickedness was there; and the place of righteousness, that iniquity was there.
3:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我又見日光之下，在審判之處有奸惡，在公義之處也有奸惡。
3:17|ASV|I said in my heart, God will judge the righteous and the wicked; for there is a time there for every purpose and for every work.
3:17|Darby|I said in my heart, God will judge the righteous and the  wicked; for there is a time there for every purpose and for  every work.
3:17|KJV|I said in mine heart, God shall judge the righteous and the wicked: for there is a time there for every purpose and for every work.
3:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我心婸﹛A神必審判義人和惡人；因為在那堙A各樣事務，各樣工作，都有定時。
3:18|ASV|I said in my heart, It is because of the sons of men, that God may prove them, and that they may see that they themselves are but as beasts.
3:18|Darby|I said in my heart, It is thus with the children of men,  that God may prove them, and that they should see that they  themselves are but beasts.
3:18|KJV|I said in mine heart concerning the estate of the sons of men, that God might manifest them, and that they might see that they themselves are beasts.
3:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我心婸﹛A這乃為世人的緣故，是神要試驗他們，使他們看見自己不過像獸一樣。
3:19|ASV|For that which befalleth the sons of men befalleth beasts; even one thing befalleth them: as the one dieth, so dieth the other; yea, they have all one breath; and man hath no preeminence above the beasts: for all is vanity.
3:19|Darby|For what befalleth the children of men befalleth beasts;  even one thing befalleth them: as the one dieth, so dieth the  other, and they have all one breath; and man hath no  pre-eminence above the beast: for all is vanity.
3:19|KJV|For that which befalleth the sons of men befalleth beasts; even one thing befalleth them: as the one dieth, so dieth the other; yea, they have all one breath; so that a man hath no preeminence above a beast: for all is vanity.
3:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為世人遭遇的，獸也遭遇，二者所遭遇的都是一樣：這個怎樣死，那個也怎樣死，氣息都是一樣。人並不強於獸；因為都是虛空。
3:20|ASV|All go unto one place; all are of the dust, and all turn to dust again.
3:20|Darby|All go unto one place: all are of the dust, and all return  to dust.
3:20|KJV|All go unto one place; all are of the dust, and all turn to dust again.
3:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|都往一處去，都是出於塵土，也都歸於塵土。
3:21|ASV|Who knoweth the spirit of man, whether it goeth upward, and the spirit of the beast, whether it goeth downward to the earth?
3:21|Darby|Who knoweth the spirit of the children of men? Doth it go  upwards? and the spirit of the beasts, doth it go downwards to  the earth?
3:21|KJV|Who knoweth the spirit of man that goeth upward, and the spirit of the beast that goeth downward to the earth?
3:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|誰知道世人的氣是往上升，獸的氣是下入地呢？
3:22<version name="ASV">Wherefore I saw that there is nothing better, than that a man should rejoice in his works; for that is his portion: for who shall bring him back to see what shall be after him? </p><p /><br /></version>
3:22<version name="Darby">And I have seen that there is nothing better than that man  should rejoice in his own works; for that is his portion; for  who shall bring him to see what shall be after him? </p><p /><br /></version>
3:22<version name="KJV">Wherefore I perceive that there is nothing better, than that a man should rejoice in his own works; for that is his portion: for who shall bring him to see what shall be after him?</p><p /><br /></version>
3:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|故此，我見人莫強如在他所作的事上快樂，因為這是他的分。他身後的事，誰會領他來看呢？
4:1|ASV|Then I returned and saw all the oppressions that are done under the sun: and, behold, the tears of such as were oppressed, and they had no comforter; and on the side of their oppressors there was power; but they had no comforter.
4:1|Darby|And I returned and saw all the oppressions that are done  under the sun: and behold, the tears of the oppressed, and they  had no comforter; and on the side of their oppressors was  power, and they had no comforter.
4:1|KJV|So I returned, and considered all the oppressions that are done under the sun: and behold the tears of such as were oppressed, and they had no comforter; and on the side of their oppressors there was power; but they had no comforter.
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我又見日光之下所行的一切欺壓。看哪，受欺壓的流淚，無人安慰；欺壓他們的有勢力，也無人安慰他們。
4:2|ASV|Wherefore I praised the dead that have been long dead more than the living that are yet alive;
4:2|Darby|Then I praised the dead who are already dead more than the  living who are yet alive;
4:2|KJV|Wherefore I praised the dead which are already dead more than the living which are yet alive.
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此，我讚歎那早已死的死人，勝過那還活著的活人。
4:3|ASV|yea, better than them both did I esteem him that hath not yet been, who hath not seen the evil work that is done under the sun.
4:3|Darby|and more fortunate than both is he who hath not yet been,  who hath not seen the evil work that is done under the sun.
4:3|KJV|Yea, better is he than both they, which hath not yet been, who hath not seen the evil work that is done under the sun.
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且我以為那未曾生的，就是未見過日光之下惡事的，比這兩等人更好。
4:4|ASV|Then I saw all labor and every skilful work, that for this a man is envied of his neighbor. This also is vanity and a striving after wind.
4:4|Darby|And I saw all labour, and all success of work, that it is  man's jealousy of his neighbour. This also is vanity and  pursuit of the wind.
4:4|KJV|Again, I considered all travail, and every right work, that for this a man is envied of his neighbour. This is also vanity and vexation of spirit.
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我又見人一切的勞碌，和工作上各樣的技能，被鄰舍所嫉妒。這也是虛空，也是捕風。
4:5|ASV|The fool foldeth his hands together, and eateth his own flesh.
4:5|Darby|The fool foldeth his hands together, and eateth his own  flesh.
4:5|KJV|The fool foldeth his hands together, and eateth his own flesh.
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|愚昧人抱著手，喫自己的肉。
4:6|ASV|Better is a handful, with quietness, than two handfuls with labor and striving after wind.
4:6|Darby|Better is a handful with quietness, than both hands full  with labour and pursuit of the wind.
4:6|KJV|Better is an handful with quietness, than both the hands full with travail and vexation of spirit.
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|滿了一把，得享安靜，強如滿了兩把，勞碌捕風。
4:7|ASV|Then I returned and saw vanity under the sun.
4:7|Darby|And I returned and saw vanity under the sun.
4:7|KJV|Then I returned, and I saw vanity under the sun.
4:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我又見日光之下有一件虛空的事。
4:8|ASV|There is one that is alone, and he hath not a second; yea, he hath neither son nor brother; yet is there no end of all his labor, neither are his eyes satisfied with riches. For whom then, saith he, do I labor, and deprive my soul of good? This also is vanity, yea, it is a sore travail.
4:8|Darby|There is one [alone] and without a second; also he hath  neither son nor brother: yet is there no end of all his labour,  neither is his eye satisfied with riches, and [he saith not],  For whom then am I labouring, and depriving my soul of good?  This also is vanity and a grievous occupation.
4:8|KJV|There is one alone, and there is not a second; yea, he hath neither child nor brother: yet is there no end of all his labour; neither is his eye satisfied with riches; neither saith he, For whom do I labour, and bereave my soul of good? This is also vanity, yea, it is a sore travail.
4:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有人孤單無二，無子無兄，卻勞碌不息，眼目也不以財富為足。他說，我勞勞碌碌，刻苦自己，不享福樂，到底是為誰呢？這也是虛空，是極重的辛勞。
4:9|ASV|Two are better than one, because they have a good reward for their labor.
4:9|Darby|Two are better than one; because they have a good reward for  their labour.
4:9|KJV|Two are better than one; because they have a good reward for their labour.
4:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|兩個人總比一個人好，因為二人勞碌，可得美好的酬報；
4:10|ASV|For if they fall, the one will lift up his fellow; but woe to him that is alone when he falleth, and hath not another to lift him up.
4:10|Darby|For if they fall, the one will lift up his fellow; but woe  to him that is alone when he falleth, and who hath not another  to lift him up!
4:10|KJV|For if they fall, the one will lift up his fellow: but woe to him that is alone when he falleth; for he hath not another to help him up.
4:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若是跌倒，一人可以扶起他的同伴。若是孤身跌倒，沒有別人扶他起來，這人就有禍了！
4:11|ASV|Again, if two lie together, then they have warmth; but how can one be warm alone?
4:11|Darby|Again, if two lie together, then they have warmth; but how  can one alone be warm?
4:11|KJV|Again, if two lie together, then they have heat: but how can one be warm alone?
4:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|再者，二人同睡就都暖和，一人獨睡怎能暖和呢？
4:12|ASV|And if a man prevail against him that is alone, two shall withstand him; and a threefold cord is not quickly broken.
4:12|Darby|And if a [man] overpower the one, the two shall withstand  him; and a threefold cord is not quickly broken.
4:12|KJV|And if one prevail against him, two shall withstand him; and a threefold cord is not quickly broken.
4:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有人能打勝孤身一人，若有二人便能抵擋他；三股合成的繩子，不容易折斷。
4:13|ASV|Better is a poor and wise youth than an old and foolish king, who knoweth not how to receive admonition any more.
4:13|Darby|Better is a poor but wise youth than an old and foolish  king, who knoweth no more how to be admonished.
4:13|KJV|Better is a poor and a wise child than an old and foolish king, who will no more be admonished.
4:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|貧窮而有智慧的少年人，勝過年老不再納諫的愚昧王。
4:14|ASV|For out of prison he came forth to be king; yea, even in his kingdom he was born poor.
4:14|Darby|For out of the prison-house he came forth to reign,  although he was born poor in his kingdom.
4:14|KJV|For out of prison he cometh to reign; whereas also he that is born in his kingdom becometh poor.
4:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為人能從監牢中出來作王，雖然他在國中生來原是貧窮的。
4:15|ASV|I saw all the living that walk under the sun, that they were with the youth, the second, that stood up in his stead.
4:15|Darby|I saw all the living that walk under the sun, with the  child, the second, that should stand up in his stead.
4:15|KJV|I considered all the living which walk under the sun, with the second child that shall stand up in his stead.
4:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我見日光之下一切行動的活人都隨從那少年人，就是起來代替老王的繼承人。
4:16<version name="ASV">There was no end of all the people, even of all them over whom he was: yet they that come after shall not rejoice in him. Surely this also is vanity and a striving after wind. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:16<version name="Darby">[There is] no end of all the people, of all that stood  before them; those however that come after shall not rejoice in  him. Surely this also is vanity and a striving after the wind. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:16<version name="KJV">There is no end of all the people, even of all that have been before them: they also that come after shall not rejoice in him. Surely this also is vanity and vexation of spirit.</p><p /><br /></version>
4:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他所治理的眾人，就是他的百姓，多得無數；但後來的人並不喜悅他。這實在也是虛空，也是捕風。
5:1|ASV|Keep thy foot when thou goest to the house of God; for to draw nigh to hear is better than to give the sacrifice of fools: for they know not that they do evil.
5:1|Darby|Keep thy foot when thou goest to the house of God, and draw  near to hear, rather than to give the sacrifice of fools: for  they know not that they do evil.
5:1|KJV|Keep thy foot when thou goest to the house of God, and be more ready to hear, than to give the sacrifice of fools: for they consider not that they do evil.
5:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你到神的殿要謹慎腳步；近前聆聽，勝過愚昧人獻祭；因為他們不知道所作的是惡。
5:2|ASV|Be not rash with thy mouth, and let not thy heart be hasty to utter anything before God; for God is in heaven, and thou upon earth: therefore let thy words be few.
5:2|Darby|Be not rash with thy mouth, and let not thy heart be hasty  to utter anything before God: for God is in the heavens, and  thou upon earth; therefore let thy words be few.
5:2|KJV|Be not rash with thy mouth, and let not thine heart be hasty to utter any thing before God: for God is in heaven, and thou upon earth: therefore let thy words be few.
5:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你在神面前不可冒失開口，也不可心急發言；因為神在天上，你在地上，所以你的言語要寡少。
5:3|ASV|For a dream cometh with a multitude of business, and a fool's voice with a multitude of words.
5:3|Darby|For a dream cometh through the multitude of business, and a  fool's voice through a multitude of words.
5:3|KJV|For a dream cometh through the multitude of business; and a fool's voice is known by multitude of words.
5:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|煩擾多，令人作夢；言語多，顯出愚昧。
5:4|ASV|When thou vowest a vow unto God, defer not to pay it; for he hath no pleasure in fools: pay that which thou vowest.
5:4|Darby|When thou vowest a vow unto God, defer not to pay it; for he  hath no pleasure in fools: pay that which thou hast vowed.
5:4|KJV|When thou vowest a vow unto God, defer not to pay it; for he hath no pleasure in fools: pay that which thou hast vowed.
5:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你向神許願，償還不可遲延，因祂不喜悅愚昧人。你許了願，就當償還。
5:5|ASV|Better is it that thou shouldest not vow, than that thou shouldest vow and not pay.
5:5|Darby|Better is it that thou shouldest not vow, than that thou  shouldest vow and not pay.
5:5|KJV|Better is it that thou shouldest not vow, than that thou shouldest vow and not pay.
5:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你許願不還，不如不許。
5:6|ASV|Suffer not thy mouth to cause thy flesh to sin; neither say thou before the angel, that is was an error: wherefore should God be angry at thy voice, and destroy the work of thy hands?
5:6|Darby|Suffer not thy mouth to cause thy flesh to sin; neither say  thou before the angel, that it was an inadvertence. Wherefore  should God be wroth at thy voice, and destroy the work of thy  hands?
5:6|KJV|Suffer not thy mouth to cause thy flesh to sin; neither say thou before the angel, that it was an error: wherefore should God be angry at thy voice, and destroy the work of thine hands?
5:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不可任你的口使肉體犯罪，也不可在使者面前說是錯許了。為何使神因你的聲音發怒，敗壞你手所作的呢？
5:7|ASV|For in the multitude of dreams there are vanities, and in many words: but fear thou God.
5:7|Darby|For in the multitude of dreams are vanities; so with many  words: but fear God.
5:7|KJV|For in the multitude of dreams and many words there are also divers vanities: but fear thou God.
5:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|多夢和多言，其中也都是虛空；你只要敬畏神。
5:8|ASV|If thou seest the oppression of the poor, and the violent taking away of justice and righteousness in a province, marvel not at the matter: for one higher than the high regardeth; and there are higher than they.
5:8|Darby|If thou seest the oppression of the poor, and violent  perverting of judgment and justice in a province, marvel not at  the matter; for a higher than the high is watching, and there  are higher than they.
5:8|KJV|If thou seest the oppression of the poor, and violent perverting of judgment and justice in a province, marvel not at the matter: for he that is higher than the highest regardeth; and there be higher than they.
5:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你若在一省之中見窮人受欺壓，公義和公理被奪去，不要因此詫異；因有一位高過居高位的在鑒察；在他們以上還有更高的。
5:9|ASV|Moreover the profit of the earth is for all: the king himself is served by the field.
5:9|Darby|Moreover the earth is every way profitable: the king  [himself] is dependent upon the field.
5:9|KJV|Moreover the profit of the earth is for all: the king himself is served by the field.
5:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|君王注重田地的耕種，對國總是有益。
5:10|ASV|He that loveth silver shall not be satisfied with silver; nor he that loveth abundance, with increase: this also is vanity.
5:10|Darby|He that loveth silver shall not be satisfied with silver,  nor he that loveth abundance with increase. This also is  vanity.
5:10|KJV|He that loveth silver shall not be satisfied with silver; nor he that loveth abundance with increase: this is also vanity.
5:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|愛銀子的，不因得銀子知足；愛豐富的，也不因有收入知足。這也是虛空。
5:11|ASV|When goods increase, they are increased that eat them; and what advantage is there to the owner thereof, save the beholding of them with his eyes?
5:11|Darby|When goods increase, they are increased that eat them; and  what profit is there to the owner thereof, except the beholding  [of them] with his eyes?
5:11|KJV|When goods increase, they are increased that eat them: and what good is there to the owners thereof, saving the beholding of them with their eyes?
5:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|貨物增多，喫的人也增多，物主得甚麼益處呢？不過眼看而已。
5:12|ASV|The sleep of a laboring man is sweet, whether he eat little or much; but the fulness of the rich will not suffer him to sleep.
5:12|Darby|The sleep of the labourer is sweet, whether he have eaten  little or much; but the fulness of the rich doth not suffer him  to sleep.
5:12|KJV|The sleep of a labouring man is sweet, whether he eat little or much: but the abundance of the rich will not suffer him to sleep.
5:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|勞力的人不拘喫多喫少，睡得香甜；富足人的豐足，卻不容他睡覺。
5:13|ASV|There is a grievous evil which I have seen under the sun, namely, riches kept by the owner thereof to his hurt:
5:13|Darby|There is a grievous evil that I have seen under the sun:  riches kept for the owners thereof to their hurt;
5:13|KJV|There is a sore evil which I have seen under the sun, namely, riches kept for the owners thereof to their hurt.
5:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我見日光之下有一大禍患，就是財主守住財富，反害自己。
5:14|ASV|and those riches perish by evil adventure; and if he hath begotten a son, there is nothing in his hand.
5:14|Darby|or those riches perish by some evil circumstance, and if he  have begotten a son, there is nothing in his hand.
5:14|KJV|But those riches perish by evil travail: and he begetteth a son, and there is nothing in his hand.
5:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因生意不順，這些財富就喪失；那人若生了兒子，手堣]一無所有。
5:15|ASV|As he came forth from his mother's womb, naked shall he go again as he came, and shall take nothing for his labor, which he may carry away in his hand.
5:15|Darby|As he came forth from his mother's womb, naked shall he go  away again as he came, and shall take nothing of his labour,  which he may carry away in his hand.
5:15|KJV|As he came forth of his mother's womb, naked shall he return to go as he came, and shall take nothing of his labour, which he may carry away in his hand.
5:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他怎樣出母腹赤身而來，也必照樣赤身而去；他所勞碌得來的，手中分毫不能帶去。
5:16|ASV|And this also is a grievous evil, that in all points as he came, so shall he go: and what profit hath he that he laboreth for the wind?
5:16|Darby|And this also is a grievous evil, that in all points as he  came so doth he go away, and what profit hath he, in having  laboured for the wind?
5:16|KJV|And this also is a sore evil, that in all points as he came, so shall he go: and what profit hath he that hath laboured for the wind?
5:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他來的情形怎樣，他去的情形也怎樣，這也是一大禍患；他為風勞碌有甚麼益處呢？
5:17|ASV|All his days also he eateth in darkness, and he is sore vexed, and hath sickness and wrath.
5:17|Darby|All his days also he eateth in darkness, and hath much  vexation, and sickness, and irritation.
5:17|KJV|All his days also he eateth in darkness, and he hath much sorrow and wrath with his sickness.
5:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他終身在黑暗中喫喝，多有煩惱、病痛、憤怨。
5:18|ASV|Behold, that which I have seen to be good and to be comely is for one to eat and to drink, and to enjoy good in all his labor, wherein he laboreth under the sun, all the days of his life which God hath given him: for this is his portion.
5:18|Darby|Behold what I have seen good and comely: [it is] to eat and  to drink, and to enjoy good in all his labour wherewith [man]  laboureth under the sun, all the days of his life which God  hath given him: for that is his portion.
5:18|KJV|Behold that which I have seen: it is good and comely for one to eat and to drink, and to enjoy the good of all his labour that he taketh under the sun all the days of his life, which God giveth him: for it is his portion.
5:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我所見為善為美的，就是人在神賜他一生有數的日子喫喝，在日光之下一切勞碌中享美福，因為這是他的分。
5:19|ASV|Every man also to whom God hath given riches and wealth, and hath given him power to eat thereof, and to take his portion, and to rejoice in his labor-this is the gift of God.
5:19|Darby|Every man also to whom God hath given riches and wealth,  and power to eat thereof, and to take his portion and to  rejoice in his labour: that is a gift of God.
5:19|KJV|Every man also to whom God hath given riches and wealth, and hath given him power to eat thereof, and to take his portion, and to rejoice in his labour; this is the gift of God.
5:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神賜各人貲財豐富，使他能以喫用，能取自己的分，在他勞碌中快樂，這乃是神的恩賜。
5:20<version name="ASV">For he shall not much remember the days of his life; because God answereth him in the joy of his heart. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:20<version name="Darby">For he will not much remember the days of his life, because  God answereth [him] with the joy of his heart. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:20<version name="KJV">For he shall not much remember the days of his life; because God answereth him in the joy of his heart.</p><p /><br /></version>
5:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他不多思念自己一生的日子，因為神使他的心忙於享樂。
6:1|ASV|There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, and it is heavy upon men:
6:1|Darby|There is an evil that I have seen under the sun, and it is  frequent among men:
6:1|KJV|There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, and it is common among men:
6:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我見日光之下有一禍患，重壓在人身上，
6:2|ASV|a man to whom God giveth riches, wealth, and honor, so that he lacketh nothing for his soul of all that he desireth, yet God giveth him not power to eat thereof, but an alien eateth it; this is vanity, and it is an evil disease.
6:2|Darby|one to whom God giveth riches, wealth, and honour, and he  wanteth nothing for his soul of all that he desireth, yet God  giveth him not power to eat thereof, but a stranger eateth it:  this is vanity, and a sore evil.
6:2|KJV|A man to whom God hath given riches, wealth, and honour, so that he wanteth nothing for his soul of all that he desireth, yet God giveth him not power to eat thereof, but a stranger eateth it: this is vanity, and it is an evil disease.
6:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就是人蒙神賜他貲財、豐富、尊榮，以致他心堜痁@的一樣都不缺，只是神使他不能喫用，反有外人來喫用。這是虛空，也是大禍患。
6:3|ASV|If a man beget a hundred children, and live many years, so that the days of his years are many, but his soul be not filled with good, and moreover he have no burial; I say, that an untimely birth is better than he:
6:3|Darby|If a man beget a hundred [sons], and live many years, so  that the days of his years be many, but his soul be not filled  with good, and also he have no burial, I say an untimely birth  is better than he.
6:3|KJV|If a man beget an hundred children, and live many years, so that the days of his years be many, and his soul be not filled with good, and also that he have no burial; I say, that an untimely birth is better than he.
6:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人若生一百個兒女，活許多歲數，以致他的年日甚多，心堳o不得滿享福樂，又不得安葬；我就說，那不到期而落的胎比他倒好；
6:4|ASV|for it cometh in vanity, and departeth in darkness, and the name thereof is covered with darkness;
6:4|Darby|For it cometh in vanity, and departeth in darkness, and its  name is covered with darkness;
6:4|KJV|For he cometh in with vanity, and departeth in darkness, and his name shall be covered with darkness.
6:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為這胎虛虛而來，暗暗而去，名字被黑暗遮蔽；
6:5|ASV|moreover it hath not seen the sun nor known it; this hath rest rather than the other:
6:5|Darby|moreover it hath not seen nor known the sun: this hath rest  rather than the other.
6:5|KJV|Moreover he hath not seen the sun, nor known any thing: this hath more rest than the other.
6:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且沒有見過天日，也毫無知覺；這胎比那人倒享安息。
6:6|ASV|yea, though he live a thousand years twice told, and yet enjoy no good, do not all go to one place?
6:6|Darby|Yea, though he live twice a thousand years, yet hath he seen  no good: do not all go to one place?
6:6|KJV|Yea, though he live a thousand years twice told, yet hath he seen no good: do not all go to one place?
6:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那人即使活千年，再活千年，卻不得享美福，眾人豈不都歸一個地方去麼？
6:7|ASV|All the labor of man is for his mouth, and yet the appetite is not filled.
6:7|Darby|All the labour of man is for his mouth, and yet the appetite  is not filled.
6:7|KJV|All the labour of man is for his mouth, and yet the appetite is not filled.
6:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人的勞碌都是為口腹，口慾卻不滿足。
6:8|ASV|For what advantage hath the wise more than the fool? or what hath the poor man, that knoweth how to walk before the living?
6:8|Darby|For what advantage hath the wise above the fool? what hath  the poor, that knoweth to walk before the living?
6:8|KJV|For what hath the wise more than the fool? what hath the poor, that knoweth to walk before the living?
6:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|智慧人比愚昧人有甚麼長處呢？窮人在活人面前知道如何行，有甚麼長處呢？
6:9|ASV|Better is the sight of the eyes than the wandering of the desire: this also is vanity and a striving after wind.
6:9|Darby|Better is the seeing of the eyes than the wandering of the  desire: this also is vanity and pursuit of the wind.
6:9|KJV|Better is the sight of the eyes than the wandering of the desire: this is also vanity and vexation of spirit.
6:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|眼睛看見，比心埵k想要好。這也是虛空，也是捕風。
6:10|ASV|Whatsoever hath been, the name thereof was given long ago; and it is know what man is; neither can he contend with him that is mightier than he.
6:10|Darby|That which is hath already been named; and what man is, is  known, and that he cannot contend with him that is mightier  than he.
6:10|KJV|That which hath been is named already, and it is known that it is man: neither may he contend with him that is mightier than he.
6:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現今有的，早已命定了；大家都知道人是怎樣，他不能與那比自己力大的相爭。
6:11|ASV|Seeing there are many things that increase vanity, what is man the better?
6:11|Darby|For there are many things that increase vanity: what is man  advantaged?
6:11|KJV|Seeing there be many things that increase vanity, what is man the better?
6:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|加增虛空的事既多，這與人有甚麼益處呢？
6:12<version name="ASV">For who knoweth what is good for man in his life, all the days of his vain life which he spendeth as a shadow? for who can tell a man what shall be after him under the sun? </p><p /><br /></version>
6:12<version name="Darby">For who knoweth what is good for man in life, all the days  of his vain life which he spendeth as a shadow? for who can  tell man what shall be after him under the sun? </p><p /><br /></version>
6:12<version name="KJV">For who knoweth what is good for man in this life, all the days of his vain life which he spendeth as a shadow? for who can tell a man what shall be after him under the sun?</p><p /><br /></version>
6:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人一生虛度的日子，如同影兒經過，誰知道一生中甚麼與他有益呢？誰能告訴人身後在日光之下有甚麼事呢？
7:1|ASV|A good name is better than precious oil; and the day of death, than the day of one's birth.
7:1|Darby|A [good] name is better than precious ointment, and the day  of death than the day of one's birth.
7:1|KJV|A good name is better than precious ointment; and the day of death than the day of one's birth.
7:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|名譽強如貴重的膏油；人死的日子勝過出生的日子。
7:2|ASV|It is better to go to the house of mourning than to go to the house of feasting: for that is the end of all men; and the living will lay it to his heart.
7:2|Darby|It is better to go to the house of mourning than to go to  the house of feasting: in that that is the end of all men, and  the living taketh it to heart.
7:2|KJV|It is better to go to the house of mourning, than to go to the house of feasting: for that is the end of all men; and the living will lay it to his heart.
7:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|往遭喪的家去，強如往宴樂的家去；因為死是眾人的結局，活人必將這事放在心上。
7:3|ASV|Sorrow is better than laughter; for by the sadness of the countenance the heart is made glad.
7:3|Darby|Vexation is better than laughter; for by the sadness of the  countenance the heart is made better.
7:3|KJV|Sorrow is better than laughter: for by the sadness of the countenance the heart is made better.
7:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|憂愁強如喜笑；因為愁容使心得益處。
7:4|ASV|The heart of the wise is in the house of mourning; but the heart of fools is in the house of mirth.
7:4|Darby|The heart of the wise is in the house of mourning, but the  heart of fools in the house of mirth.
7:4|KJV|The heart of the wise is in the house of mourning; but the heart of fools is in the house of mirth.
7:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|智慧人的心在遭喪之家；愚昧人的心在快樂之家。
7:5|ASV|It is better to hear the rebuke of the wise, than for a man to hear the song of fools.
7:5|Darby|It is better for a man to hear the rebuke of the wise, than  to hear the song of fools.
7:5|KJV|It is better to hear the rebuke of the wise, than for a man to hear the song of fools.
7:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|聽智慧人的責備，強如聽愚昧人的歌唱。
7:6|ASV|For as the crackling of thorns under a pot, so is the laughter of the fool: this also is vanity.
7:6|Darby|For as the crackling of thorns under a pot, so is the  laughter of the fool. This also is vanity.
7:6|KJV|For as the crackling of thorns under a pot, so is the laughter of the fool: this also is vanity.
7:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|愚昧人的笑聲，好像鍋下燒荊棘的爆聲；這也是虛空。
7:7|ASV|Surely extortion maketh the wise man foolish; and a bribe destroyeth the understanding.
7:7|Darby|Surely oppression maketh a wise man mad, and a gift  destroyeth the heart.
7:7|KJV|Surely oppression maketh a wise man mad; and a gift destroyeth the heart.
7:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|欺壓會使智慧人狂妄；賄賂能敗壞人心。
7:8|ASV|Better is the end of a thing than the beginning thereof; and the patient in spirit is better than the proud in spirit.
7:8|Darby|Better is the end of a thing than its beginning; better is a  patient spirit than a proud spirit.
7:8|KJV|Better is the end of a thing than the beginning thereof: and the patient in spirit is better than the proud in spirit.
7:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|事情的終局，強如事情的起頭；靈塈埻@，勝過靈堸甽ヾC
7:9|ASV|Be not hasty in thy spirit to be angry; for anger resteth in the bosom of fools.
7:9|Darby|Be not hasty in thy spirit to be vexed; for vexation resteth  in the bosom of fools.
7:9|KJV|Be not hasty in thy spirit to be angry: for anger resteth in the bosom of fools.
7:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你不要靈堳磑撈o怒，因為惱怒存在愚昧人的懷中。
7:10|ASV|Say not thou, What is the cause that the former days were better than these? for thou dost not inquire wisely concerning this.
7:10|Darby|Say not, How is it that the former days were better than  these? for thou dost not inquire wisely concerning this.
7:10|KJV|Say not thou, What is the cause that the former days were better than these? for thou dost not enquire wisely concerning this.
7:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不要說，為何先前的日子強過如今的日子呢？你這樣問，不是出於智慧。
7:11|ASV|Wisdom is as good as an inheritance; yea, more excellent is it for them that see the sun.
7:11|Darby|Wisdom is as good as an inheritance, and profitable to them  that see the sun.
7:11|KJV|Wisdom is good with an inheritance: and by it there is profit to them that see the sun.
7:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|智慧和基業都是好的，對得見天日的人乃是益處。
7:12|ASV|For wisdom is a defence, even as money is a defence; but the excellency of knowledge is, that wisdom preserveth the life of him that hath it.
7:12|Darby|For wisdom is a defence [as] money is a defence; but the  excellency of knowledge is, [that] wisdom maketh them that  possess it to live.
7:12|KJV|For wisdom is a defence, and money is a defence: but the excellency of knowledge is, that wisdom giveth life to them that have it.
7:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為智慧護庇人，好像銀錢護庇人一樣。惟獨智慧能保全智慧人的生命；這就是知識的益處。
7:13|ASV|Consider the work of God: for who can make that straight, which he hath made crooked?
7:13|Darby|Consider the work of God; for who can make straight what he  hath made crooked?
7:13|KJV|Consider the work of God: for who can make that straight, which he hath made crooked?
7:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要察看神的作為；因神所彎曲的，誰能變為直呢？
7:14|ASV|In the day of prosperity be joyful, and in the day of adversity consider; yea, God hath made the one side by side with the other, to the end that man should not find out anything  that shall be after him.
7:14|Darby|In the day of prosperity enjoy good, and in the day of  adversity consider: God hath also set the one beside the other,  to the end that man should find out nothing [of what shall be]  after him.
7:14|KJV|In the day of prosperity be joyful, but in the day of adversity consider: God also hath set the one over against the other, to the end that man should find nothing after him.
7:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|遇亨通的日子，你當喜樂；遭患難的日子，你當思想；神造了這樣，也造了那樣，為叫人查不出身後有甚麼事。
7:15|ASV|All this have I seen in my days of vanity: there is a righteous man that perisheth in his righteousness, and there is a wicked man that prolongeth his life in his evil-doing.
7:15|Darby|All [this] have I seen in the days of my vanity: there is a  righteous [man] that perisheth by his righteousness, and there  is a wicked [man] that prolongeth [his days] by his wickedness.
7:15|KJV|All things have I seen in the days of my vanity: there is a just man that perisheth in his righteousness, and there is a wicked man that prolongeth his life in his wickedness.
7:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在虛度的日子中見過一切的事：有義人在自己的義中滅亡；有惡人在自己的惡中享長壽。
7:16|ASV|Be not righteous overmuch; neither make thyself overwise: why shouldest thou destroy thyself?
7:16|Darby|Be not righteous overmuch; neither make thyself overwise:  why shouldest thou destroy thyself?
7:16|KJV|Be not righteous over much; neither make thyself over wise: why shouldest thou destroy thyself ?
7:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不要行義過分，也不要過於自逞智慧，何必自取敗亡呢？
7:17|ASV|Be not overmuch wicked, neither be thou foolish: why shouldest thou die before thy time?
7:17|Darby|Be not overmuch wicked, neither be thou foolish: why  shouldest thou die before thy time?
7:17|KJV|Be not over much wicked, neither be thou foolish: why shouldest thou die before thy time?
7:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不要行惡過分，也不要作愚昧人，何必不到期而死呢？
7:18|ASV|It is good that thou shouldest take hold of this; yea, also from that withdraw not thy hand: for he that feareth God shall come forth from them all.
7:18|Darby|It is good that thou shouldest take hold of this; yea, also  from that withdraw not thy hand: for he that feareth God cometh  forth from them all.
7:18|KJV|It is good that thou shouldest take hold of this; yea, also from this withdraw not thine hand: for he that feareth God shall come forth of them all.
7:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你最好持住這個，那個也不要放鬆；因為敬畏神的人，必全都兼顧。
7:19|ASV|Wisdom is a strength to the wise man more than ten rulers that are in a city.
7:19|Darby|Wisdom strengtheneth the wise more than ten mighty [men]  that are in a city.
7:19|KJV|Wisdom strengtheneth the wise more than ten mighty men which are in the city.
7:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|智慧使有智慧的人，比城中十個掌權的人更有能力。
7:20|ASV|Surely there is not a righteous man upon earth, that doeth good, and sinneth not.
7:20|Darby|Surely there is not a righteous man upon earth, that doeth  good and sinneth not.
7:20|KJV|For there is not a just man upon earth, that doeth good, and sinneth not.
7:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|行善而不犯罪的義人，地上實在沒有。
7:21|ASV|Also take not heed unto all words that are spoken, lest thou hear thy servant curse thee;
7:21|Darby|Also give not heed unto all words that are spoken, lest  thou hear thy servant curse thee.
7:21|KJV|Also take no heed unto all words that are spoken; lest thou hear thy servant curse thee:
7:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人所說的一切話，你不要放在心上，恐怕聽見你的僕人咒詛你。
7:22|ASV|for oftentimes also thine own heart knoweth that thou thyself likewise hast cursed others.
7:22|Darby|For also thine own heart knoweth that oftentimes thou  thyself likewise hast cursed others.
7:22|KJV|For oftentimes also thine own heart knoweth that thou thyself likewise hast cursed others.
7:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為你心堛器D，自己也曾多次咒詛別人。
7:23|ASV|All this have I proved in wisdom: I said, I will be wise; but it was far from me.
7:23|Darby|All this have I tried by wisdom: I said, I will be wise;  but it was far from me.
7:23|KJV|All this have I proved by wisdom: I said, I will be wise; but it was far from me.
7:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我曾用智慧試驗這一切事；我說，我要有智慧，智慧卻離我遠。
7:24|ASV|That which is, is far off and exceeding deep; who can find it out?
7:24|Darby|Whatever hath been, is far off, and exceeding deep: who  will find it out?
7:24|KJV|That which is far off, and exceeding deep, who can find it out?
7:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|已有的事離我甚遠，深而又深，誰能測透呢？
7:25|ASV|I turned about, and my heart was set to know and to search out, and to seek wisdom and the reason of things, and to know that wickedness is folly, and that foolishness is madness.
7:25|Darby|I turned, I and my heart, to know, and to search, and to  seek out wisdom and reason, and to know wickedness to be folly,  and foolishness to be madness;
7:25|KJV|I applied mine heart to know, and to search, and to seek out wisdom, and the reason of things, and to know the wickedness of folly, even of foolishness and madness:
7:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我轉念，一心要知道，要查究，要尋求智慧和事理；又要知道邪惡為愚昧，愚昧為狂妄。
7:26|ASV|And I find more bitter than death the woman whose heart is snares and nets, and whose hands are bands: whoso pleaseth God shall escape from her; but the sinner shall be taken by her.
7:26|Darby|and I found more bitter than death the woman whose heart is  nets and snares, [and] whose hands are bands: whoso pleaseth  God shall escape from her; but the sinner shall be caught by  her.
7:26|KJV|And I find more bitter than death the woman, whose heart is snares and nets, and her hands as bands: whoso pleaseth God shall escape from her; but the sinner shall be taken by her.
7:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我發現有一等婦人比死還苦毒：她的心是陷阱網羅，手是鎖鍊。蒙神喜悅的人必躲避她；有罪的人卻被她纏住。
7:27|ASV|Behold, this have I found, saith the Preacher, laying one thing to another, to find out the account;
7:27|Darby|See this which I have found, saith the Preacher,  [searching] one by one to find out the reason;
7:27|KJV|Behold, this have I found, saith the preacher, counting one by one, to find out the account:
7:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|傳道者說，看哪，這是我發現的；我逐一推算，要找出事理，
7:28|ASV|which my soul still seeketh, but I have not found: one man among a thousand have I found; but a woman among all those have I not found.
7:28|Darby|which my soul yet seeketh, and I have not found: one man  among a thousand have I found, but a woman among all those have  I not found.
7:28|KJV|Which yet my soul seeketh, but I find not: one man among a thousand have I found; but a woman among all those have I not found.
7:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我心仍在尋找，卻未尋到。在一千人中，我尋到一個正直人，但在這些人中，卻尋不到一個婦人。
7:29<version name="ASV">Behold, this only have I found: that God made man upright; but they have sought out many inventions. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:29<version name="Darby">Only see this which I have found: that God made man  upright, but they have sought out many devices. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:29<version name="KJV">Lo, this only have I found, that God hath made man upright; but they have sought out many inventions.</p><p /><br /></version>
7:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|看哪，我所找到的只有一件，就是神將人造得正直，但他們卻尋出許多巧計。
8:1|ASV|Who is as the wise man? and who knoweth the interpretation of a thing? A man's wisdom maketh his face to shine, and the hardness of his face is changed.
8:1|Darby|Who is as the wise? and who knoweth the explanation of  things? A man's wisdom maketh his face to shine, and the  boldness of his face is changed.
8:1|KJV|Who is as the wise man? and who knoweth the interpretation of a thing? a man's wisdom maketh his face to shine, and the boldness of his face shall be changed.
8:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|誰如智慧人呢？誰知道事情的解釋呢？人的智慧使他的臉發光，並使他臉上的戾氣改變。
8:2|ASV|I  counsel thee, Keep the king's command, and that in regard of the oath of God.
8:2|Darby|I [say], Keep the king's commandment, and [that] on account  of the oath of God.
8:2|KJV|I counsel thee to keep the king's commandment, and that in regard of the oath of God.
8:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我勸你遵守王的命令；因為這是你在神前起的誓。
8:3|ASV|Be not hasty to go out of his presence; persist not in an evil thing: for he doeth whatsoever pleaseth him.
8:3|Darby|Be not hasty to go out of his sight; persist not in an evil  thing: for he doeth whatever pleaseth him,
8:3|KJV|Be not hasty to go out of his sight: stand not in an evil thing; for he doeth whatsoever pleaseth him.
8:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不要急著離開王的面前，不要參與惡事，因為凡王所喜悅的事，他都要行。
8:4|ASV|For the king's word hath power; and who may say unto him, What doest thou?
8:4|Darby|because the word of a king is power; and who may say unto  him, What doest thou?
8:4|KJV|Where the word of a king is, there is power: and who may say unto him, What doest thou?
8:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王的話本有權力，誰會問他說，你在作甚麼呢？
8:5|ASV|Whoso keepeth the commandment shall know no evil thing; and a wise man's heart discerneth time and judgment:
8:5|Darby|Whoso keepeth the commandment shall know no evil thing; and  a wise man's heart knoweth time and manner.
8:5|KJV|Whoso keepeth the commandment shall feel no evil thing: and a wise man's heart discerneth both time and judgment.
8:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡遵守命令的，必不經歷禍患；智慧人的心能曉得時機和定例。
8:6|ASV|for to every purpose there is a time and judgment; because the misery of man is great upon him:
8:6|Darby|For to every purpose there is time and manner. For the  misery of man is great upon him;
8:6|KJV|Because to every purpose there is time and judgment, therefore the misery of man is great upon him.
8:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|各樣事務成就都有時機和定例，縱然人的苦難重壓在他身上；
8:7|ASV|for he knoweth not that which shall be; for who can tell him how it shall be?
8:7|Darby|for he knoweth not that which shall be; for who can tell him  how it shall be?
8:7|KJV|For he knoweth not that which shall be: for who can tell him when it shall be?
8:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他不知道將來的事，因為將來如何，誰能告訴他呢？
8:8|ASV|There is no man that hath power over the spirit to retain the spirit; neither hath he power over the day of death; and there is no discharge in war: neither shall wickedness deliver him that is given to it.
8:8|Darby|There is no man who hath control over the spirit to retain  the spirit; and no one hath control over the day of death; and  there is no discharge in that war, neither shall wickedness  deliver those that are given to it.
8:8|KJV|There is no man that hath power over the spirit to retain the spirit; neither hath he power in the day of death: and there is no discharge in that war; neither shall wickedness deliver those that are given to it.
8:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|無人有權力掌管氣息，將氣息留住；也無人有權力掌管死期；在爭戰時，無人能免役，邪惡也不能救自己的主人。
8:9|ASV|All this have I seen, and applied my heart unto every work that is done under the sun: there is a time wherein one man hath power over another to his hurt.
8:9|Darby|All this have I seen, and applied my heart unto every work  that is done under the sun: there is a time when man ruleth man  to his hurt.
8:9|KJV|All this have I seen, and applied my heart unto every work that is done under the sun: there is a time wherein one man ruleth over another to his own hurt.
8:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這一切我都見過，也專心查考日光之下所作的一切事；有時這人管轄那人，使他受害。
8:10|ASV|So I saw the wicked buried, and they came to the grave; and they that had done right went away from the holy place, and were forgotten in the city: this also is vanity.
8:10|Darby|And I have also seen the wicked buried and going away; and  such as had acted rightly went from [the] holy place, and were  forgotten in the city. This also is vanity.
8:10|KJV|And so I saw the wicked buried, who had come and gone from the place of the holy, and they were forgotten in the city where they had so done: this is also vanity.
8:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然後我見惡人得以埋葬，他們生前進入並離開聖處，卻在他們這樣行的城中被人忘記。這也是虛空。
8:11|ASV|Because sentence against an evil work is not executed speedily, therefore the heart of the sons of men is fully set in them to do evil.
8:11|Darby|Because sentence against an evil work is not executed  speedily, therefore the heart of the children of men is fully  set in them to do evil.
8:11|KJV|Because sentence against an evil work is not executed speedily, therefore the heart of the sons of men is fully set in them to do evil.
8:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為對惡事的判決不立刻執行，所以世人滿心作惡。
8:12|ASV|Though a sinner do evil a hundred times, and prolong his days, yet surely I know that it shall be well with them that fear God, that fear before him:
8:12|Darby|Though a sinner do evil a hundred times, and prolong his  [days], yet I know that it shall be well with them that fear  God, because they fear before him;
8:12|KJV|Though a sinner do evil an hundred times, and his days be prolonged, yet surely I know that it shall be well with them that fear God, which fear before him:
8:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|罪人雖然作惡百次，倒享長壽；然而我也知道，敬畏神的，就是在祂面前敬畏的人，終久必得福樂。
8:13|ASV|but it shall not be well with the wicked, neither shall he prolong his days, which are as a shadow; because he feareth not before God.
8:13|Darby|but it shall not be well with the wicked, neither shall he  prolong [his] days as a shadow, because he feareth not before  God.
8:13|KJV|But it shall not be well with the wicked, neither shall he prolong his days, which are as a shadow; because he feareth not before God.
8:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|惡人卻不得福樂，也不得享長壽；他的日子好像影兒，因他在神面前不存敬畏。
8:14|ASV|There is a vanity which is done upon the earth, that there are righteous men unto whom it happeneth according to the work of the wicked; again, there are wicked men to whom it happeneth according to the work of the righteous: I said that this also is vanity.
8:14|Darby|There is a vanity which is done upon the earth; that there  are righteous [men] unto whom it happeneth according to the  work of the wicked; and there are wicked [men] to whom it  happeneth according to the work of the righteous. I said that  this also is vanity.
8:14|KJV|There is a vanity which is done upon the earth; that there be just men, unto whom it happeneth according to the work of the wicked; again, there be wicked men, to whom it happeneth according to the work of the righteous: I said that this also is vanity.
8:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|地上有一件虛空的事，就是義人照惡人所行的遭報，又有惡人照義人所行的遭報。我說，這也是虛空。
8:15|ASV|Then I commended mirth, because a man hath no better thing under the sun, than to eat, and to drink, and to be joyful: for that shall abide with him in his labor all the days of his life which God hath given him under the sun.
8:15|Darby|And I commended mirth, because there is nothing better for  man under the sun than to eat, and to drink, and to be merry;  for that shall abide with him of his labour the days of his  life, which God hath given him under the sun.
8:15|KJV|Then I commended mirth, because a man hath no better thing under the sun, than to eat, and to drink, and to be merry: for that shall abide with him of his labour the days of his life, which God giveth him under the sun.
8:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我就稱讚快樂，原來人在日光之下，莫強如喫喝快樂；因為在日光之下神所賜他一生的日子堙A這必在他的勞碌中，時常伴隨他。
8:16|ASV|When I applied my heart to know wisdom, and to see the business that is done upon the earth (for also there is that neither day nor night seeth sleep with his eyes),
8:16|Darby|When I applied my heart to know wisdom, and to see the  business that is done upon the earth (for also there is that  neither day nor night seeth sleep with his eyes),
8:16|KJV|When I applied mine heart to know wisdom, and to see the business that is done upon the earth: (for also there is that neither day nor night seeth sleep with his eyes:)
8:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我專心要認識智慧，要看地上所作一切辛勞的事。（有晝夜不睡覺不合眼的。）
8:17<version name="ASV">then I beheld all the work of God, that man cannot find out the work that is done under the sun: because however much a man labor to seek it out, yet he shall not find it; yea moreover, though a wise man think to know it, yet shall he not be able to find it. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:17<version name="Darby">then I saw that all [is] the work of God, [and] that man  cannot find out the work that is done under the sun: because  however man may labour to seek [it] out, yet doth he not find  [it]; and even, if a wise [man] think to know [it], he shall  not be able to find [it] out. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:17<version name="KJV">Then I beheld all the work of God, that a man cannot find out the work that is done under the sun: because though a man labour to seek it out, yet he shall not find it; yea farther; though a wise man think to know it, yet shall he not be able to find it.</p><p /><br /></version>
8:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我就看明神一切的作為，知道人查不出日光之下所作的事；因為任憑人勞碌尋索，都找不出來；智慧人雖說他必知道，也找不出來。
9:1|ASV|For all this I laid to my heart, even to explore all this: that the righteous, and the wise, and their works, are in the hand of God; whether it be love or hatred, man knoweth it not; all is before them.
9:1|Darby|For all this I laid to my heart and [indeed] to investigate  all this, that the righteous, and the wise, and their works,  are in the hand of God; man knoweth neither love nor hatred:  all is before them.
9:1|KJV|For all this I considered in my heart even to declare all this, that the righteous, and the wise, and their works, are in the hand of God: no man knoweth either love or hatred by all that is before them.
9:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我將這一切事放在心上，詳細考究，就看明義人和智慧人，並他們的作為，都在神手中；或是愛，或是恨，人不能知道；一切都在他們的前面。
9:2|ASV|All things come alike to all: there is one event to the righteous and to the wicked; to the good and to the clean and to the unclean; to him that sacrificeth and to him that sacrificeth not; as is the good, so is the sinner; and he that sweareth, as he that feareth an oath.
9:2|Darby|All things [come] alike to all: one event to the righteous  and to the wicked, to the good, and to the clean, and to the  unclean, to him that sacrificeth and to him that sacrificeth  not: as is the good, so is the sinner; he that sweareth, as he  that feareth an oath.
9:2|KJV|All things come alike to all: there is one event to the righteous, and to the wicked; to the good and to the clean, and to the unclean; to him that sacrificeth, and to him that sacrificeth not: as is the good, so is the sinner; and he that sweareth, as he that feareth an oath.
9:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡臨到眾人的事都是一樣：義人和惡人，好人、潔淨人和不潔淨人，獻祭的和不獻祭的，所遭遇的都是一樣。好人如何，罪人也如何；起誓的如何，怕起誓的也如何。
9:3|ASV|This is an evil in all that is done under the sun, that there is one event unto all: yea also, the heart of the sons of men is full of evil, and madness is in their heart while they live, and after that they go to the dead.
9:3|Darby|This is an evil among all that is done under the sun, that  one thing befalleth all: yea, also the heart of the children of  men is full of evil, and madness is in their heart while they  live; and after that, [they have to go] to the dead.
9:3|KJV|This is an evil among all things that are done under the sun, that there is one event unto all: yea, also the heart of the sons of men is full of evil, and madness is in their heart while they live, and after that they go to the dead.
9:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在日光之下所行的一切事上有一禍患，就是眾人所遭遇的都是一樣；並且世人的心充滿了惡；他們活著的時候心堥g妄，後來就歸死人那堨h了。
9:4|ASV|For to him that is joined with all the living there is hope; for a living dog is better than a dead lion.
9:4|Darby|For to him that is joined to all the living there is hope;  for a living dog is better than a dead lion.
9:4|KJV|For to him that is joined to all the living there is hope: for a living dog is better than a dead lion.
9:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|與一切活人相連的，那人還有指望，因為活著的狗比死了的獅子更強。
9:5|ASV|For the living know that they shall die: but the dead know not anything, neither have they any more a reward; for the memory of them is forgotten.
9:5|Darby|For the living know that they shall die; but the dead know  not anything, neither have they any more a reward, for the  memory of them is forgotten.
9:5|KJV|For the living know that they shall die: but the dead know not any thing, neither have they any more a reward; for the memory of them is forgotten.
9:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|活著的人知道自己必死；死了的人卻毫無所知，也不再得賞賜；他們的名被人遺忘。
9:6|ASV|As well their love, as their hatred and their envy, is perished long ago; neither have they any more a portion for ever in anything that is done under the sun.
9:6|Darby|Their love also, and their hatred, and their envy is already  perished; neither have they any more for ever a portion in all  that is done under the sun.
9:6|KJV|Also their love, and their hatred, and their envy, is now perished; neither have they any more a portion for ever in any thing that is done under the sun.
9:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們的愛，他們的恨，他們的嫉妒，早都消滅了；在日光之下所行的一切事上，他們永不再有分了。
9:7|ASV|Go thy way, eat thy bread with joy, and drink thy wine with a merry heart; for God hath already accepted thy works.
9:7|Darby|Go, eat thy bread with joy, and drink thy wine with a merry  heart; for God hath already accepted thy works.
9:7|KJV|Go thy way, eat thy bread with joy, and drink thy wine with a merry heart; for God now accepteth thy works.
9:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你只管去歡歡喜喜喫你的飯，心中快樂喝你的酒，因為神已經悅納你的作為。
9:8|ASV|Let thy garments be always white; and let not thy head lack oil.
9:8|Darby|Let thy garments be always white, and let not thy head lack  oil.
9:8|KJV|Let thy garments be always white; and let thy head lack no ointment.
9:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你的衣服當時常潔白，你的頭上也不要缺少膏油。
9:9|ASV|Live joyfully with the wife whom thou lovest all the days of thy life of vanity, which he hath given thee under the sun, all thy days of vanity: for that is thy portion in life, and in thy labor wherein thou laborest under the sun.
9:9|Darby|Enjoy life with the wife whom thou lovest all the days of  the life of thy vanity, which he hath given thee under the sun,  all the days of thy vanity; for that is thy portion in life,  and in thy labour wherein thou art labouring under the sun.
9:9|KJV|Live joyfully with the wife whom thou lovest all the days of the life of thy vanity, which he hath given thee under the sun, all the days of thy vanity: for that is thy portion in this life, and in thy labour which thou takest under the sun.
9:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在你一生虛空的日子，就是神賜你在日光之下一切虛空的日子，當同你所愛的妻子，享受人生，因為那是你一生在日光之下勞碌的事上所得的分。
9:10|ASV|Whatsoever thy hand findeth to do, do it with thy might; for there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wisdom, in Sheol, whither thou goest.
9:10|Darby|Whatever thy hand findeth to do, do with thy might; for  there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wisdom, in  Sheol, whither thou goest.
9:10|KJV|Whatsoever thy hand findeth to do, do it with thy might; for there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wisdom, in the grave, whither thou goest.
9:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡你手所當作的事要盡力去作；因為在你所要去的陰間，沒有工作，沒有謀算，沒有知識，也沒有智慧。
9:11|ASV|I returned, and saw under the sun, that the race is not to the swift, nor the battle to the strong, neither yet bread to the wise, nor yet riches to men of understanding, nor yet favor to men of skill; but time and chance happeneth to them all.
9:11|Darby|I returned, and saw under the sun, that the race is not to  the swift, nor the battle to the strong, neither yet bread to  the wise, nor yet riches to the intelligent, nor yet favour to  men of knowledge; but time and chance happeneth to them all.
9:11|KJV|I returned, and saw under the sun, that the race is not to the swift, nor the battle to the strong, neither yet bread to the wise, nor yet riches to men of understanding, nor yet favour to men of skill; but time and chance happeneth to them all.
9:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我又見日光之下快跑的未必能贏，力戰的未必得勝，並且智慧的未必得糧食，聰明的未必得貲財，有知識的也未必得喜悅；所臨到眾人的，是在於時候和機會。
9:12|ASV|For man also knoweth not his time: as the fishes that are taken in an evil net, and as the birds that are caught in the snare, even so are the sons of men snared in an evil time, when it falleth suddenly upon them.
9:12|Darby|For man also knoweth not his time: as the fishes that are  taken in an evil net, and as the birds that are taken with the  snare, like them are the children of men snared in an evil  time, when it falleth suddenly upon them.
9:12|KJV|For man also knoweth not his time: as the fishes that are taken in an evil net, and as the birds that are caught in the snare; so are the sons of men snared in an evil time, when it falleth suddenly upon them.
9:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|原來人也不知道自己的時候：魚被惡網圈住，鳥被網羅捉住，禍患忽然臨到的時候，世人陷在其中也是如此。
9:13|ASV|I have also seen wisdom under the sun on this wise, and it seemed great unto me:
9:13|Darby|This also have I seen as wisdom under the sun, and it was  great unto me.
9:13|KJV|This wisdom have I seen also under the sun, and it seemed great unto me:
9:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我也見日光之下有一件事乃是智慧，據我看是大的，
9:14|ASV|There was a little city, and few men within it; and there came a great king against it, and besieged it, and built great bulwarks against it.
9:14|Darby|There was a little city, and few men within it; and there  came a great king against it, and encompassed it, and built  great bulwarks against it:
9:14|KJV|There was a little city, and few men within it; and there came a great king against it, and besieged it, and built great bulwarks against it:
9:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就是有一小城，其中的人數稀少，有大君王來攻擊，將城圍困，修築高壘攻打。
9:15|ASV|Now there was found in it a poor wise man, and he by his wisdom delivered the city; yet no man remembered that same poor man.
9:15|Darby|and there was found in it a poor wise man, who by his  wisdom delivered the city; but no man remembered that poor man.
9:15|KJV|Now there was found in it a poor wise man, and he by his wisdom delivered the city; yet no man remembered that same poor man.
9:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|城中有一個貧窮的智慧人，他用智慧救了那城，卻沒有人記念那窮人。
9:16|ASV|Then said I, Wisdom is better than strength: nevertheless the poor man's wisdom is despised, and his words are not heard.
9:16|Darby|Then said I, Wisdom is better than strength; but the poor  man's wisdom is despised, and his words are not heard.
9:16|KJV|Then said I, Wisdom is better than strength: nevertheless the poor man's wisdom is despised, and his words are not heard.
9:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我就說，智慧勝過勇力；然而那貧窮人的智慧被人藐視，他的話也無人聽從。
9:17|ASV|The words of the wise heard in quiet are better than the cry of him that ruleth among fools.
9:17|Darby|The words of the wise are heard in quiet more than the cry  of him that ruleth among fools.
9:17|KJV|The words of wise men are heard in quiet more than the cry of him that ruleth among fools.
9:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|智慧人在安靜中所說的話，比掌權者在愚昧人中的喊聲更有人聽。
9:18<version name="ASV">Wisdom is better than weapons of war; but one sinner destroyeth much good. </p><p /><br /></version>
9:18<version name="Darby">Wisdom is better than weapons of war; but one sinner  destroyeth much good. </p><p /><br /></version>
9:18<version name="KJV">Wisdom is better than weapons of war: but one sinner destroyeth much good.</p><p /><br /></version>
9:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|智慧勝過打仗的兵器；但一個罪人能敗壞許多善事。
10:1|ASV|Dead flies cause the oil of the perfumer to send forth an evil odor;  so doth a little folly outweigh wisdom and honor.
10:1|Darby|Dead flies cause the ointment of the apothecary to stink  [and] ferment; [so] a little folly is weightier than wisdom  [and] honour.
10:1|KJV|Dead flies cause the ointment of the apothecary to send forth a stinking savour: so doth a little folly him that is in reputation for wisdom and honour.
10:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|死蒼蠅使調製香料者的膏油變臭發酵；這樣，一點愚昧也敗壞智慧和尊榮。
10:2|ASV|A wise man's heart is at his right hand; but a fool's heart at his left.
10:2|Darby|The heart of a wise [man] is at his right hand; but a  fool's heart at his left.
10:2|KJV|A wise man's heart is at his right hand; but a fool's heart at his left.
10:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|智慧人的心偏右；愚昧人的心偏左。
10:3|ASV|Yea also, when the fool walketh by the way, his understanding faileth him, and he saith to every one that he is a fool.
10:3|Darby|Yea also, when he that is a fool walketh by the way, his  sense faileth [him], and he saith to every one [that] he is a  fool.
10:3|KJV|Yea also, when he that is a fool walketh by the way, his wisdom faileth him, and he saith to every one that he is a fool.
10:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且愚昧人行在路上顯出無知，告訴眾人他是愚昧人。
10:4|ASV|If the spirit of the ruler rise up against thee, leave not thy place; for gentleness allayeth great offences.
10:4|Darby|If the spirit of the ruler rise up against thee, leave not  thy place; for quietness pacifieth great offences.
10:4|KJV|If the spirit of the ruler rise up against thee, leave not thy place; for yielding pacifieth great offences.
10:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|掌權者若向你生氣，你不要離開本位，因為柔和能免大過。
10:5|ASV|There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, as it were an error which proceedeth from the ruler:
10:5|Darby|There is an evil that I have seen under the sun, as an  error [that] proceedeth from the ruler:
10:5|KJV|There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, as an error which proceedeth from the ruler:
10:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我見日光之下有一禍患，似乎出於掌權者的錯誤，
10:6|ASV|folly is set in great dignity, and the rich sit in a low place.
10:6|Darby|folly is set in great dignities, but the rich sit in a low  place.
10:6|KJV|Folly is set in great dignity, and the rich sit in low place.
10:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就是愚昧人多居高位，富足人坐在低位。
10:7|ASV|I have seen servants upon horses, and princes walking like servants upon the earth.
10:7|Darby|I have seen servants upon horses, and princes walking as  servants upon the earth.
10:7|KJV|I have seen servants upon horses, and princes walking as servants upon the earth.
10:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我見過僕人騎馬，首領像僕人在地上步行。
10:8|ASV|He that diggeth a pit shall fall into it; and whoso breaketh through a wall, a serpent shall bite him.
10:8|Darby|He that diggeth a pit falleth into it; and whoso breaketh  down a hedge, a serpent biteth him.
10:8|KJV|He that diggeth a pit shall fall into it; and whoso breaketh an hedge, a serpent shall bite him.
10:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|挖陷坑的，自己必掉在其中；拆通牆垣的，必為蛇所咬。
10:9|ASV|Whoso heweth out stones shall be hurt therewith; and he that cleaveth wood is endangered thereby.
10:9|Darby|Whoso removeth stones is hurt therewith; he that cleaveth  wood is endangered thereby.
10:9|KJV|Whoso removeth stones shall be hurt therewith; and he that cleaveth wood shall be endangered thereby.
10:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|開鑿石頭的，必受損傷；劈開木頭的，必遭危險。
10:10|ASV|If the iron be blunt, and one do not whet the edge, then must he put to more strength: but wisdom is profitable to direct.
10:10|Darby|If the iron be blunt, and one do not whet the edge, then  must he apply more strength; but wisdom is profitable to give  success.
10:10|KJV|If the iron be blunt, and he do not whet the edge, then must he put to more strength: but wisdom is profitable to direct.
10:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|鐵器鈍了，若不將刃磨快，就必多費力氣；但智慧有益，使人成功。
10:11|ASV|If the serpent bite before it is charmed, then is there no advantage in the charmer.
10:11|Darby|If the serpent bite before enchantment, then the charmer  hath no advantage.
10:11|KJV|Surely the serpent will bite without enchantment; and a babbler is no better.
10:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|未行法術以先，蛇若咬人，後行法術就無益了。
10:12|ASV|The words of a wise man's mouth are gracious; but the lips of a fool will swallow up himself.
10:12|Darby|The words of a wise man's mouth are gracious; but the lips  of a fool swallow up himself.
10:12|KJV|The words of a wise man's mouth are gracious; but the lips of a fool will swallow up himself.
10:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|智慧人的口說出恩言，愚昧人的嘴吞滅自己。
10:13|ASV|The beginning of the words of his mouth is foolishness; and the end of his talk is mischievous madness.
10:13|Darby|The beginning of the words of his mouth is folly; and the  end of his talk is mischievous madness.
10:13|KJV|The beginning of the words of his mouth is foolishness: and the end of his talk is mischievous madness.
10:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他口中的言語起頭是愚昧；他話的末尾是奸惡的狂妄。
10:14|ASV|A fool also multiplieth words: yet man knoweth not what shall be; and that which shall be after him, who can tell him?
10:14|Darby|And the fool multiplieth words: [yet] man knoweth not what  shall be; and what shall be after him, who will tell him?
10:14|KJV|A fool also is full of words: a man cannot tell what shall be; and what shall be after him, who can tell him?
10:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|愚昧人多言多語。人不知將來有甚麼事；他身後的事誰能告訴他呢？
10:15|ASV|The labor of fools wearieth every one of them; for he knoweth not how to go to the city.
10:15|Darby|The labour of fools wearieth them, because they know not  how to go to the city.
10:15|KJV|The labour of the foolish wearieth every one of them, because he knoweth not how to go to the city.
10:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|愚昧人的勞碌使自己困乏，因為連如何進城他也不知道。
10:16|ASV|Woe to thee, O land, when thy king is a child, and thy princes eat in the morning!
10:16|Darby|Woe to thee, O land, when thy king is a child, and thy  princes eat in the morning!
10:16|KJV|Woe to thee, O land, when thy king is a child, and thy princes eat in the morning!
10:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|邦國阿，你的王若是孩童，你的眾首領早晨喫喝宴樂，你就有禍了！
10:17|ASV|Happy art thou, O land, when thy king is the son of nobles, and thy princes eat in due season, for strength, and not for drunkenness!
10:17|Darby|Happy art thou, O land, when thy king is a son of nobles,  and thy princes eat in [due] season, for strength, and not for  drunkenness!
10:17|KJV|Blessed art thou, O land, when thy king is the son of nobles, and thy princes eat in due season, for strength, and not for drunkenness!
10:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|邦國阿，你的王若是貴冑之子，你的眾首領按時喫喝，為要補力，不為酒醉，你就有福了！
10:18|ASV|By slothfulness the roof sinketh in; and through idleness of the hands the house leaketh.
10:18|Darby|By much sloth fulness the framework falleth in; and  through idleness of the hands the house drippeth.
10:18|KJV|By much slothfulness the building decayeth; and through idleness of the hands the house droppeth through.
10:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因人懶惰，房頂塌下；因人手懶，房屋滴漏。
10:19|ASV|A feast is made for laughter, and wine maketh glad the life; and money answereth all things.
10:19|Darby|A feast is made for laughter, and wine maketh life merry;  but money answereth everything.
10:19|KJV|A feast is made for laughter, and wine maketh merry: but money answereth all things.
10:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人設擺筵席是為喜笑；酒使人生快活；錢叫萬事應心。
10:20<version name="ASV">Revile not the king, no, not in thy thought; and revile not the rich in thy bedchamber: for a bird of the heavens shall carry the voice, and that which hath wings shall tell the matter. </p><p /><br /></version>
10:20<version name="Darby">Curse not the king, no, not in thy thought; and curse not  the rich in thy bedchamber: for the bird of the air will carry  the voice, and that which hath wings will tell the matter. </p><p /><br /></version>
10:20<version name="KJV">Curse not the king, no not in thy thought; and curse not the rich in thy bedchamber: for a bird of the air shall carry the voice, and that which hath wings shall tell the matter.</p><p /><br /></version>
10:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你不可咒詛君王，甚至不可心懷此念；也不可在你臥房咒詛富戶；因為空中的鳥必傳送這聲音，有翅膀的也必述說這事。
11:1|ASV|Cast thy bread upon the waters; for thou shalt find it after many days.
11:1|Darby|Cast thy bread upon the waters; for thou shalt find it  after many days.
11:1|KJV|Cast thy bread upon the waters: for thou shalt find it after many days.
11:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當將你的糧食撒在水面，因為日久必能得著。
11:2|ASV|Give a portion to seven, yea, even unto eight; for thou knowest not what evil shall be upon the earth.
11:2|Darby|Give a portion to seven, and also to eight; for thou  knowest not what evil shall be upon the earth.
11:2|KJV|Give a portion to seven, and also to eight; for thou knowest not what evil shall be upon the earth.
11:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要分給七人，或分給八人，因為你不知道有甚麼災禍會臨到地上。
11:3|ASV|If the clouds be full of rain, they empty themselves upon the earth; and if a tree fall toward the south, or toward the north, in the place where the tree falleth, there shall it be.
11:3|Darby|If the clouds be full of rain, they empty themselves upon  the earth; and if a tree fall toward the south, or toward the  north, in the place where the tree falleth, there it shall be.
11:3|KJV|If the clouds be full of rain, they empty themselves upon the earth: and if the tree fall toward the south, or toward the north, in the place where the tree falleth, there it shall be.
11:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|雲若滿了雨，就必傾倒在地上；樹若向南倒或向北倒，樹倒在何處，就留在何處。
11:4|ASV|He that observeth the wind shall not sow; and he that regardeth the clouds shall not reap.
11:4|Darby|He that observeth the wind will not sow; and he that  regardeth the clouds will not reap.
11:4|KJV|He that observeth the wind shall not sow; and he that regardeth the clouds shall not reap.
11:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|看風的，必不撒種；望雲的，必不收割。
11:5|ASV|As thou knowest not what is the way of the wind,  nor how the bones do grow in the womb of her that is with child; even so thou knowest not the work of God who doeth all.
11:5|Darby|As thou knowest not what is the way of the spirit, how the  bones [grow] in the womb of her that is with child, even so  thou knowest not the work of God who maketh all.
11:5|KJV|As thou knowest not what is the way of the spirit, nor how the bones do grow in the womb of her that is with child: even so thou knowest not the works of God who maketh all.
11:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你不知道風的途徑，也不知道骨頭在孕婦的胎中如何長成；照樣，你也不知道造萬物之神的作為。
11:6|ASV|In the morning sow thy seed, and in the evening withhold not thy hand; for thou knowest not which shall prosper, whether this or that, or whether they both shall be alike good.
11:6|Darby|In the morning sow thy seed, and in the evening withhold  not thy hand; for thou knowest not which shall prosper, whether  this or that, or whether they both shall be alike good.
11:6|KJV|In the morning sow thy seed, and in the evening withhold not thine hand: for thou knowest not whether shall prosper, either this or that, or whether they both shall be alike good.
11:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|早晨要撒種，晚上也不要歇手，因為你不知道那一樣發旺；或是這樣，或是那樣，或是兩樣都好。
11:7|ASV|Truly the light is sweet, and a pleasant thing it is for the eyes to behold the sun.
11:7|Darby|Now the light is sweet, and pleasant is it to the eyes to  see the sun;
11:7|KJV|Truly the light is sweet, and a pleasant thing it is for the eyes to behold the sun:
11:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|光是佳美的，眼見日光也是可悅的。
11:8|ASV|Yea, if a man live many years, let him rejoice in them all; but let him remember the days of darkness, for they shall be many. All that cometh is vanity.
11:8|Darby|but if a man live many years, [and] rejoice in them all,  yet let him remember the days of darkness; for they shall be  many: all that cometh is vanity.
11:8|KJV|But if a man live many years, and rejoice in them all; yet let him remember the days of darkness; for they shall be many. All that cometh is vanity.
11:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人若活多年，就當快樂多年；然而也當記得黑暗的日子，因為這些日子必多；那要來的都是虛空。
11:9|ASV|Rejoice, O young man, in thy youth, and let thy heart cheer thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thy heart, and in the sight of thine eyes; but know thou, that for all these things God will bring thee into judgment.
11:9|Darby|Rejoice, young man, in thy youth; and let thy heart cheer  thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thy  heart, and in the sight of thine eyes; but know that for all  these [things] God will bring thee into judgment.
11:9|KJV|Rejoice, O young man, in thy youth; and let thy heart cheer thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thine heart, and in the sight of thine eyes: but know thou, that for all these things God will bring thee into judgment.
11:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|少年人哪，你在幼年時當快樂；在幼年的日子，使你的心歡暢，照你心所願行的，你眼所愛看的去行。你卻要知道，為這一切的事，神必審問你。
11:10<version name="ASV">Therefore remove sorrow from thy heart, and put away evil from thy flesh; for youth and the dawn of life are vanity. </p><p /><br /></version>
11:10<version name="Darby">Then remove discontent from thy heart, and put away evil  from thy flesh; for childhood and youth are vanity. </p><p /><br /></version>
11:10<version name="KJV">Therefore remove sorrow from thy heart, and put away evil from thy flesh: for childhood and youth are vanity.</p><p /><br /></version>
11:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以你當從心中除掉愁煩，從肉體克除邪惡；因為幼年之時和人生的初期，都是虛空的。
12:1|ASV|Remember also thy Creator in the days of thy youth, before the evil days come, and the years draw nigh, when thou shalt say, I have no pleasure in them;
12:1|Darby|And remember thy Creator in the days of thy youth, before  the evil days come, and the years draw nigh, of which thou  shalt say, I have no pleasure in them;
12:1|KJV|Remember now thy Creator in the days of thy youth, while the evil days come not, nor the years draw nigh, when thou shalt say, I have no pleasure in them;
12:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你趁著年幼，衰敗的日子尚未來到，就是你所說，我毫無樂趣的那些年日未曾臨近之先，當記念造你的主。
12:2|ASV|before the sun, and the light, and the moon, and the stars, are darkened, and the clouds return after the rain;
12:2|Darby|before the sun, and the light, and the moon, and the stars,  be darkened, and the clouds return after the rain;
12:2|KJV|While the sun, or the light, or the moon, or the stars, be not darkened, nor the clouds return after the rain:
12:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不要等到日頭、光明、月亮、星宿變為昏暗，雨後雲彩返回；
12:3|ASV|in the day when the keepers of the house shall tremble, and the strong men shall bow themselves, and the grinders cease because they are few, and those that look out of the windows shall be darkened,
12:3|Darby|in the day when the keepers of the house tremble, and the  strong men bow themselves, and the grinders cease because they  are few, and those that look out of the windows are darkened,
12:3|KJV|In the day when the keepers of the house shall tremble, and the strong men shall bow themselves, and the grinders cease because they are few, and those that look out of the windows be darkened,
12:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時看守房屋的發顫，有力氣的男人屈身，推磨的婦人稀少就止息，從窗戶往外看的都是昏暗；
12:4|ASV|and the doors shall be shut in the street; when the sound of the grinding is low, and one shall rise up at the voice of a bird, and all the daughters of music shall be brought low;
12:4|Darby|and the doors are shut toward the street; when the sound of  the grinding is subdued, and they rise up at the voice of the  bird, and all the daughters of song are brought low;
12:4|KJV|And the doors shall be shut in the streets, when the sound of the grinding is low, and he shall rise up at the voice of the bird, and all the daughters of musick shall be brought low;
12:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|街上門戶關閉，推磨的響聲低微，雀鳥一叫，人就起來，唱歌的女子都衰微；
12:5|ASV|yea, they shall be afraid of that which is high, and terrors shall be in the way; and the almond-tree shall blossom, and the grasshopper shall be a burden, and desire shall fail; because man goeth to his everlasting home, and the mourners go about the streets:
12:5|Darby|they are also afraid of what is high, and terrors are in  the way, and the almond is despised, and the grasshopper is a  burden, and the caper-berry is without effect; (for man goeth  to his age-long home, and the mourners go about the streets;)
12:5|KJV|Also when they shall be afraid of that which is high, and fears shall be in the way, and the almond tree shall flourish, and the grasshopper shall be a burden, and desire shall fail: because man goeth to his long home, and the mourners go about the streets:
12:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人怕高處，路上有驚慌；杏樹開花，蚱蜢成為重擔，藥物也失了效；（因為人歸他永遠的家，弔喪的在街上往來；）
12:6|ASV|before the silver cord is loosed, or the golden bowl is broken, or the pitcher is broken at the fountain, or the wheel broken at the cistern,
12:6|Darby|-- before the silver cord be loosed, or the golden bowl be  broken, or the pitcher be shattered at the fountain, or the  wheel be broken at the cistern;
12:6|KJV|Or ever the silver cord be loosed, or the golden bowl be broken, or the pitcher be broken at the fountain, or the wheel broken at the cistern.
12:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不要等到銀鍊折斷，金罐破裂，瓶子在泉旁破碎，水輪在井口破爛，
12:7|ASV|and the dust returneth to the earth as it was, and the spirit returneth unto God who gave it.
12:7|Darby|and the dust return to the earth as it was, and the spirit  return unto God who gave it.
12:7|KJV|Then shall the dust return to the earth as it was: and the spirit shall return unto God who gave it.
12:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|塵土仍歸於地，氣息仍歸於賜氣息的神。
12:8|ASV|Vanity of vanities, saith the Preacher; all is vanity.
12:8|Darby|Vanity of vanities, saith the Preacher: all is vanity.
12:8|KJV|Vanity of vanities, saith the preacher; all is vanity.
12:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|傳道者說，虛空的虛空，凡事都是虛空。
12:9|ASV|And further, because the Preacher was wise, he still taught the people knowledge; yea, he pondered, and sought out, and set in order many proverbs.
12:9|Darby|And moreover, because the Preacher was wise, he still  taught the people knowledge; and he pondered, and sought out,  [and] set in order many proverbs.
12:9|KJV|And moreover, because the preacher was wise, he still taught the people knowledge; yea, he gave good heed, and sought out, and set in order many proverbs.
12:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|傳道者不僅有智慧，也將知識教訓眾人；他又衡量又考察，又編集許多箴言。
12:10|ASV|The Preacher sought to find out acceptable words, and that which was written uprightly, even words of truth.
12:10|Darby|The Preacher sought to find out acceptable words; and that  which was written is upright, words of truth.
12:10|KJV|The preacher sought to find out acceptable words: and that which was written was upright, even words of truth.
12:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|傳道者專心尋求可喜悅的言語，憑正直寫下真實話。
12:11|ASV|The words of the wise are as goads; and as nails well fastened are the words of the masters of assemblies, which are given from one shepherd.
12:11|Darby|The words of the wise are as goads, and the collections  [of them] as nails fastened in: they are given from one  shepherd.
12:11|KJV|The words of the wise are as goads, and as nails fastened by the masters of assemblies, which are given from one shepherd.
12:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|智慧人的言語好像犁棒，他們所輯錄的言語像釘穩的釘子，都是一個牧者所賜的。
12:12|ASV|And furthermore, my son, be admonished: of making many books there is no end; and much study is a weariness of the flesh.
12:12|Darby|And besides, my son, be warned by them: of making many  books there is no end, and much study is a weariness of the  flesh.
12:12|KJV|And further, by these, my son, be admonished: of making many books there is no end; and much study is a weariness of the flesh.
12:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我兒，還有一層，你當留意：著書多，沒有窮盡；讀書多，身體疲倦。
12:13|ASV|This is the end of the matter; all hath been heard: fear God, and keep his commandments; for this is the whole duty of man.
12:13|Darby|Let us hear the end of the whole matter: Fear God, and  keep his commandments; for this is the whole of man.
12:13|KJV|Let us hear the conclusion of the whole matter: Fear God, and keep his commandments: for this is the whole duty of man.
12:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這一切事都已聽見了，結語就是：敬畏神，謹守祂的誡命，這就是人所當盡的本分。
12:14<version name="ASV">For God will bring every work into judgment, with every hidden thing, whether it be good, or whether it be evil. </p><p /><br /></version>
12:14<version name="Darby">For God shall bring every work into judgment, with every  secret thing, whether it be good or whether it be evil. </p><p /><br /></version>
12:14<version name="KJV">For God shall bring every work into judgment, with every secret thing, whether it be good, or whether it be evil.</p><p /><br /></version>
12:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為人所作的事，連一切隱藏的事，無論是善是惡，神都必審問。
