1:1|ASV|Now it came to pass in the days of Ahasuerus (this is Ahasuerus who reigned from India even unto Ethiopia, over a hundred and seven and twenty provinces),
1:1|Darby|And it came to pass in the days of Ahasuerus (that is, the  Ahasuerus that reigned from India even to Ethiopia, over a  hundred and twenty-seven provinces),
1:1|KJV|Now it came to pass in the days of Ahasuerus, (this is Ahasuerus which reigned, from India even unto Ethiopia, over an hundred and seven and twenty provinces:)
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當亞哈隨魯作王的日子，（這亞哈隨魯從印度直到古實，統管一百二十七省，）
1:2|ASV|that in those days, when the king Ahasuerus sat on the throne of his kingdom, which was in Shushan the palace,
1:2|Darby|in those days, when the king Ahasuerus sat on the throne of  his kingdom, which was in Shushan the fortress,
1:2|KJV|That in those days, when the king Ahasuerus sat on the throne of his kingdom, which was in Shushan the palace,
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那些日子，亞哈隨魯王在書珊京城登了國位。
1:3|ASV|in the third year of his reign, he made a feast unto all his princes and his servants; the power of Persia and Media, the nobles and princes of the provinces, being before him;
1:3|Darby|in the third year of his reign, he made a feast to all his  princes and his servants; the power of Persia and Media, the  nobles and the princes of the provinces being before him;
1:3|KJV|In the third year of his reign, he made a feast unto all his princes and his servants; the power of Persia and Media, the nobles and princes of the provinces, being before him:
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在位第三年，他為一切首領臣僕設擺筵宴。有波斯和瑪代的權貴、貴冑、和各省的首領在他面前；
1:4|ASV|when he showed the riches of his glorious kingdom and the honor of his excellent majesty many days, even a hundred and fourscore days.
1:4|Darby|when he shewed the glorious wealth of his kingdom and the  splendid magnificence of his grandeur many days, a hundred and  eighty days.
1:4|KJV|When he shewed the riches of his glorious kingdom and the honour of his excellent majesty many days, even an hundred and fourscore days.
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他把他國榮耀的豐富，和他盛大威嚴的華貴，給他們看了許多日，就是一百八十日。
1:5|ASV|And when these days were fulfilled, the king made a feast unto all the people that were present in Shushan the palace, both great and small, seven days, in the court of the garden of the king's palace.
1:5|Darby|And when these days were expired, the king made a feast to  all the people that were present in Shushan the fortress, both  to great and small, seven days, in the court of the garden of  the king's palace.
1:5|KJV|And when these days were expired, the king made a feast unto all the people that were present in Shushan the palace, both unto great and small, seven days, in the court of the garden of the king's palace;
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些日子滿了，王又為所有在書珊京城的人民，無論尊大或卑小，在王宮花園的院內設擺筵宴七日。
1:6|ASV|There were hangings of white cloth,  of green, and of blue, fastened with cords of fine linen and purple to silver rings and pillars of marble: the couches were of gold and silver, upon a pavement of red, and white, and yellow, and black marble.
1:6|Darby|White, green, and blue [hangings] were fastened with cords  of byssus and purple to silver rings and pillars of white  marble; couches of gold and silver [lay] upon a pavement of red  and white marble, and alabaster, and black marble.
1:6|KJV|Where were white, green, and blue, hangings, fastened with cords of fine linen and purple to silver rings and pillars of marble: the beds were of gold and silver, upon a pavement of red, and blue, and white, and black, marble.
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有白色棉織的幔子、藍色的掛帳，用細麻繩、紫色繩繫在銀環和白玉石柱上，有金銀的床榻擺在斑岩、白玉石、珠母、黑玉石鋪的石地上。
1:7|ASV|And they gave them drink in vessels of gold (the vessels being diverse one from another), and royal wine in abundance, according to the bounty of the king.
1:7|Darby|And they gave drink in vessels of gold (the vessels being  diverse one from another), and royal wine in abundance,  according to the king's bounty.
1:7|KJV|And they gave them drink in vessels of gold, (the vessels being diverse one from another,) and royal wine in abundance, according to the state of the king.
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|用金器皿賜酒，器皿各有不同；照著王的厚意，所賜的御酒甚多。
1:8|ASV|And the drinking was according to the law; none could compel: for so the king had appointed to all the officers of his house, that they should do according to every man's pleasure.
1:8|Darby|And the drinking was, according to commandment, without  constraint; for so the king had appointed to all the magnates  of his house, that they should do according to every man's  pleasure.
1:8|KJV|And the drinking was according to the law; none did compel: for so the king had appointed to all the officers of his house, that they should do according to every man's pleasure.
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|喝酒乃照著定例，不准勉強人，因王吩咐宮堛漱@切臣宰，要照各人的意願待他們。
1:9|ASV|Also Vashti the queen made a feast for the women in the royal house which belonged to king Ahasuerus.
1:9|Darby|Also the queen Vashti made a feast for the women of the  royal house which belonged to king Ahasuerus.
1:9|KJV|Also Vashti the queen made a feast for the women in the royal house which belonged to king Ahasuerus.
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王后瓦實提在亞哈隨魯王的王宮中，也為婦女設擺筵宴。
1:10|ASV|On the seventh day, when the heart of the king was merry with wine, he commanded Mehuman, Biztha, Harbona, Bigtha, and Abagtha, Zethar, and Carcas, the seven chamberlains that ministered in the presence of Ahasuerus the king,
1:10|Darby|On the seventh day, when the king's heart was merry with  wine, he commanded Mehuman, Biztha, Harbona, Bigtha, and  Abagtha, Zethar, and Carcas, the seven chamberlains that served  in the presence of king Ahasuerus,
1:10|KJV|On the seventh day, when the heart of the king was merry with wine, he commanded Mehuman, Biztha, Harbona, Bigtha, and Abagtha, Zethar, and Carcas, the seven chamberlains that served in the presence of Ahasuerus the king,
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|第七日，亞哈隨魯王飲酒，心中快樂，就吩咐在他面前侍立的七個太監米戶幔、比斯他、哈波拿、比革他、亞拔他、西達、甲迦，
1:11|ASV|to bring Vashti the queen before the king with the crown royal, to show the peoples and the princes her beauty; for she was fair to look on.
1:11|Darby|to bring Vashti the queen before the king with the royal  crown to shew the peoples and the princes her beauty; for she  was of beautiful countenance.
1:11|KJV|To bring Vashti the queen before the king with the crown royal, to shew the people and the princes her beauty: for she was fair to look on.
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|請王后瓦實提戴著后冠到王面前，使各民和臣宰看她的美麗，因為她容貌甚美。
1:12|ASV|But the queen Vashti refused to come at the king's commandment by the chamberlains: therefore was the king very wroth, and his anger burned in him.
1:12|Darby|But the queen Vashti refused to come at the word of the  king which was [sent] by the chamberlains; and the king was  very wroth, and his fury burned in him.
1:12|KJV|But the queen Vashti refused to come at the king's commandment by his chamberlains: therefore was the king very wroth, and his anger burned in him.
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王后瓦實提卻不肯遵王藉太監所傳的命令而來，所以王甚發怒，怒火中燒。
1:13|ASV|Then the king said to the wise men, who knew the times, (for so was the king's manner toward all that knew law and judgment;
1:13|Darby|And the king said to the wise men who knew the times (for  so was the king's business [conducted] before all that knew law  and judgment;
1:13|KJV|Then the king said to the wise men, which knew the times, (for so was the king's manner toward all that knew law and judgment:
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王就問通達時務的智慧人說，（按王的常規，辦事必先詢問一切通曉法例和公理的人；
1:14|ASV|and the next unto him were Carshena, Shethar, Admatha, Tarshish, Meres, Marsena, and Memucan, the seven princes of Persia and Media, who saw the king's face, and sat first in the kingdom),
1:14|Darby|and the next to him were Carshena, Shethar, Admatha,  Tarshish, Meres, Marsena, [and] Memucan, the seven princes of  Persia and Media, who saw the king's face, and who sat first in  the kingdom),
1:14|KJV|And the next unto him was Carshena, Shethar, Admatha, Tarshish, Meres, Marsena, and Memucan, the seven princes of Persia and Media, which saw the king's face, and which sat the first in the kingdom;)
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那在王左右的是波斯和瑪代的七個首領甲示拿、示達、押瑪他、他施斯、米力、瑪西拿和米母干，他們常見王面，在國中坐首位，）
1:15|ASV|What shall we do unto the queen Vashti according to law, because she hath not done the bidding of the king Ahasuerus by the chamberlains?
1:15|Darby|What shall be done to the queen Vashti according to law,  because she has not performed the word of the king Ahasuerus by  the chamberlains?
1:15|KJV|What shall we do unto the queen Vashti according to law, because she hath not performed the commandment of the king Ahasuerus by the chamberlains?
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王后瓦實提不遵行亞哈隨魯王藉太監所傳的命令，照法例應當怎樣對待她？
1:16|ASV|And Memucan answered before the king and the princes, Vashti the queen hath not done wrong to the king only, but also to all the princes, and to all the peoples that are in all the provinces of the king Ahasuerus.
1:16|Darby|Then said Memucan before the king and the princes, The  queen Vashti has not done wrong to the king only, but also to  all the princes, and to all the peoples that are in all the  provinces of the king Ahasuerus.
1:16|KJV|And Memucan answered before the king and the princes, Vashti the queen hath not done wrong to the king only, but also to all the princes, and to all the people that are in all the provinces of the king Ahasuerus.
1:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|米母干在王和眾首領面前回答說，王后瓦實提不但得罪王，也得罪亞哈隨魯王各省的臣民；
1:17|ASV|For this deed of the queen will come abroad unto all women, to make their husbands contemptible in their eyes, when it shall be reported, The king Ahasuerus commanded Vashti the queen to be brought in before him, but she came not.
1:17|Darby|For the act of the queen will come abroad to all women, so  as to render their husbands contemptible in their eyes, when  they shall say, The king Ahasuerus commanded the queen Vashti  to be brought in before him, and she came not!
1:17|KJV|For this deed of the queen shall come abroad unto all women, so that they shall despise their husbands in their eyes, when it shall be reported, The king Ahasuerus commanded Vashti the queen to be brought in before him, but she came not.
1:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為王后所行的這事必傳到眾婦人的耳中，說，亞哈隨魯王吩咐王后瓦實提到王面前，她卻不來，這就使她們藐視自己的丈夫。
1:18|ASV|And this day will the princesses of Persia and Media who have heard of the deed of the queen say the like unto all the king's princes. So will there arise much contempt and wrath.
1:18|Darby|And the princesses of Persia and Media who have heard of  the queen's act, will say it this day to all the king's  princes, and there will be contempt and anger enough.
1:18|KJV|Likewise shall the ladies of Persia and Media say this day unto all the king's princes, which have heard of the deed of the queen. Thus shall there arise too much contempt and wrath.
1:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|今日波斯和瑪代的眾夫人聽見王后所行的這事，必向王的眾臣照樣行；這樣就必多有藐視和忿怒的事了。
1:19|ASV|If it please the king, let there go forth a royal commandment from him, and let it be written among the laws of the Persians and the Medes, that it be not altered, that Vashti come no more before king Ahasuerus; and let the king give her royal estate unto another that is better than she.
1:19|Darby|If it please the king, let a royal order go forth from him,  and let it be written among the laws of the Persians and the  Medes, that it may not pass, That Vashti come no more before  king Ahasuerus; and let the king give her royal estate to  another that is better than she;
1:19|KJV|If it please the king, let there go a royal commandment from him, and let it be written among the laws of the Persians and the Medes, that it be not altered, That Vashti come no more before king Ahasuerus; and let the king give her royal estate unto another that is better than she.
1:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王若以為美，可以降旨，寫在波斯和瑪代人的法例中，永不廢除，不准瓦實提再到亞哈隨魯王面前，又請王將她王后的位分賜給比她好的人。
1:20|ASV|And when the king's decree which he shall make shall be published throughout all his kingdom (for it is great), all the wives will give to their husbands honor, both to great and small.
1:20|Darby|and when the king's edict which he shall make shall be  heard throughout his realm -- for it is great -- all the wives  shall give to their husbands honour, from the greatest to the  least.
1:20|KJV|And when the king's decree which he shall make shall be published throughout all his empire, (for it is great,) all the wives shall give to their husbands honour, both to great and small.
1:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王所降的旨意傳遍通國，（國度本來廣大，）所有的婦人，無論丈夫尊大或卑小，都必尊敬他。
1:21|ASV|And the saying pleased the king and the princes; and the king did according to the word of Memucan:
1:21|Darby|And the saying pleased the king and the princes; and the  king did according to the word of Memucan.
1:21|KJV|And the saying pleased the king and the princes; and the king did according to the word of Memucan:
1:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王和眾首領都以米母干的話為美，王就照這話去行，
1:22<version name="ASV">for he sent letters into all the king's provinces, into every province according to the writing thereof, and to every people after their language, that every man should bear rule in his own house, and should speak according to the language of his people. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:22<version name="Darby">And he sent letters into all the king's provinces, into  every province according to the writing thereof, and to every  people according to their language, That every man should bear  rule in his own house, and should speak according to the  language of his people. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:22<version name="KJV">For he sent letters into all the king's provinces, into every province according to the writing thereof, and to every people after their language, that every man should bear rule in his own house, and that it should be published according to the language of every people.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|發詔書到王的各省，依照各省的文字達於各省，依照各族的方言達於各族，使作丈夫的在自己家中作主，各說本族的方言。
2:1|ASV|After these things, when the wrath of king Ahasuerus was pacified, he remembered Vashti, and what she had done, and what was decreed against her.
2:1|Darby|After these things, when the fury of king Ahasuerus was  appeased, he remembered Vashti, and what she had done, and what  was decreed against her.
2:1|KJV|After these things, when the wrath of king Ahasuerus was appeased, he remembered Vashti, and what she had done, and what was decreed against her.
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些事以後，亞哈隨魯王的忿怒止息，就想念瓦實提和她所行的，並怎樣降旨辦她。
2:2|ASV|Then said the king's servants that ministered unto him, Let there be fair young virgins sought for the king:
2:2|Darby|Then said the king's servants that attended upon him, Let  there be maidens, virgins of beautiful countenance, sought for  the king;
2:2|KJV|Then said the king's servants that ministered unto him, Let there be fair young virgins sought for the king:
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是王的侍臣對王說，不如為王尋找美貌的年少處女。
2:3|ASV|and let the king appoint officers in all the provinces of his kingdom, that they may gather together all the fair young virgins unto Shushan the palace, to the house of the women, unto the custody of Hegai the king's chamberlain, keeper of the women; and let their things for purification be given them;
2:3|Darby|and let the king appoint officers in all the provinces of  his kingdom, that they may gather together all the young  virgins of beautiful countenance to Shushan the fortress, to  the house of the women, unto the custody of Hegai the king's  chamberlain, keeper of the women; and let their things for  purification be given.
2:3|KJV|And let the king appoint officers in all the provinces of his kingdom, that they may gather together all the fair young virgins unto Shushan the palace, to the house of the women, unto the custody of Hege the king's chamberlain, keeper of the women; and let their things for purification be given them:
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王可以派官員在國中的各省，把一切美貌的年少處女招聚到書珊京城的女院，交在王的太監，那照管女子的希該手下，給她們美容潤身的用品。
2:4|ASV|and let the maiden that pleaseth the king be queen instead of Vashti. And the thing pleased the king; and he did so.
2:4|Darby|And let the maiden that pleaseth the king be queen instead  of Vashti. And the thing pleased the king; and he did so.
2:4|KJV|And let the maiden which pleaseth the king be queen instead of Vashti. And the thing pleased the king; and he did so.
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王所喜愛的少女可以立為王后，代替瓦實提。王以這事為美，就如此行。
2:5|ASV|There was a certain Jew in Shushan the palace, whose name was Mordecai, the son of Jair, the son of Shimei, the son of Kish, a Benjamite,
2:5|Darby|There was in Shushan the fortress a certain Jew, whose name  was Mordecai, the son of Jair, the son of Shimei, the son of  Kish, a Benjaminite,
2:5|KJV|Now in Shushan the palace there was a certain Jew, whose name was Mordecai, the son of Jair, the son of Shimei, the son of Kish, a Benjamite;
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在書珊京城有一個猶大人，名叫末底改，是便雅憫人基士的曾孫，示每的孫子，睚珥的兒子；
2:6|ASV|who had been carried away from Jerusalem with the captives that had been carried away with Jeconiah king of Judah, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away.
2:6|Darby|who had been carried away from Jerusalem with the captives  who had been carried away with Jeconiah king of Judah, whom  Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away.
2:6|KJV|Who had been carried away from Jerusalem with the captivity which had been carried away with Jeconiah king of Judah, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away.
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|從前巴比倫王尼布甲尼撒將猶大王耶哥尼雅遷徙去，末底改也在那些與耶哥尼雅一同被擄的人中，從耶路撒冷被遷去。
2:7|ASV|And he brought up Hadassah, that is, Esther, his uncle's daughter: for she had neither father nor mother, and the maiden was fair and beautiful; and when her father and mother were dead, Mordecai took her for his own daughter.
2:7|Darby|And he brought up Hadassah, that is, Esther, his uncle's  daughter; for she had neither father nor mother -- and the  maiden was fair and beautiful -- and when her father and mother  were dead, Mordecai took her for his own daughter.
2:7|KJV|And he brought up Hadassah, that is, Esther, his uncle's daughter: for she had neither father nor mother, and the maid was fair and beautiful; whom Mordecai, when her father and mother were dead, took for his own daughter.
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|末底改撫養他叔叔的女兒哈大沙，就是以斯帖，因為她沒有父母；這女子形貌美麗。她父母死了，末底改就收她為自己的女兒。
2:8|ASV|So it came to pass, when the king's commandment and his decree was heard, and when many maidens were gathered together unto Shushan the palace, to the custody of Hegai, that Esther was taken into the king's house, to the custody of Hegai, keeper of the women.
2:8|Darby|And it came to pass when the king's commandment and his  decree was heard, and when many maidens were gathered together  unto Shushan the fortress, unto the custody of Hegai, that  Esther also was brought into the king's house, unto the custody  of Hegai, keeper of the women.
2:8|KJV|So it came to pass, when the king's commandment and his decree was heard, and when many maidens were gathered together unto Shushan the palace, to the custody of Hegai, that Esther was brought also unto the king's house, to the custody of Hegai, keeper of the women.
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王的諭旨和法令傳出，許多少女被招聚到書珊京城，交在希該手下，以斯帖也在這時候被帶進王宮，交在照管女子的希該手下。
2:9|ASV|And the maiden pleased him, and she obtained kindness of him; and he speedily gave her her things for purification, with her portions, and the seven maidens who were meet to be given her out of the king's house: and he removed her and her maidens to the best place of the house of the women.
2:9|Darby|And the maiden pleased him, and obtained favour before him;  and he speedily gave her her things for purification, and her  portions, and the seven maidens selected to be given her, out  of the king's house; and he removed her and her maids to the  best [place] of the house of the women.
2:9|KJV|And the maiden pleased him, and she obtained kindness of him; and he speedily gave her her things for purification, with such things as belonged to her, and seven maidens, which were meet to be given her, out of the king's house: and he preferred her and her maids unto the best place of the house of the women.
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這少女得希該喜悅，就在他面前得恩慈。希該急速給她美容潤身的用品，和她所當得的分，又給她所當得、七個從王宮挑選的侍女，並使她和她的侍女搬入女院上好的地方。
2:10|ASV|Esther had not made known her people nor her kindred; for Mordecai had charged her that she should not make it known.
2:10|Darby|Esther had not made known her people nor her birth; for  Mordecai had charged her that she should not make it known.
2:10|KJV|Esther had not shewed her people nor her kindred: for Mordecai had charged her that she should not shew it.
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以斯帖未曾將她是那一族、有那些親屬告訴人，因為末底改囑咐她不可叫人知道。
2:11|ASV|And Mordecai walked every day before the court of the women's house, to know how Esther did, and what would become of her.
2:11|Darby|And Mordecai walked every day before the court of the  women's house, to know how Esther did, and what should become  of her.
2:11|KJV|And Mordecai walked every day before the court of the women's house, to know how Esther did, and what should become of her.
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|末底改天天在女院前行走，要知道以斯帖平安不平安，並情況如何。
2:12|ASV|Now when the turn of every maiden was come to go in to king Ahasuerus, after that it had been done to her according to the law for the women twelve months (for so were the days of their purifications accomplished, to wit, six months with oil of myrrh, and six months with sweet odors and with the things for the purifying of the women),
2:12|Darby|And when every maiden's turn came to go in to king  Ahasuerus after that she had been treated for twelve months,  according to the manner of the women (for so were the days of  their purification accomplished -- six months with oil of  myrrh, and six months with spices, and with things for the  purifying of the women,
2:12|KJV|Now when every maid's turn was come to go in to king Ahasuerus, after that she had been twelve months, according to the manner of the women, (for so were the days of their purifications accomplished, to wit, six months with oil of myrrh, and six months with sweet odours, and with other things for the purifying of the women;)
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|原來女子要先美容潤身，六個月用沒藥油，六個月用香料和女子美容潤身的用品，美容潤身的日期纔滿足；每個少女按女子的定例豫備滿十二個月，挨次進去見亞哈隨魯王時，
2:13|ASV|then in this wise came the maiden unto the king: whatsoever she desired was given her to go with her out of the house of the women unto the king's house.
2:13|Darby|and thus came the maiden in unto the king), whatever she  desired was given her to go with her out of the house of the  women to the king's house.
2:13|KJV|Then thus came every maiden unto the king; whatsoever she desired was given her to go with her out of the house of the women unto the king's house.
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|乃是這樣進去見王：從女院到王宮的時候，凡她所要的，都必給她帶去。
2:14|ASV|In the evening she went, and on the morrow she returned into the second house of the women, to the custody of Shaashgaz, the king's chamberlain, who kept the concubines: she came in unto the king no more, except the king delighted in her, and she were called by name.
2:14|Darby|In the evening she went, and on the morrow she returned  into the second house of the women, unto the custody of  Shaashgaz, the king's chamberlain, keeper of the concubines.  She came in to the king no more, unless the king delighted in  her, and she were called by name.
2:14|KJV|In the evening she went, and on the morrow she returned into the second house of the women, to the custody of Shaashgaz, the king's chamberlain, which kept the concubines: she came in unto the king no more, except the king delighted in her, and that she were called by name.
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|晚上進去，次日早晨回到女子第二院，交在王的太監，那照管妃嬪的沙甲手下。除非王喜愛她，她被題名召見，就不再進去見王。
2:15|ASV|Now when the turn of Esther, the daughter of Abihail the uncle of Mordecai, who had taken her for his daughter, was come to go in unto the king, she required nothing but what Hegai the king's chamberlain, the keeper of the women, appointed. And Esther obtained favor in the sight of all them that looked upon her.
2:15|Darby|And when the turn of Esther, the daughter of Abihail the  uncle of Mordecai, who had taken her for his daughter, came to  go in to the king, she required nothing but what Hegai the  king's chamberlain, keeper of the women, appointed. And Esther  obtained grace in the sight of all them that saw her.
2:15|KJV|Now when the turn of Esther, the daughter of Abihail the uncle of Mordecai, who had taken her for his daughter, was come to go in unto the king, she required nothing but what Hegai the king's chamberlain, the keeper of the women, appointed. And Esther obtained favour in the sight of all them that looked upon her.
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|末底改叔叔亞比孩的女兒，就是末底改收為自己女兒的以斯帖，按次序當進去見王的時候，除了照管女子的太監希該所指定的，她別無所求。凡看見以斯帖的都喜悅她。
2:16|ASV|So Esther was taken unto king Ahasuerus into his house royal in the tenth month, which is the month Tebeth, in the seventh year of his reign.
2:16|Darby|So Esther was taken to king Ahasuerus, into his royal  house, in the tenth month, that is, the month Tebeth, in the  seventh year of his reign.
2:16|KJV|So Esther was taken unto king Ahasuerus into his house royal in the tenth month, which is the month Tebeth, in the seventh year of his reign.
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞哈隨魯王在位第七年十月，就是提別月，以斯帖被引入王宮見王。
2:17|ASV|And the king loved Esther above all the women, and she obtained favor and kindness in his sight more than all the virgins; so that he set the royal crown upon her head, and made her queen instead of Vashti.
2:17|Darby|And the king loved Esther above all the women, and she  obtained grace and favour in his sight more than all the  virgins, and he set the royal crown upon her head, and made her  queen instead of Vashti.
2:17|KJV|And the king loved Esther above all the women, and she obtained grace and favour in his sight more than all the virgins; so that he set the royal crown upon her head, and made her queen instead of Vashti.
2:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王愛以斯帖過於愛眾女子；她在王面前得蒙恩寵與恩慈，比眾處女更甚；王就把后冠戴在她頭上，立她為王后，代替瓦實提。
2:18|ASV|Then the king made a great feast unto all his princes and his servants, even Esther's feast; and he made a release to the provinces, and gave gifts, according to the bounty of the king.
2:18|Darby|And the king made a great feast to all his princes and his  servants, Esther's feast; and he made a release to the  provinces, and gave presents according to the king's bounty.
2:18|KJV|Then the king made a great feast unto all his princes and his servants, even Esther's feast; and he made a release to the provinces, and gave gifts, according to the state of the king.
2:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王給眾首領和臣僕設擺盛大的筵宴，稱之為以斯帖的筵宴，又向各省行豁免的事，並照王的厚意大頒賞賜。
2:19|ASV|And when the virgins were gathered together the second time, then Mordecai was sitting in the king's gate.
2:19|Darby|And when the virgins were gathered together the second  time, Mordecai sat in the king's gate.
2:19|KJV|And when the virgins were gathered together the second time, then Mordecai sat in the king's gate.
2:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|第二次招聚處女的時候，末底改坐在王門那堙C
2:20|ASV|Esther had not yet made known her kindred nor her people; as Mordecai had charged her: for Esther did the commandment of Mordecai, like as when she was brought up with him.
2:20|Darby|(Esther, as Mordecai had charged her, had not yet made  known her birth nor her people; for Esther did what Mordecai  told her, like as when she was brought up with him.)
2:20|KJV|Esther had not yet shewed her kindred nor her people; as Mordecai had charged her: for Esther did the commandment of Mordecai, like as when she was brought up with him.
2:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以斯帖照著末底改所囑咐的，還沒有將她有那些親屬，是那一族告訴人；因為以斯帖遵行末底改所說的，如同受他撫養的時候一樣。
2:21|ASV|In those days, while Mordecai was sitting in the king's gate, two of the king's chamberlains, Bigthan and Teresh, of those that kept the threshold, were wroth, and sought to lay hands on the king Ahasuerus.
2:21|Darby|In those days, while Mordecai sat in the king's gate, two  of the king's chamberlains, Bigthan and Teresh, of those which  kept the threshold, were wroth, and sought to lay hand on the  king Ahasuerus.
2:21|KJV|In those days, while Mordecai sat in the king's gate, two of the king's chamberlains, Bigthan and Teresh, of those which kept the door, were wroth, and sought to lay hands on the king Ahasuerus.
2:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當那些日子，末底改坐在王門那堙A王有兩個太監辟探和提列，是守門的，惱恨亞哈隨魯王，想要下手害他。
2:22|ASV|And the thing became known to Mordecai, who showed it unto Esther the queen; and Esther told the king thereof in Mordecai's name.
2:22|Darby|And the thing became known to Mordecai, and he related it  to Esther the queen, and Esther told it to the king in  Mordecai's name.
2:22|KJV|And the thing was known to Mordecai, who told it unto Esther the queen; and Esther certified the king thereof in Mordecai's name.
2:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這事給末底改知道了，他就告訴王后以斯帖；以斯帖奉末底改的名，報告於王。
2:23<version name="ASV">And when inquisition was made of the matter, and it was found to be so, they were both hanged on a tree: and it was written in the book of the chronicles before the king. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:23<version name="Darby">And the matter was investigated and found out; and they  were both hanged on a tree. And it was written in the book of  the chronicles before the king. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:23<version name="KJV">And when inquisition was made of the matter, it was found out; therefore they were both hanged on a tree: and it was written in the book of the chronicles before the king.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這事經過究察，果然是實，就把二人掛在木架上；這事且在王面前寫在年代志上。
3:1|ASV|After these things did king Ahasuerus promote Haman the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, and advanced him, and set his seat above all the princes that were with him.
3:1|Darby|After these things king Ahasuerus promoted Haman the son of  Hammedatha the Agagite, and advanced him, and set his seat  above all the princes that were with him.
3:1|KJV|After these things did king Ahasuerus promote Haman the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, and advanced him, and set his seat above all the princes that were with him.
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些事以後，亞哈隨魯王使亞甲族哈米大他的兒子哈曼尊大，抬舉他，叫他位居與他在一起的眾首領之上。
3:2|ASV|And all the king's servants, that were in the king's gate, bowed down, and did reverence to Haman; for the king had so commanded concerning him. But Mordecai bowed not down, nor did him reverence.
3:2|Darby|And all the king's servants that were in the king's gate  bowed and did Haman reverence, for the king had so commanded  concerning him. But Mordecai bowed not, nor did [him]  reverence.
3:2|KJV|And all the king's servants, that were in the king's gate, bowed, and reverenced Haman: for the king had so commanded concerning him. But Mordecai bowed not, nor did him reverence.
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在王門那堙A王的一切臣僕都跪拜哈曼，因為王曾如此吩咐；惟獨末底改不跪不拜。
3:3|ASV|Then the king's servants, that were in the king's gate, said unto Mordecai, Why transgressest thou the king's commandment?
3:3|Darby|Then the king's servants, who were in the king's gate, said  to Mordecai, Why transgressest thou the king's commandment?
3:3|KJV|Then the king's servants, which were in the king's gate, said unto Mordecai, Why transgressest thou the king's commandment?
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在王門那堙A王的臣僕問末底改說，你為何違犯王的命令呢？
3:4|ASV|Now it came to pass, when they spake daily unto him, and he hearkened not unto them, that they told Haman, to see whether Mordecai's matters would stand: for he had told them that he was a Jew.
3:4|Darby|And it came to pass as they spoke daily to him, and he  hearkened not to them, that they informed Haman, to see whether  Mordecai's matters would stand; for he had told them that he  was a Jew.
3:4|KJV|Now it came to pass, when they spake daily unto him, and he hearkened not unto them, that they told Haman, to see whether Mordecai's matters would stand: for he had told them that he was a Jew.
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們天天這樣對他說，他還是不聽，他們就告訴哈曼，要看末底改的話站得住站不住，因他已經告訴他們自己是猶大人。
3:5|ASV|And when Haman saw that Mordecai bowed not down, nor did him reverence, then was Haman full of wrath.
3:5|Darby|And when Haman saw that Mordecai bowed not, nor did him  reverence, Haman was full of fury.
3:5|KJV|And when Haman saw that Mordecai bowed not, nor did him reverence, then was Haman full of wrath.
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈曼見末底改向他不跪不拜，就怒氣填胸。
3:6|ASV|But he thought scorn to lay hands on Mordecai alone; for they had made known to him the people of Mordecai: wherefore Haman sought to destroy all the Jews that were throughout the whole kingdom of Ahasuerus, even the people of Mordecai.
3:6|Darby|But he scorned to lay hands on Mordecai alone; for they had  made known to him the people of Mordecai; therefore Haman  sought to destroy all the Jews that were in all the kingdom of  Ahasuerus -- the people of Mordecai.
3:6|KJV|And he thought scorn to lay hands on Mordecai alone; for they had shewed him the people of Mordecai: wherefore Haman sought to destroy all the Jews that were throughout the whole kingdom of Ahasuerus, even the people of Mordecai.
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈曼不屑只下手害末底改一人，因他們已將末底改的本族告訴他，所以他想要滅絕亞哈隨魯王通國所有的猶大人，就是末底改的本族。
3:7|ASV|In the first month, which is the month Nisan, in the twelfth year of king Ahasuerus, they cast Pur, that is, the lot, before Haman from day to day, and from month to month, to the twelfth month, which is the month Adar.
3:7|Darby|In the first month, that is, the month Nisan, in the twelfth  year of king Ahasuerus, they cast Pur, that is, the lot, before  Haman for each day and for each month, to the twelfth [month],  that is, the month Adar.
3:7|KJV|In the first month, that is, the month Nisan, in the twelfth year of king Ahasuerus, they cast Pur, that is, the lot, before Haman from day to day, and from month to month, to the twelfth month, that is, the month Adar.
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞哈隨魯王十二年正月，就是尼散月，人在哈曼面前，按日子和月分掣普珥，就是掣籤，擇定了十二月，就是亞達月。
3:8|ASV|And Haman said unto king Ahasuerus, There is a certain people scattered abroad and dispersed among the peoples in all the provinces of thy kingdom; and their laws are diverse from those of every people; neither keep they the king's laws: therefore it is not for the king's profit to suffer them.
3:8|Darby|And Haman said to king Ahasuerus, There is a people  scattered abroad and dispersed among the peoples in all the  provinces of thy kingdom; and their laws are diverse from  [those of] every people, and they keep not the king's laws; and  it is not for the king's profit to suffer them.
3:8|KJV|And Haman said unto king Ahasuerus, There is a certain people scattered abroad and dispersed among the people in all the provinces of thy kingdom; and their laws are diverse from all people; neither keep they the king's laws: therefore it is not for the king's profit to suffer them.
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈曼對亞哈隨魯王說，有一種民散居在王國各省的民中；他們的律例與萬民的律例不同，他們也不遵行王的律例，所以容留他們對王並不妥當。
3:9|ASV|If it please the king, let it be written that they be destroyed: and I will pay ten thousand talents of silver into the hands of those that have the charge of the king's business, to bring it into the king's treasuries.
3:9|Darby|If it please the king, let it be written that they may be  destroyed, and I will pay ten thousand talents of silver into  the hands of those that have charge of the affairs, to bring  [it] into the king's treasuries.
3:9|KJV|If it please the king, let it be written that they may be destroyed: and I will pay ten thousand talents of silver to the hands of those that have the charge of the business, to bring it into the king's treasuries.
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王若以為美，請下詔滅絕他們；我就稱一萬他連得銀子，交給辦理王事的人，納入王的府庫。
3:10|ASV|And the king took his ring from his hand, and gave it unto Haman the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, the Jews' enemy.
3:10|Darby|And the king took his ring from his hand, and gave it to  Haman the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, the Jews' enemy.
3:10|KJV|And the king took his ring from his hand, and gave it unto Haman the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, the Jews' enemy.
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是王從自己手上摘下戒指，給猶大人的仇敵亞甲族哈米大他的兒子哈曼。
3:11|ASV|And the king said unto Haman, The silver is given to thee, the people also, to do with them as it seemeth good to thee.
3:11|Darby|And the king said to Haman, The silver is given to thee,  the people also, to do with them as seems good to thee.
3:11|KJV|And the king said unto Haman, The silver is given to thee, the people also, to do with them as it seemeth good to thee.
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王對哈曼說，這銀子仍賜給你，這民也交給你，你看怎樣好，就怎樣待他們。
3:12|ASV|Then were the king's scribes called in the first month, on the thirteenth day thereof; and there was written according to all that Haman commanded unto the king's satraps, and to the governors that were over every province, and to the princes of every people, to every province according to the writing thereof, and to every people after their language; in the name of king Ahasuerus was it written, and it was sealed with the king's ring.
3:12|Darby|Then were the king's scribes called, in the first month, on  the thirteenth day of the [month], and there was written  according to all that Haman commanded unto the king's satraps,  and to the governors over every province, and to the princes of  every people; to every province according to the writing  thereof, and to every people according to their language: in  the name of king Ahasuerus was it written, and sealed with the  king's ring.
3:12|KJV|Then were the king's scribes called on the thirteenth day of the first month, and there was written according to all that Haman had commanded unto the king's lieutenants, and to the governors that were over every province, and to the rulers of every people of every province according to the writing thereof, and to every people after their language; in the name of king Ahasuerus was it written, and sealed with the king's ring.
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|正月十三日，王的書記被召來，照著哈曼一切所吩咐的寫了詔書，傳與王的總督、各省的省長、和各族的首領，依照各省的文字達於各省，依照各族的方言達於各族；是奉亞哈隨魯王的名寫的，並且用王的戒指蓋了印。
3:13|ASV|And letters were sent by posts into all the king's provinces, to destroy, to slay, and to cause to perish, all Jews, both young and old, little children and women, in one day, even upon the thirteenth day of the twelfth month, which is the month Adar, and to take the spoil of them for a prey.
3:13|Darby|And the letters were sent by couriers into all the king's  provinces, to destroy, to kill, and to cause to perish, all  Jews, both young and old, little children and women, in one  day, upon the thirteenth of the twelfth month, that is, the  month Adar, and [to take] the spoil of them for a prey.
3:13|KJV|And the letters were sent by posts into all the king's provinces, to destroy, to kill, and to cause to perish, all Jews, both young and old, little children and women, in one day, even upon the thirteenth day of the twelfth month, which is the month Adar, and to take the spoil of them for a prey.
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|詔書由驛卒送達王的各省，吩咐要將所有的猶大人，無論老少婦女孩子，在一日之間，在十二月，就是亞達月十三日，全然殲毀，殺戮滅絕，並奪他們的財物為掠物。
3:14|ASV|A copy of the writing, that the decree should be given out in every province, was published unto all the peoples, that they should be ready against that day.
3:14|Darby|That the decree might be given in every province, a copy of  the writing was published to all peoples, that they should be  ready against that day.
3:14|KJV|The copy of the writing for a commandment to be given in every province was published unto all people, that they should be ready against that day.
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這文書經過抄錄，頒行各省成為法令，向各族宣示，使他們豫備等候那日。
3:15<version name="ASV">The posts went forth in haste by the king's commandment, and the decree was given out in Shushan the palace. And the king and Haman sat down to drink; but the city of Shushan was perplexed. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:15<version name="Darby">The couriers went out, being hastened by the king's  commandment, and the decree was given in Shushan the fortress.  And the king and Haman sat down to drink; but the city of  Shushan was in consternation. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:15<version name="KJV">The posts went out, being hastened by the king's commandment, and the decree was given in Shushan the palace. And the king and Haman sat down to drink; but the city Shushan was perplexed.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|驛卒奉王的諭旨急忙出發；法令也在書珊京城頒佈。王和哈曼坐下飲酒，書珊城卻一片慌亂。
4:1|ASV|Now when Mordecai knew all that was done, Mordecai rent his clothes, and put on sackcloth with ashes, and went out into the midst of the city, and cried with a loud and a bitter cry;
4:1|Darby|And when Mordecai knew all that was done, Mordecai rent his  garments, and put on sackcloth with ashes, and went out into  the midst of the city, and cried with a loud and bitter cry,
4:1|KJV|When Mordecai perceived all that was done, Mordecai rent his clothes, and put on sackcloth with ashes, and went out into the midst of the city, and cried with a loud and a bitter cry;
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|末底改知道所發生的這一切事，就撕裂衣服，穿麻衣，蒙灰塵，在城中行走，大聲哀號。
4:2|ASV|and he came even before the king's gate: for none might enter within the king's gate clothed with sackcloth.
4:2|Darby|and came even before the king's gate; for none might enter  into the king's gate clothed with sackcloth.
4:2|KJV|And came even before the king's gate: for none might enter into the king's gate clothed with sackcloth.
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|到了王門前停住腳步，因為穿麻衣的不可進王門。
4:3|ASV|And in every province, whithersoever the king's commandment and his decree came, there was great mourning among the Jews, and fasting, and weeping, and wailing; and many lay in sackcloth and ashes.
4:3|Darby|And in every province, wherever the king's commandment and  his decree came, there was great mourning among the Jews, and  fasting, and weeping, and wailing: many lay in sackcloth and  ashes.
4:3|KJV|And in every province, whithersoever the king's commandment and his decree came, there was great mourning among the Jews, and fasting, and weeping, and wailing; and many lay in sackcloth and ashes.
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王的諭旨和法令所到的各省各處，猶大人大大悲哀，禁食哭泣哀號，穿麻衣躺在灰中的甚多。
4:4|ASV|And Esther's maidens and her chamberlains came and told it her; and the queen was exceedingly grieved: and she sent raiment to clothe Mordecai, and to take his sackcloth from off him; but he received it not.
4:4|Darby|And Esther's maids and her chamberlains came and told [it]  her; and the queen was exceedingly grieved: and she sent  raiment to clothe Mordecai, and to take away his sackcloth from  him; but he received [it] not.
4:4|KJV|So Esther's maids and her chamberlains came and told it her. Then was the queen exceedingly grieved; and she sent raiment to clothe Mordecai, and to take away his sackcloth from him: but he received it not.
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王后以斯帖的宮女和太監來把這事告訴以斯帖，她甚是憂愁，就送衣服給末底改穿，要他脫下麻衣，他卻不接受。
4:5|ASV|Then called Esther for Hathach, one of the king's chamberlains, whom he had appointed to attend upon her, and charged him to go to Mordecai, to know what this was, and why it was.
4:5|Darby|Then Esther called for Hatach, [one] of the king's  chamberlains, whom he had appointed to wait upon her, and gave  him a commandment to Mordecai, to know what it was, and why it  was.
4:5|KJV|Then called Esther for Hatach, one of the king's chamberlains, whom he had appointed to attend upon her, and gave him a commandment to Mordecai, to know what it was, and why it was.
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以斯帖就把王所派伺候她的一個太監，名叫哈他革召來，吩咐他去見末底改，要知道這是甚麼事，是為甚麼緣故。
4:6|ASV|So Hathach went forth to Mordecai unto the broad place of the city, which was before the king's gate.
4:6|Darby|And Hatach went forth to Mordecai, unto the public place of  the city which was before the king's gate.
4:6|KJV|So Hatach went forth to Mordecai unto the street of the city, which was before the king's gate.
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是哈他革出到王門前城的寬闊處，見末底改。
4:7|ASV|And Mordecai told him of all that had happened unto him, and the exact sum of the money that Haman had promised to pay to the king's treasuries for the Jews, to destroy them.
4:7|Darby|And Mordecai told him of all that had happened to him, and  of the sum of money that Haman had promised to pay to the  king's treasuries for the Jews, to destroy them.
4:7|KJV|And Mordecai told him of all that had happened unto him, and of the sum of the money that Haman had promised to pay to the king's treasuries for the Jews, to destroy them.
4:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|末底改將自己所遇的一切事，並哈曼為滅絕猶大人應許捐入王庫的準確銀數，都告訴了他；
4:8|ASV|Also he gave him the copy of the writing of the decree that was given out in Shushan to destroy them, to show it unto Esther, and to declare it unto her, and to charge her that she should go in unto the king, to make supplication unto him, and to make request before him, for her people.
4:8|Darby|And he gave him a copy of the writing of the decree that had  been given at Shushan to destroy them, to shew [it] to Esther,  and to declare [it] to her, and to charge her that she should  go in unto the king, to make supplication to him, and to make  request before him, for her people.
4:8|KJV|Also he gave him the copy of the writing of the decree that was given at Shushan to destroy them, to shew it unto Esther, and to declare it unto her, and to charge her that she should go in unto the king, to make supplication unto him, and to make request before him for her people.
4:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又將所抄寫在書珊頒佈，要滅絕猶大人的法令交給哈他革，要他給以斯帖看，向她說明，並囑咐她進去見王，向王求情，為本族的人在王面前懇求。
4:9|ASV|And Hathach came and told Esther the words of Mordecai.
4:9|Darby|And Hatach came and told Esther the words of Mordecai.
4:9|KJV|And Hatach came and told Esther the words of Mordecai.
4:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈他革回來，將末底改的話告訴以斯帖；
4:10|ASV|Then Esther spake unto Hathach, and gave him a message unto Mordecai  saying:
4:10|Darby|And Esther spoke to Hatach, and gave him commandment unto  Mordecai:
4:10|KJV|Again Esther spake unto Hatach, and gave him commandment unto Mordecai;
4:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以斯帖就把以下的話告訴哈他革，吩咐他去見末底改，說，
4:11|ASV|All the king's servants, and the people of the king's provinces, do know, that whosoever, whether man or woman, shall come unto the king into the inner court, who is not called, there is one law for him, that he be put to death, except those to whom the king shall hold out the golden sceptre, that he may live: but I have not been called to come in unto the king these thirty days.
4:11|Darby|All the king's servants and the people of the king's  provinces do know that whoever, whether man or woman, shall  come to the king into the inner court, who is not called, there  is *one* law, to put [him] to death, except [such] to whom the  king shall hold out the golden sceptre, that he may live; and I  have not been called to come in unto the king these thirty  days.
4:11|KJV|All the king's servants, and the people of the king's provinces, do know, that whosoever, whether man or women, shall come unto the king into the inner court, who is not called, there is one law of his to put him to death, except such to whom the king shall hold out the golden sceptre, that he may live: but I have not been called to come in unto the king these thirty days.
4:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王的一切臣僕和王各省的人民都知道一條法令，無論男女，若不蒙召就進入內院見王，必被處死，除非王向他伸出金杖，叫他得以存活；現在我沒有蒙召進去見王已經三十日了。
4:12|ASV|And they told to Mordecai Esther's words.
4:12|Darby|And they told Mordecai Esther's words.
4:12|KJV|And they told to Mordecai Esther's words.
4:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人就把以斯帖的話告訴末底改。
4:13|ASV|Then Mordecai bade them return answer unto Esther, Think not with thyself that thou shalt escape in the king's house, more than all the Jews.
4:13|Darby|And Mordecai bade to answer Esther: Imagine not in thy  heart that thou shalt escape in the king's house, more than all  the Jews.
4:13|KJV|Then Mordecai commanded to answer Esther, Think not with thyself that thou shalt escape in the king's house, more than all the Jews.
4:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|末底改叫人回覆以斯帖說，你不要以為在王宮奡N強過一切猶大人，得免這禍。
4:14|ASV|For if thou altogether holdest thy peace at this time, then will relief and deliverance arise to the Jews from another place, but thou and thy father's house will perish: and who knoweth whether thou art not come to the kingdom for such a time as this?
4:14|Darby|For if thou altogether holdest thy peace at this time, then  shall there arise relief and deliverance to the Jews from  another place; but thou and thy father's house shall perish.  And who knows whether thou art [not] come to the kingdom for  such a time as this?
4:14|KJV|For if thou altogether holdest thy peace at this time, then shall there enlargement and deliverance arise to the Jews from another place; but thou and thy father's house shall be destroyed: and who knoweth whether thou art come to the kingdom for such a time as this?
4:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|此時你若閉口不言，猶大人必從別處得解脫，蒙拯救；你和你父家就必滅亡。焉知你得了王后的位分，不是為現今這樣的時機麼？
4:15|ASV|Then Esther bade them return answer unto Mordecai,
4:15|Darby|And Esther bade to answer Mordecai:
4:15|KJV|Then Esther bade them return Mordecai this answer,
4:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以斯帖就叫人回報末底改說，
4:16|ASV|Go, gather together all the Jews that are present in Shushan, and fast ye for me, and neither eat nor drink three days, night or day: I also and my maidens will fast in like manner; and so will I go in unto the king, which is not according to the law: and if I perish, I perish.
4:16|Darby|Go, gather together all the Jews that are found in Shushan,  and fast for me, and neither eat nor drink three days, night or  day: I also and my maidens will fast likewise, and so will I go  in unto the king, which is not according to the law; and if I  perish, I perish.
4:16|KJV|Go, gather together all the Jews that are present in Shushan, and fast ye for me, and neither eat nor drink three days, night or day: I also and my maidens will fast likewise; and so will I go in unto the king, which is not according to the law: and if I perish, I perish.
4:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你當去招聚書珊城所有的猶大人，為我禁食，三日之內，晝夜不喫不喝；我和我的侍女也要這樣禁食。然後我就違令進去見王；我若滅亡就滅亡罷。
4:17<version name="ASV">So Mordecai went his way, and did according to all that Esther had commanded him. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:17<version name="Darby">And Mordecai went his way, and did according to all that  Esther had commanded him. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:17<version name="KJV">So Mordecai went his way, and did according to all that Esther had commanded him.</p><p /><br /></version>
4:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是末底改就去照以斯帖一切所吩咐的而行。
5:1|ASV|Now it came to pass on the third day, that Esther put on her royal apparel, and stood in the inner court of the king's house, over against the king's house: and the king sat upon his royal throne in the royal house, over against the entrance of the house.
5:1|Darby|And it came to pass on the third day, that Esther put on  royal apparel, and stood in the inner court of the king's  house, over against the king's house. And the king sat upon his  royal throne in the royal house, over against the entrance to  the house.
5:1|KJV|Now it came to pass on the third day, that Esther put on her royal apparel, and stood in the inner court of the king's house, over against the king's house: and the king sat upon his royal throne in the royal house, over against the gate of the house.
5:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|第三日，以斯帖穿上朝服，進王宮的內院，對殿站立。王在殿塈丹b寶座上，對著殿門。
5:2|ASV|And it was so, when the king saw Esther the queen standing in the court, that she obtained favor in his sight; and the king held out to Esther the golden sceptre that was in his hand. So Esther drew near, and touched the top of the sceptre.
5:2|Darby|And it was so, when the king saw the queen Esther standing  in the court, that she obtained grace in his sight; and the  king held out to Esther the golden sceptre that was in his  hand; and Esther drew near, and touched the top of the sceptre.
5:2|KJV|And it was so, when the king saw Esther the queen standing in the court, that she obtained favour in his sight: and the king held out to Esther the golden sceptre that was in his hand. So Esther drew near, and touched the top of the sceptre.
5:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王見王后以斯帖站在院內，以斯帖在王眼前蒙恩，王向她伸出手中的金杖；以斯帖便進前摸杖頭。
5:3|ASV|Then said the king unto her, What wilt thou, queen Esther? and what is thy request? it shall be given thee even to the half of the kingdom.
5:3|Darby|And the king said to her, What wilt thou, queen Esther? and  what is thy request? it shall be given thee even to the half of  the kingdom.
5:3|KJV|Then said the king unto her, What wilt thou, queen Esther? and what is thy request? it shall be even given thee to the half of the kingdom.
5:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王對她說，王后以斯帖阿，你有甚麼事？你求甚麼？就是國的一半，也必賜給你。
5:4|ASV|And Esther said, If it seem good unto the king, let the king and Haman come this day unto the banquet that I have prepared for him.
5:4|Darby|And Esther said, If it seem good to the king, let the king  and Haman come this day to the banquet that I have prepared for  him.
5:4|KJV|And Esther answered, If it seem good unto the king, let the king and Haman come this day unto the banquet that I have prepared for him.
5:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以斯帖說，王若以為美，就請王和哈曼今日赴我所豫備的筵席。
5:5|ASV|Then the king said, Cause Haman to make haste, that it may be done as Esther hath said. So the king and Haman came to the banquet that Esther had prepared.
5:5|Darby|And the king said, Hasten Haman, that it may be done as  Esther has said. And the king and Haman came to the banquet  that Esther had prepared.
5:5|KJV|Then the king said, Cause Haman to make haste, that he may do as Esther hath said. So the king and Haman came to the banquet that Esther had prepared.
5:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王說，快把哈曼叫來，我們好照著以斯帖的話去行。於是王帶著哈曼赴以斯帖所豫備的筵席。
5:6|ASV|And the king said unto Esther at the banquet of wine, What is thy petition? and it shall be granted thee: and what is thy request? even to the half of the kingdom it shall be performed.
5:6|Darby|And the king said to Esther at the banquet of wine, What is  thy petition? and it shall be granted thee; and what is thy  request? even to the half of the kingdom it shall be done.
5:6|KJV|And the king said unto Esther at the banquet of wine, What is thy petition? and it shall be granted thee: and what is thy request? even to the half of the kingdom it shall be performed.
5:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在酒筵中，王問以斯帖說，你要甚麼？我必賜給你。你求甚麼？就是國的一半，也必為你成就。
5:7|ASV|Then answered Esther, and said, My petition and my request is:
5:7|Darby|And Esther answered and said, My petition and my request is,
5:7|KJV|Then answered Esther, and said, My petition and my request is;
5:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以斯帖回答說，我有所要，我有所求。
5:8|ASV|if I have found favor in the sight of the king, and if it please the king to grant my petition, and to perform my request, let the king and Haman come to the banquet that I shall prepare for them, and I will do to-morrow as the king hath said.
5:8|Darby|If I have found grace in the sight of the king, and if it  please the king to grant my petition, and to perform my  request, let the king and Haman come to the banquet that I  shall prepare for them, and I will do to-morrow according to  the king's word.
5:8|KJV|If I have found favour in the sight of the king, and if it please the king to grant my petition, and to perform my request, let the king and Haman come to the banquet that I shall prepare for them, and I will do to morrow as the king hath said.
5:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我若在王眼前蒙恩，王若喜悅賜我所要的，成就我所求的，就請王和哈曼再赴我所要豫備的筵席；明日我必照王所問的說明。
5:9|ASV|Then went Haman forth that day joyful and glad of heart: but when Haman saw Mordecai in the king's gate, that he stood not up nor moved for him, he was filled with wrath against Mordecai.
5:9|Darby|And Haman went forth that day joyful and glad of heart; but  when Haman saw Mordecai in the king's gate, that he stood not  up nor moved for him, he was full of fury against Mordecai.
5:9|KJV|Then went Haman forth that day joyful and with a glad heart: but when Haman saw Mordecai in the king's gate, that he stood not up, nor moved for him, he was full of indignation against Mordecai.
5:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那日哈曼心中歡喜快樂的出來；但見末底改在王門不站起來，也不因他戰抖，就滿心惱怒末底改。
5:10|ASV|Nevertheless Haman refrained himself, and went home; and he sent and fetched his friends and Zeresh his wife.
5:10|Darby|But Haman controlled himself, and came home; and he sent  and called for his friends, and Zeresh his wife.
5:10|KJV|Nevertheless Haman refrained himself: and when he came home, he sent and called for his friends, and Zeresh his wife.
5:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈曼暫且忍耐回家，叫人請他朋友和他妻子細利斯來。
5:11|ASV|And Haman recounted unto them the glory of his riches, and the multitude of his children, and all the things wherein the king had promoted him, and how he had advanced him above the princes and servants of the king.
5:11|Darby|And Haman told them of the glory of his riches, and the  multitude of his children, and all wherein the king had  promoted him, and how he had advanced him above the princes and  servants of the king.
5:11|KJV|And Haman told them of the glory of his riches, and the multitude of his children, and all the things wherein the king had promoted him, and how he had advanced him above the princes and servants of the king.
5:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈曼將他財富的榮耀、兒女的眾多、以及王使他尊大、抬舉他超乎眾首領和王的臣僕之上的一切事，都述說給他們聽。
5:12|ASV|Haman said moreover, Yea, Esther the queen did let no man come in with the king unto the banquet that she had prepared but myself; and to-morrow also am I invited by her together with the king.
5:12|Darby|And Haman said, Yea, Esther the queen let no man come in  with the king to the banquet that she had prepared but myself;  and to-morrow also I am invited to her with the king.
5:12|KJV|Haman said moreover, Yea, Esther the queen did let no man come in with the king unto the banquet that she had prepared but myself; and to morrow am I invited unto her also with the king.
5:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈曼又說，王后以斯帖豫備筵席，除了我之外，沒有請別人隨王赴席，明日王后又請我隨王赴席。
5:13|ASV|Yet all this availeth me nothing, so long as I see Mordecai the Jew sitting at the king's gate.
5:13|Darby|Yet all this is of no avail to me so long as I see Mordecai  the Jew sitting at the king's gate.
5:13|KJV|Yet all this availeth me nothing, so long as I see Mordecai the Jew sitting at the king's gate.
5:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只是每逢我見猶大人末底改坐在王門那堙A這一切對我就都沒有甚麼意思。
5:14<version name="ASV">Then said Zeresh his wife and all his friends unto him, Let a gallows be made fifty cubits high, and in the morning speak thou unto the king that Mordecai may be hanged thereon: then go thou in merrily with the king unto the banquet. And the thing pleased Haman; and he caused the gallows to be made. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:14<version name="Darby">Then said Zeresh his wife and all his friends to him, Let a  gallows be made of fifty cubits high, and in the morning speak  to the king that Mordecai may be hanged on it: then go in  merrily with the king to the banquet. And the thing pleased  Haman; and he caused the gallows to be made. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:14<version name="KJV">Then said Zeresh his wife and all his friends unto him, Let a gallows be made of fifty cubits high, and to morrow speak thou unto the king that Mordecai may be hanged thereon: then go thou in merrily with the king unto the banquet. And the thing pleased Haman; and he caused the gallows to be made.</p><p /><br /></version>
5:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他的妻子細利斯和他一切的朋友對他說，不如叫人作一個五十肘高的木架，明早求王將末底改掛在其上，然後你可以歡歡喜喜的隨王赴席。哈曼以這話為美，就叫人作了木架。
6:1|ASV|On that night could not the king sleep; and he commanded to bring the book of records of the chronicles, and they were read before the king.
6:1|Darby|On that night sleep fled from the king. And he commanded to  bring the book of records of the chronicles; and they were read  before the king.
6:1|KJV|On that night could not the king sleep, and he commanded to bring the book of records of the chronicles; and they were read before the king.
6:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那夜王睡不著覺，就吩咐人取年代記事錄來；人就在王面前念給他聽。
6:2|ASV|And it was found written, that Mordecai had told of Bigthana and Teresh, two of the king's chamberlains, of those that kept the threshold, who had sought to lay hands on the king Ahasuerus.
6:2|Darby|And it was found written, that Mordecai had told of Bigthana  and Teresh, two of the king's chamberlains, keepers of the  threshold, who had sought to lay hand on king Ahasuerus.
6:2|KJV|And it was found written, that Mordecai had told of Bigthana and Teresh, two of the king's chamberlains, the keepers of the door, who sought to lay hand on the king Ahasuerus.
6:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|正念到其上寫著說，王有兩個太監辟探和提列，是守門的，想要下手害亞哈隨魯王，末底改告發了他們。
6:3|ASV|And the king said, What honor and dignity hath been bestowed on Mordecai for this? Then said the king's servants that ministered unto him, There is nothing done for him.
6:3|Darby|And the king said, What honour and dignity has been done to  Mordecai for this? And the king's servants that attended upon  him said, Nothing has been done for him.
6:3|KJV|And the king said, What honour and dignity hath been done to Mordecai for this? Then said the king's servants that ministered unto him, There is nothing done for him.
6:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王說，末底改行了這事，賜他甚麼尊榮爵位沒有？伺候王的臣僕說，沒有賜他甚麼。
6:4|ASV|And the king said, Who is in the court? Now Haman was come into the outward court of the king's house, to speak unto the king to hang Mordecai on the gallows that he had prepared for him.
6:4|Darby|And the king said, Who is in the court? Now Haman had come  into the outward court of the king's house, to speak to the  king to hang Mordecai on the gallows that he had prepared for  him.
6:4|KJV|And the king said, Who is in the court? Now Haman was come into the outward court of the king's house, to speak unto the king to hang Mordecai on the gallows that he had prepared for him.
6:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王說，誰在院子堙H那時哈曼正進王宮的外院，要求王將末底改掛在他所豫備的木架上。
6:5|ASV|And the king's servants said unto him, Behold, Haman standeth in the court. And the king said, Let him come in.
6:5|Darby|And the king's servants said to him, Behold, Haman is  standing in the court. And the king said, Let him come in.
6:5|KJV|And the king's servants said unto him, Behold, Haman standeth in the court. And the king said, Let him come in.
6:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王的臣僕說，看哪，哈曼站在院內。王說，讓他進來。
6:6|ASV|So Haman came in. And the king said unto him, What shall be done unto the man whom the king delighteth to honor? Now Haman said in his heart, To whom would the king delight to do honor more than to myself?
6:6|Darby|So Haman came in. And the king said to him, What is to be  done with the man whom the king delights to honour? Now Haman  thought in his heart, To whom would the king delight to do  honour more than to me?
6:6|KJV|So Haman came in. And the king said unto him, What shall be done unto the man whom the king delighteth to honour? Now Haman thought in his heart, To whom would the king delight to do honour more than to myself?
6:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈曼就進去；王問他說，王喜歡賜尊榮的人，當如何待他呢？哈曼心婸﹛A王喜歡賜尊榮的，不是我是誰呢？
6:7|ASV|And Haman said unto the king, For the man whom the king delighteth to honor,
6:7|Darby|And Haman answered the king, For the man whom the king  delights to honour,
6:7|KJV|And Haman answered the king, For the man whom the king delighteth to honour,
6:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈曼就對王說，對於王喜歡賜尊榮的人，
6:8|ASV|let royal apparel be brought which the king useth to wear, and the horse that the king rideth upon, and on the head of which a crown royal is set:
6:8|Darby|let the royal apparel be brought with which the king arrays  himself, and the horse that the king rides upon, and on the  head of which the royal crown is set;
6:8|KJV|Let the royal apparel be brought which the king useth to wear, and the horse that the king rideth upon, and the crown royal which is set upon his head:
6:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當將王穿過的朝服，和王所騎過、頭戴御冠的馬帶來，
6:9|ASV|and let the apparel and the horse be delivered to the hand of one of the king's most noble princes, that they may array the man therewith whom the king delighteth to honor, and cause him to ride on horseback through the street of the city, and proclaim before him, Thus shall it be done to the man whom the king delighteth to honor.
6:9|Darby|and let the apparel and horse be delivered into the hand of  one of the king's most noble princes, and let them array the  man whom the king delights to honour, and cause him to ride on  the horse through the street of the city, and proclaim before  him, Thus shall it be done to the man whom the king delights to  honour!
6:9|KJV|And let this apparel and horse be delivered to the hand of one of the king's most noble princes, that they may array the man withal whom the king delighteth to honour, and bring him on horseback through the street of the city, and proclaim before him, Thus shall it be done to the man whom the king delighteth to honour.
6:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|將朝服和馬交在王極尊貴的一個大臣手中，命人將朝服給王喜歡賜尊榮的人穿上，使他騎上馬，走遍城堛熊韞哄A叫人在他面前宣告說，王喜歡賜尊榮的人，就如此待他。
6:10|ASV|Then the king said to Haman, Make haste, and take the apparel and the horse, as thou hast said, and do even so to Mordecai the Jew, that sitteth at the king's gate: let nothing fail of all that thou hast spoken.
6:10|Darby|And the king said to Haman, Make haste, take the apparel  and the horse, as thou hast said, and do so to Mordecai the  Jew, who sits at the king's gate: let nothing fail of all that  thou hast said.
6:10|KJV|Then the king said to Haman, Make haste, and take the apparel and the horse, as thou hast said, and do even so to Mordecai the Jew, that sitteth at the king's gate: let nothing fail of all that thou hast spoken.
6:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王對哈曼說，照你所說的，快快取朝服和馬，去向坐在王門那堛熊S大人末底改那樣行。凡你所說的，一樣不可缺。
6:11|ASV|Then took Haman the apparel and the horse, and arrayed Mordecai, and caused him to ride through the street of the city, and proclaimed before him, Thus shall it be done unto the man whom the king delighteth to honor.
6:11|Darby|And Haman took the apparel and the horse, and arrayed  Mordecai, and caused him to ride through the street of the  city, and proclaimed before him, Thus shall it be done to the  man whom the king delights to honour!
6:11|KJV|Then took Haman the apparel and the horse, and arrayed Mordecai, and brought him on horseback through the street of the city, and proclaimed before him, Thus shall it be done unto the man whom the king delighteth to honour.
6:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是哈曼取了朝服和馬，將朝服給末底改穿上，使他騎上馬，走遍城堛熊韞哄A並在他面前宣告說，王喜歡賜尊榮的人，就如此待他。
6:12|ASV|And Mordecai came again to the king's gate. But Haman hasted to his house, mourning and having his head covered.
6:12|Darby|And Mordecai came again to the king's gate. But Haman  hasted to his house, mourning and having his head covered.
6:12|KJV|And Mordecai came again to the king's gate. But Haman hasted to his house mourning, and having his head covered.
6:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|末底改仍回到王門那堙F哈曼卻悲哀的蒙著頭，急忙回家去了。
6:13|ASV|And Haman recounted unto Zeresh his wife and all his friends everything that had befallen him. Then said his wise men and Zeresh his wife unto him, If Mordecai, before whom thou hast begun to fall, be of the seed of the Jews, thou shalt not prevail against him, but shalt surely fall before him.
6:13|Darby|And Haman recounted to Zeresh his wife and to all his  friends all that had befallen him. Then said his wise men and  Zeresh his wife to him, If Mordecai be of the seed of the Jews,  before whom thou hast begun to fall, thou shalt not prevail  against him, but wilt certainly fall before him.
6:13|KJV|And Haman told Zeresh his wife and all his friends every thing that had befallen him. Then said his wise men and Zeresh his wife unto him, If Mordecai be of the seed of the Jews, before whom thou hast begun to fall, thou shalt not prevail against him, but shalt surely fall before him.
6:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈曼將所遭遇的一切事，述說給他的妻子細利斯和他的眾朋友聽。他的智慧人和他的妻子細利斯對他說，你在末底改面前開始敗落，他如果是猶大種族，你必不能勝他，終必在他面前敗落。
6:14<version name="ASV">While they were yet talking with him, came the king's chamberlains, and hasted to bring Haman unto the banquet that Esther had prepared. </p><p /><br /></version>
6:14<version name="Darby">While they were yet talking with him, the king's  chamberlains came, and hasted to bring Haman to the banquet  that Esther had prepared. </p><p /><br /></version>
6:14<version name="KJV">And while they were yet talking with him, came the king's chamberlains, and hasted to bring Haman unto the banquet that Esther had prepared.</p><p /><br /></version>
6:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們還與哈曼說話的時候，王的太監來到，催哈曼快去赴以斯帖所豫備的筵席。
7:1|ASV|So the king and Haman came to banquet with Esther the queen.
7:1|Darby|And the king and Haman came to drink with Esther the queen.
7:1|KJV|So the king and Haman came to banquet with Esther the queen.
7:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王和哈曼進去，與王后以斯帖一同宴飲。
7:2|ASV|And the king said again unto Esther on the second day at the banquet of wine, What is thy petition, queen Esther? and it shall be granted thee: and what is thy request? even to the half of the kingdom it shall be performed.
7:2|Darby|And the king said again to Esther on the second day, at the  banquet of wine, What is thy petition, queen Esther? and it  shall be granted thee; and what is thy request? even to the  half of the kingdom it shall be done.
7:2|KJV|And the king said again unto Esther on the second day at the banquet of wine, What is thy petition, queen Esther? and it shall be granted thee: and what is thy request? and it shall be performed, even to the half of the kingdom.
7:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在這第二天的酒筵中，王又問以斯帖說，王后以斯帖阿，你要甚麼？我必賜給你。你求甚麼？就是國的一半，也必為你成就。
7:3|ASV|Then Esther the queen answered and said, If I have found favor in thy sight, O king, and if it please the king, let my life be given me at my petition, and my people at my request:
7:3|Darby|And Esther the queen answered and said, If I have found  grace in thy sight, O king, and if it please the king, let my  life be given me at my petition, and my people at my request;
7:3|KJV|Then Esther the queen answered and said, If I have found favour in thy sight, O king, and if it please the king, let my life be given me at my petition, and my people at my request:
7:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王后以斯帖回答說，王阿，我若在你眼前蒙恩，王若以為美，我所要的是王將我的性命賜給我，我所求的是王將我的本族賜給我；
7:4|ASV|for we are sold, I and my people, to be destroyed, to be slain, and to perish. But if we had been sold for bondmen and bondwomen, I had held my peace, although the adversary could not have compensated for the king's damage.
7:4|Darby|for we are sold, I and my people, to be destroyed, to be  slain, and to perish. But if we had been sold for bondmen and  bondwomen, I had held my tongue, although the adversary could  not compensate the king's damage.
7:4|KJV|For we are sold, I and my people, to be destroyed, to be slain, and to perish. But if we had been sold for bondmen and bondwomen, I had held my tongue, although the enemy could not countervail the king's damage.
7:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因我和我的本族被賣了，要被殲毀，殺戮滅絕。我們若僅僅被賣為奴為婢，我也閉口不言，因為不值得叫王因敵人受攪擾。
7:5|ASV|Then spake the king Ahasuerus and said unto Esther the queen, Who is he, and where is he, that durst presume in his heart to do so?
7:5|Darby|And king Ahasuerus spoke and said to Esther the queen, Who  is he, and where is he that has filled his heart to do so?
7:5|KJV|Then the king Ahasuerus answered and said unto Esther the queen, Who is he, and where is he, that durst presume in his heart to do so?
7:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞哈隨魯王問王后以斯帖說，擅敢起意如此行的是誰？這人在那堙H
7:6|ASV|And Esther said, An adversary and an enemy, even this wicked Haman. Then Haman was afraid before the king and the queen.
7:6|Darby|And Esther said, The adversary and enemy is this wicked  Haman. Then Haman was terrified before the king and the queen.
7:6|KJV|And Esther said, The adversary and enemy is this wicked Haman. Then Haman was afraid before the king and the queen.
7:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以斯帖說，敵人仇人就是這惡人哈曼。哈曼在王和王后面前就甚驚惶。
7:7|ASV|And the king arose in his wrath from the banquet of wine and went into the palace garden: and Haman stood up to make request for his life to Esther the queen; for he saw that there was evil determined against him by the king.
7:7|Darby|And the king in his wrath rose up from the banquet of wine,  [and went] into the palace garden; but Haman stayed to make  request for his life to Esther the queen, for he saw that there  was evil determined against him by the king.
7:7|KJV|And the king arising from the banquet of wine in his wrath went into the palace garden: and Haman stood up to make request for his life to Esther the queen; for he saw that there was evil determined against him by the king.
7:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是王在怒中起來，離開酒席往王宮的花園去了；哈曼見王定意要加禍處罰他，就起來，求王后以斯帖救命。
7:8|ASV|Then the king returned out of the palace garden into the place of the banquet of wine; and Haman was fallen upon the couch whereon Esther was. Then said the king, Will he even force the queen before me in the house? As the word went out of the king's mouth, they covered Haman's face.
7:8|Darby|And the king returned out of the palace garden into the  house of the banquet of wine, and Haman was fallen upon the  couch on which Esther was. And the king said, Will he even  force the queen before me in the house? The word went forth out  of the king's mouth, and they covered Haman's face.
7:8|KJV|Then the king returned out of the palace garden into the place of the banquet of wine; and Haman was fallen upon the bed whereon Esther was. Then said the king, Will he force the queen also before me in the house? As the word went out of king's mouth, they covered Haman's face.
7:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王從王宮花園回到酒筵的宮內，哈曼正伏在以斯帖所靠的榻上。王說，他竟敢在這宮內，在我面前凌辱王后麼？這話一出王口，人就蒙了哈曼的臉。
7:9|ASV|Then said Harbonah, one of the chamberlains that were before the king, Behold also, the gallows fifty cubits high, which Haman hath made for Mordecai, who spake good for the king, standeth in the house of Haman. And the king said, Hang him thereon.
7:9|Darby|And Harbonah, one of the chamberlains, said before the king,  Behold, also, the gallows fifty cubits high, that Haman made  for Mordecai, who spoke good for the king, stands in the house  of Haman. And the king said, Hang him on it!
7:9|KJV|And Harbonah, one of the chamberlains, said before the king, Behold also, the gallows fifty cubits high, which Haman had made for Mordecai, who spoken good for the king, standeth in the house of Haman. Then the king said, Hang him thereon.
7:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在王面前的一個太監哈波拿說，哈曼還為那曾說善言救王的末底改，作了五十肘高的木架，現今立在哈曼家堙C王說，把哈曼掛在其上。
7:10<version name="ASV">So they hanged Haman on the gallows that he had prepared for Mordecai. Then was the king's wrath pacified. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:10<version name="Darby">So they hanged Haman on the gallows that he had prepared  for Mordecai. And the king's wrath was appeased. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:10<version name="KJV">So they hanged Haman on the gallows that he had prepared for Mordecai. Then was the king's wrath pacified.</p><p /><br /></version>
7:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是人將哈曼掛在他為末底改所豫備的木架上。王的忿怒這纔止息。
8:1|ASV|On that day did the king Ahasuerus give the house of Haman the Jews' enemy unto Esther the queen. And Mordecai came before the king; for Esther had told what he was unto her.
8:1|Darby|On that day did king Ahasuerus give the house of Haman the  Jews' oppressor to Esther the queen. And Mordecai came before  the king; for Esther had told what he was to her.
8:1|KJV|On that day did the king Ahasuerus give the house of Haman the Jews' enemy unto Esther the queen. And Mordecai came before the king; for Esther had told what he was unto her.
8:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當日，亞哈隨魯王把猶大人仇敵哈曼的家產賜給王后以斯帖。末底改也來到王面前，因為以斯帖已經把末底改是她甚麼親屬，告訴了王。
8:2|ASV|And the king took off his ring, which he had taken from Haman, and gave it unto Mordecai. And Esther set Mordecai over the house of Haman.
8:2|Darby|And the king took off his ring, which he had taken from  Haman, and gave it to Mordecai. And Esther set Mordecai over  the house of Haman.
8:2|KJV|And the king took off his ring, which he had taken from Haman, and gave it unto Mordecai. And Esther set Mordecai over the house of Haman.
8:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王摘下自己的戒指，就是他從哈曼取回的，給了末底改。以斯帖派末底改管理哈曼的家產。
8:3|ASV|And Esther spake yet again before the king, and fell down at his feet, and besought him with tears to put away the mischief of Haman the Agagite, and his device that he had devised against the Jews.
8:3|Darby|And Esther spoke yet again before the king, and fell down at  his feet, and besought him with tears to put away the mischief  of Haman the Agagite, and his device which he had devised  against the Jews.
8:3|KJV|And Esther spake yet again before the king, and fell down at his feet, and besought him with tears to put away the mischief of Haman the Agagite, and his device that he had devised against the Jews.
8:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以斯帖又在王面前進言；她俯伏在王腳前，流淚哀告，求他除掉亞甲族哈曼所設計要害猶大人的惡謀。
8:4|ASV|Then the king held out to Esther the golden sceptre. So Esther arose, and stood before the king.
8:4|Darby|And the king held out the golden sceptre toward Esther. And  Esther arose and stood before the king,
8:4|KJV|Then the king held out the golden sceptre toward Esther. So Esther arose, and stood before the king,
8:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王向以斯帖伸出金杖；以斯帖就起來，站在王前，
8:5|ASV|And she said, If it please the king, and if I have found favor in his sight, and the thing seem right before the king, and I be pleasing in his eyes, let it be written to reverse the letters devised by Haman, the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, which he wrote to destroy the Jews that are in all the king's provinces:
8:5|Darby|and said, If it please the king and if I have found grace  before him, and the thing seem right to the king, and I be  pleasing in his sight, let it be written to reverse the letters  devised by Haman the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, which he  wrote to destroy the Jews that are in all the king's provinces.
8:5|KJV|And said, If it please the king, and if I have favour in his sight, and the thing seem right before the king, and I be pleasing in his eyes, let it be written to reverse the letters devised by Haman the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, which he wrote to destroy the Jews which are in all the king's provinces:
8:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|說，王若以為美，我若在王面前蒙恩，這事若在王面前顯為對，我若在王眼前蒙喜悅，請王寫詔書，撤回亞甲族哈米大他的兒子哈曼設謀傳達的詔書，就是他所寫，要除滅在王各省之猶大人的。
8:6|ASV|for how can I endure to see the evil that shall come unto my people? or how can I endure to see the destruction of my kindred?
8:6|Darby|For how shall I endure to see the evil that shall befall my  people? and how shall I endure to see the destruction of my  kindred?
8:6|KJV|For how can I endure to see the evil that shall come unto my people? or how can I endure to see the destruction of my kindred?
8:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我何忍見我本族的人遭禍？何忍見我的親族被滅呢？
8:7|ASV|Then the king Ahasuerus said unto Esther the queen and to Mordecai the Jew, Behold, I have given Esther the house of Haman, and him they have hanged upon the gallows, because he laid his hand upon the Jews.
8:7|Darby|And king Ahasuerus said to queen Esther and to Mordecai the  Jew, Behold, I have given Esther the house of Haman, and him  they have hanged upon the gallows, because he stretched forth  his hand against the Jews.
8:7|KJV|Then the king Ahasuerus said unto Esther the queen and to Mordecai the Jew, Behold, I have given Esther the house of Haman, and him they have hanged upon the gallows, because he laid his hand upon the Jews.
8:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞哈隨魯王對王后以斯帖和猶大人末底改說，因哈曼下手害猶大人，我已將他的家產賜給以斯帖，人也將哈曼掛在木架上。
8:8|ASV|Write ye also to the Jews, as it pleaseth you, in the king's name, and seal it with the king's ring; for the writing which is written in the king's name, and sealed with the king's ring, may no man reverse.
8:8|Darby|Write ye then for the Jews as seems good to you, in the  king's name, and seal [it] with the king's ring. For a writing  that is written in the king's name, and sealed with the king's  ring, cannot be reversed.
8:8|KJV|Write ye also for the Jews, as it liketh you, in the king's name, and seal it with the king's ring: for the writing which is written in the king's name, and sealed with the king's ring, may no man reverse.
8:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們可以照你們所看為好的，奉王的名寫詔書給猶大人，用王的戒指蓋印；因為奉王名所寫、用王戒指蓋印的諭旨，人都不能撤回。
8:9|ASV|Then were the king's scribes called at that time, in the third month Sivan, on the three and twentieth day thereof; and it was written according to all that Mordecai commanded unto the Jews, and to the satraps, and the governors and princes of the provinces which are from India unto Ethiopia, a hundred twenty and seven provinces, unto every province according to the writing thereof, and unto every people after their language, and to the Jews according to their writing, and according to their language.
8:9|Darby|Then were the king's scribes called at that time, in the  third month, that is, the month Sivan, on the three and  twentieth [day] thereof; and it was written according to all  that Mordecai commanded, to the Jews, and to the satraps, and  the governors, and the princes of the provinces which are from  India even to Ethiopia, a hundred and twenty-seven provinces,  to every province according to the writing thereof, and to  every people according to their language, and to the Jews  according to their writing and according to their language.
8:9|KJV|Then were the king's scribes called at that time in the third month, that is, the month Sivan, on the three and twentieth day thereof; and it was written according to all that Mordecai commanded unto the Jews, and to the lieutenants, and the deputies and rulers of the provinces which are from India unto Ethiopia, an hundred twenty and seven provinces, unto every province according to the writing thereof, and unto every people after their language, and to the Jews according to their writing, and according to their language.
8:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時是三月，就是西彎月，二十三日，王的書記被召了來，照著末底改一切所吩咐的寫了詔書，傳與那從印度直到古實一百二十七省的猶大人、總督、省長和首領，依照各省的文字達於各省，依照各族的方言達於各族，並依照猶大人的文字和方言達於猶大人。
8:10|ASV|And he wrote the name of king Ahasuerus, and sealed it with the king's ring, and sent letters by post on horseback, riding on swift steeds that were used in the king's service, bred of the stud:
8:10|Darby|And he wrote in the name of king Ahasuerus, and sealed [it]  with the king's ring, and sent letters by couriers on horseback  riding on coursers, horses of blood reared in the breeding  studs:
8:10|KJV|And he wrote in the king Ahasuerus' name, and sealed it with the king's ring, and sent letters by posts on horseback, and riders on mules, camels, and young dromedaries:
8:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|末底改奉亞哈隨魯王的名寫詔書，用王的戒指蓋印，把詔書交由驛卒，騎王用的御圈快馬送達各處。
8:11|ASV|wherein the king granted the Jews that were in every city to gather themselves together, and to stand for their life, to destroy, to slay, and to cause to perish, all the power of the people and province that would assault them, their little ones and women, and to take the spoil of them for a prey,
8:11|Darby|[stating] that the king granted the Jews that were in every  city to gather themselves together, and to stand for their  life, to destroy, to slay, and to cause to perish, all the  power of the people and province that might assault them,  [their] little ones and women, and to [take] the spoil of them  for a prey,
8:11|KJV|Wherein the king granted the Jews which were in every city to gather themselves together, and to stand for their life, to destroy, to slay and to cause to perish, all the power of the people and province that would assault them, both little ones and women, and to take the spoil of them for a prey,
8:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|詔書中，王准各城的猶大人聚集保護自己的性命，殲毀殺戮滅絕各族各省要攻擊猶大人的一切仇敵，並他們的孩子和婦女，奪取他們的財物為掠物，
8:12|ASV|upon one day in all the provinces of king Ahasuerus,  namely, upon the thirteenth day of the twelfth month, which is the month Adar.
8:12|Darby|upon one day in all the provinces of king Ahasuerus, upon  the thirteenth of the twelfth month, that is, the month Adar.
8:12|KJV|Upon one day in all the provinces of king Ahasuerus, namely, upon the thirteenth day of the twelfth month, which is the month Adar.
8:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這要在一日之間，在十二月，就是亞達月，十三日，在亞哈隨魯王的各省執行。
8:13|ASV|A copy of the writing, that the decree should be given out in every province, was published unto all the peoples, and that the Jews should be ready against that day to avenge themselves on their enemies.
8:13|Darby|That the decree might be given in every province, a copy of  the writing was published to all the peoples, and that the Jews  should be ready against that day to avenge themselves on their  enemies.
8:13|KJV|The copy of the writing for a commandment to be given in every province was published unto all people, and that the Jews should be ready against that day to avenge themselves on their enemies.
8:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這文書經過抄錄，頒行各省成為法令，向各族宣示，使猶大人豫備等候那日，在仇敵身上報仇。
8:14|ASV|So the posts that rode upon swift steeds that were used in the king's service went out, being hastened and pressed on by the king's commandment; and the decree was given out in Shushan the palace.
8:14|Darby|The couriers mounted on coursers [and] horses of blood went  out, being hastened and pressed on by the king's commandment.  And the decree was given at Shushan the fortress.
8:14|KJV|So the posts that rode upon mules and camels went out, being hastened and pressed on by the king's commandment. And the decree was given at Shushan the palace.
8:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是騎御用快馬的驛卒被王命催促，急忙起行；法令在書珊京城頒佈。
8:15|ASV|And Mordecai went forth from the presence of the king in royal apparel of blue and white, and with a great crown of gold, and with a robe of fine linen and purple: and the city of Shushan shouted and was glad.
8:15|Darby|And Mordecai went out from the presence of the king in  royal apparel of blue and white, and with a great crown of  gold, and with a mantle of byssus and purple; and the city of  Shushan shouted and was glad.
8:15|KJV|And Mordecai went out from the presence of the king in royal apparel of blue and white, and with a great crown of gold, and with a garment of fine linen and purple: and the city of Shushan rejoiced and was glad.
8:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|末底改穿著藍色白色的朝服，頭戴大金冠冕，又穿紫色細麻布的外袍，從王面前出來；書珊城的人民都歡呼快樂。
8:16|ASV|The Jews had light and gladness, and joy and honor.
8:16|Darby|The Jews had light, and joy, and gladness, and honour.
8:16|KJV|The Jews had light, and gladness, and joy, and honour.
8:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|猶大人有光榮，歡喜快樂而得尊貴。
8:17<version name="ASV">And in every province, and in every city, whithersoever the king's commandment and his decree came, the Jews had gladness and joy, a feast and a good day. And many from among the peoples of the land became Jews; for the fear of the Jews was fallen upon them. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:17<version name="Darby">And in every province, and in every city, wherever the  king's commandment and his decree came, the Jews had joy and  gladness, a feast and a good day. And many among the peoples of  the land became Jews; for the fear of the Jews had fallen upon  them. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:17<version name="KJV">And in every province, and in every city, whithersoever the king's commandment and his decree came, the Jews had joy and gladness, a feast and a good day. And many of the people of the land became Jews; for the fear of the Jews fell upon them.</p><p /><br /></version>
8:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王的諭旨和法令所到的各省各城，猶大人都歡喜快樂，設擺筵宴，以那日為吉日。那地的各族中，有許多人因懼怕猶大人，就入了猶大籍。
9:1|ASV|Now in the twelfth month, which is the month Adar, on the thirteenth day of the same, when the king's commandment and his decree drew near to be put in execution, on the day that the enemies of the Jews hoped to have rule over them, (whereas it was turned to the contrary, that the Jews had rule over them that hated them,)
9:1|Darby|And in the twelfth month, that is, the month Adar, on the  thirteenth day thereof, when the king's commandment and his  decree drew near to be put in execution, in the day that the  enemies of the Jews hoped to have power over them (but it was  turned to the contrary, that the Jews had power over them that  hated them),
9:1|KJV|Now in the twelfth month, that is, the month Adar, on the thirteenth day of the same, when the king's commandment and his decree drew near to be put in execution, in the day that the enemies of the Jews hoped to have power over them, (though it was turned to the contrary, that the Jews had rule over them that hated them;)
9:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|十二月，就是亞達月，十三日，王的諭旨和法令將要執行；那是猶大人的仇敵盼望轄制他們，猶大人反倒轄制恨他們之人的日子，
9:2|ASV|the Jews gathered themselves together in their cities throughout all the provinces of the king Ahasuerus, to lay hand on such as sought their hurt: and no man could withstand them; for the fear of them was fallen upon all the peoples.
9:2|Darby|the Jews gathered themselves together in their cities  throughout the provinces of king Ahasuerus, to lay hand on such  as sought their hurt. And no man could withstand them; for the  fear of them had fallen upon all the peoples.
9:2|KJV|The Jews gathered themselves together in their cities throughout all the provinces of the king Ahasuerus, to lay hand on such as sought their hurt: and no man could withstand them; for the fear of them fell upon all people.
9:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|猶大人在亞哈隨魯王各省自己的城婸E集，下手擊殺那些想要害他們的人。無人能抵擋他們，因為各族都懼怕他們。
9:3|ASV|And all the princes of the provinces, and the satraps, and the governors, and they that did the king's business, helped the Jews; because the fear of Mordecai was fallen upon them.
9:3|Darby|And all the princes of the provinces, and the satraps, and  the governors and officers of the king, helped the Jews; for  the fear of Mordecai had fallen upon them.
9:3|KJV|And all the rulers of the provinces, and the lieutenants, and the deputies, and officers of the king, helped the Jews; because the fear of Mordecai fell upon them.
9:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|各省的首領、總督、省長、和辦理王事的人，因懼怕末底改，就都幫助猶大人。
9:4|ASV|For Mordecai was great in the king's house, and his fame went forth throughout all the provinces; for the man Mordecai waxed greater and greater.
9:4|Darby|For Mordecai was great in the king's house, and his fame  went forth throughout the provinces; for the man Mordecai  became continually greater.
9:4|KJV|For Mordecai was great in the king's house, and his fame went out throughout all the provinces: for this man Mordecai waxed greater and greater.
9:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|末底改在朝中為大，名聲傳遍各省；末底改日漸昌大。
9:5|ASV|And the Jews smote all their enemies with the stroke of the sword, and with slaughter and destruction, and did what they would unto them that hated them.
9:5|Darby|And the Jews smote all their enemies with the stroke of the  sword and slaughter and destruction, and did what they would to  those that hated them.
9:5|KJV|Thus the Jews smote all their enemies with the stroke of the sword, and slaughter, and destruction, and did what they would unto those that hated them.
9:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|猶大人用刀擊殺一切仇敵，殺戮滅絕，任意對待恨他們的人。
9:6|ASV|And in Shushan the palace the Jews slew and destroyed five hundred men.
9:6|Darby|And in Shushan the fortress the Jews slew and destroyed five  hundred men.
9:6|KJV|And in Shushan the palace the Jews slew and destroyed five hundred men.
9:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在書珊京城，猶大人殺滅了五百人。
9:7|ASV|And Parshandatha, and Dalphon, and Aspatha,
9:7|Darby|And Parshandatha, and Dalphon, and Aspatha,
9:7|KJV|And Parshandatha, and Dalphon, and Aspatha,
9:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|還有巴珊大他、達分、亞斯帕他、
9:8|ASV|and Poratha, and Adalia, and Aridatha,
9:8|Darby|and Poratha, and Adalia, and Aridatha,
9:8|KJV|And Poratha, and Adalia, and Aridatha,
9:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|破拉他、亞大利雅、亞利大他、
9:9|ASV|and Parmashta, and Arisai, and Aridai, and Vaizatha,
9:9|Darby|and Parmashta, and Arisai, and Aridai, and Vajezatha,
9:9|KJV|And Parmashta, and Arisai, and Aridai, and Vajezatha,
9:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|帕瑪斯他、亞利賽、亞利代、瓦耶撒他，
9:10|ASV|the ten sons of Haman the son of Hammedatha, the Jew's enemy, slew they; but on the spoil they laid not their hand.
9:10|Darby|the ten sons of Haman the son of Hammedatha, the oppressor  of the Jews, they slew; but they laid not their hands on the  prey.
9:10|KJV|The ten sons of Haman the son of Hammedatha, the enemy of the Jews, slew they; but on the spoil laid they not their hand.
9:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這十人都是哈米大他的孫子，猶大人仇敵哈曼的兒子，猶大人也把他們殺了；但猶大人沒有下手掠奪財物。
9:11|ASV|On that day the number of those that were slain in Shushan the palace was brought before the king.
9:11|Darby|On that day the number of those that were slain in Shushan  the fortress was brought before the king.
9:11|KJV|On that day the number of those that were slain in Shushan the palace was brought before the king.
9:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當日在書珊京城被殺的人數，呈到王面前。
9:12|ASV|And the king said unto Esther the queen, The Jews have slain and destroyed five hundred men in Shushan the palace, and the ten sons of Haman; what then have they done in the rest of the king's provinces! Now what is thy petition? and it shall be granted thee: or what is thy request further? and it shall be done.
9:12|Darby|And the king said to Esther the queen, The Jews have slain  and destroyed five hundred men in Shushan the fortress, and the  ten sons of Haman; what have they done in the rest of the  king's provinces? And what is thy petition? and it shall be  granted thee; and what is thy request further? and it shall be  done.
9:12|KJV|And the king said unto Esther the queen, The Jews have slain and destroyed five hundred men in Shushan the palace, and the ten sons of Haman; what have they done in the rest of the king's provinces? now what is thy petition? and it shall be granted thee: or what is thy request further? and it shall be done.
9:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王對王后以斯帖說，猶大人在書珊京城殺滅了五百人，又殺了哈曼的十個兒子；在王其餘各省不知如何呢！現在你要甚麼？我必賜給你。你還求甚麼？也必為你成就。
9:13|ASV|Then said Esther, If it please the king, let it be granted to the Jews that are in Shushan to do to-morrow also according unto this day's decree, and let Haman's ten sons be hanged upon the gallows.
9:13|Darby|And Esther said, If it please the king, let it be granted  to the Jews that are in Shushan to do to-morrow also according  to this day's decree, and let Haman's ten sons be hanged upon  the gallows.
9:13|KJV|Then said Esther, If it please the king, let it be granted to the Jews which are in Shushan to do to morrow also according unto this day's decree, and let Haman's ten sons be hanged upon the gallows.
9:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以斯帖說，王若以為美，求你准書珊的猶大人，明日也照今日的法令行，並將哈曼十個兒子的屍首掛在木架上。
9:14|ASV|And the king commanded it so to be done: and a decree was given out in Shushan; and they hanged Haman's ten sons.
9:14|Darby|And the king commanded it so to be done: and the decree was  given at Shushan; and they hanged Haman's ten sons.
9:14|KJV|And the king commanded it so to be done: and the decree was given at Shushan; and they hanged Haman's ten sons.
9:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王便下令如此行；法令在書珊頒佈，人就把哈曼十個兒子的屍首掛了起來。
9:15|ASV|And the Jews that were in Shushan gathered themselves together on the fourteenth day also of the month Adar, and slew three hundred men in Shushan; but on the spoil they laid not their hand.
9:15|Darby|And the Jews that were in Shushan gathered themselves  together on the fourteenth day also of the month Adar, and slew  three hundred men at Shushan; but they laid not their hand on  the prey.
9:15|KJV|For the Jews that were in Shushan gathered themselves together on the fourteenth day also of the month Adar, and slew three hundred men at Shushan; but on the prey they laid not their hand.
9:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞達月十四日，書珊的猶大人又聚集，在書珊殺了三百人，但沒有下手掠奪財物。
9:16|ASV|And the other Jews that were in the king's provinces gathered themselves together, and stood for their lives, and had rest from their enemies, and slew of them that hated them seventy and five thousand; but on the spoil they laid not their hand.
9:16|Darby|And the other Jews that were in the king's provinces  gathered themselves together, and stood for their life, and had  rest from their enemies; and they slew of them that hated them  seventy-five thousand (but they laid not their hand on the  prey),
9:16|KJV|But the other Jews that were in the king's provinces gathered themselves together, and stood for their lives, and had rest from their enemies, and slew of their foes seventy and five thousand, but they laid not their hands on the prey,
9:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在王各省其餘的猶大人也都聚集保護自己的性命，脫離仇敵，得享安息。他們殺了恨他們的人七萬五千，但沒有下手掠奪財物。
9:17|ASV|This was done on the thirteenth day of the month Adar; and on the fourteenth day of the same they rested, and made it a day of feasting and gladness.
9:17|Darby|on the thirteenth day of the month Adar; and on the  fourteenth of the same they rested, and made it a day of  feasting and joy.
9:17|KJV|On the thirteenth day of the month Adar; and on the fourteenth day of the same rested they, and made it a day of feasting and gladness.
9:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這是在亞達月十三日的事；這月十四日他們享安息，並以這日為設筵歡樂的日子。
9:18|ASV|But the Jews that were in Shushan assembled together on the thirteenth day thereof, and on the fourteenth thereof; and on the fifteenth day of the same they rested, and made it a day of feasting and gladness.
9:18|Darby|But the Jews that were at Shushan gathered themselves  together on the thirteenth [day] thereof, and on the fourteenth  thereof; and on the fifteenth of the same they rested, and made  it a day of feasting and joy.
9:18|KJV|But the Jews that were at Shushan assembled together on the thirteenth day thereof, and on the fourteenth thereof; and on the fifteenth day of the same they rested, and made it a day of feasting and gladness.
9:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但書珊的猶大人，在十三日、十四日聚集殺戮仇敵；這月十五日纔享安息，並以這日為設筵歡樂的日子。
9:19|ASV|Therefore do the Jews of the villages, that dwell in the unwalled towns, make the fourteenth day of the month Adar a day of gladness and feasting, and a good day, and of sending portions one to another.
9:19|Darby|Therefore the Jews of the villages that dwell in the  country towns make the fourteenth of the month Adar a day of  joy and feasting, and a good day, and on which they send  portions one to another.
9:19|KJV|Therefore the Jews of the villages, that dwelt in the unwalled towns, made the fourteenth day of the month Adar a day of gladness and feasting, and a good day, and of sending portions one to another.
9:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以住在無城牆之村莊的猶大鄉民，都定亞達月十四日為設筵歡樂的吉日，彼此餽送禮物。
9:20|ASV|And Mordecai wrote these things, and sent letters unto all the Jews that were in all the provinces of the king Ahasuerus, both nigh and far,
9:20|Darby|And Mordecai wrote these things, and sent letters to all  the Jews near and far that were in all the provinces of king  Ahasuerus,
9:20|KJV|And Mordecai wrote these things, and sent letters unto all the Jews that were in all the provinces of the king Ahasuerus, both nigh and far,
9:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|末底改記錄這些事，並將書信送達亞哈隨魯王各省遠近所有的猶大人，
9:21|ASV|to enjoin them that they should keep the fourteenth day of the month Adar, and the fifteenth day of the same, yearly,
9:21|Darby|to establish [this] among them, that they should keep the  fourteenth day of the month Adar, and the fifteenth day of the  same, yearly,
9:21|KJV|To stablish this among them, that they should keep the fourteenth day of the month Adar, and the fifteenth day of the same, yearly,
9:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|囑咐他們每年要守亞達月十四日和十五日，
9:22|ASV|as the days wherein the Jews had rest from their enemies, and the month which was turned unto them from sorrow to gladness, and from mourning into a good day; that they should make them days of feasting and gladness, and of sending portions one to another, and gifts to the poor.
9:22|Darby|as the days on which the Jews rested from their enemies,  and the month that was turned to them from sorrow to joy, and  from mourning into a good day; that they should make them days  of feasting and joy, and of sending portions one to another,  and gifts to the poor.
9:22|KJV|As the days wherein the Jews rested from their enemies, and the month which was turned unto them from sorrow to joy, and from mourning into a good day: that they should make them days of feasting and joy, and of sending portions one to another, and gifts to the poor.
9:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|作為猶大人脫離仇敵得安息的日子，並轉憂為喜、轉悲哀為吉日的月分；且定這兩日為設筵歡樂、彼此餽送、賙濟窮人的日子。
9:23|ASV|And the Jews undertook to do as they had begun, and as Mordecai had written unto them;
9:23|Darby|And the Jews undertook to do as they had begun, and as  Mordecai had written to them.
9:23|KJV|And the Jews undertook to do as they had begun, and as Mordecai had written unto them;
9:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是，猶大人執行他們所開始實行，並末底改所寫要他們作的事。
9:24|ASV|because Haman the son of Hammedatha, the Agagite, the enemy of all the Jews, had plotted against the Jews to destroy them, and had cast Pur, that is the lot, to consume them, and to destroy them;
9:24|Darby|For Haman the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, the oppressor  of all the Jews, had devised against the Jews to destroy them,  and had cast Pur, that is, the lot, to consume them and to  destroy them;
9:24|KJV|Because Haman the son of Hammedatha, the Agagite, the enemy of all the Jews, had devised against the Jews to destroy them, and had cast Pur, that is, the lot, to consume them, and to destroy them;
9:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|原本所有猶大人的仇敵，亞甲族哈米大他的兒子哈曼，設謀害猶大人，要滅絕他們，並且掣了普珥，就是掣了籤，要擊潰滅絕他們；
9:25|ASV|but when the matter came before the king, he commanded by letters that his wicked device, which he had devised against the Jews, should return upon his own head, and that he and his sons should be hanged on the gallows.
9:25|Darby|and when [Esther] came before the king, he commanded by  letters that his wicked device, which he had devised against  the Jews, should return upon his own head; and they hanged him  and his sons on the gallows.
9:25|KJV|But when Esther came before the king, he commanded by letters that his wicked device, which he devised against the Jews, should return upon his own head, and that he and his sons should be hanged on the gallows.
9:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但以斯帖來到王面前，王便寫詔書，吩咐使哈曼謀害猶大人的惡謀，反過來加到他自己頭上，並吩咐把他和他的眾子都掛在木架上。
9:26|ASV|Wherefore they called these days Purim, after the name of Pur. Therefore because of all the words of this letter, and of that which they had seen concerning this matter, and that which had come unto them,
9:26|Darby|Therefore they called these days Purim after the name of  Pur. Therefore, according to all the words of this letter, and  for what they had seen concerning this matter and what had  happened to them,
9:26|KJV|Wherefore they called these days Purim after the name of Pur. Therefore for all the words of this letter, and of that which they had seen concerning this matter, and which had come unto them,
9:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|照著普珥這名字，人就稱這兩日為普珥日。因這信上一切的話，又因他們在這事上所看見的，並他們所遭遇的，
9:27|ASV|the Jews ordained, and took upon them, and upon their seed, and upon all such as joined themselves unto them, so that it should not fail, that they would keep these two days according to the writing thereof, and according to the appointed time thereof, every year;
9:27|Darby|the Jews ordained and took upon them, and upon their seed,  and upon all such as joined themselves to them, so that it  should not fail, that they would observe these two days  according to their writing and according to their fixed time,  every year;
9:27|KJV|The Jews ordained, and took upon them, and upon their seed, and upon all such as joined themselves unto them, so as it should not fail, that they would keep these two days according to their writing, and according to their appointed time every year;
9:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|猶大人就立了定例，應承自己與後裔，並歸附他們的人，每年必按所記載的，並按指定的日期守這兩日，永遠不廢；
9:28|ASV|and that these days should be remembered and kept throughout every generation, every family, every province, and every city; and that these days of Purim should not fail from among the Jews, nor the remembrance of them perish from their seed.
9:28|Darby|and that these days should be remembered and observed  throughout every generation, in every family, every province,  and every city, and that these days of Purim should not fail  from among the Jews, nor the memorial of them cease from among  their seed.
9:28|KJV|And that these days should be remembered and kept throughout every generation, every family, every province, and every city; and that these days of Purim should not fail from among the Jews, nor the memorial of them perish from their seed.
9:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|世世代代、家家戶戶、各省各城，人必記念遵守這兩日，使這普珥日在猶大人中不被廢掉，在他們後裔中也不被忘記。
9:29|ASV|Then Esther the queen, the daughter of Abihail, and Mordecai the Jew, wrote with all authority to confirm this second letter of Purim.
9:29|Darby|And queen Esther the daughter of Abihail, and Mordecai the  Jew, wrote with all authority to confirm this second letter of  Purim.
9:29|KJV|Then Esther the queen, the daughter of Abihail, and Mordecai the Jew, wrote with all authority, to confirm this second letter of Purim.
9:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞比孩的女兒王后以斯帖，和猶大人末底改，以全權寫了第二封信，確立普珥日的事，
9:30|ASV|And he sent letters unto all the Jews, to the hundred twenty and seven provinces of the kingdom of Ahasuerus, with words of peace and truth,
9:30|Darby|And he sent letters to all the Jews, to the hundred and  twenty-seven provinces of the kingdom of Ahasuerus, words of  peace and truth,
9:30|KJV|And he sent the letters unto all the Jews, to the hundred twenty and seven provinces of the kingdom of Ahasuerus, with words of peace and truth,
9:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|末底改將書信，就是和平真誠的話，送達亞哈隨魯國中一百二十七省所有的猶大人，
9:31|ASV|to confirm these days of Purim in their appointed times, according as Mordecai the Jew and Esther the queen had enjoined them, and as they had ordained for themselves and for their seed, in the matter of the fastings and their cry.
9:31|Darby|to confirm these days of Purim in their fixed times,  according as Mordecai the Jew and queen Esther had enjoined  them, and as they had decreed for themselves and for their  seed, as to the matters of the fastings and their cry.
9:31|KJV|To confirm these days of Purim in their times appointed, according as Mordecai the Jew and Esther the queen had enjoined them, and as they had decreed for themselves and for their seed, the matters of the fastings and their cry.
9:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|勸他們按所定的日期，守這兩日為普珥日，禁食呼求，是照猶大人末底改和王后以斯帖為他們所定的，也是照他們為自己與後裔所定的。
9:32<version name="ASV">And the commandment of Esther confirmed these matters of Purim; and it was written in the book. </p><p /><br /></version>
9:32<version name="Darby">And the decree of Esther confirmed these matters of Purim;  and it was written in the book. </p><p /><br /></version>
9:32<version name="KJV">And the decree of Esther confirmed these matters of Purim; and it was written in the book.</p><p /><br /></version>
9:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以斯帖的命令確立了普珥日的這些事；這命令也記錄在書上。
10:1|ASV|And the king Ahasuerus laid a tribute upon the land, and upon the isles of the sea.
10:1|Darby|And king Ahasuerus laid a tribute upon the land and the  isles of the sea.
10:1|KJV|And the king Ahasuerus laid a tribute upon the land, and upon the isles of the sea.
10:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞哈隨魯王使陸地和海島的人民都進貢。
10:2|ASV|And all the acts of his power and of his might, and the full account of the greatness of Mordecai, whereunto the king advanced him, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Media and Persia?
10:2|Darby|And all the acts of his power and of his might, and the  declaration of the greatness of Mordecai, to which the king  advanced him, are they not written in the book of the  chronicles of the kings of Media and Persia?
10:2|KJV|And all the acts of his power and of his might, and the declaration of the greatness of Mordecai, whereunto the king advanced him, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Media and Persia?
10:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他以權柄勇力所行的，並王使末底改得尊大的詳確經過，豈不都寫在瑪代和波斯王的年代志上麼？
10:3<version name="ASV">For Mordecai the Jew was next unto king Ahasuerus, and great among the Jews, and accepted of the multitude of his brethren, seeking the good of his people, and speaking peace to all his seed. </p><p /><br /></version>
10:3<version name="Darby">For Mordecai the Jew was second to king Ahasuerus, and  great among the Jews, and accepted of the multitude of his  brethren, seeking the welfare of his people, and speaking peace  to all his seed. </p><p /><br /></version>
10:3<version name="KJV">For Mordecai the Jew was next unto king Ahasuerus, and great among the Jews, and accepted of the multitude of his brethren, seeking the wealth of his people, and speaking peace to all his seed.</p><p /><br /></version>
10:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|猶大人末底改作亞哈隨魯王的宰相，在猶大人中為大，得他眾弟兄的喜悅；他為本族的人求好處，為他種族所有人的幸福說話。
