1:1|ASV|In the second year of Darius the king, in the sixth month, in the first day of the month, came the word of Jehovah by Haggai the prophet unto Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, saying,
1:1|Darby|In the second year of Darius the king, in the sixth month,  on the first day of the month, came the word of Jehovah by the  prophet Haggai unto Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor  of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest,  saying,
1:1|KJV|In the second year of Darius the king, in the sixth month, in the first day of the month, came the word of the LORD by Haggai the prophet unto Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Josedech, the high priest, saying,
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|大利烏王第二年六月初一日，耶和華的話藉申言者哈該，臨到撒拉鐵的兒子猶大省長所羅巴伯，和約撒答的兒子大祭司約書亞，說，
1:2|ASV|Thus speaketh Jehovah of hosts, saying, This people say, It is not the time for us to come, the time for Jehovah's house to be built.
1:2|Darby|Thus speaketh Jehovah of hosts, saying, This people say, The  time is not come, the time that Jehovah's house should be  built.
1:2|KJV|Thus speaketh the LORD of hosts, saying, This people say, The time is not come, the time that the LORD's house should be built.
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬軍之耶和華如此說，這百姓說，建造耶和華殿的時候尚未來到。
1:3|ASV|Then came the word of Jehovah by Haggai the prophet, saying,
1:3|Darby|And the word of Jehovah came by Haggai the prophet, saying,
1:3|KJV|Then came the word of the LORD by Haggai the prophet, saying,
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時耶和華的話藉申言者哈該臨到，說，
1:4|ASV|Is it a time for you yourselves to dwell in your ceiled houses, while this house lieth waste?
1:4|Darby|Is it time for you that ye should dwell in your wainscoted  houses, while this house lieth waste?
1:4|KJV|Is it time for you, O ye, to dwell in your cieled houses, and this house lie waste?
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這殿仍然荒涼，這時候你們自己還住天花板的房屋麼？
1:5|ASV|Now therefore thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Consider your ways.
1:5|Darby|And now thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Consider your ways.
1:5|KJV|Now therefore thus saith the LORD of hosts; Consider your ways.
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現在萬軍之耶和華如此說，你們要省察自己的行徑。
1:6|ASV|Ye have sown much, and bring in little; ye eat, but ye have not enough; ye drink, but ye are not filled with drink; ye clothe you, but there is none warm; and he that earneth wages earneth wages to put it into a bag with holes.
1:6|Darby|Ye have sown much, and bring in little; ye eat, but are not  satisfied; ye drink, but are not filled with drink; ye clothe  yourselves, but there is none warm; and he that earneth wages  earneth wages for a bag with holes.
1:6|KJV|Ye have sown much, and bring in little; ye eat, but ye have not enough; ye drink, but ye are not filled with drink; ye clothe you, but there is none warm; and he that earneth wages earneth wages to put it into a bag with holes.
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們撒的種多，收的卻少；你們喫，卻不得飽；喝，卻不得足；穿衣服，卻不得暖；得工錢的，將工錢裝在破漏的囊中。
1:7|ASV|Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Consider your ways.
1:7|Darby|Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Consider your ways.
1:7|KJV|Thus saith the LORD of hosts; Consider your ways.
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬軍之耶和華如此說，你們要省察自己的行徑。
1:8|ASV|Go up to the mountain, and bring wood, and build the house; and I will take pleasure in it, and I will be glorified, saith Jehovah.
1:8|Darby|Go up to the mountain and bring wood, and build the house,  and I will take pleasure in it, and I will be glorified, saith  Jehovah.
1:8|KJV|Go up to the mountain, and bring wood, and build the house; and I will take pleasure in it, and I will be glorified, saith the LORD.
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要上山取木料，建造這殿；我就因此喜樂，且得榮耀；這是耶和華說的。
1:9|ASV|Ye looked for much, and, lo, it came to little; and when ye brought it home, I did blow upon it. Why? saith Jehovah of hosts. Because of my house that lieth waste, while ye run every man to his own house.
1:9|Darby|Ye looked for much, and behold it was little; and when ye  brought it home, I blew upon it. Wherefore? saith Jehovah of  hosts. Because of my house that lieth waste, whilst ye run  every man to his own house.
1:9|KJV|Ye looked for much, and, lo it came to little; and when ye brought it home, I did blow upon it. Why? saith the LORD of hosts. Because of mine house that is waste, and ye run every man unto his own house.
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們盼望多得，所得的卻少；你們收到家中，我就吹去。這是為甚麼呢？因為我的殿荒涼，你們各人卻奔向自己的房屋；這是萬軍之耶和華說的。
1:10|ASV|Therefore for your sake the heavens withhold the dew, and the earth withholdeth its fruit.
1:10|Darby|Therefore over you the heavens withhold their dew, and the  earth withholdeth its fruit.
1:10|KJV|Therefore the heaven over you is stayed from dew, and the earth is stayed from her fruit.
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以為你們的緣故，天就不降甘露，地也不出土產。
1:11|ASV|And I called for a drought upon the land, and upon the mountains, and upon the grain, and upon the new wine, and upon the oil, and upon that which the ground bringeth forth, and upon men, and upon cattle, and upon all the labor of the hands.
1:11|Darby|And I called for a drought upon the land, and upon the  mountains, and upon the corn, and upon the new wine, and upon  the oil, and upon that which the ground bringeth forth, and  upon man, and upon cattle, and upon all the labour of the  hands.
1:11|KJV|And I called for a drought upon the land, and upon the mountains, and upon the corn, and upon the new wine, and upon the oil, and upon that which the ground bringeth forth, and upon men, and upon cattle, and upon all the labour of the hands.
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我召喚乾旱臨到地土、山岡、五穀、新酒和新油，並地的出產、人民、牲畜，以及人手一切勞碌得來的。
1:12|ASV|Then Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, with all the remnant of the people, obeyed the voice of Jehovah their God, and the words of Haggai the prophet, as Jehovah their God had sent him; and the people did fear before Jehovah.
1:12|Darby|And Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Joshua the son of  Jehozadak, the high priest, and all the remnant of the people,  hearkened to the voice of Jehovah their God, and the words of  Haggai the prophet, according as Jehovah their God had sent  him, and the people feared before Jehovah.
1:12|KJV|Then Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Joshua the son of Josedech, the high priest, with all the remnant of the people, obeyed the voice of the LORD their God, and the words of Haggai the prophet, as the LORD their God had sent him, and the people did fear before the LORD.
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時，撒拉鐵的兒子所羅巴伯和約撒答的兒子大祭司約書亞，並一切餘剩的百姓，都聽從耶和華他們神的話，和耶和華他們神所差來申言者哈該的話；百姓也在耶和華面前存敬畏的心。
1:13|ASV|Then spake Haggai Jehovah's messenger in Jehovah's message unto the people, saying, I am with you, saith Jehovah.
1:13|Darby|Then spoke Haggai, Jehovah's messenger, in Jehovah's  message unto the people, saying, I am with you, saith Jehovah.
1:13|KJV|Then spake Haggai the LORD's messenger in the LORD's message unto the people, saying, I am with you, saith the LORD.
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華的使者哈該奉耶和華的差使對百姓說，耶和華說，我與你們同在。
1:14|ASV|And Jehovah stirred up the spirit of Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and the spirit of Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and the spirit of all the remnant of the people; and they came and did work on the house of Jehovah of hosts, their God,
1:14|Darby|And Jehovah stirred up the spirit of Zerubbabel the son of  Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and the spirit of Joshua the son  of Jehozadak, the high priest, and the spirit of all the  remnant of the people; and they came and worked at the house of  Jehovah of hosts, their God,
1:14|KJV|And the LORD stirred up the spirit of Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and the spirit of Joshua the son of Josedech, the high priest, and the spirit of all the remnant of the people; and they came and did work in the house of the LORD of hosts, their God,
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華激動撒拉鐵的兒子猶大省長所羅巴伯的靈，和約撒答的兒子大祭司約書亞的靈，並一切餘剩之百姓的靈；他們就來，在萬軍之耶和華他們神的殿作工。
1:15<version name="ASV">in the four and twentieth day of the month, in the sixth month, in the second year of Darius the king. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:15<version name="Darby">in the four and twentieth day of the sixth month, in the  second year of Darius the king. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:15<version name="KJV">In the four and twentieth day of the sixth month, in the second year of Darius the king.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這是在大利烏王第二年六月二十四日。
2:1|ASV|In the seventh month, in the one and twentieth day of the month, came the word of Jehovah by Haggai the prophet, saying,
2:1|Darby|In the seventh [month], on the one and twentieth [day] of  the month, came the word of Jehovah by the prophet Haggai,  saying,
2:1|KJV|In the seventh month, in the one and twentieth day of the month, came the word of the LORD by the prophet Haggai, saying,
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|七月二十一日，耶和華的話藉申言者哈該臨到，說，
2:2|ASV|Speak now to Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and to the remnant of the people, saying,
2:2|Darby|Speak now to Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of  Judah, and to Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and  to the remnant of the people, saying,
2:2|KJV|Speak now to Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Josedech, the high priest, and to the residue of the people, saying,
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要告訴撒拉鐵的兒子猶大省長所羅巴伯，和約撒答的兒子大祭司約書亞，並餘剩的百姓，說，
2:3|ASV|Who is left among you that saw this house in its former glory? and how do ye see it now? is it not in your eyes as nothing?
2:3|Darby|Who is left among you that saw this house in its former  glory? and how do ye see it now? Is it not as nothing in your  eyes?
2:3|KJV|Who is left among you that saw this house in her first glory? and how do ye see it now? is it not in your eyes in comparison of it as nothing?
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們中間存留的，有誰見過這殿先前的榮耀呢？現在你們看著如何？豈不在你們眼中看如無有麼？
2:4|ASV|Yet now be strong, O Zerubbabel, saith Jehovah; and be strong, O Joshua, son of Jehozadak, the high priest; and be strong, all ye people of the land, saith Jehovah, and work: for I am with you, saith Jehovah of hosts,
2:4|Darby|But now be strong, Zerubbabel, saith Jehovah; and be strong,  Joshua son of Jehozadak, the high priest; and be strong, all ye  people of the land, saith Jehovah, and work: for I am with you,  saith Jehovah of hosts.
2:4|KJV|Yet now be strong, O Zerubbabel, saith the LORD; and be strong, O Joshua, son of Josedech, the high priest; and be strong, all ye people of the land, saith the LORD, and work: for I am with you, saith the LORD of hosts:
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華說，所羅巴伯阿，雖然如此，現在你當剛強；約撒答的兒子大祭司約書亞阿，你也當剛強；耶和華說，這地的一切百姓，你們都當剛強作工，因為我與你們同在；這是萬軍之耶和華說的。
2:5|ASV|according to the word that I covenanted with you when ye came out of Egypt, and my Spirit abode among you: fear ye not.
2:5|Darby|The word that I covenanted with you when ye came out of  Egypt, and my Spirit, remain among you: fear ye not.
2:5|KJV|According to the word that I covenanted with you when ye came out of Egypt, so my spirit remaineth among you: fear ye not.
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這就是你們出埃及時我與你們立約的話；現今我的靈留在你們中間；你們不要懼怕。
2:6|ASV|For thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Yet once, it is a little while, and I will shake the heavens, and the earth, and the sea, and the dry land;
2:6|Darby|For thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Yet once, it is a little  while, and I will shake the heavens, and the earth, and the  sea, and the dry [land];
2:6|KJV|For thus saith the LORD of hosts; Yet once, it is a little while, and I will shake the heavens, and the earth, and the sea, and the dry land;
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為萬軍之耶和華如此說，過不多時我必再一次震動天、地、海與旱地；
2:7|ASV|and I will shake all nations; and the precious things of all nations shall come; and I will fill this house with glory, saith Jehovah of hosts.
2:7|Darby|and I will shake all nations, and the desire of all nations  shall come; and I will fill this house with glory, saith  Jehovah of hosts.
2:7|KJV|And I will shake all nations, and the desire of all nations shall come: and I will fill this house with glory, saith the LORD of hosts.
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必震動萬國，萬國所羨慕的必來到；我必使這殿滿了榮耀；這是萬軍之耶和華說的。
2:8|ASV|The silver is mine, and the gold is mine, saith Jehovah of hosts.
2:8|Darby|The silver is mine, and the gold is mine, saith Jehovah of  hosts.
2:8|KJV|The silver is mine, and the gold is mine, saith the LORD of hosts.
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬軍之耶和華說，銀子是我的，金子也是我的。
2:9|ASV|The latter glory of this house shall be greater than the former, saith Jehovah of hosts; and in this place will I give peace, saith Jehovah of hosts.
2:9|Darby|The latter glory of this house shall be greater than the  former, saith Jehovah of hosts; and in this place will I give  peace, saith Jehovah of hosts.
2:9|KJV|The glory of this latter house shall be greater than of the former, saith the LORD of hosts: and in this place will I give peace, saith the LORD of hosts.
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這殿後來的榮耀，必大過先前的榮耀，這是萬軍之耶和華說的；在這地方我必賜平安，這是萬軍之耶和華說的。
2:10|ASV|In the four and twentieth day of the ninth month, in the second year of Darius, came the word of Jehovah by Haggai the prophet, saying,
2:10|Darby|On the four and twentieth [day] of the ninth [month], in  the second year of Darius, came the word of Jehovah by Haggai  the prophet, saying,
2:10|KJV|In the four and twentieth day of the ninth month, in the second year of Darius, came the word of the LORD by Haggai the prophet, saying,
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|大利烏王第二年九月二十四日，耶和華的話臨到申言者哈該，說，
2:11|ASV|Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Ask now the priests concerning the law, saying,
2:11|Darby|Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Ask now the priests  [concerning] the law, saying,
2:11|KJV|Thus saith the LORD of hosts; Ask now the priests concerning the law, saying,
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬軍之耶和華如此說，你要向祭司求問訓誨，說，
2:12|ASV|If one bear holy flesh in the skirt of his garment, and with his skirt do touch bread, or pottage, or wine, or oil, or any food, shall it become holy? And the priests answered and said, No.
2:12|Darby|If one bear holy flesh in the skirt of his garment, and  with his skirt do touch bread, or pottage, or wine, or oil, or  any food -- shall it become holy? And the priests answered and  said, No.
2:12|KJV|If one bear holy flesh in the skirt of his garment, and with his skirt do touch bread, or pottage, or wine, or oil, or any meat, shall it be holy? And the priests answered and said, No.
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若有人用衣襟兜聖肉，這衣襟挨著餅，或煮的食物，或酒，或油，或任何別的食物，這些便成為聖麼？祭司回答說，不成為聖。
2:13|ASV|Then said Haggai, If one that is unclean by reason of a dead body touch any of these, shall it be unclean? And the priests answered and said, It shall be unclean.
2:13|Darby|And Haggai said, If one that is unclean by a dead body  touch any of these, is it become unclean? And the priests  answered and said, It shall be unclean.
2:13|KJV|Then said Haggai, If one that is unclean by a dead body touch any of these, shall it be unclean? And the priests answered and said, It shall be unclean.
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈該又說，若有人因摸死屍而不潔，然後挨著這些物的任何一樣，這物就為不潔麼？祭司回答說，必為不潔。
2:14|ASV|Then answered Haggai and said, So is this people, and so is this nation before me, saith Jehovah; and so is every work of their hands; and that which they offer there is unclean.
2:14|Darby|Then answered Haggai and said, So is this people, and so is  this nation before me, saith Jehovah, and so is every work of  their hands; and that which they offer there is unclean.
2:14|KJV|Then answered Haggai, and said, So is this people, and so is this nation before me, saith the LORD; and so is every work of their hands; and that which they offer there is unclean.
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是哈該回答說，耶和華說，在我面前這民也是如此，這國也是如此；他們手中的各樣工作，都是如此。因此，他們在那堜痁m的，乃為不潔。
2:15|ASV|And now, I pray you, consider from this day and backward, before a stone was laid upon a stone in the temple of Jehovah.
2:15|Darby|And now, I pray you, consider from this day and onward,  from before a stone was laid upon a stone in the temple of  Jehovah,
2:15|KJV|And now, I pray you, consider from this day and upward, from before a stone was laid upon a stone in the temple of the LORD:
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現在你們要省察，此日以前，在耶和華的殿還沒有一塊石頭壘在石頭上以前，
2:16|ASV|Through all that time, when one came to a heap of twenty measures, there were but ten; when one came to the winevat to draw out fifty vessels, there were but twenty.
2:16|Darby|-- before those [days] were, when one came to a heap of  twenty [measures], there were but ten; when one came to the vat  to draw out fifty press-measures, there were but twenty.
2:16|KJV|Since those days were, when one came to an heap of twenty measures, there were but ten: when one came to the pressfat for to draw out fifty vessels out of the press, there were but twenty.
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在這些日子以前，有人來到穀堆，想得二十細亞，只得了十細亞；有人來到酒池，想舀五十桶，只得了二十桶。
2:17|ASV|I smote you with blasting and with mildew and with hail in all the work of your hands; yet ye turned not to me, saith Jehovah.
2:17|Darby|I smote you with blasting and with mildew and with hail in  all the work of your hands; and ye [turned] not to me, saith  Jehovah.
2:17|KJV|I smote you with blasting and with mildew and with hail in all the labours of your hands; yet ye turned not to me, saith the LORD.
2:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在你們手中的各樣工作上，我以旱風、霉爛、冰雹攻擊你們，你們仍不歸向我；這是耶和華說的。
2:18|ASV|Consider, I pray you, from this day and backward, from the four and twentieth day of the ninth month, since the day that the foundation of Jehovah's temple was laid, consider it.
2:18|Darby|Consider, I pray you, from this day and onward, from the  four and twentieth day of the ninth [month], from the day that  the foundation of Jehovah's temple was laid, consider [it].
2:18|KJV|Consider now from this day and upward, from the four and twentieth day of the ninth month, even from the day that the foundation of the LORD's temple was laid, consider it.
2:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要省察此日以前，就是從九月二十四日起，從耶和華殿立定根基的日子起，你們要省察。
2:19|ASV|Is the seed yet in the barn? yea, the vine, and the fig-tree, and the pomegranate, and the olive-tree have not brought forth; from this day will I bless you.
2:19|Darby|Is the seed yet in the barn? yea, the vine, and the  fig-tree, and the pomegranate, and the olive-tree have not  brought forth: from this day will I bless [you].
2:19|KJV|Is the seed yet in the barn? yea, as yet the vine, and the fig tree, and the pomegranate, and the olive tree, hath not brought forth: from this day will I bless you.
2:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|倉堣揭魚\種麼？甚至葡萄樹、無花果樹、石榴樹、橄欖樹都沒有結果子；從今日起，我必賜福與你們。
2:20|ASV|And the word of Jehovah came the second time unto Haggai in the four and twentieth day of the month, saying,
2:20|Darby|And the word of Jehovah came the second time unto Haggai on  the four and twentieth [day] of the month, saying,
2:20|KJV|And again the word of the LORD came unto Haggai in the four and twentieth day of the month, saying,
2:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這月二十四日，耶和華的話第二次臨到哈該，說，
2:21|ASV|Speak to Zerubbabel, governor of Judah, saying, I will shake the heavens and the earth;
2:21|Darby|Speak to Zerubbabel, governor of Judah, saying, I will  shake the heavens and the earth;
2:21|KJV|Speak to Zerubbabel, governor of Judah, saying, I will shake the heavens and the earth;
2:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要告訴猶大省長所羅巴伯說，我必震動天地。
2:22|ASV|and I will overthrow the throne of kingdoms; and I will destroy the strength of the kingdoms of the nations; and I will overthrow the chariots, and those that ride in them; and the horses and their riders shall come down, every one by the sword of his brother.
2:22|Darby|and I will overthrow the throne of kingdoms, and I will  destroy the strength of the kingdoms of the nations; and I will  overthrow the chariots, and those that ride therein; and the  horses and their riders shall come down, every one by the sword  of his brother.
2:22|KJV|And I will overthrow the throne of kingdoms, and I will destroy the strength of the kingdoms of the heathen; and I will overthrow the chariots, and those that ride in them; and the horses and their riders shall come down, every one by the sword of his brother.
2:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必傾覆列國的寶座，除滅列邦的勢力；我必傾覆戰車和坐在其上的，馬和騎馬的都必墜落，各人被弟兄的刀所殺。
2:23<version name="ASV">In that day, saith Jehovah of hosts, will I take thee, O Zerubbabel, my servant, the son of Shealtiel, saith Jehovah, and will make thee as a signet; for I have chosen thee, saith Jehovah of hosts. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:23<version name="Darby">In that day, saith Jehovah of hosts, will I take thee,  Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel, my servant, saith Jehovah, and  will make thee as a signet; for I have chosen thee, saith  Jehovah of hosts. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:23<version name="KJV">In that day, saith the LORD of hosts, will I take thee, O Zerubbabel, my servant, the son of Shealtiel, saith the LORD, and will make thee as a signet: for I have chosen thee, saith the LORD of hosts.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華說，撒拉鐵的兒子，我僕人所羅巴伯阿，到那日，萬軍之耶和華說，我必選取你，使你為印記，因我揀選了你；這是萬軍之耶和華說的。
