1:1|ASV|God, having of old time spoken unto the fathers in the prophets by divers portions and in divers manners,
1:1|Darby|God having spoken in many parts and in many ways formerly to  the fathers in the prophets,
1:1|KJV|God, who at sundry times and in divers manners spake in time past unto the fathers by the prophets,
1:1<version name="WYC">God, that spake sometime by prophets in many manners to our fathers, <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22982a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神既在古時，藉著眾申言者，多分多方向列祖說話，
1:2|ASV|hath at the end of these days spoken unto us in his Son, whom he appointed heir of all things, through whom also he made the worlds;
1:2|Darby|at the end of these days has spoken to us in [the person of  the] Son, whom he has established heir of all things, by whom  also he made the worlds;
1:2|KJV|Hath in these last days spoken unto us by his Son, whom he hath appointed heir of all things, by whom also he made the worlds;
1:2|WYC|at the last in these days he hath spoken to us by the Son; whom he hath ordained heir of all things, and by whom he made the worlds.
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就在這末後的日子，在子裡向我們說話；神已立祂作承受萬有者，也曾藉著祂造了宇宙；
1:3|ASV|who being the effulgence of his glory, and the very image of his substance, and upholding all things by the word of his power, when he had made purification of sins, sat down on the right hand of the Majesty on high;
1:3|Darby|who being [the] effulgence of his glory and [the] expression  of his substance, and upholding all things by the word of his  power, having made [by himself] the purification of sins, set  himself down on the right hand of the greatness on high,
1:3|KJV|Who being the brightness of his glory, and the express image of his person, and upholding all things by the word of his power, when he had by himself purged our sins, sat down on the right hand of the Majesty on high:
1:3|WYC|Which when also he is the brightness of glory, and [the] figure of his substance, and beareth all things [and bearing all things] by word of his virtue, he maketh purgation of sins, and sitteth on the right half of the majesty in heavens [sitteth on the right half of majesty in high things];
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂是神榮耀的光輝，是神本質的印像，用祂大能的話維持、載著並推動萬有；祂成就了洗罪的事，就坐在高處至尊至大者的右邊；
1:4|ASV|having become by so much better than the angels, as he hath inherited a more excellent name than they.
1:4|Darby|taking a place by so much better than the angels, as he  inherits a name more excellent than they.
1:4|KJV|Being made so much better than the angels, as he hath by inheritance obtained a more excellent name than they.
1:4<version name="WYC">and so much is made better than angels, by how much he hath inherited a more diverse name [a more different, <i>or excellent</i>, name] before them.</version>
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂所承受的名，既比天使的名更超特，祂就比天使更美。
1:5|ASV|For unto which of the angels said he at any time, Thou art my Son, This day have I begotten thee? and again, I will be to him a Father, And he shall be to me a Son?
1:5|Darby|For to which of the angels said he ever, *Thou* art my Son:  this day have *I* begotten thee? and again, *I* will be to him  for father, and *he* shall be to me for son?
1:5|KJV|For unto which of the angels said he at any time, Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee? And again, I will be to him a Father, and he shall be to me a Son?
1:5|WYC|For to which of the angels said God any time, Thou art my Son, I have engendered thee to day [I have to day gendered thee]?  And again, I shall be to him into a Father, and he shall be to me into a Son?
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神曾對那一個天使說過，“你是我的兒子，我今日生了你？”又說，“我要作祂的父，祂要作我的兒子？”
1:6|ASV|And when he again bringeth in the firstborn into the world he saith, And let all the angels of God worship him.
1:6|Darby|and again, when he brings in the firstborn into the  habitable world, he says, And let all God's angels worship him.
1:6|KJV|And again, when he bringeth in the firstbegotten into the world, he saith, And let all the angels of God worship him.
1:6|WYC|And when again he bringeth in the first begotten Son into the world [And when again he bringeth in the first begotten into the roundness of the earth], he saith, And all the angels of God worship him.
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|再者，神再帶長子到世上來的時候，就說，“神的眾使者都要拜祂。”
1:7|ASV|And of the angels he saith, Who maketh his angels winds, And his ministers a flame a fire:
1:7|Darby|And as to the angels he says, Who makes his angels spirits  and his ministers a flame of fire;
1:7|KJV|And of the angels he saith, Who maketh his angels spirits, and his ministers a flame of fire.
1:7|WYC|But he saith to angels [And soothly to angels he saith], He that maketh his angels spirits, and his ministers flame of fire.
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|論到使者，祂說，“神使祂的使者為風，並使祂的僕役為火焰。”
1:8|ASV|but of the Son he saith, Thy throne, O God, is for ever and ever; And the sceptre of uprightness is the sceptre of thy kingdom.
1:8|Darby|but as to the Son, Thy throne, O God, [is] to the age of the  age, and a sceptre of uprightness [is] the sceptre of thy  kingdom.
1:8|KJV|But unto the Son he saith, Thy throne, O God, is for ever and ever: a sceptre of righteousness is the sceptre of thy kingdom.
1:8<version name="WYC">But to the Son <i>he saith</i>, God, thy throne <i>is</i> into the world of world [into the world of worlds]; a rod of equity <i>is</i> the rod of thy realm;</version>
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|論到子卻說，“神阿，你的寶座是永永遠遠的，你國的權杖是正直的權杖。
1:9|ASV|Thou hast loved righteousness, and hated iniquity; Therefore God, thy God, hath anointed thee With the oil of gladness above thy fellows.
1:9|Darby|Thou hast loved righteousness and hast hated lawlessness;  therefore God, thy God, has anointed thee with oil of gladness  above thy companions.
1:9|KJV|Thou hast loved righteousness, and hated iniquity; therefore God, even thy God, hath anointed thee with the oil of gladness above thy fellows.
1:9<version name="WYC">thou hast loved rightwiseness, and hatedest wickedness; therefore the God, thy God, anointed thee with oil of joy [therefore God, thy God, anointed thee with oil of gladness, <i>or joy</i>], more than thy fellows.</version>
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你愛公義，恨惡不法；所以神，就是你的神，用歡樂的油膏你，勝過膏你的同夥。”
1:10|ASV|And, Thou, Lord, in the beginning didst lay the foundation of the earth, And the heavens are the works of thy hands:
1:10|Darby|And, *Thou* in the beginning, Lord, hast founded the earth,  and works of thy hands are the heavens.
1:10|KJV|And, Thou, Lord, in the beginning hast laid the foundation of the earth; and the heavens are the works of thine hands:
1:10|WYC|And, Thou, Lord, in the beginning foundedest the earth, and heavens be works of thine hands;
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又說，“主阿，你起初立了地的根基，諸天也是你手的工作；
1:11|ASV|They shall perish; but thou continuest: And they all shall wax old as doth a garment;
1:11|Darby|They shall perish, but *thou* continuest still; and they  all shall grow old as a garment,
1:11|KJV|They shall perish; but thou remainest; and they all shall wax old as doth a garment;
1:11|WYC|they shall perish, but thou shalt perfectly dwell; and all shall wax old as a cloak [as a cloth],
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|天地都要滅沒，你卻長存；一切都要像衣服漸漸舊了，
1:12|ASV|And as a mantle shalt thou roll them up, As a garment, and they shall be changed: But thou art the same, And thy years shall not fail.
1:12|Darby|and as a covering shalt thou roll them up, and they shall  be changed; but *thou* art the Same, and thy years shall not  fail.
1:12|KJV|And as a vesture shalt thou fold them up, and they shall be changed: but thou art the same, and thy years shall not fail.
1:12|WYC|and thou shalt change them as a cloak [as a cloth], and they shall be changed.  But thou art the same thyself, and thy years shall not fail.
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要將天地像外衣一樣捲起來，天地就像衣服一樣改變了；惟有你仍是一樣，你的年數也沒有窮盡。”
1:13|ASV|But of which of the angels hath he said at any time, Sit thou on my right hand, Till I make thine enemies the footstool of thy feet?
1:13|Darby|But as to which of the angels said he ever, Sit at my right  hand until I put thine enemies [as] footstool of thy feet?
1:13|KJV|But to which of the angels said he at any time, Sit on my right hand, until I make thine enemies thy footstool?
1:13|WYC|But to which of the angels said God at any time, Sit thou on my right half, till I put thine enemies a stool of thy feet?
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神曾對那一個天使說過，“你坐在我的右邊，等我使你的仇敵作你的腳凳？”
1:14<version name="ASV">Are they not all ministering spirits, sent forth to do service for the sake of them that shall inherit salvation? </p><p /><br /></version>
1:14<version name="Darby">Are they not all ministering spirits, sent out for service  on account of those who shall inherit salvation? </p><p /><br /></version>
1:14<version name="KJV">Are they not all ministering spirits, sent forth to minister for them who shall be heirs of salvation?</p><p /><br /></version>
1:14|WYC|Whether they all be not serving spirits, sent to serve for them [sent into ministry for them] that take the heritage of health?
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|天使豈不都是服役的靈，奉差遣為那些將要承受救恩的人效力麼？
2:1|ASV|Therefore we ought to give the more earnest heed to the things that were heard, lest haply we drift away from them.
2:1|Darby|For this reason we should give heed more abundantly to the  things [we have] heard, lest in any way we should slip away.
2:1|KJV|Therefore we ought to give the more earnest heed to the things which we have heard, lest at any time we should let them slip.
2:1|WYC|Therefore more plenteously it behooveth us to keep those things [Therefore it behooveth us to keep more plenteously those things], that we have heard, lest peradventure we float away.
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，我們必須越發注重所聽見的，恐怕我們隨流漂去。
2:2|ASV|For if the word spoken through angels proved stedfast, and every transgression and disobedience received a just recompense of reward;
2:2|Darby|For if the word which was spoken by angels was firm, and  every transgression and disobedience received just retribution,
2:2|KJV|For if the word spoken by angels was stedfast, and every transgression and disobedience received a just recompence of reward;
2:2<version name="WYC">For if that word that was said by angels, was made firm, and each breaking of the law and unobedience [and each trespassing, <i>or breaking of the law</i>, and unobedience] took just retribution of meed,</version>
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那藉著天使所說的話，既是確定的，凡干犯、悖逆的，又都受了該受的報應；
2:3|ASV|how shall we escape, if we neglect so great a salvation? which having at the first been spoken through the Lord, was confirmed unto us by them that heard;
2:3|Darby|how shall *we* escape if we have been negligent of so great  salvation, which, having had its commencement in being spoken  [of] by the Lord, has been confirmed to us by those who have  heard;
2:3|KJV|How shall we escape, if we neglect so great salvation; which at the first began to be spoken by the Lord, and was confirmed unto us by them that heard him;
2:3|WYC|how shall we escape, if we despise so great an health?  Which, when it had taken beginning to be told out by the Lord, of them that heard is confirmed into us.
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們若忽略了這麼大的救恩，怎能逃罪？這救恩起先是主親自講的，後來聽見的人給我們證實了；
2:4|ASV|God also bearing witness with them, both by signs and wonders, and by manifold powers, and by gifts of the Holy Spirit, according to his own will.
2:4|Darby|God bearing, besides, witness with [them] to [it], both by  signs and wonders, and various acts of power, and distributions  of [the] Holy Spirit, according to his will?
2:4|KJV|God also bearing them witness, both with signs and wonders, and with divers miracles, and gifts of the Holy Ghost, according to his own will?
2:4|WYC|For God witnessed together by miracles, and wonders, and great marvels, and diverse works of power, and partings of the Holy Ghost, by his will. [God together witnessing by signs, and wonders, and great marvels, and diverse virtues, and distributions of the Holy Ghost, after his will.]
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又有神按自己的旨意，用神蹟、奇事、並各樣的異能、以及聖靈分給的恩賜，同他們作見證。
2:5|ASV|For not unto angels did he subject the world to come, whereof we speak.
2:5|Darby|For he has not subjected to angels the habitable world which  is to come, of which we speak;
2:5|KJV|For unto the angels hath he not put in subjection the world to come, whereof we speak.
2:5|WYC|But not to angels God subjected the world that is to coming [Forsooth not to angels God subjected the roundness of the earth to come], of which we speak.
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們所說要來的世界，神原沒有交給天使管轄。
2:6|ASV|But one hath somewhere testified, saying, What is man, that thou art mindful of him? Or the son of man, that thou visitest him?
2:6|Darby|but one has testified somewhere, saying, What is man, that  thou rememberest him, or son of man that thou visitest him?
2:6|KJV|But one in a certain place testified, saying, What is man, that thou art mindful of him? or the son of man that thou visitest him?
2:6|WYC|But some man witnessed in a place, and said [Soothly some man witnessed in some place, saying], What thing is man, that thou art mindful of him, or man's son, for thou visitest him?
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但有人在經上某處鄭重見證說，“人算甚麼，你竟顧念他？世人算甚麼，你竟眷顧他？
2:7|ASV|Thou madest him a little lower than the angels; Thou crownedst him with glory and honor, And didst set him over the works of thy hands:
2:7|Darby|Thou hast made him some little inferior to the angels; thou  hast crowned him with glory and honour, [and hast set him over  the works of thy hands;]
2:7|KJV|Thou madest him a little lower than the angels; thou crownedst him with glory and honour, and didst set him over the works of thy hands:
2:7|WYC|Thou hast made him a little less than angels [Thou madest him a little less from angels]; thou hast crowned him with glory and honour; and thou hast ordained him on [upon] the works of thine hands.
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你使祂比天使微小一點，賜祂榮耀尊貴為冠冕，並派祂管理你手所造的，
2:8|ASV|Thou didst put all things in subjection under his feet. For in that he subjected all things unto him, he left nothing that is not subject to him. But now we see not yet all things subjected to him.
2:8|Darby|thou hast subjected all things under his feet. For in  subjecting all things to him, he has left nothing unsubject to  him. But now we see not yet all things subjected to *him*,
2:8|KJV|Thou hast put all things in subjection under his feet. For in that he put all in subjection under him, he left nothing that is not put under him. But now we see not yet all things put under him.
2:8|WYC|Thou hast made all things subject under his feet.  And in that that he subjected all things to him, he left nothing unsubject to him [he left nothing unsubjected to him].  But now we see not yet all things subject to him;
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|叫萬有都服在祂的腳下。”既叫萬有都服祂，就沒有留下一樣不服祂的。只是如今我們還不見萬有都服祂，
2:9|ASV|But we behold him who hath been made a little lower than the angels, even Jesus, because of the suffering of death crowned with glory and honor, that by the grace of God he should taste of death for every man.
2:9|Darby|but we see Jesus, who [was] made some little inferior to  angels on account of the suffering of death, crowned with glory  and honour; so that by the grace of God he should taste death  for every thing.
2:9|KJV|But we see Jesus, who was made a little lower than the angels for the suffering of death, crowned with glory and honour; that he by the grace of God should taste death for every man.
2:9|WYC|but we see him that was made a little less than angels, Jesus, for the passion of death crowned with glory and honour, that he through [the] grace of God should taste death for all men.
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|惟獨看見耶穌得了榮耀尊貴為冠冕，祂為著受死的苦，成為比天使微小一點的，好叫祂因著神的恩，為樣樣嘗到死味。
2:10|ASV|For it became him, for whom are all things, and through whom are all things, in bringing many sons unto glory, to make the author of their salvation perfect through sufferings.
2:10|Darby|For it became him, for whom [are] all things, and by whom  [are] all things, in bringing many sons to glory, to make  perfect the leader of their salvation through sufferings.
2:10|KJV|For it became him, for whom are all things, and by whom are all things, in bringing many sons unto glory, to make the captain of their salvation perfect through sufferings.
2:10<version name="WYC">For it beseemed him, for whom all things, and by whom all things <i>were made</i>, which had brought many sons into glory, <i>and was</i> author of the health of them, that he had an end by passion. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23005a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|原來萬有因祂而有，藉祂而造的那位，為著要領許多的兒子進榮耀裡去，就藉著苦難成全他們救恩的創始者，這對祂本是合宜的。
2:11|ASV|For both he that sanctifieth and they that are sanctified are all of one: for which cause he is not ashamed to call them brethren,
2:11|Darby|For both he that sanctifies and those sanctified [are] all  of one; for which cause he is not ashamed to call them  brethren,
2:11|KJV|For both he that sanctifieth and they who are sanctified are all of one: for which cause he is not ashamed to call them brethren,
2:11<version name="WYC">For he that halloweth, and they that be hallowed, <i>be</i> all of one; for which cause he is not ashamed to call them brethren,</version>
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因那聖別人的，和那些被聖別的，都是出於一；因這緣故，祂稱他們為弟兄，並不以為恥，說，
2:12|ASV|saying, I will declare thy name unto my brethren, In the midst of the congregation will I sing thy praise.
2:12|Darby|saying, I will declare thy name to my brethren; in [the]  midst of [the] assembly will I sing thy praises.
2:12|KJV|Saying, I will declare thy name unto my brethren, in the midst of the church will I sing praise unto thee.
2:12|WYC|saying, I shall tell thy name to my brethren; in the middle of the church I shall praise thee.
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|“我要向我的弟兄宣告你的名，在召會中我要歌頌你。”
2:13|ASV|And again, I will put my trust in him. And again, Behold, I and the children whom God hath given me.
2:13|Darby|And again, I will trust in him. And again, Behold, I and  the children which God has given me.
2:13|KJV|And again, I will put my trust in him. And again, Behold I and the children which God hath given me.
2:13|WYC|And again, I shall be trusting into him; and again, Lo! I and my children, which God gave to me.
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又說，“我要信靠祂。”又說，“看哪，我與神所給我的兒女。”
2:14|ASV|Since then the children are sharers in flesh and blood, he also himself in like manner partook of the same; that through death he might bring to nought him that had the power of death, that is, the devil;
2:14|Darby|Since therefore the children partake of blood and flesh, he  also, in like manner, took part in the same, that through death  he might annul him who has the might of death, that is, the  devil;
2:14|KJV|Forasmuch then as the children are partakers of flesh and blood, he also himself likewise took part of the same; that through death he might destroy him that had the power of death, that is, the devil;
2:14|WYC|Therefore for children communed to flesh and blood, and he also took part of the same, that by death he should destroy him that had lordship of death, that is to say, the devil,
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|兒女既同有血肉之體，祂也照樣親自有分於血肉之體，為要藉著死，廢除那掌死權的，就是魔鬼，
2:15|ASV|and might deliver all them who through fear of death were all their lifetime subject to bondage.
2:15|Darby|and might set free all those who through fear of death  through the whole of their life were subject to bondage.
2:15|KJV|And deliver them who through fear of death were all their lifetime subject to bondage.
2:15|WYC|and that he should deliver them that by dread of death [and should deliver them that by dread of death], by all life were bound to servage.
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並要釋放那些一生因怕死而受挾於奴役的人。
2:16|ASV|For verily not to angels doth he give help, but he giveth help to the seed of Abraham.
2:16|Darby|For he does not indeed take hold of angels [by the hand],  but he takes hold of the seed of Abraham.
2:16|KJV|For verily he took not on him the nature of angels; but he took on him the seed of Abraham.
2:16|WYC|And he took [to] never angels, but he took [to] the seed of Abraham.
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|誠然祂不是救援天使，乃是救援亞伯拉罕的後裔。
2:17|ASV|Wherefore it behooved him in all things to be made like unto his brethren, that he might become a merciful and faithful high priest in things pertaining to God, to make propitiation for the sins of the people.
2:17|Darby|Wherefore it behoved him in all things to be made like to  [his] brethren, that he might be a merciful and faithful high  priest in things relating to God, to make propitiation for the  sins of the people;
2:17|KJV|Wherefore in all things it behoved him to be made like unto his brethren, that he might be a merciful and faithful high priest in things pertaining to God, to make reconciliation for the sins of the people.
2:17|WYC|Wherefore he ought to be likened to brethren by all things, that he should be made merciful and a faithful bishop to God, that he should be merciful to the trespasses of the people.
2:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以祂凡事該與祂的弟兄一樣，為要在關於神的事上，成為憐憫、忠信的大祭司，好為百姓的罪成就平息。
2:18<version name="ASV">For in that he himself hath suffered being tempted, he is able to succor them that are tempted. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:18<version name="Darby">for, in that himself has suffered, being tempted, he is  able to help those that are being tempted. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:18<version name="KJV">For in that he himself hath suffered being tempted, he is able to succour them that are tempted.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:18|WYC|For in that thing in which he suffered, and was tempted, he is mighty to help also them that be tempted.
2:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為祂既然在所受的苦上被試誘，就能幫助被試誘的人。
3:1|ASV|Wherefore, holy brethren, partakers of a heavenly calling, consider the Apostle and High Priest of our confession, even Jesus;
3:1|Darby|Wherefore, holy brethren, partakers of [the] heavenly  calling, consider the Apostle and High Priest of our  confession, Jesus,
3:1|KJV|Wherefore, holy brethren, partakers of the heavenly calling, consider the Apostle and High Priest of our profession, Christ Jesus;
3:1|WYC|Therefore [Wherefore], holy brethren, and partners of heavenly calling, behold ye the apostle and the bishop of our confession, Jesus,
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，有分於屬天呼召的聖別弟兄們，你們應當留意思想我們所承認為使徒、為大祭司的耶穌；
3:2|ASV|who was faithful to him that appointed him, as also was Moses in all his house.
3:2|Darby|who is faithful to him that has constituted him, as Moses  also in all his house.
3:2|KJV|Who was faithful to him that appointed him, as also Moses was faithful in all his house.
3:2|WYC|which is true to him that made him, as also Moses in all the house of him.
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂對那設立祂的忠信，如同摩西在神的全家忠信一樣。
3:3|ASV|For he hath been counted worthy of more glory than Moses, by so much as he that built the house hath more honor than the house.
3:3|Darby|For *he* has been counted worthy of greater glory than  Moses, by how much he that has built it has more honour than  the house.
3:3|KJV|For this man was counted worthy of more glory than Moses, inasmuch as he who hath builded the house hath more honour than the house.
3:3<version name="WYC">But this <i>bishop</i> [Forsooth this <i>bishop</i>] is had worthy of more glory than Moses, by as much as he hath more honour of the house, that made the house.</version>
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂比摩西被斷為配得更多的榮耀，就像建設房屋的比房屋更尊貴。
3:4|ASV|For every house is builded by some one; but he that built all things is God.
3:4|Darby|For every house is built by some one; but he who has built  all things [is] God.
3:4|KJV|For every house is builded by some man; but he that built all things is God.
3:4|WYC|For each house is made of some man; [forsooth] he that made all things of nought is God.
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為每一座房屋都是由人建設的，但建設萬有的乃是神。
3:5|ASV|And Moses indeed was faithful in all his house as a servant, for a testimony of those things which were afterward to be spoken;
3:5|Darby|And Moses indeed [was] faithful in all his house, as a  ministering servant, for a testimony of the things to be spoken  after;
3:5|KJV|And Moses verily was faithful in all his house, as a servant, for a testimony of those things which were to be spoken after;
3:5|WYC|And [soothly] Moses was true in all his house, as a servant, into witnessing of those things that were to be said;
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|摩西為僕人，在神的全家忠信，為要給將來傳講的事作見證；
3:6|ASV|but Christ as a son, over his house; whose house are we, if we hold fast our boldness and the glorying of our hope firm unto the end.
3:6|Darby|but Christ, as Son over his house, whose house are *we*, if  indeed we hold fast the boldness and the boast of hope firm to  the end.
3:6|KJV|But Christ as a son over his own house; whose house are we, if we hold fast the confidence and the rejoicing of the hope firm unto the end.
3:6|WYC|but Christ as a son in his house.  Which house we be, if we hold firm trust and glory of hope into [unto] the end.
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但基督為兒子，治理神的家；我們若將因盼望而有的膽量和誇耀堅守到底，便是祂的家了。
3:7|ASV|Wherefore, even as the Holy Spirit saith, To-day if ye shall hear his voice,
3:7|Darby|Wherefore, even as says the Holy Spirit, To-day if ye will  hear his voice,
3:7|KJV|Wherefore (as the Holy Ghost saith, To day if ye will hear his voice,
3:7|WYC|Wherefore as the Holy Ghost saith, To day, if ye have heard his voice,
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，正如聖靈所說的，“你們今日若聽見祂的聲音，
3:8|ASV|Harden not your hearts, as in the provocation, Like as in the day of the trial in the wilderness,
3:8|Darby|harden not your hearts, as in the provocation, in the day of  temptation in the wilderness;
3:8|KJV|Harden not your hearts, as in the provocation, in the day of temptation in the wilderness:
3:8|WYC|do not ye harden your hearts, as in wrathing, like the day of temptation in desert [after the day of temptation in desert];
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就不可硬著心，像在曠野惹祂發怒時，試探祂的日子一樣；
3:9|ASV|Where your fathers tried me by proving me, And saw my works forty years.
3:9|Darby|where your fathers tempted [me], by proving [me], and saw my  works forty years.
3:9|KJV|When your fathers tempted me, proved me, and saw my works forty years.
3:9|WYC|where your fathers tempted me, and proved, and saw my works forty years. [where your fathers tempted me, proved, and saw my works.]
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在那裡你們的祖宗以試驗試探我，並且觀看我的作為四十年。
3:10|ASV|Wherefore I was displeased with this generation, And said, They do always err in their heart: But they did not know my ways;
3:10|Darby|Wherefore I was wroth with this generation, and said, They  always err in heart; and *they* have not known my ways;
3:10|KJV|Wherefore I was grieved with that generation, and said, They do alway err in their heart; and they have not known my ways.
3:10<version name="WYC">Wherefore I was wroth [Wherefore I was offended, <i>or wroth</i>,] to this generation, and I said, Evermore they err in heart, for they knew not my ways;</version>
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我厭煩那一代的人，說，他們心裡時常迷糊，竟不曉得我的法則；
3:11|ASV|As I sware in my wrath, They shall not enter into my rest.
3:11|Darby|so I swore in my wrath, If they shall enter into my rest.
3:11|KJV|So I sware in my wrath, They shall not enter into my rest.)
3:11|WYC|to which I swore in my wrath, they shall not enter into my rest. [to whom I swore in my wrath, if they shall enter into my rest.]
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我就在怒中起誓說，他們絕不可進入我的安息。”
3:12|ASV|Take heed, brethren, lest haply there shall be in any one of you an evil heart of unbelief, in falling away from the living God:
3:12|Darby|See, brethren, lest there be in any one of you a wicked  heart of unbelief, in turning away from [the] living God.
3:12|KJV|Take heed, brethren, lest there be in any of you an evil heart of unbelief, in departing from the living God.
3:12|WYC|Brethren, see ye, lest peradventure in any of you be an evil heart of unbelief, to depart from the living God.
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，你們要謹慎，免得你們中間，或有人存著不信的惡心，將活神離棄了。
3:13|ASV|but exhort one another day by day, so long as it is called To-day; lest any one of you be hardened by the deceitfulness of sin:
3:13|Darby|But encourage yourselves each day, as long as it is called  To-day, that none of you be hardened by the deceitfulness of  sin.
3:13|KJV|But exhort one another daily, while it is called To day; lest any of you be hardened through the deceitfulness of sin.
3:13|WYC|But admonish yourselves by all days, the while to day is named, that none of you be hardened by fallacy of sin [that none of you be hardened by falseness of sin].
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|總要趁著還有稱為“今日”的時候，天天彼此相勸，免得你們中間有人被罪迷惑，心就剛硬了。
3:14|ASV|for we are become partakers of Christ, if we hold fast the beginning of our confidence firm unto the end:
3:14|Darby|For we are become companions of the Christ if indeed we  hold the beginning of the assurance firm to the end;
3:14|KJV|For we are made partakers of Christ, if we hold the beginning of our confidence stedfast unto the end;
3:14|WYC|For we be made partners of Christ, if nevertheless we hold the beginning of his substance firm into the end.
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|“你們今日若聽見祂的聲音，就不可硬著心，像惹祂發怒的時候一樣。”當這話還在說的時候，
3:15|ASV|while it is said, To-day if ye shall hear his voice, Harden not your hearts, as in the provocation.
3:15|Darby|in that it is said, To-day if ye will hear his voice, do  not harden your hearts, as in the provocation;
3:15|KJV|While it is said, To day if ye will hear his voice, harden not your hearts, as in the provocation.
3:15|WYC|While it is said, to day, if ye have heard the voice of him, do not ye harden your hearts, as in that wrathing.
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們若將起初的確信堅守到底，就必作基督的同夥了。
3:16|ASV|For who, when they heard, did provoke? nay, did not all they that came out of Egypt by Moses?
3:16|Darby|(for who was it, who, having heard, provoked? but [was it]  not all who came out of Egypt by Moses?
3:16|KJV|For some, when they had heard, did provoke: howbeit not all that came out of Egypt by Moses.
3:16|WYC|For some men hearing wrathed [Soothly some hearing wrathed], but not all they that went out of Egypt by Moses.
3:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|原來那聽見而惹祂發怒的是誰？豈不是那些藉著摩西從埃及出來的眾人麼？
3:17|ASV|And with whom was he displeased forty years? was it not with them that sinned, whose bodies fell in the wilderness?
3:17|Darby|And with whom was he wroth forty years? [Was it] not with  those who had sinned, whose carcases fell in the wilderness?
3:17|KJV|But with whom was he grieved forty years? was it not with them that had sinned, whose carcases fell in the wilderness?
3:17|WYC|But to whom was he wrathed forty years?  Whether not to them that sinned, whose carrions were cast down in desert [into desert]?
3:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神四十年之久，又厭煩了誰？豈不是那些犯罪，屍首倒在曠野的人麼？
3:18|ASV|And to whom sware he that they should not enter into his rest, but to them that were disobedient?
3:18|Darby|And to whom sware he that they should not enter into his  rest, but to those who had not hearkened to the word?
3:18|KJV|And to whom sware he that they should not enter into his rest, but to them that believed not?
3:18<version name="WYC">And to whom swore he, that they should not enter into the rest of him <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23031a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>, no but to them that were unbelieveful?</version>
3:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又向誰起誓說，他們必不得進入祂的安息？豈不是向那些不信從的人麼？
3:19<version name="ASV">And we see that they were not able to enter in because of unbelief. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:19<version name="Darby">And we see that they could not enter in on account of  unbelief;) </p><p /><br /></version>
3:19<version name="KJV">So we see that they could not enter in because of unbelief.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:19|WYC|And we see, that they might not enter into the rest of him for unbelief.
3:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣我們看出，他們不能進入，是因為不信的緣故了。
4:1|ASV|Let us fear therefore, lest haply, a promise being left of entering into his rest, any one of you should seem to have come short of it.
4:1|Darby|Let us therefore fear, lest, a promise being left of  entering into his rest, any one of you might seem to have  failed [of it].
4:1|KJV|Let us therefore fear, lest, a promise being left us of entering into his rest, any of you should seem to come short of it.
4:1<version name="WYC">Therefore dread we, least peradventure while the promise of entering into his rest is left, that any of us be guessed to be away [be guessed, <i>or deemed</i>, for to fail].</version>
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，我們應當畏懼，免得那進入祂安息的應許，雖然留給我們，你們中間卻有人像是趕不上了。
4:2|ASV|For indeed we have had good tidings preached unto us, even as also they: but the word of hearing did not profit them, because it was not united by faith with them that heard.
4:2|Darby|For indeed we have had glad tidings presented to us, even as  they also; but the word of the report did not profit *them*,  not being mixed with faith in those who heard.
4:2|KJV|For unto us was the gospel preached, as well as unto them: but the word preached did not profit them, not being mixed with faith in them that heard it.
4:2|WYC|For it is told also to us, as to them [Forsooth it is told to us, as and to them].  And the word that was heard profited not to them, not mingled to faith of those things that they heard.
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為有福音傳給我們，像傳給他們一樣；只是所聽見的話與他們無益，因為這話在聽見的人裡面，沒有與信心調和。
4:3|ASV|For we who have believed do enter into that rest; even as he hath said, As I sware in my wrath, They shall not enter into my rest: although the works were finished from the foundation of the world.
4:3|Darby|For we enter into the rest who have believed; as he said, As  I have sworn in my wrath, If they shall enter into my rest;  although the works had been completed from [the] foundation of  [the] world.
4:3|KJV|For we which have believed do enter into rest, as he said, As I have sworn in my wrath, if they shall enter into my rest: although the works were finished from the foundation of the world.
4:3<version name="WYC">For we that have believed, shall enter into rest, as he said, As I swore in my wrath, they shall not enter into my rest.  And when the works were made perfect at the ordinance of the world, <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23035a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但我們已經相信的人，卻進入那安息，正如神所說，“我就在怒中起誓，他們絕不可進入我的安息。”其實造物之工，從創世以來已經完成了。
4:4|ASV|For he hath said somewhere of the seventh day on this wise, And God rested on the seventh day from all his works;
4:4|Darby|For he has said somewhere of the seventh [day] thus, And God  rested on the seventh day from all his works:
4:4|KJV|For he spake in a certain place of the seventh day on this wise, And God did rest the seventh day from all his works.
4:4|WYC|he said thus in a place of the seventh day [he said thus in some place of the seventh day], And God rested in the seventh day from all his works.
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為論到第七日，祂在某處這樣說，“到第七日，神就歇了祂一切的工，”
4:5|ASV|and in this place again, They shall not enter into my rest.
4:5|Darby|and in this again, If they shall enter into my rest.
4:5|KJV|And in this place again, If they shall enter into my rest.
4:5<version name="WYC">And in this <i>place</i> again, They shall not enter into my rest. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23037b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|而在這裡又說，“他們絕不可進入我的安息。”
4:6|ASV|Seeing therefore it remaineth that some should enter thereinto, and they to whom the good tidings were before preached failed to enter in because of disobedience,
4:6|Darby|Seeing therefore it remains that some enter into it, and  those who first received the glad tidings did not enter in on  account of not hearkening to the word,
4:6|KJV|Seeing therefore it remaineth that some must enter therein, and they to whom it was first preached entered not in because of unbelief:
4:6|WYC|Therefore for it followeth, that some men shall enter into it, and they to which it was told to before [and they first to whom it is told], entered not for their unbelief.
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，這安息既留下給一些人進入，而那先前有福音傳給他們的人，因為不信從，不得進入，
4:7|ASV|he again defineth a certain day, To-day, saying in David so long a time afterward (even as hath been said before), To-day if ye shall hear his voice, Harden not your hearts.
4:7|Darby|again he determines a certain day, saying, in David,  'To-day,' after so long a time; (according as it has been said  before), To-day, if ye will hear his voice, harden not your  hearts.
4:7|KJV|Again, he limiteth a certain day, saying in David, To day, after so long a time; as it is said, To day if ye will hear his voice, harden not your hearts.
4:7|WYC|Again, he determineth some day, and saith in David, To day, after so much time of time [Again, he termineth some day, saying in David, To day, after so much of time], as it is before-said, To day if ye have heard his voice, do not ye harden your hearts.
4:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神就再指定一個日子，就是過了這麼長的時間，在大衛書上所說的今日，正如祂前面所說的：“你們今日若聽見祂的聲音，就不可硬著心。”
4:8|ASV|For if Joshua had given them rest, he would not have spoken afterward of another day.
4:8|Darby|For if Jesus had brought them into rest, he would not have  spoken afterwards about another day.
4:8|KJV|For if Jesus had given them rest, then would he not afterward have spoken of another day.
4:8|WYC|For if Jesus had given rest to them, he should never speak of other after this day [after that day].
4:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若是約書亞已經使他們得了安息，此後神就不會題起別的日子了。
4:9|ASV|There remaineth therefore a sabbath rest for the people of God.
4:9|Darby|There remains then a sabbatism to the people of God.
4:9|KJV|There remaineth therefore a rest to the people of God.
4:9|WYC|Therefore the sabbath is left to the people of God. [Therefore rest is left to the people of God.]
4:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，必有一安息日的安息，為神的子民存留。
4:10|ASV|For he that is entered into his rest hath himself also rested from his works, as God did from his.
4:10|Darby|For he that has entered into his rest, he also has rested  from his works, as God did from his own.
4:10|KJV|For he that is entered into his rest, he also hath ceased from his own works, as God did from his.
4:10|WYC|For he that is entered into his rest, [and he] rested of his works, as also God of his.
4:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為那進入祂安息的，也歇了自己的工，正如神歇了自己的工一樣。
4:11|ASV|Let us therefore give diligence to enter into that rest, that no man fall after the same example of disobedience.
4:11|Darby|Let us therefore use diligence to enter into that rest,  that no one may fall after the same example of not hearkening  to the word.
4:11|KJV|Let us labour therefore to enter into that rest, lest any man fall after the same example of unbelief.
4:11|WYC|Therefore haste we to enter into that rest, that no man fall into the same ensample of unbelief [that no man fall into the same example of unbelief].
4:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我們務必竭力進入那安息，免得有人隨著那不信從的樣子跌倒了。
4:12|ASV|For the word of God is living, and active, and sharper than any two-edged sword, and piercing even to the dividing of soul and spirit, of both joints and marrow, and quick to discern the thoughts and intents of the heart.
4:12|Darby|For the word of God [is] living and operative, and sharper  than any two-edged sword, and penetrating to [the] division of  soul and spirit, both of joints and marrow, and a discerner of  the thoughts and intents of [the] heart.
4:12|KJV|For the word of God is quick, and powerful, and sharper than any twoedged sword, piercing even to the dividing asunder of soul and spirit, and of the joints and marrow, and is a discerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart.
4:12<version name="WYC">For the word of God is quick, and speedy in working, and more able to pierce than any twain-edged sword [two-edged sword], and stretcheth forth [till] to the parting of the soul and of the spirit, and of the jointures and marrows, and deemer of thoughts, and of intents of hearts <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23044c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup>.</version>
4:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神的話是活的，是有功效的，比一切兩刃的劍更鋒利，能以刺入、甚至剖開魂與靈，骨節與骨髓，連心中的思念和主意都能辨明。
4:13|ASV|And there is no creature that is not manifest in his sight: but all things are naked and laid open before the eyes of him with whom we have to do.
4:13|Darby|And there is not a creature unapparent before him; but all  things [are] naked and laid bare to his eyes, with whom we have  to do.
4:13|KJV|Neither is there any creature that is not manifest in his sight: but all things are naked and opened unto the eyes of him with whom we have to do.
4:13|WYC|And no creature is invisible in the sight of God.  For all things be naked and open to his eyes, to whom a word to us.
4:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且被造的，沒有一個在祂面前不是顯明的，反而萬有在我們必須向祂交賬的主眼前，都是赤露敞開的。
4:14|ASV|Having then a great high priest, who hath passed through the heavens, Jesus the Son of God, let us hold fast our confession.
4:14|Darby|Having therefore a great high priest who has passed through  the heavens, Jesus the Son of God, let us hold fast the  confession.
4:14|KJV|Seeing then that we have a great high priest, that is passed into the heavens, Jesus the Son of God, let us hold fast our profession.
4:14<version name="WYC">Therefore we that have a great bishop, that pierced heavens, Jesus, the Son of God, hold we the acknowledging of our hope [hold we the confession, <i>or</i> <i>acknowledging</i>, of our faith].</version>
4:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，我們既有一位經過了諸天，尊大的大祭司，就是神的兒子耶穌，便當堅守所承認的。
4:15|ASV|For we have not a high priest that cannot be touched with the feeling of our infirmities; but one that hath been in all points tempted like as we are, yet without sin.
4:15|Darby|For we have not a high priest not able to sympathise with  our infirmities, but tempted in all things in like manner, sin  apart.
4:15|KJV|For we have not an high priest which cannot be touched with the feeling of our infirmities; but was in all points tempted like as we are, yet without sin.
4:15|WYC|For we have not a bishop, that may not have compassion on our infirmities, but was tempted by all things by likeness, without sin.
4:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因我們並非有一位不能同情我們軟弱的大祭司，祂乃是在各方面受過試誘，與我們一樣，只是沒有罪。
4:16<version name="ASV">Let us therefore draw near with boldness unto the throne of grace, that we may receive mercy, and may find grace to help  us in time of need. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:16<version name="Darby">Let us approach therefore with boldness to the throne of  grace, that we may receive mercy, and find grace for seasonable  help. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:16<version name="KJV">Let us therefore come boldly unto the throne of grace, that we may obtain mercy, and find grace to help in time of need.</p><p /><br /></version>
4:16|WYC|Therefore go we with trust to the throne of his grace, that we get mercy, and find grace in opportune help [in covenable help].
4:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我們只管坦然無懼的來到施恩的寶座前，為要受憐憫，得恩典，作應時的幫助。
5:1|ASV|For every high priest, being taken from among men, is appointed for men in things pertaining to God, that he may offer both gifts and sacrifices for sins:
5:1|Darby|For every high priest taken from amongst men is established  for men in things relating to God, that he may offer both gifts  and sacrifices for sins;
5:1|KJV|For every high priest taken from among men is ordained for men in things pertaining to God, that he may offer both gifts and sacrifices for sins:
5:1|WYC|For each bishop taken of men, is ordained for men in these things that be to God [in those things that be to God], that he offer gifts and sacrifices for sins.
5:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡從人間選取的大祭司，都是被設立替人辦理關於神的事，為要獻上禮物和為著罪的祭物。
5:2|ASV|who can bear gently with the ignorant and erring, for that he himself also is compassed with infirmity;
5:2|Darby|being able to exercise forbearance towards the ignorant and  erring, since he himself also is clothed with infirmity;
5:2|KJV|Who can have compassion on the ignorant, and on them that are out of the way; for that he himself also is compassed with infirmity.
5:2|WYC|Which may together sorrow with them, that be unknowing and err [that know not and err]; for also he is environed with infirmity.
5:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他能體諒那無知和失迷的，因為他自己也為軟弱所困；
5:3|ASV|and by reason thereof is bound, as for the people, so also for himself, to offer for sins.
5:3|Darby|and, on account of this [infirmity], he ought, even as for  the people, so also for himself, to offer for sins.
5:3|KJV|And by reason hereof he ought, as for the people, so also for himself, to offer for sins.
5:3|WYC|And therefore he oweth, as for the people, so also for himself, to offer for sins.
5:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此，他怎樣為百姓為著罪獻祭，也應當照樣為自己獻祭。
5:4|ASV|And no man taketh the honor unto himself, but when he is called of God, even as was Aaron.
5:4|Darby|And no one takes the honour to himself but [as] called by  God, even as Aaron also.
5:4|KJV|And no man taketh this honour unto himself, but he that is called of God, as was Aaron.
5:4<version name="WYC">Neither any man taketh to him honour, but he that is called of God, as Aaron <i>was</i>.</version>
5:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這大祭司的尊貴，不是人自取的，乃是人蒙神呼召所得的，像亞倫一樣。
5:5|ASV|So Christ also glorified not himself to be made a high priest, but he that spake unto him, Thou art my Son, This day have I begotten thee:
5:5|Darby|Thus the Christ also has not glorified himself to be made a  high priest; but he who had said to him, *Thou* art my Son, *I*  have to-day begotten thee.
5:5|KJV|So also Christ glorified not himself to be made an high priest; but he that said unto him, Thou art my Son, to day have I begotten thee.
5:5|WYC|So [and] Christ clarified not himself, that he were bishop, but he that spake to him, Thou art my Son, to day I engendered thee [to day I gendered thee].
5:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，基督也不是自取榮耀作大祭司，乃是那向祂說“你是我的兒子，我今日生了你”的，榮耀了祂；
5:6|ASV|as he saith also in another place, Thou art a priest for ever After the order of Melchizedek.
5:6|Darby|Even as also in another [place] he says, *Thou* [art] a  priest for ever according to the order of Melchisedec.
5:6|KJV|As he saith also in another place, Thou art a priest for ever after the order of Melchisedec.
5:6|WYC|As [and] in another place he saith, Thou art a priest without end [Thou art a priest into without end], after the order of Melchisedec.
5:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就如神在另一處又說，“你是照著麥基洗德的等次，永遠為祭司。”
5:7|ASV|Who in the days of his flesh, having offered up prayers and supplications with strong crying and tears unto him that was able to save him from death, and having been heard for his godly fear,
5:7|Darby|Who in the days of his flesh, having offered up both  supplications and entreaties to him who was able to save him  out of death, with strong crying and tears; (and having been  heard because of his piety;)
5:7|KJV|Who in the days of his flesh, when he had offered up prayers and supplications with strong crying and tears unto him that was able to save him from death, and was heard in that he feared;
5:7|WYC|Which in the days of his flesh offered, with great cry and tears, prayers and beseechings to him that might make him safe from death, and was heard for his reverence.
5:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|基督在肉身的日子，強烈的哭號，流淚向那能救祂出死的，獻上祈禱和懇求，因祂的虔誠，就蒙了垂聽；
5:8|ASV|though he was a Son, yet learned obedience by the things which he suffered;
5:8|Darby|though he were Son, he learned obedience from the things  which he suffered;
5:8|KJV|Though he were a Son, yet learned he obedience by the things which he suffered;
5:8|WYC|And when he was God's Son, he learned obedience of these things that he suffered;
5:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂雖然為兒子，還是因所受的苦難學了順從；
5:9|ASV|and having been made perfect, he became unto all them that obey him the author of eternal salvation;
5:9|Darby|and having been perfected, became to all them that obey him,  author of eternal salvation;
5:9|KJV|And being made perfect, he became the author of eternal salvation unto all them that obey him;
5:9|WYC|and he brought to the end is made cause of everlasting health [and he led to perfection is made cause of everlasting health] to all that obey him,
5:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂既得以成全，就對凡順從祂的人，成了永遠救恩的根源，
5:10|ASV|named of God a high priest after the order of Melchizedek.
5:10|Darby|addressed by God [as] high priest according to the order of  Melchisedec.
5:10|KJV|Called of God an high priest after the order of Melchisedec.
5:10<version name="WYC"><i>and is </i>called of God a bishop, by the order of Melchisedec. [called of God a bishop, by the order of Melchisedec.]</version>
5:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|蒙神照著麥基洗德的等次，稱為大祭司。
5:11|ASV|Of whom we have many things to say, and hard of interpretation, seeing ye are become dull of hearing.
5:11|Darby|Concerning whom we have much to say, and hard to be  interpreted in speaking [of it], since ye are become dull in  hearing.
5:11|KJV|Of whom we have many things to say, and hard to be uttered, seeing ye are dull of hearing.
5:11<version name="WYC">Of whom <i>there is </i>to us a great word for to say, and able to be expounded, for ye be made feeble to hear.</version>
5:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|關於麥基洗德，我們有許多話要說，且是難以解明的，因為你們聽覺遲鈍。
5:12|ASV|For when by reason of the time ye ought to be teachers, ye have need again that some one teach you the rudiments of the first principles of the oracles of God; and are become such as have need of milk, and not of solid food.
5:12|Darby|For when for the time ye ought to be teachers, ye have  again need that [one] should teach you what [are] the elements  of the beginning of the oracles of God, and are become such as  have need of milk, [and] not of solid food.
5:12|KJV|For when for the time ye ought to be teachers, ye have need that one teach you again which be the first principles of the oracles of God; and are become such as have need of milk, and not of strong meat.
5:12<version name="WYC">For when ye ought to be masters for a time, again ye need that ye be taught, which be the letters of the beginning of God's words [which be the elements, <i>or letters</i>, of the beginning of God's words].  And ye be made those, to whom is need of milk, and not [of] firm meat.</version>
5:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|按時間說，你們該作教師；可是你們還需要有人將神諭言開端的要綱教導你們；並且成了那必須用奶，不能喫乾糧的人。
5:13|ASV|For every one that partaketh of milk is without experience of the word of righteousness; for he is a babe.
5:13|Darby|For every one that partakes of milk [is] unskilled in the  word of righteousness, for he is a babe;
5:13|KJV|For every one that useth milk is unskilful in the word of righteousness: for he is a babe.
5:13|WYC|For each that is partner of milk, is without part of the word of rightwiseness, for he is a little child.
5:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡只能享用奶的，對公義的話都是沒有經驗的，因為他是嬰孩；
5:14<version name="ASV">But solid food is for fullgrown men, even those who by reason of use have their senses exercised to discern good and evil. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:14<version name="Darby">but solid food belongs to full-grown men, who, on account  of habit, have their senses exercised for distinguishing both  good and evil. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:14<version name="KJV">But strong meat belongeth to them that are of full age, even those who by reason of use have their senses exercised to discern both good and evil.</p><p /><br /></version>
5:14|WYC|But of perfect men is firm meat, of them that for custom have [their] wits exercised to discretion of good and of evil [of good and evil].
5:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只有長成的人，纔能喫乾糧，他們的官能因習用而受了操練，就能分辨好壞了。
6:1|ASV|Wherefore leaving the doctrine of the first principles of Christ, let us press on unto perfection; not laying again a foundation of repentance from dead works, and of faith toward God,
6:1|Darby|Wherefore, leaving the word of the beginning of the Christ,  let us go on [to what belongs] to full growth, not laying again  a foundation of repentance from dead works and faith in God,
6:1|KJV|Therefore leaving the principles of the doctrine of Christ, let us go on unto perfection; not laying again the foundation of repentance from dead works, and of faith toward God,
6:1<version name="WYC">Therefore we bringing in a word of the beginning of Christ, be we born to the perfection <i>of him</i>, not again laying the foundament of penance from dead works, and of the faith to God, <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23063a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
6:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，我們既離開了那論到基督之開端的話，就當竭力前進，達到完全、成熟，不再立根基，就是悔改脫開死行，信靠神，
6:2|ASV|of the teaching of baptisms, and of laying on of hands, and of resurrection of the dead, and of eternal judgment.
6:2|Darby|of [the] doctrine of washings, and of imposition of hands,  and of resurrection of [the] dead, and of eternal judgment;
6:2|KJV|Of the doctrine of baptisms, and of laying on of hands, and of resurrection of the dead, and of eternal judgment.
6:2|WYC|and of teaching of baptisms, and of laying on of hands, and of rising again of dead men, and of everlasting doom.
6:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|浸洗的教訓，按手，死人的復活，以及永遠的審判。
6:3|ASV|And this will we do, if God permit.
6:3|Darby|and this will we do if God permit.
6:3|KJV|And this will we do, if God permit.
6:3|WYC|And this thing we shall do, if God shall suffer.
6:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神若准許，我們必如此行。
6:4|ASV|For as touching those who were once enlightened and tasted of the heavenly gift, and were made partakers of the Holy Spirit,
6:4|Darby|For it is impossible to renew again to repentance those once  enlightened, and who have tasted of the heavenly gift, and have  been made partakers of [the] Holy Spirit,
6:4|KJV|For it is impossible for those who were once enlightened, and have tasted of the heavenly gift, and were made partakers of the Holy Ghost,
6:4|WYC|But it is impossible, that they that be once lightened [them that once be illumined], and have tasted also an heavenly gift, and be made partners of the Holy Ghost,
6:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為那些曾經蒙了光照，嘗過屬天的恩賜，又有分於聖靈，
6:5|ASV|and tasted the good word of God, and the powers of the age to come,
6:5|Darby|and have tasted the good word of God, and [the] works of  power of [the] age to come,
6:5|KJV|And have tasted the good word of God, and the powers of the world to come,
6:5|WYC|and nevertheless have tasted the good word of God, and the virtues of the world to coming [and virtues of the world to come],
6:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並嘗過神美善的話，以及來世的能力，
6:6|ASV|and then fell away, it is impossible to renew them again unto repentance; seeing they crucify to themselves the Son of God afresh, and put him to an open shame.
6:6|Darby|and have fallen away, crucifying for themselves [as they do]  the Son of God, and making a show of [him].
6:6|KJV|If they shall fall away, to renew them again unto repentance; seeing they crucify to themselves the Son of God afresh, and put him to an open shame.
6:6<version name="WYC">and be slid far away, that they be renewed again to penance.  <i>Which</i> again crucify to themselves the Son of God, and have him to scorn.</version>
6:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|而偏離的人，不可能再重新悔改，為自己把神的兒子重釘十字架，明明的羞辱祂。
6:7|ASV|For the land which hath drunk the rain that cometh oft upon it, and bringeth forth herbs meet for them for whose sake it is also tilled, receiveth blessing from God:
6:7|Darby|For ground which drinks the rain which comes often upon it,  and produces useful herbs for those for whose sakes also it is  tilled, partakes of blessing from God;
6:7|KJV|For the earth which drinketh in the rain that cometh oft upon it, and bringeth forth herbs meet for them by whom it is dressed, receiveth blessing from God:
6:7|WYC|For the earth that drinketh rain oft coming on it, and bringeth forth suitable herb to them of which it is tilled [Forsooth the earth drinking rain oft coming upon it, and bringing forth covenable herb to them of whom it is tilled], taketh blessing of God.
6:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就如田地，吸收了屢次下在其上的雨水，並且生產菜蔬，合乎耕種的人用，就從神得享祝福；
6:8|ASV|but if it beareth thorns and thistles, it is rejected and nigh unto a curse; whose end is to be burned.
6:8|Darby|but bringing forth thorns and briars, it is found worthless  and nigh to a curse, whose end [is] to be burned.
6:8|KJV|But that which beareth thorns and briers is rejected, and is nigh unto cursing; whose end is to be burned.
6:8|WYC|But that that is bringing forth thorns and briers, is reprovable, and next to curse, whose ending shall be into burning.
6:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但若長出荊棘和蒺藜，就被廢棄，近於咒詛，結局就是焚燒。
6:9|ASV|But, beloved, we are persuaded better things of you, and things that accompany salvation, though we thus speak:
6:9|Darby|But we are persuaded concerning you, beloved, better things,  and connected with salvation, even if we speak thus.
6:9|KJV|But, beloved, we are persuaded better things of you, and things that accompany salvation, though we thus speak.
6:9|WYC|But, ye most dear-worthy, we trust of you better things, and near(er) to health, though we speak so.
6:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而，親愛的，我們雖是這樣說，卻深信你們的光景強過這些，且都是聯於救恩的。
6:10|ASV|for God is not unrighteous to forget your work and the love which ye showed toward his name, in that ye ministered unto the saints, and still do minister.
6:10|Darby|For God [is] not unrighteous to forget your work, and the  love which ye have shewn to his name, having ministered to the  saints, and [still] ministering.
6:10|KJV|For God is not unrighteous to forget your work and labour of love, which ye have shewed toward his name, in that ye have ministered to the saints, and do minister.
6:10|WYC|For God is not unjust, that he forget your work and love, which ye have showed in his name; for ye have ministered to saints, and minister.
6:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神並非不公義，竟忘記你們所作的工，和你們為著祂的名所顯出的愛，就是先前供應聖徒，如今還是供應。
6:11|ASV|And we desire that each one of you may show the same diligence unto the fulness of hope even to the end:
6:11|Darby|But we desire earnestly that each one of you shew the same  diligence to the full assurance of hope unto the end;
6:11|KJV|And we desire that every one of you do shew the same diligence to the full assurance of hope unto the end:
6:11|WYC|And we covet that each of you show the same busyness to the filling of hope [to the full-filling of hope] into the end;
6:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只是我們切願你們各人都顯出同樣的殷勤，以致對你們所盼望的有充分的確信，一直到底；
6:12|ASV|that ye be not sluggish, but imitators of them who through faith and patience inherit the promises.
6:12|Darby|that ye be not sluggish, but imitators of those who through  faith and patience have been inheritors of the promises.
6:12|KJV|That ye be not slothful, but followers of them who through faith and patience inherit the promises.
6:12|WYC|that ye be not made slow, but also followers of them, which by faith and patience shall inherit the promises.
6:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|使你們不怠惰，反倒效法那些藉著信和恆忍承受應許的人。
6:13|ASV|For when God made promise to Abraham, since he could swear by none greater, he sware by himself,
6:13|Darby|For God, having promised to Abraham, since he had no  greater to swear by, swore by himself,
6:13|KJV|For when God made promise to Abraham, because he could swear by no greater, he sware by himself,
6:13|WYC|For God promising to Abraham, for he had none greater, by whom he should swear, swore by himself,
6:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神應許亞伯拉罕的時候，因為沒有比自己更大的可以指著起誓，就指著自己起誓，說，
6:14|ASV|saying, Surely blessing I will bless thee, and multiplying I will multiply thee.
6:14|Darby|saying, Surely blessing I will bless thee, and multiplying  I will multiply thee;
6:14|KJV|Saying, Surely blessing I will bless thee, and multiplying I will multiply thee.
6:14|WYC|and said [saying], I blessing shall bless thee, and I multiplying shall multiply thee;
6:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|“保定的，論福，我必賜福給你；論繁增，我必使你繁增。”
6:15|ASV|And thus, having patiently endured, he obtained the promise.
6:15|Darby|and thus, having had long patience, he got the promise.
6:15|KJV|And so, after he had patiently endured, he obtained the promise.
6:15|WYC|and so he long abiding had the promise. [and so he long suffering got repromission.]
6:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，亞伯拉罕既恆久忍耐，就得了所應許的。
6:16|ASV|For men swear by the greater: and in every dispute of theirs the oath is final for confirmation.
6:16|Darby|For men indeed swear by a greater, and with them the oath  is a term to all dispute, as making matters sure.
6:16|KJV|For men verily swear by the greater: and an oath for confirmation is to them an end of all strife.
6:16<version name="WYC">For men swear by a greater than themselves, and the end of all their plea [and the end of all their controversy, <i>or debate</i>,] is an oath to confirmation.</version>
6:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人都是指著比自己大的起誓，而起誓乃是人各樣爭論的了結，作為保證。
6:17|ASV|Wherein God, being minded to show more abundantly unto the heirs of the promise the immutability of his counsel, interposed with an oath;
6:17|Darby|Wherein God, willing to shew more abundantly to the heirs  of the promise the unchangeableness of his purpose, intervened  by an oath,
6:17|KJV|Wherein God, willing more abundantly to shew unto the heirs of promise the immutability of his counsel, confirmed it by an oath:
6:17<version name="WYC">In which thing God willing to show plenteouslier to the heirs of his promise the firmness of his counsel, put betwixt an oath, <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23079b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
6:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，神既願意向那承受應許的人，格外顯明祂的旨意是不更改的，就介入以起誓擔保；
6:18|ASV|that by two immutable things, in which it is impossible for God to lie, we may have a strong encouragement, who have fled for refuge to lay hold of the hope set before us:
6:18|Darby|that by two unchangeable things, in which [it was]  impossible that God should lie, we might have a strong  encouragement, who have fled for refuge to lay hold on the hope  set before us,
6:18|KJV|That by two immutable things, in which it was impossible for God to lie, we might have a strong consolation, who have fled for refuge to lay hold upon the hope set before us:
6:18<version name="WYC">that by two things unmoveable, by which it is impossible that God lie, we have a strongest solace, that flee together to hold the hope that is put forth to us. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23080c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup></version>
6:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|好藉這兩件不更改的事，就是神在其中不能說謊的，叫我們這逃往避難所，持定擺在前頭盼望的人，可以得著有力的鼓勵；
6:19|ASV|which we have as an anchor of the soul, a hope both sure and stedfast and entering into that which is within the veil;
6:19|Darby|which we have as anchor of the soul, both secure and firm,  and entering into that within the veil,
6:19|KJV|Which hope we have as an anchor of the soul, both sure and stedfast, and which entereth into that within the veil;
6:19<version name="WYC">Which <i>hope</i> as an anchor we have secure to the soul, and firm, and going into the inner things of hiding;</version>
6:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們有這盼望如同魂的錨，又牢靠又堅固，且通入幔內；
6:20<version name="ASV">whither as a forerunner Jesus entered for us, having become a high priest for ever after the order of Melchizedek. </p><p /><br /></version>
6:20<version name="Darby">where Jesus is entered as forerunner for us, become for  ever a high priest according to the order of Melchisedec. </p><p /><br /></version>
6:20<version name="KJV">Whither the forerunner is for us entered, even Jesus, made an high priest for ever after the order of Melchisedec.</p><p /><br /></version>
6:20|WYC|where the before-goer, Jesus, that is made bishop without end by the order of Melchisedec, entered for us. [where the fore-goer for us entered in, Jesus, made bishop into without end after the order of Melchisedec.]
6:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|作先鋒的耶穌，既照著麥基洗德的等次，成了永遠的大祭司，就為我們進入幔內。
7:1|ASV|For this Melchizedek, king of Salem, priest of God Most High, who met Abraham returning from the slaughter of the kings and blessed him,
7:1|Darby|For this Melchisedec, King of Salem, priest of the most high  God, who met Abraham returning from smiting the kings, and  blessed him;
7:1|KJV|For this Melchisedec, king of Salem, priest of the most high God, who met Abraham returning from the slaughter of the kings, and blessed him;
7:1|WYC|And this Melchisedec, king of Salem, and priest of the highest God [the priest of the highest God], which met Abraham, as he turned again from the slaying of the kings, and blessed him;
7:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這麥基洗德，撒冷王，至高神的祭司，就是那當亞伯拉罕殺敗諸王回來的時候，迎接他，並給他祝福的。
7:2|ASV|to whom also Abraham divided a tenth part of all (being first, by interpretation, King of righteousness, and then also King of Salem, which is King of peace;
7:2|Darby|to whom Abraham gave also the tenth portion of all; first  being interpreted King of righteousness, and then also King of  Salem, which is King of peace;
7:2|KJV|To whom also Abraham gave a tenth part of all; first being by interpretation King of righteousness, and after that also King of Salem, which is, King of peace;
7:2|WYC|to whom also Abraham parted tithes of all things; first he is said king of rightwiseness [first soothly the which is interpreted king of rightwiseness], and afterward king of Salem, that is to say, king of peace,
7:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞伯拉罕也將所得的一切，分了十分之一給他。首先，他的名字繙出來是公義王；其次，他又是撒冷王，就是平安王。
7:3|ASV|without father, without mother, without genealogy, having neither beginning of days nor end of life, but made like unto the Son of God), abideth a priest continually.
7:3|Darby|without father, without mother, without genealogy; having  neither beginning of days nor end of life, but assimilated to  the Son of God, abides a priest continually.
7:3|KJV|Without father, without mother, without descent, having neither beginning of days, nor end of life; but made like unto the Son of God; abideth a priest continually.
7:3<version name="WYC">without father, without mother, without genealogy, neither having beginning of days, neither end of life; and he <i>is</i> likened to the Son of God, and dwelleth priest without end [forsooth he likened to the Son of God, dwelleth priest into without end].</version>
7:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他無父，無母，無族譜，既無時日之始，也無生命之終，乃與神的兒子相似，是永久為祭司的。
7:4|ASV|Now consider how great this man was, unto whom Abraham, the patriarch, gave a tenth out of the chief spoils.
7:4|Darby|Now consider how great this [personage] was, to whom [even]  the patriarch Abraham gave a tenth out of the spoils.
7:4|KJV|Now consider how great this man was, unto whom even the patriarch Abraham gave the tenth of the spoils.
7:4<version name="WYC">But behold ye how great is this [<i>man</i>] [Forsooth behold ye how great this is], to whom Abraham the patriarch gave tithes of the best things.</version>
7:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要想想，先祖亞伯拉罕把上等擄物中的十分之一給他，這人是何等尊大！
7:5|ASV|And they indeed of the sons of Levi that receive the priest's office have commandment to take tithes of the people according to the law, that is, of their brethren, though these have come out of the loins of Abraham:
7:5|Darby|And they indeed from among the sons of Levi, who receive the  priesthood, have commandment to take tithes from the people  according to the law, that is from their brethren, though these  are come out of the loins of Abraham:
7:5|KJV|And verily they that are of the sons of Levi, who receive the office of the priesthood, have a commandment to take tithes of the people according to the law, that is, of their brethren, though they come out of the loins of Abraham:
7:5|WYC|For men of the sons of Levi taking priesthood have commandment to take tithes of the people, by the law [And soothly men taking priesthood of the sons of Levi have commandment to take tithes of the people, after the law], that is to say, of their brethren, though also they went out of the loins of Abraham.
7:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那些領受祭司職任的利未子孫，奉命照著律法從百姓，就是從他們的弟兄，收取十分之一，儘管他們的弟兄是從亞伯拉罕腰中出來的；
7:6|ASV|but he whose genealogy is not counted from them hath taken tithes of Abraham, and hath blessed him that hath the promises.
7:6|Darby|but he who has no genealogy from them has tithed Abraham,  and blessed him who had the promises.
7:6|KJV|But he whose descent is not counted from them received tithes of Abraham, and blessed him that had the promises.
7:6<version name="WYC">But he whose generation is not numbered in them, took tithes of Abraham; and he blessed this <i>Abraham</i>, which had repromissions.</version>
7:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但那不與他們同譜系的，倒收取亞伯拉罕的十分之一，並為那蒙受應許的祝福。
7:7|ASV|But without any dispute the less is blessed of the better.
7:7|Darby|But beyond all gainsaying, the inferior is blessed by the  better.
7:7|KJV|And without all contradiction the less is blessed of the better.
7:7|WYC|Without any gainsaying [Forsooth without any against-saying], that that is less, is blessed of the better.
7:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|向來都是卑小的蒙尊優的祝福，這是一無可駁的。
7:8|ASV|And here men that die receive tithes; but there one, of whom it is witnessed that he liveth.
7:8|Darby|And here dying men receive tithes; but there [one] of whom  the witness is that he lives;
7:8|KJV|And here men that die receive tithes; but there he receiveth them, of whom it is witnessed that he liveth.
7:8|WYC|And here deadly men take tithes; but there he beareth witnessing, that he liveth. [And here soothly men dying take tithes; forsooth there it is witnessed, that he liveth.]
7:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在這裡，收取十分之一的，是必死的人；在那裡，卻是那被證實為活著的。
7:9|ASV|And, so to say, through Abraham even Levi, who receiveth tithes, hath paid tithes;
7:9|Darby|and, so to speak, through Abraham, Levi also, who received  tithes, has been made to pay tithes.
7:9|KJV|And as I may so say, Levi also, who receiveth tithes, payed tithes in Abraham.
7:9|WYC|And that it be said so [And that it is so said], by Abraham also Levi, that took tithes, was tithed;
7:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且可以這樣說，那收取十分之一的利未，也是藉著亞伯拉罕納了十分之一；
7:10|ASV|for he was yet in the loins of his father, when Melchizedek met him.
7:10|Darby|For he was yet in the loins of his father when Melchisedec  met him.
7:10|KJV|For he was yet in the loins of his father, when Melchisedec met him.
7:10|WYC|and yet he was in his father's loins, when Melchisedec met him.
7:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為麥基洗德迎接亞伯拉罕的時候，利未還在他祖宗的腰中。
7:11|ASV|Now if there was perfection through the Levitical priesthood (for under it hath the people received the law), what further need was there that another priest should arise after the order of Melchizedek, and not be reckoned after the order of Aaron?
7:11|Darby|If indeed then perfection were by the Levitical priesthood,  for the people had their law given to them in connexion with  *it*, what need [was there] still that a different priest  should arise according to the order of Melchisedec, and not be  named after the order of Aaron?
7:11|KJV|If therefore perfection were by the Levitical priesthood, (for under it the people received the law,) what further need was there that another priest should rise after the order of Melchisedec, and not be called after the order of Aaron?
7:11|WYC|Therefore if perfection was by the priesthood of Levi, for under him the people took the law, what yet was it needful, another priest to rise, by the order of Melchisedec, and not to be said by the order of Aaron [what yet was it needful, another priest to rise, after the order of Melchisedec, and not to be said after the order of Aaron]?
7:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，藉著利未人的祭司職分，若真能使人得完全，（百姓原是根據這職分領受了律法，）又何需另外興起一位祭司，照著麥基洗德的等次，不照著亞倫的等次來稱謂？
7:12|ASV|For the priesthood being changed, there is made of necessity a change also of the law.
7:12|Darby|For, the priesthood being changed, there takes place of  necessity a change of law also.
7:12|KJV|For the priesthood being changed, there is made of necessity a change also of the law.
7:12|WYC|For why when the priesthood is translated, it is need [it is needful] that also [the] translation of the law be made.
7:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祭司的職分既已更換，律法也必須更換。
7:13|ASV|For he of whom these things are said belongeth to another tribe, from which no man hath given attendance at the altar.
7:13|Darby|For he, of whom these things are said, belongs to a  different tribe, of which no one has [ever] been attached to  the service of the altar.
7:13|KJV|For he of whom these things are spoken pertaineth to another tribe, of which no man gave attendance at the altar.
7:13<version name="WYC">But he in whom these things be said, is of another lineage, of which no man was priest to the altar [of which no man was priest, <i>or ready</i>, to the altar].</version>
7:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為這些話所說到的人，原有分於別的支派，那支派裡沒有一人伺候過祭壇。
7:14|ASV|For it is evident that our Lord hath sprung out of Judah; as to which tribe Moses spake nothing concerning priests.
7:14|Darby|For it is clear that our Lord has sprung out of Juda, as to  which tribe Moses spake nothing as to priests.
7:14|KJV|For it is evident that our Lord sprang out of Juda; of which tribe Moses spake nothing concerning priesthood.
7:14|WYC|For it is open [Soothly it is openly known], that our Lord is born of Juda, in which lineage Moses spake nothing of priests.
7:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們的主明顯是從猶大支派出來的；論到這支派，摩西並沒有講到祭司的事。
7:15|ASV|And what we say is yet more abundantly evident, if after the likeness of Melchizedek there ariseth another priest,
7:15|Darby|And it is yet more abundantly evident, since a different  priest arises according to the similitude of Melchisedec,
7:15|KJV|And it is yet far more evident: for that after the similitude of Melchisedec there ariseth another priest,
7:15|WYC|And more yet it is known, if by the order of Melchisedec another priest is risen up; [And more yet it is known, if after the order of Melchisedec another priest riseth;]
7:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|既然照麥基洗德的樣式，興起一位不同的祭司來，我們的話就更是顯然的了；
7:16|ASV|who hath been made, not after the law of a carnal commandment, but after the power of an endless life:
7:16|Darby|who has been constituted not according to law of fleshly  commandment, but according to power of indissoluble life.
7:16|KJV|Who is made, not after the law of a carnal commandment, but after the power of an endless life.
7:16<version name="WYC">which is not made by the law of fleshly commandment, but by [the] virtue of life that may not be undone. [the which is not made after the law of fleshly commandment, but after virtue of life indissoluble, <i>or that may not be undone</i>.]</version>
7:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂成了祭司，不是照著屬肉之誡命的律法，乃是照著不能毀壞之生命的大能；
7:17|ASV|for it is witnessed of him, Thou art a priest for ever After the order of Melchizedek.
7:17|Darby|For it is borne witness, *Thou* art a priest for ever  according to the order of Melchisedec.
7:17|KJV|For he testifieth, Thou art a priest for ever after the order of Melchisedec.
7:17|WYC|For he witnesseth, That thou art a priest without end, by the order of Melchisedec; [Soothly he witnesseth, For thou art a priest into without end, after the order of Melchisedec;]
7:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為有為祂作見證的說，“你是照著麥基洗德的等次，永遠為祭司。”
7:18|ASV|For there is a disannulling of a foregoing commandment because of its weakness and unprofitableness
7:18|Darby|For there is a setting aside of the commandment going  before for its weakness and unprofitableness,
7:18|KJV|For there is verily a disannulling of the commandment going before for the weakness and unprofitableness thereof.
7:18|WYC|that reproving of the commandment before-going is made, for the unfirmness and unprofit of it.
7:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|一面是先前的誡命，因其軟弱和無益，而被廢掉，
7:19|ASV|(for the law made nothing perfect), and a bringing in thereupon of a better hope, through which we draw nigh unto God.
7:19|Darby|(for the law perfected nothing,) and the introduction of a  better hope by which we draw nigh to God.
7:19|KJV|For the law made nothing perfect, but the bringing in of a better hope did; by the which we draw nigh unto God.
7:19|WYC|For why the law brought nothing to perfection, but there is a bringing in of a better hope, by which we approach to God [by which we nigh to God].
7:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|（律法原來一無所成，）另一面卻在其上引進更美的盼望，藉此我們可以親近神。
7:20|ASV|And inasmuch as it is not without the taking of an oath
7:20|Darby|And by how much [it was] not without the swearing of an  oath;
7:20|KJV|And inasmuch as not without an oath he was made priest:
7:20<version name="WYC">And how great it is, not without swearing [<i>that Christ is made priest after the order of  Melchisedec</i>];</version>
7:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|再者，耶穌為祭司，既不是不起誓立的，
7:21|ASV|(for they indeed have been made priests without an oath; but he with an oath by him that saith of him, The Lord sware and will not repent himself, Thou art a priest for ever);
7:21|Darby|(for they are become priests without the swearing of an  oath, but he with the swearing of an oath, by him who said, as  to him, The Lord has sworn, and will not repent [of it], *Thou*  [art] priest for ever [according to the order of Melchisedec];)
7:21|KJV|(For those priests were made without an oath; but this with an oath by him that said unto him, The Lord sware and will not repent, Thou art a priest for ever after the order of Melchisedec:)
7:21|WYC|but the others [forsooth others] be made priests without an oath; but this priest with an oath, by him that said to him, The Lord swore, and it shall not rue him, Thou art a priest without end, by the order of Melchisedec [Thou art a priest into without end, after the order of  Melchisedec];
7:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|（那些人為祭司，原不是起誓立的，耶穌卻是起誓立的，是藉著那對祂說，“主起了誓絕不後悔，你是永遠為祭司”的，）
7:22|ASV|by so much also hath Jesus become the surety of a better covenant.
7:22|Darby|by so much Jesus became surety of a better covenant.
7:22|KJV|By so much was Jesus made a surety of a better testament.
7:22|WYC|in so much Jesus is made [better] promiser of the better testament.
7:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂就成了更美之約的保證。
7:23|ASV|And they indeed have been made priests many in number, because that by death they are hindered from continuing:
7:23|Darby|And they have been many priests, on account of being  hindered from continuing by death;
7:23|KJV|And they truly were many priests, because they were not suffered to continue by reason of death:
7:23|WYC|And [soothly] the others were made many priests, therefore for they were forbidden by death to dwell still [for that they were forbidden by death to dwell];
7:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那些為祭司的，人數眾多，是因為有死攔阻，不能長久；
7:24|ASV|but he, because he abideth for ever, hath his priesthood unchangeable.
7:24|Darby|but he, because of his continuing for ever, has the  priesthood unchangeable.
7:24|KJV|But this man, because he continueth ever, hath an unchangeable priesthood.
7:24<version name="WYC">but this <i>man</i>, for he dwelleth without end [for that he dwelleth into without end], hath an everlasting priesthood.</version>
7:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但耶穌既是永遠長存的，祂就有不能更換的祭司職分。
7:25|ASV|Wherefore also he is able to save to the uttermost them that draw near unto God through him, seeing he ever liveth to make intercession for them.
7:25|Darby|Whence also he is able to save completely those who  approach by him to God, always living to intercede for them.
7:25|KJV|Wherefore he is able also to save them to the uttermost that come unto God by him, seeing he ever liveth to make intercession for them.
7:25|WYC|Wherefore also he may save without end, coming nigh by himself to God, and evermore liveth to pray for us. [Wherefore and he may save into without end, coming nigh by himself to God, evermore living to pray for us.]
7:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，那藉著祂來到神面前的人，祂都能拯救到底；因為祂是長遠活著，為他們代求。
7:26|ASV|For such a high priest became us, holy, guileless, undefiled, separated from sinners, and made higher than the heavens;
7:26|Darby|For such a high priest became us, holy, harmless,  undefiled, separated from sinners, and become higher than the  heavens:
7:26|KJV|For such an high priest became us, who is holy, harmless, undefiled, separate from sinners, and made higher than the heavens;
7:26<version name="WYC">For it beseemed that such a man were a bishop to us, holy, innocent, undefouled, clean, separated from sinful men, and made higher than heavens; <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23108a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
7:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|像這樣聖而無邪惡、無玷污、與罪人分別，並且高過諸天的大祭司，原是與我們合宜的；
7:27|ASV|who needeth not daily, like those high priests, to offer up sacrifices, first for his own sins, and then for the sins of the people: for this he did once for all, when he offered up himself.
7:27|Darby|who has not day by day need, as the high priests, first to  offer up sacrifices for his own sins, then [for] those of the  people; for this he did once for all [in] having offered up  himself.
7:27|KJV|Who needeth not daily, as those high priests, to offer up sacrifice, first for his own sins, and then for the people's: for this he did once, when he offered up himself.
7:27|WYC|which hath not need each day, as priests, first for his own guilts to offer sacrifices, and afterward for the people; for he did this thing in offering himself once [soothly he did this thing, once offering himself].
7:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂不像那些大祭司，每天必須先為自己的罪，再為百姓的罪獻上祭物，因為祂獻上自己，就把這事一次永遠的作成了。
7:28<version name="ASV">For the law appointeth men high priests, having infirmity; but the word of the oath, which was after the law, appointeth a Son, perfected for evermore. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:28<version name="Darby">For the law constitutes men high priests, having infirmity;  but the word of the swearing of the oath which [is] after the  law, a Son perfected for ever. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:28<version name="KJV">For the law maketh men high priests which have infirmity; but the word of the oath, which was since the law, maketh the Son, who is consecrated for evermore.</p><p /><br /></version>
7:28<version name="WYC">And the law ordained men priests having frailty [having sickness, <i>or frailty</i>]; but the word of swearing, which is after the law, <i>ordained</i> the Son perfect without end [<i>ordained</i> the Son perfect into without end].</version>
7:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|律法本是立軟弱的人為大祭司，但在律法以後所起誓的話，卻是立兒子為大祭司，乃是成全直到永遠的。
8:1|ASV|Now in the things which we are saying the chief point is this: We have such a high priest, who sat down on the right hand of the throne of the Majesty in the heavens,
8:1|Darby|Now a summary of the things of which we are speaking [is],  We have such a one high priest who has sat down on [the] right  hand of the throne of the greatness in the heavens;
8:1|KJV|Now of the things which we have spoken this is the sum: We have such an high priest, who is set on the right hand of the throne of the Majesty in the heavens;
8:1|WYC|But a recapitulation on those things that be said.  We have such a bishop, that sat on the right half of the seat of greatness in heavens,
8:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們所講之事的要點，就是我們有這樣的大祭司，祂已經坐在諸天之上至尊至大者寶座的右邊，
8:2|ASV|a minister of the sanctuary, and of the true tabernacle, which the Lord pitched, not man.
8:2|Darby|minister of the holy places and of the true tabernacle,  which the Lord has pitched, [and] not man.
8:2|KJV|A minister of the sanctuary, and of the true tabernacle, which the Lord pitched, and not man.
8:2|WYC|the minister of saints, and of the very tabernacle, that God made [that God set], and not man.
8:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|作了聖所，就是真帳幕的執事；這帳幕是主所支的，不是人所支的。
8:3|ASV|For every high priest is appointed to offer both gifts and sacrifices: wherefore it is necessary that this high priest also have somewhat to offer.
8:3|Darby|For every high priest is constituted for the offering both  of gifts and sacrifices; whence it is needful that this one  also should have something which he may offer.
8:3|KJV|For every high priest is ordained to offer gifts and sacrifices: wherefore it is of necessity that this man have somewhat also to offer.
8:3<version name="WYC">For each bishop is ordained to offer gifts and sacrifices; wherefore it is need, that also this <i>bishop</i> have something that he shall offer [wherefore it is need, and this <i>man</i>, for to have something that he shall offer].</version>
8:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡大祭司都是為獻禮物和祭物設立的，所以這一位也必須有所獻的。
8:4|ASV|Now if he were on earth, he would not be a priest at all, seeing there are those who offer the gifts according to the law;
8:4|Darby|If then indeed he were upon earth, he would not even be a  priest, there being those who offer the gifts according to the  law,
8:4|KJV|For if he were on earth, he should not be a priest, seeing that there are priests that offer gifts according to the law:
8:4|WYC|Therefore if he were on earth, he were no priest, when there were that should offer gifts by the law, [Therefore if he were on earth, he were not priest, when there were that should offer gifts after the law,]
8:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此祂若在地上，必不得作祭司，因為已經有照律法獻禮物的祭司；
8:5|ASV|who serve that which is a copy and shadow of the heavenly things, even as Moses is warned of God when he is about to make the tabernacle: for, See, saith he, that thou make all things according to the pattern that was showed thee in the mount.
8:5|Darby|(who serve the representation and shadow of heavenly things,  according as Moses was oracularly told [when] about to make the  tabernacle; for See, saith He, that thou make all things  according to the pattern which has been shewn to thee in the  mountain.)
8:5|KJV|Who serve unto the example and shadow of heavenly things, as Moses was admonished of God when he was about to make the tabernacle: for, See, saith he, that thou make all things according to the pattern shewed to thee in the mount.
8:5<version name="WYC">which serve to the exemplar and shadow of heavenly things.  As it was answered to Moses, when he should end the tabernacle, See, he said, make thou all things by the exemplar, that is showed to thee in the mount. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23115a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
8:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們的事奉，乃是天上事物的樣本和影兒，正如摩西將要完成帳幕的時候，蒙神指示他說，“你要謹慎，照著在山上所指示你的模型，作各樣的物件。”
8:6|ASV|But now hath he obtained a ministry the more excellent, by so much as he is also the mediator of a better covenant, which hath been enacted upon better promises.
8:6|Darby|But now he has got a more excellent ministry, by so much as  he is mediator of a better covenant, which is established on  the footing of better promises.
8:6|KJV|But now hath he obtained a more excellent ministry, by how much also he is the mediator of a better covenant, which was established upon better promises.
8:6|WYC|But now he hath gotten a better ministry, by so much as he is a mediator of a better testament [by how much and he is a mediator of a better testament], which is confirmed with better promises.
8:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但如今耶穌已經得著更超特的職任，正如祂也是更美之約的中保；這約是憑更美的應許立定為法的。
8:7|ASV|For if that first covenant had been faultless, then would no place have been sought for a second.
8:7|Darby|For if that first was faultless, place had not been sought  for a second.
8:7|KJV|For if that first covenant had been faultless, then should no place have been sought for the second.
8:7|WYC|For if that first had lacked blame [For if that first had been voided from blame], the place of the second should not have been sought.
8:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|原來那第一約若沒有瑕疵，就沒有尋求第二約的必要了。
8:8|ASV|For finding fault with them, he saith, Behold, the days come, saith the Lord, That I will make a new covenant with the house of Israel and with the house of Judah;
8:8|Darby|For finding fault, he says to them, Behold, days come, saith  the Lord, and I will consummate a new covenant as regards the  house of Israel, and as regards the house of Juda;
8:8|KJV|For finding fault with them, he saith, Behold, the days come, saith the Lord, when I will make a new covenant with the house of Israel and with the house of Judah:
8:8|WYC|For he reproving them saith [Forsooth reproving them he saith], Lo! days come, saith the Lord, and I shall make perfect a new testament on the house of Israel, and on the house of Juda;
8:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但神既找出祂百姓的瑕疵，就說，“看哪，日子將到，主說，我要與以色列家和猶大家，立定新約，
8:9|ASV|Not according to the covenant that I made with their fathers In the day that I took them by the hand to lead them forth out of the land of Egypt; For they continued not in my covenant, And I regarded them not, saith the Lord.
8:9|Darby|not according to the covenant which I made to their fathers  in [the] day of my taking their hand to lead them out of the  land of Egypt; because *they* did not continue in my covenant,  and *I* did not regard them, saith [the] Lord.
8:9|KJV|Not according to the covenant that I made with their fathers in the day when I took them by the hand to lead them out of the land of Egypt; because they continued not in my covenant, and I regarded them not, saith the Lord.
8:9|WYC|not like the testament [not after the testament] that I made to their fathers, in the day in which I caught their hand, that I should lead them out of the land of Egypt; for they dwelled not perfectly in my testament, and I have despised them, saith the Lord.
8:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不是照著我拉他們祖宗的手，領他們出埃及地的日子，與他們所立的約；因為他們沒有恆守我的約，我也不理他們；這是主說的。
8:10|ASV|For this is the covenant that I will make with the house of Israel After those days, saith the Lord; I will put my laws into their mind, And on their heart also will I write them: And I will be to them a God, And they shall be to me a people:
8:10|Darby|Because this [is] the covenant that I will covenant to the  house of Israel after those days, saith the Lord: Giving my  laws into their mind, I will write them also upon their hearts;  and I will be to them for God, and *they* shall be to me for  people.
8:10|KJV|For this is the covenant that I will make with the house of Israel after those days, saith the Lord; I will put my laws into their mind, and write them in their hearts: and I will be to them a God, and they shall be to me a people:
8:10<version name="WYC">But this is the testament, which I shall assign to the house of Israel after those days <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23120b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup>, saith the Lord, in giving my laws into the souls of them, and into the hearts of them I shall above write them; and I shall be to them into a God [and I shall be to them into God], and they shall be to me into a people.</version>
8:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主又說，因為這是那些日子以後，我要與以色列家所立的約：我要將我的律法賜在他們心思裡，並且將這些律法寫在他們心上；我要作他們的神，他們要作我的子民。
8:11|ASV|And they shall not teach every man his fellow-citizen, And every man his brother, saying, Know the Lord: For all shall know me, From the least to the greatest of them.
8:11|Darby|And they shall not teach each his fellow-citizen, and each  his brother, saying, Know the Lord; because all shall know me  in themselves, from [the] little one [among them] unto [the]  great among them.
8:11|KJV|And they shall not teach every man his neighbour, and every man his brother, saying, Know the Lord: for all shall know me, from the least to the greatest.
8:11|WYC|And each man shall not teach his neighbour, and each man his brother, saying, Know thou the Lord; for all men shall know me, from the least to the more of them [from the less unto the more of them].
8:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們各人絕不用教導自己同國之民，各人也絕不用教導自己的弟兄，說，你該認識主；因為他們從最小的到至大的，都必認識我；
8:12|ASV|For I will be merciful to their iniquities, And their sins will I remember no more.
8:12|Darby|Because I will be merciful to their unrighteousnesses, and  their sins and their lawlessnesses I will never remember any  more.
8:12|KJV|For I will be merciful to their unrighteousness, and their sins and their iniquities will I remember no more.
8:12|WYC|For I shall be merciful to the wickedness of them, and now I shall not bethink on the sins of them.
8:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我要寬恕他們的不義，絕不再記念他們的罪。”
8:13<version name="ASV">In that he saith, A new covenant he hath made the first old. But that which is becoming old and waxeth aged is nigh unto vanishing away. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:13<version name="Darby">In that he says New, he has made the first old; but that  which grows old and aged [is] near disappearing. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:13<version name="KJV">In that he saith, A new covenant, he hath made the first old. Now that which decayeth and waxeth old is ready to vanish away.</p><p /><br /></version>
8:13|WYC|But in saying a new, the former waxed old; and that that is of many days, and waxeth old, is nigh the death [is nigh death].
8:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|既說新約，就以第一約為舊了。但那漸漸陳舊並衰老的，就快要消逝了。
9:1|ASV|Now even a first covenant had ordinances of divine service, and its sanctuary, a sanctuary of this world.
9:1|Darby|The first therefore also indeed had ordinances of service,  and the sanctuary, a worldly one.
9:1|KJV|Then verily the first covenant had also ordinances of divine service, and a worldly sanctuary.
9:1<version name="WYC">[Soothly] And the former <i>testament</i> had justifyings of worship, and holy thing during for a time [and holy thing worldly, <i>that is, during for a time</i>].</version>
9:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，第一約的確有敬拜的章則，和屬世界的聖幕。
9:2|ASV|For there was a tabernacle prepared, the first, wherein were the candlestick, and the table, and the showbread; which is called the Holy place.
9:2|Darby|For a tabernacle was set up; the first, in which [were] both  the candlestick and the table and the exposition of the loaves,  which is called Holy;
9:2|KJV|For there was a tabernacle made; the first, wherein was the candlestick, and the table, and the shewbread; which is called the sanctuary.
9:2|WYC|For the tabernacle was made first, in which were candlesticks, and [a] board, and setting forth of loaves [and putting forth of loaves], which is said holy.
9:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為有豫備好的帳幕，頭一層叫作聖所，裡面有燈臺、桌子和陳設餅；
9:3|ASV|And after the second veil, the tabernacle which is called the Holy of holies;
9:3|Darby|but after the second veil a tabernacle which is called Holy  of holies,
9:3|KJV|And after the second veil, the tabernacle which is called the Holiest of all;
9:3<version name="WYC">And after the veil, the second tabernacle, that is said sanctum sanctorum, <i>that is, holy of holy things</i>;</version>
9:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|第二幔子後，還有一層帳幕，叫作至聖所，
9:4|ASV|having a golden altar of incense, and the ark of the covenant overlaid round about with gold, wherein was a golden pot holding the manna, and Aaron's rod that budded, and the tables of the covenant;
9:4|Darby|having a golden censer, and the ark of the covenant, covered  round in every part with gold, in which [were] the golden pot  that had the manna, and the rod of Aaron that had sprouted, and  the tables of the covenant;
9:4|KJV|Which had the golden censer, and the ark of the covenant overlaid round about with gold, wherein was the golden pot that had manna, and Aaron's rod that budded, and the tables of the covenant;
9:4<version name="WYC">having a golden censer, and the ark of the testament, covered about on each side with gold, in which <i>was</i> a pot of gold having manna, and the rod of Aaron that flowered [and the rod of Aaron that flourished], and the tables of the testament;</version>
9:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有金香壇，和四面包金的約櫃，櫃裡有盛嗎哪的金罐、和亞倫發過芽的杖、並兩塊約版；
9:5|ASV|and above it cherubim of glory overshadowing the mercy-seat; of which things we cannot now speak severally.
9:5|Darby|and above over it the cherubim of glory shadowing the  mercy-seat; concerning which it is not now [the time] to speak  in detail.
9:5|KJV|And over it the cherubims of glory shadowing the mercyseat; of which we cannot now speak particularly.
9:5<version name="WYC">on which things were cherubims of glory, overshadowing the propitiatory [upon which things were cherubims of glory, shadowing the propitiatory, <i>or</i> <i>mercyable place</i>]; of which things it is not now to say by all.</version>
9:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|櫃上面有榮耀的基路伯覆蔭著平息處；關於這幾件，現在不能一一細說。
9:6|ASV|Now these things having been thus prepared, the priests go in continually into the first tabernacle, accomplishing the services;
9:6|Darby|Now these things being thus ordered, into the first  tabernacle the priests enter at all times, accomplishing the  services;
9:6|KJV|Now when these things were thus ordained, the priests went always into the first tabernacle, accomplishing the service of God.
9:6|WYC|But when these were made thus together, priests entered evermore in the former tabernacle, doing the offices of sacrifices [ending the offices of sacraments];
9:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些物件都這樣豫備好了，眾祭司就常常進入頭一層帳幕，完成敬拜；
9:7|ASV|but into the second the high priest alone, once in the year, not without blood, which he offereth for himself, and for the errors of the people:
9:7|Darby|but into the second, the high priest only, once a year, not  without blood, which he offers for himself and for the errors  of the people:
9:7|KJV|But into the second went the high priest alone once every year, not without blood, which he offered for himself, and for the errors of the people:
9:7<version name="WYC">but in the second <i>tabernacle</i>, the bishop [alone] <i>entered</i> once in the year, not without blood, which he offered for his ignorance and the people's.</version>
9:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於第二層帳幕，只有大祭司一年一次獨自進去，沒有不帶著血，為自己和百姓誤犯的罪獻上的；
9:8|ASV|the Holy Spirit this signifying, that the way into the holy place hath not yet been made manifest, while the first tabernacle is yet standing;
9:8|Darby|the Holy Spirit shewing this, that the way of the [holy of]  holies has not yet been made manifest while as yet the first  tabernacle has [its] standing;
9:8|KJV|The Holy Ghost this signifying, that the way into the holiest of all was not yet made manifest, while as the first tabernacle was yet standing:
9:8|WYC|For the Holy Ghost signified this thing [The Holy Ghost signifying this thing], that not yet the way of saints was opened, while the former tabernacle had state.
9:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|聖靈如此指明，當頭一層帳幕仍然存立的時候，至聖所的路還未顯明；
9:9|ASV|which is a figure for the time present; according to which are offered both gifts and sacrifices that cannot, as touching the conscience, make the worshipper perfect,
9:9|Darby|the which [is] an image for the present time, according to  which both gifts and sacrifices, unable to perfect as to  conscience him that worshipped, are offered,
9:9|KJV|Which was a figure for the time then present, in which were offered both gifts and sacrifices, that could not make him that did the service perfect, as pertaining to the conscience;
9:9|WYC|Which parable is of this present time, by which also gifts and sacrifices be offered, which be not able to make [which may not make] a man serving perfect by conscience,
9:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那頭一層帳幕作現今時期的一個象徵，按這象徵所獻的禮物和祭物，就著良心說，都不能叫敬拜的人得以完全；
9:10|ASV|being only (with meats and drinks and divers washings) carnal ordinances, imposed until a time of reformation.
9:10|Darby|[consisting] only of meats and drinks and divers washings,  ordinances of flesh, imposed until [the] time of setting things  right.
9:10|KJV|Which stood only in meats and drinks, and divers washings, and carnal ordinances, imposed on them until the time of reformation.
9:10|WYC|only in meats, and drinks, and diverse washings, and rightwisenesses of flesh, that were set to the time of correction [put unto the time of correction].
9:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些不過是在於飲食和各樣的浸洗，都是屬肉體的章則，制定到更正的時期。
9:11|ASV|But Christ having come a high priest of the good things to come, through the greater and more perfect tabernacle, not made with hands, that is to say, not of this creation,
9:11|Darby|But Christ being come high priest of the good things to  come, by the better and more perfect tabernacle not made with  hand, (that is, not of this creation,)
9:11|KJV|But Christ being come an high priest of good things to come, by a greater and more perfect tabernacle, not made with hands, that is to say, not of this building;
9:11<version name="WYC">But Christ being a bishop of goods to coming, <i>entered</i> by a larger and perfecter tabernacle [Forsooth Christ being a bishop of goods to come, by a larger and perfecter tabernacle], not made by hand, that is to say, not of this making,</version>
9:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但基督已經來到，作了那已經實現之美事的大祭司，經過那更大、更全備的帳幕，不是人手所造的，就是不屬這受造世界的；
9:12|ASV|nor yet through the blood of goats and calves, but through his own blood, entered in once for all into the holy place, having obtained eternal redemption.
9:12|Darby|nor by blood of goats and calves, but by his own blood, has  entered in once for all into the [holy of] holies, having found  an eternal redemption.
9:12|KJV|Neither by the blood of goats and calves, but by his own blood he entered in once into the holy place, having obtained eternal redemption for us.
9:12|WYC|neither by blood of goat bucks, or of calves, but by his own blood, entered once into the holy things, that were found by an everlasting redemption. [neither by blood of goat bucks, or calves, but by his own blood, entered once into holy things, when everlasting redemption was found.]
9:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且不是藉著山羊和牛犢的血，乃是藉著祂自己的血，一次永遠的進入至聖所，便得到了永遠的救贖。
9:13|ASV|For if the blood of goats and bulls, and the ashes of a heifer sprinkling them that have been defiled, sanctify unto the cleanness of the flesh:
9:13|Darby|For if the blood of goats and bulls, and a heifer's ashes  sprinkling the defiled, sanctifies for the purity of the flesh,
9:13|KJV|For if the blood of bulls and of goats, and the ashes of an heifer sprinkling the unclean, sanctifieth to the purifying of the flesh:
9:13|WYC|For if the blood of goat bucks, and of bulls, and the ashes of a cow calf sprinkled, halloweth unclean men to the cleansing of flesh,
9:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若山羊和公牛的血，並母牛犢的灰，灑在污穢的人身上，尚且使人聖別，以致人的肉身得著潔淨，
9:14|ASV|how much more shall the blood of Christ, who through the eternal Spirit offered himself without blemish unto God, cleanse your conscience from dead works to serve the living God?
9:14|Darby|how much rather shall the blood of the Christ, who by the  eternal Spirit offered himself spotless to God, purify your  conscience from dead works to worship [the] living God?
9:14|KJV|How much more shall the blood of Christ, who through the eternal Spirit offered himself without spot to God, purge your conscience from dead works to serve the living God?
9:14|WYC|how much more the blood of Christ, which by the Holy Ghost offered himself unwemmed to God, shall cleanse our conscience from dead works, to serve God that liveth [for to serve to living God]?
9:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|何況基督藉著永遠的靈，將自己無瑕無疵的獻給神，祂的血豈不更潔淨我們的良心，使其脫離死行，叫我們事奉活神麼？
9:15|ASV|And for this cause he is the mediator of a new covenant, that a death having taken place for the redemption of the transgressions that were under the first covenant, they that have been called may receive the promise of the eternal inheritance.
9:15|Darby|And for this reason he is mediator of a new covenant, so  that, death having taken place for redemption of the  transgressions under the first covenant, the called might  receive the promise of the eternal inheritance.
9:15|KJV|And for this cause he is the mediator of the new testament, that by means of death, for the redemption of the transgressions that were under the first testament, they which are called might receive the promise of eternal inheritance.
9:15|WYC|And therefore he is a mediator of the new testament, that by death falling betwixt [that death falling between], into redemption of the trespassings that were under the former testament, they that be called take the promise of everlasting heritage.
9:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，祂作了新約的中保，既然受死，贖了人在第一約之下的過犯，便叫蒙召之人得著所應許永遠的產業。
9:16|ASV|For where a testament is, there must of necessity be the death of him that made it.
9:16|Darby|(For where [there is] a testament, the death of the  testator must needs come in.
9:16|KJV|For where a testament is, there must also of necessity be the death of the testator.
9:16|WYC|For where a testament is, it is need, that the death of the testament maker come betwixt [come between].
9:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡有遺命，立遺命者的死必須證實出來；
9:17|ASV|For a testament is of force where there hath been death: for it doth never avail while he that made it liveth.
9:17|Darby|For a testament [is] of force when men are dead, since it  is in no way of force while the testator is alive.)
9:17|KJV|For a testament is of force after men are dead: otherwise it is of no strength at all while the testator liveth.
9:17<version name="WYC">For a testament is confirmed in dead <i>men</i>; else it is not worth [else it is (of) no worth], while he liveth, that made the testament.</version>
9:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為留遺命的人死了，遺命纔得確定；立遺命的人還活著的時候，遺命是沒有效力的。
9:18|ASV|Wherefore even the first  covenant hath not been dedicated without blood.
9:18|Darby|Whence neither the first was inaugurated without blood.
9:18|KJV|Whereupon neither the first testament was dedicated without blood.
9:18|WYC|Wherefore neither the first testament was hallowed without blood.
9:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以第一約也不是不用血創立的。
9:19|ASV|For when every commandment had been spoken by Moses unto all the people according to the law, he took the blood of the calves and the goats, with water and scarlet wool and hyssop, and sprinkled both the book itself and all the people,
9:19|Darby|For every commandment having been spoken according to [the]  law by Moses to all the people; having taken the blood of  calves and goats, with water and scarlet wool and hyssop, he  sprinkled both the book itself and all the people,
9:19|KJV|For when Moses had spoken every precept to all the people according to the law, he took the blood of calves and of goats, with water, and scarlet wool, and hyssop, and sprinkled both the book, and all the people,
9:19|WYC|For when each commandment of the law was read of Moses to all the people, he took the blood of calves, and of bucks of goats, with water, and red wool, and hyssop, and besprinkled [sprinkled] both that book and all the people,
9:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為各條誡命既由摩西照著律法，向眾百姓講過了，他就拿牛犢和山羊的血，用水和朱紅色絨並牛膝草，灑在那約書上，並眾百姓身上，說，
9:20|ASV|saying, This is the blood of the covenant which God commanded to you-ward.
9:20|Darby|saying, This [is] the blood of the covenant which God has  enjoined to you.
9:20|KJV|Saying, This is the blood of the testament which God hath enjoined unto you.
9:20|WYC|and said [saying], This is the blood of the testament, that God commanded to you.
9:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|“這就是神與你們所立之約的血。”
9:21|ASV|Moreover the tabernacle and all the vessels of the ministry he sprinkled in like manner with the blood.
9:21|Darby|And the tabernacle too and all the vessels of service he  sprinkled in like manner with blood;
9:21|KJV|Moreover he sprinkled with blood both the tabernacle, and all the vessels of the ministry.
9:21<version name="WYC">Also he sprinkled with blood the tabernacle, and all the vessels of the service in like manner [and all the vessels of ministry, <i>or service</i>, in like manner].</version>
9:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他又照樣把血灑在帳幕和一切敬拜用的器皿上。
9:22|ASV|And according to the law, I may almost say, all things are cleansed with blood, and apart from shedding of blood there is no remission.
9:22|Darby|and almost all things are purified with blood according to  the law, and without blood-shedding there is no remission.
9:22|KJV|And almost all things are by the law purged with blood; and without shedding of blood is no remission.
9:22|WYC|And almost all things be cleansed in blood by the law; and without shedding of blood remission of sins is not made.
9:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|按著律法，凡物差不多都是用血潔淨的，沒有流血，就沒有赦罪。
9:23|ASV|It was necessary therefore that the copies of the things in the heavens should be cleansed with these; but the heavenly things themselves with better sacrifices than these.
9:23|Darby|[It was] necessary then that the figurative representations  of the things in the heavens should be purified with these; but  the heavenly things themselves with sacrifices better than  these.
9:23|KJV|It was therefore necessary that the patterns of things in the heavens should be purified with these; but the heavenly things themselves with better sacrifices than these.
9:23|WYC|Therefore it is need, that the exemplars [that the samplers] of heavenly things be cleansed with these things; but those heavenly things with better sacrifices than these.
9:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，諸天上之物的樣本，必須用這些祭物去潔淨；但那天上之物的本身，必須用比這些更美的祭物去潔淨。
9:24|ASV|For Christ entered not into a holy place made with hands, like in pattern to the true; but into heaven itself, now to appear before the face of God for us:
9:24|Darby|For the Christ is not entered into holy places made with  hand, figures of the true, but into heaven itself, now to  appear before the face of God for us:
9:24|KJV|For Christ is not entered into the holy places made with hands, which are the figures of the true; but into heaven itself, now to appear in the presence of God for us:
9:24<version name="WYC">For Jesus entered not into holy things made by hands, <i>that be</i> [the] exemplars of very things, but into heaven itself, that he appear now to the face of God for us; <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23147a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
9:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為基督並不是進入人手所造的聖所，那不過是真聖所的複本，乃是進入了天的本身，如今為我們顯在神面前；
9:25|ASV|nor yet that he should offer himself often, as the high priest entereth into the holy place year by year with blood not his own;
9:25|Darby|nor in order that he should offer himself often, as the  high priest enters into the holy places every year with blood  not his own;
9:25|KJV|Nor yet that he should offer himself often, as the high priest entereth into the holy place every year with blood of others;
9:25|WYC|neither [nor] that he offer himself oft, as the bishop entered into holy things by all years in alien blood,
9:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂也不是多次將自己獻上，像那大祭司每年帶著牛羊的血進入至聖所；
9:26|ASV|else must he often have suffered since the foundation of the world: but now once at the end of the ages hath he been manifested to put away sin by the sacrifice of himself.
9:26|Darby|since he had [then] been obliged often to suffer from the  foundation of the world. But now once in the consummation of  the ages he has been manifested for [the] putting away of sin  by his sacrifice.
9:26|KJV|For then must he often have suffered since the foundation of the world: but now once in the end of the world hath he appeared to put away sin by the sacrifice of himself.
9:26|WYC|else it behooved him to suffer oft [else it behooved him oft to suffer] from the beginning of the world; but now once in the ending of the worlds, to the destruction of sin by his sacrifice he appeared.
9:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|如果這樣，從創世以來，祂就必須多次受苦了；但如今祂在諸世代的終結顯明了一次，好藉著獻上自己為祭，把罪除掉。
9:27|ASV|And inasmuch as it is appointed unto men once to die, and after this cometh judgment;
9:27|Darby|And forasmuch as it is the portion of men once to die, and  after this judgment;
9:27|KJV|And as it is appointed unto men once to die, but after this the judgment:
9:27<version name="WYC">And as it is ordained to men, once to die, but after this <i>is</i> the doom,</version>
9:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|按著定命，人人都有一死，死後且有審判；
9:28<version name="ASV">so Christ also, having been once offered to bear the sins of many, shall appear a second time, apart from sin, to them that wait for him, unto salvation. </p><p /><br /></version>
9:28<version name="Darby">thus the Christ also, having been once offered to bear the  sins of many, shall appear to those that look for him the  second time without sin for salvation. </p><p /><br /></version>
9:28<version name="KJV">So Christ was once offered to bear the sins of many; and unto them that look for him shall he appear the second time without sin unto salvation.</p><p /><br /></version>
9:28<version name="WYC">so Christ was offered once, to void the sins of many men [for to void, <i>or do away</i>, the sins of many men]; the second <i>time</i> he shall appear without sin to men that abide him into health.</version>
9:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|基督也是這樣，既一次被獻，擔當了多人的罪，將來還要向那熱切等待祂的人第二次顯現，並與罪無關，乃為拯救他們。
10:1|ASV|For the law having a shadow of the good things to come, not the very image of the things, can never with the same sacrifices year by year, which they offer continually, make perfect them that draw nigh.
10:1|Darby|For the law, having a shadow of the coming good things, not  the image itself of the things, can never, by the same  sacrifices which they offer continually yearly, perfect those  who approach.
10:1|KJV|For the law having a shadow of good things to come, and not the very image of the things, can never with those sacrifices which they offered year by year continually make the comers thereunto perfect.
10:1|WYC|For the law having a shadow of good things to come, not that image of things, may never make men approaching perfect by those same sacrifices, which they offer without ceasing by all years; [Forsooth the law having shadow of goods to come, not that image of things, by all years by those same hosts, which they offer without ceasing, never may make men coming nigh perfect;]
10:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|律法有要來美事的影兒，沒有本物的形像，總不能藉著每年不斷獻上的同樣祭物，叫那些進前來的人得到完全。
10:2|ASV|Else would they not have ceased to be offered? because the worshippers, having been once cleansed, would have had no more consciousness of sins.
10:2|Darby|Since, would they not indeed have ceased being offered, on  account of the worshippers once purged having no longer any  conscience of sins?
10:2|KJV|For then would they not have ceased to be offered? because that the worshippers once purged should have had no more conscience of sins.
10:2|WYC|else they should have ceased to be offered, for as much as the worshippers cleansed once, had not furthermore conscience of sin [had no conscience of sin furthermore].
10:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不然，敬拜的人既一次得了潔淨，良心不再覺得有罪，獻祭的事豈不就已停止了麼？
10:3|ASV|But in those sacrifices there is a remembrance made of sins year by year.
10:3|Darby|But in these [there is] a calling to mind of sins yearly.
10:3|KJV|But in those sacrifices there is a remembrance again made of sins every year.
10:3<version name="WYC">But in them [<i>by oft offering</i>] mind of sins is made by all years.</version>
10:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但那些祭物使人每年想起罪來；
10:4|ASV|For it is impossible that the blood of bulls and goats should take away sins.
10:4|Darby|For blood of bulls and goats [is] incapable of taking away  sins.
10:4|KJV|For it is not possible that the blood of bulls and of goats should take away sins.
10:4|WYC|For it is impossible that sins be done away by blood of bulls, and of bucks of goats.
10:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為公牛和山羊的血是不能除罪的。
10:5|ASV|Wherefore when he cometh into the world, he saith, Sacrifice and offering thou wouldest not, But a body didst thou prepare for me;
10:5|Darby|Wherefore coming into the world he says, Sacrifice and  offering thou willedst not; but thou hast prepared me a body.
10:5|KJV|Wherefore when he cometh into the world, he saith, Sacrifice and offering thou wouldest not, but a body hast thou prepared me:
10:5|WYC|Therefore he entering into the world, saith, Thou wouldest not sacrifice and offering; but thou hast shaped a body to me;
10:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以基督到世上來的時候，就說，“祭物和供物是你不願要的，你卻為我豫備了身體；
10:6|ASV|In whole burnt offerings and  sacrifices for sin thou hadst no pleasure:
10:6|Darby|Thou tookest no pleasure in burnt-offerings and sacrifices  for sin.
10:6|KJV|In burnt offerings and sacrifices for sin thou hast had no pleasure.
10:6|WYC|[and] burnt sacrifices also for sin pleased not to thee.
10:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|燔祭和贖罪祭是你不喜悅的；
10:7|ASV|Then said I, Lo, I am come (In the roll of the book it is written of me) To do thy will, O God.
10:7|Darby|Then I said, Lo, I come (in [the] roll of the book it is  written of me) to do, O God, thy will.
10:7|KJV|Then said I, Lo, I come (in the volume of the book it is written of me,) to do thy will, O God.
10:7|WYC|Then I said, Lo! I come; in the beginning of the book it is written of me, that I do thy will, [thou] God.
10:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是我說，看哪，我來了，神阿，是要實行你的旨意。（我的事經卷上已經記載了。）”
10:8|ASV|Saying above, Sacrifices and offerings and whole burnt offerings and sacrifices for sin thou wouldest not, neither hadst pleasure therein (the which are offered according to the law),
10:8|Darby|Above, saying Sacrifices and offerings and burnt-offerings  and sacrifices for sin thou willedst not, neither tookest  pleasure in (which are offered according to the law);
10:8|KJV|Above when he said, Sacrifice and offering and burnt offerings and offering for sin thou wouldest not, neither hadst pleasure therein; which are offered by the law;
10:8<version name="WYC">He saying before, That thou wouldest not sacrifices, and offerings, and burnt sacrifices for sin [He above saying, <i>or before</i>, For thou wouldest not hosts, and offerings, and burnt sacrifices, for sin], nor those things be pleasant to thee, which be offered by the law,</version>
10:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以上說，“祭物和供物，燔祭和贖罪祭，是你不願要的，也是你不喜悅的。”（這些都是按著律法獻的。）
10:9|ASV|then hath he said, Lo, I am come to do thy will. He taketh away the first, that he may establish the second.
10:9|Darby|then he said, Lo, I come to do thy will. He takes away the  first that he may establish the second;
10:9|KJV|Then said he, Lo, I come to do thy will, O God. He taketh away the first, that he may establish the second.
10:9|WYC|then I said, Lo! I come, that I do thy will, God.  He doeth away the first, that he make steadfast the second.
10:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|後來又說，“看哪，我來了，是要實行你的旨意。”可見祂除去那先有的，為要立定那後來的；
10:10|ASV|By which will we have been sanctified through the offering of the body of Jesus Christ once for all.
10:10|Darby|by which will we have been sanctified through the offering  of the body of Jesus Christ once for all.
10:10|KJV|By the which will we are sanctified through the offering of the body of Jesus Christ once for all.
10:10|WYC|In which will we be hallowed by the offering of the body of Christ Jesus once.
10:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們憑這旨意，藉耶穌基督一次永遠的獻上身體，就得以聖別。
10:11|ASV|And every priest indeed standeth day by day ministering and offering oftentimes the same sacrifices, the which can never take away sins:
10:11|Darby|And every priest stands daily ministering, and offering  often the same sacrifices, which can never take away sins.
10:11|KJV|And every priest standeth daily ministering and offering oftentimes the same sacrifices, which can never take away sins:
10:11<version name="WYC">And each priest is ready ministering each day, and oft times offering the same sacrifices, which be never able to do away sins. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23162a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
10:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|再者，凡祭司都是天天站著供職，屢次獻上同樣永不能除罪的祭物。
10:12|ASV|but he, when he had offered one sacrifice for sins for ever, sat down on the right hand of God;
10:12|Darby|But *he*, having offered one sacrifice for sins, sat down  in perpetuity at [the] right hand of God,
10:12|KJV|But this man, after he had offered one sacrifice for sins for ever, sat down on the right hand of God;
10:12<version name="WYC">But this <i>man</i> offering one sacrifice for sins, for evermore sitteth in the right half of God the Father [for evermore sitteth on the right half of God the Father];</version>
10:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|惟獨這一位既為罪一次獻上祭物，就永久在神的右邊坐下了；
10:13|ASV|henceforth expecting till his enemies be made the footstool of his feet.
10:13|Darby|waiting from henceforth until his enemies be set [for the]  footstool of his feet.
10:13|KJV|From henceforth expecting till his enemies be made his footstool.
10:13|WYC|from thenceforth abiding, till his enemies be put a stool of his feet [till his enemies be put a stool under his feet].
10:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|從此等候祂的仇敵，放在祂的腳下作腳凳。
10:14|ASV|For by one offering he hath perfected for ever them that are sanctified.
10:14|Darby|For by one offering he has perfected in perpetuity the  sanctified.
10:14|KJV|For by one offering he hath perfected for ever them that are sanctified.
10:14|WYC|For by one offering he made perfect for ever hallowed men.
10:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為祂一次獻祭，便叫那些得以聖別的人永久完全。
10:15|ASV|And the Holy Spirit also beareth witness to us; for after he hath said,
10:15|Darby|And the Holy Spirit also bears us witness [of it]; for  after what was said:
10:15|KJV|Whereof the Holy Ghost also is a witness to us: for after that he had said before,
10:15|WYC|And the Holy Ghost witnesseth to us; for after that he said [forsooth afterward he said],
10:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|聖靈也對我們作見證，因為祂說過，
10:16|ASV|This is the covenant that I will make with them After those days, saith the Lord: I will put my laws on their heart, And upon their mind also will I write them; then saith he,
10:16|Darby|This [is] the covenant which I will establish towards them  after those days, saith [the] Lord: Giving my laws into their  hearts, I will write them also in their understandings;
10:16|KJV|This is the covenant that I will make with them after those days, saith the Lord, I will put my laws into their hearts, and in their minds will I write them;
10:16|WYC|This is the testament, which I shall witness to them after those days, the Lord saith [saith the Lord], in giving my laws in the hearts of them, and in the souls of them I shall above write them;
10:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|“主說，這是那些日子以後，我要與他們所立的約：我要將我的律法賜在他們心裡，並且將這些律法寫在他們心思裡。”
10:17|ASV|And their sins and their iniquities will I remember no more.
10:17|Darby|and their sins and their lawlessnesses I will never  remember any more.
10:17|KJV|And their sins and iniquities will I remember no more.
10:17|WYC|and now I shall no more think on the sins and the wickedness of them [and wickednesses of them].
10:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以後又說，“我絕不再記念他們的罪和不法。”
10:18|ASV|Now where remission of these is, there is no more offering for sin.
10:18|Darby|But where there [is] remission of these, [there is] no  longer a sacrifice for sin.
10:18|KJV|Now where remission of these is, there is no more offering for sin.
10:18<version name="WYC">And where remission of these is, now <i>is</i> there none offering for sin.</version>
10:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些罪既都蒙了赦免，就不用再為罪獻祭了。
10:19|ASV|Having therefore, brethren, boldness to enter into the holy place by the blood of Jesus,
10:19|Darby|Having therefore, brethren, boldness for entering into the  [holy of] holies by the blood of Jesus,
10:19|KJV|Having therefore, brethren, boldness to enter into the holiest by the blood of Jesus,
10:19|WYC|Therefore, brethren, having trust into the entering of holy things in the blood of Christ,
10:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，我們既因耶穌的血，得以坦然進入至聖所，
10:20|ASV|by the way which he dedicated for us, a new and living way, through the veil, that is to say, his flesh;
10:20|Darby|the new and living way which he has dedicated for us  through the veil, that is, his flesh,
10:20|KJV|By a new and living way, which he hath consecrated for us, through the veil, that is to say, his flesh;
10:20<version name="WYC">which [he] hallowed to us a new way, and living by the covering [by a veil, <i>or covering</i>], that is to say, his flesh,</version>
10:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|是藉著祂給我們開創了一條又新又活的路，從幔子經過，這幔子就是祂的肉體，
10:21|ASV|and having a great priest over the house of God;
10:21|Darby|and [having] a great priest over the house of God,
10:21|KJV|And having an high priest over the house of God;
10:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又有一位尊大的祭司治理神的家，
10:22|ASV|let us draw near with a true heart in fulness of faith, having our hearts sprinkled from an evil conscience: and having our body washed with pure water,
10:22|Darby|let us approach with a true heart, in full assurance of  faith, sprinkled as to our hearts from a wicked conscience, and  washed as to our body with pure water.
10:22|KJV|Let us draw near with a true heart in full assurance of faith, having our hearts sprinkled from an evil conscience, and our bodies washed with pure water.
10:22|WYC|approach we with very heart in the plenty of faith [nigh we with very heart in the plenty of faith]; and be our hearts sprinkled from an evil conscience, and our bodies washed with clean water,
10:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且在心一面，我們已經被基督的血灑過，脫開了邪惡的良心，在身體一面，也已經用清水洗淨了，就當存著真誠的心，以十分確信的信，前來進入至聖所；
10:23|ASV|let us hold fast the confession of our hope that it waver not; for he is faithful that promised:
10:23|Darby|Let us hold fast the confession of the hope unwavering,  (for he [is] faithful who has promised;)
10:23|KJV|Let us hold fast the profession of our faith without wavering; (for he is faithful that promised;)
10:23|WYC|and hold we the confession of our hope, bowing to no side [hold we the confession of our hope unbowing, unpliable]; for he is true that hath made the promise.
10:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又當堅守我們所承認的盼望，不至搖動，因為那應許我們的是信實的；
10:24|ASV|and let us consider one another to provoke unto love and good works;
10:24|Darby|and let us consider one another for provoking to love and  good works;
10:24|KJV|And let us consider one another to provoke unto love and to good works:
10:24|WYC|And behold we together in the stirring of charity and of good works;
10:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|且當彼此相顧，激發愛心，勉勵行善；
10:25|ASV|not forsaking our own assembling together, as the custom of some is, but exhorting one another; and so much the more, as ye see the day drawing nigh.
10:25|Darby|not forsaking the assembling of ourselves together, as the  custom [is] with some; but encouraging [one another], and by so  much the more as ye see the day drawing near.
10:25|KJV|Not forsaking the assembling of ourselves together, as the manner of some is; but exhorting one another: and so much the more, as ye see the day approaching.
10:25<version name="WYC">not forsaking our gathering together, as it is the custom to some men, but comforting [<i>them</i>], and by so much the more, by how much ye see the day approaching. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23175b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
10:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不可放棄我們自己的聚集，好像有些人習慣了一樣，倒要彼此勸勉；既看見那日子臨近，就更當如此。
10:26|ASV|For if we sin wilfully after that we have received the knowledge of the truth, there remaineth no more a sacrifice for sins,
10:26|Darby|For where we sin wilfully after receiving the knowledge of  the truth, there no longer remains any sacrifice for sins,
10:26|KJV|For if we sin wilfully after that we have received the knowledge of the truth, there remaineth no more sacrifice for sins,
10:26|WYC|For why now a sacrifice for sins is not left to us, that sin willfully, after that we have taken the knowing of truth. [Forsooth to us sinning willfully, after the knowing of truth taken, now an host for sins is not left.]
10:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們認識了真理之後，還故意犯罪，為著罪的牛羊祭物是不再有的了；
10:27|ASV|but a certain fearful expectation of judgment, and a fierceness of fire which shall devour the adversaries.
10:27|Darby|but a certain fearful expectation of judgment, and heat of  fire about to devour the adversaries.
10:27|KJV|But a certain fearful looking for of judgment and fiery indignation, which shall devour the adversaries.
10:27|WYC|For why some abiding of doom is dreadful, and the following of fire, which shall waste adversaries.
10:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|惟有恐懼等候審判、和那將要吞滅眾敵人的烈火。
10:28|ASV|A man that hath set at nought Moses law dieth without compassion on the word of two or three witnesses:
10:28|Darby|Any one that has disregarded Moses' law dies without mercy  on [the testimony of] two or three witnesses:
10:28|KJV|He that despised Moses' law died without mercy under two or three witnesses:
10:28|WYC|Who that breaketh Moses' law, dieth without any mercy, by two or three witnesses;
10:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|任何人干犯摩西的律法，憑兩三個見證人，尚且不得憐恤而死，
10:29|ASV|of how much sorer punishment, think ye, shall he be judged worthy, who hath trodden under foot the Son of God, and hath counted the blood of the covenant wherewith he was sanctified an unholy thing, and hath done despite unto the Spirit of grace?
10:29|Darby|of how much worse punishment, think ye, shall he be judged  worthy who has trodden under foot the Son of God, and esteemed  the blood of the covenant, whereby he has been sanctified,  common, and has insulted the Spirit of grace?
10:29|KJV|Of how much sorer punishment, suppose ye, shall he be thought worthy, who hath trodden under foot the Son of God, and hath counted the blood of the covenant, wherewith he was sanctified, an unholy thing, and hath done despite unto the Spirit of grace?
10:29<version name="WYC">how much more guess ye, that he deserveth worse torments [him to deserve worse torments], which defouleth the Son of God, and holdeth the blood of the testament polluted, in which he is hallowed, and doeth despite [and shall do wrong, <i>or despite</i>,] to the Spirit of grace?</version>
10:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|何況那踐踏神的兒子，將他藉以成聖的立約之血當作俗物，又褻慢恩典之靈的，你們想，他該受怎樣更重的刑罰？
10:30|ASV|For we know him that said, Vengeance belongeth unto me, I will recompense. And again, The Lord shall judge his people.
10:30|Darby|For we know him that said, To me [belongs] vengeance; *I*  will recompense, saith the Lord: and again, The Lord shall  judge his people.
10:30|KJV|For we know him that hath said, Vengeance belongeth unto me, I will recompense, saith the Lord. And again, The Lord shall judge his people.
10:30|WYC|For we know him that said, To me vengeance, and I shall yield.  And again, For the Lord shall deem his people.
10:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們知道誰曾說，“伸冤在我，我必報應。”又說，“主要審判祂的百姓。”
10:31|ASV|It is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God.
10:31|Darby|[It is] a fearful thing falling into [the] hands of [the]  living God.
10:31|KJV|It is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God.
10:31<version name="WYC">It is fearedful to fall into the hands of God living. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23181c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup></version>
10:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|落在活神的手裡是可怕的。
10:32|ASV|But call to remembrance the former days, in which, after ye were enlightened, ye endured a great conflict of sufferings;
10:32|Darby|But call to mind the earlier days in which, having been  enlightened, ye endured much conflict of sufferings;
10:32|KJV|But call to remembrance the former days, in which, after ye were illuminated, ye endured a great fight of afflictions;
10:32<version name="WYC">And have ye mind on the former days, in which ye were lightened, and suffered great strife of passions [in which ye lightened sustained great strife, <i>or fight</i>, of passions].</version>
10:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而你們要回想往日，那時你們蒙了光照，就忍受了各樣苦難中的大爭戰；
10:33|ASV|partly, being made a gazingstock both by reproaches and afflictions; and partly, becoming partakers with them that were so used.
10:33|Darby|on the one hand, when ye were made a spectacle both in  reproaches and afflictions; and on the other, when ye became  partakers with those who were passing through them.
10:33|KJV|Partly, whilst ye were made a gazingstock both by reproaches and afflictions; and partly, whilst ye became companions of them that were so used.
10:33|WYC|And in the tother ye were made a spectacle by shames and tribulations; in another ye were made fellows of men living so. [And soothly in the tother ye were made a spectacle by reproofs and tribulations; in the tother forsooth ye be made fellows of men living so.]
10:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|一面被辱罵，遭患難，成了給眾人觀看的一臺戲；一面作了那些受如此對待之人的同伴。
10:34|ASV|For ye both had compassion on them that were in bonds, and took joyfully the spoiling of you possessions, knowing that ye have for yourselves a better possession and an abiding one.
10:34|Darby|For ye both sympathised with prisoners and accepted with  joy the plunder of your goods, knowing that ye have for  yourselves a better substance, and an abiding one.
10:34|KJV|For ye had compassion of me in my bonds, and took joyfully the spoiling of your goods, knowing in yourselves that ye have in heaven a better and an enduring substance.
10:34|WYC|For also to bound men ye had compassion, and ye received with joy the robbing of your goods, knowing that ye have a better and a dwelling substance [and ye received with joy the raven of your goods, knowing you to have a better and dwelling substance].
10:34|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為你們同情了那些被捆鎖的人，並且你們的家業被搶奪，你們也歡喜接受，知道自己有更美長存的家業。
10:35|ASV|Cast not away therefore your boldness, which hath great recompense of reward.
10:35|Darby|Cast not away therefore your confidence, which has great  recompense.
10:35|KJV|Cast not away therefore your confidence, which hath great recompence of reward.
10:35|WYC|Therefore do not ye lose your trust, which hath great rewarding.
10:35|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以不可丟棄你們的膽量；這膽量是會得大賞賜的。
10:36|ASV|For ye have need of patience, that, having done the will of God, ye may receive the promise.
10:36|Darby|For ye have need of endurance in order that, having done  the will of God, ye may receive the promise.
10:36|KJV|For ye have need of patience, that, after ye have done the will of God, ye might receive the promise.
10:36|WYC|For patience is needful to you, that ye do the will of God, and bring again the promise [that ye doing the will of God, bring again the promise].
10:36|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們所需要的乃是忍耐，使你們行完了神的旨意，就可以得著所應許的。
10:37|ASV|For yet a very little while, He that cometh shall come, and shall not tarry.
10:37|Darby|For yet a very little while he that comes will come, and  will not delay.
10:37|KJV|For yet a little while, and he that shall come will come, and will not tarry.
10:37|WYC|For yet a little, and he that is to come shall come, and he shall not tarry.
10:37|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|“因為還有一點點時候，那要來的就來，並不遲延。
10:38|ASV|But my righteous one shall live by faith: And if he shrink back, my soul hath no pleasure in him.
10:38|Darby|But the just shall live by faith; and, if he draw back, my  soul does not take pleasure in him.
10:38|KJV|Now the just shall live by faith: but if any man draw back, my soul shall have no pleasure in him.
10:38|WYC|For my just man liveth of faith; that if he withdraweth himself, he shall not please to my soul.
10:38|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只是我的義人必本於信活著；他若退縮，我的心就不喜悅他。”
10:39<version name="ASV">But we are not of them that shrink back unto perdition; but of them that have faith unto the saving of the soul. </p><p /><br /></version>
10:39<version name="Darby">But *we* are not drawers back to perdition, but of faith  to saving [the] soul. </p><p /><br /></version>
10:39<version name="KJV">But we are not of them who draw back unto perdition; but of them that believe to the saving of the soul.</p><p /><br /></version>
10:39|WYC|But we be not the sons of withdrawing away into perdition, but of faith into [the] getting of soul.
10:39|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們卻不是退縮以致遭毀壞的人，乃是有信心以致得著魂的人。
11:1|ASV|Now faith is assurance of things hoped for, a conviction of things not seen.
11:1|Darby|Now faith is [the] substantiating of things hoped for,  [the] conviction of things not seen.
11:1|KJV|Now faith is the substance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not seen.
11:1<version name="WYC">But faith is the substance of things that be to be hoped, and an argument of things not appearing. [Forsooth faith is the substance of things to be hoped, an argument, <i>or certainty</i>, of things not appearing.]</version>
11:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|信就是所望之事的質實，是未見之事的確證。
11:2|ASV|For therein the elders had witness borne to them.
11:2|Darby|For in [the power of] this the elders have obtained  testimony.
11:2|KJV|For by it the elders obtained a good report.
11:2<version name="WYC">And in this <i>faith</i> old men have gotten witnessing.</version>
11:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|古人在這信上得了美好的見證。
11:3|ASV|By faith we understand that the worlds have been framed by the word of God, so that what is seen hath not been made out of things which appear.
11:3|Darby|By faith we apprehend that the worlds were framed by [the]  word of God, so that that which is seen should not take its  origin from things which appear.
11:3|KJV|Through faith we understand that the worlds were framed by the word of God, so that things which are seen were not made of things which do appear.
11:3<version name="WYC">By faith we understand that the worlds were made by God's word [By faith we understand the worlds to be shaped, <i>or made</i>, by God's word], that visible things were made of invisible things.</version>
11:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們因著信，知道宇宙是憑神的話結構起來的；這樣，所看見的並不是從顯然之物而成的。
11:4|ASV|By faith Abel offered unto God a more excellent sacrifice than Cain, through which he had witness borne to him that he was righteous, God bearing witness in respect of his gifts: and through it he being dead yet speaketh.
11:4|Darby|By faith Abel offered to God a more excellent sacrifice  than Cain, by which he obtained testimony of being righteous,  God bearing testimony to his gifts, and by it, having died, he  yet speaks.
11:4|KJV|By faith Abel offered unto God a more excellent sacrifice than Cain, by which he obtained witness that he was righteous, God testifying of his gifts: and by it he being dead yet speaketh.
11:4<version name="WYC">By faith Abel offered a much more sacrifice than Cain to God, by which he got witnessing to be just, for God bare witnessing to his gifts <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23193a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>; and by that <i>faith</i> he dead speaketh yet.</version>
11:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞伯因著信獻祭給神，比該隱所獻的更美，藉此便得了稱許為義的見證，就是神指著他的禮物所作的見證；他雖然死了，卻藉著這信仍舊說話。
11:5|ASV|By faith Enoch was translated that he should not see death; and he was not found, because God translated him: for he hath had witness borne to him that before his translation he had been well-pleasing unto God:
11:5|Darby|By faith Enoch was translated that he should not see death;  and was not found, because God had translated him; for before  [his] translation he has the testimony that he had pleased God.
11:5|KJV|By faith Enoch was translated that he should not see death; and was not found, because God had translated him: for before his translation he had this testimony, that he pleased God.
11:5|WYC|By faith Enoch was translated, that he should not see death; and he was not found, for the Lord translated him.  For before [the] translation he had witnessing that he pleased God.
11:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以諾因著信被接去，不至於見死，人也找不著他，因為神把他接去了；原來他被接去以前，已經得了蒙神喜悅的見證。
11:6|ASV|And without faith it is impossible to be well-pleasing unto him; for he that cometh to God must believe that he is, and that he is a rewarder of them that seek after him.
11:6|Darby|But without faith [it is] impossible to please [him]. For  he that draws near to God must believe that he is, and [that]  he is a rewarder of them who seek him out.
11:6|KJV|But without faith it is impossible to please him: for he that cometh to God must believe that he is, and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently seek him.
11:6|WYC|And it is impossible to please God without faith.  For it behooveth that a man coming to God, believe that he is, and that he is [a] rewarder of men that seek him.
11:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人非有信，就不能得神的喜悅；因為到神面前來的人，必須信有神，且信祂賞賜那尋求祂的人。
11:7|ASV|By faith Noah, being warned of God concerning things not seen as yet, moved with godly fear, prepared an ark to the saving of his house; through which he condemned the world, and became heir of the righteousness which is according to faith.
11:7|Darby|By faith, Noah, oracularly warned concerning things not yet  seen, moved with fear, prepared an ark for the saving of his  house; by which he condemned the world, and became heir of the  righteousness which [is] according to faith.
11:7|KJV|By faith Noah, being warned of God of things not seen as yet, moved with fear, prepared an ark to the saving of his house; by the which he condemned the world, and became heir of the righteousness which is by faith.
11:7<version name="WYC">By faith Noah dreaded, through answer taken of these things that yet were not seen, and shaped a ship into the health of his house [By faith Noah, an answer taken of these things that yet were not seen, dreading shaped an ark, <i>or ship</i>, into the health of his house]; by which he condemned the world, and is ordained heir of rightwiseness, which is by faith.</version>
11:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|挪亞因著信，既蒙神指示他未見的事，就為虔敬所動，豫備了一隻方舟，使他全家得救，藉此就定了那世界的罪，並且承受了那照著信而得的義。
11:8|ASV|By faith Abraham, when he was called, obeyed to go out unto a place which he was to receive for an inheritance; and he went out, not knowing whither he went.
11:8|Darby|By faith Abraham, being called, obeyed to go out into the  place which he was to receive for an inheritance, and went out,  not knowing where he was going.
11:8|KJV|By faith Abraham, when he was called to go out into a place which he should after receive for an inheritance, obeyed; and he went out, not knowing whither he went.
11:8|WYC|By faith he that is called Abraham, obeyed to go out into a place, which he should take into heritage; and he went out, not witting whither he should go.
11:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞伯拉罕因著信，蒙召的時候，就遵命出去，往將來要得為業的地方去；他出去了，還不知道往那裡去。
11:9|ASV|By faith he became a sojourner in the land of promise, as in a land not his own, dwelling in tents, with Isaac and Jacob, the heirs with him of the same promise:
11:9|Darby|By faith he sojourned as a stranger in the land of promise  as a foreign country, having dwelt in tents with Isaac and  Jacob, the heirs with [him] of the same promise;
11:9|KJV|By faith he sojourned in the land of promise, as in a strange country, dwelling in tabernacles with Isaac and Jacob, the heirs with him of the same promise:
11:9<version name="WYC">By faith he dwelt in the land of promise, as in an alien <i>land</i>, dwelling in little houses with Isaac and Jacob, even-heirs of the same promise.</version>
11:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他因著信，在應許之地作客，好像在異地，與承受同樣應許的以撒、雅各一同居住在帳棚裡；
11:10|ASV|for he looked for the city which hath the foundations, whose builder and maker is God.
11:10|Darby|for he waited for the city which has foundations, of which  God is [the] artificer and constructor.
11:10|KJV|For he looked for a city which hath foundations, whose builder and maker is God.
11:10|WYC|For he abode a city having foundaments, whose craftsman and maker is God.
11:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為他等候那座有根基的城，其設計者並建築者乃是神。
11:11|ASV|By faith even Sarah herself received power to conceive seed when she was past age, since she counted him faithful who had promised:
11:11|Darby|By faith also Sarah herself received strength for [the]  conception of seed, and [that] beyond a seasonable age; since  she counted him faithful who promised.
11:11|KJV|Through faith also Sara herself received strength to conceive seed, and was delivered of a child when she was past age, because she judged him faithful who had promised.
11:11|WYC|By faith also that Sara barren, took virtue in conceiving of seed, yea, against the time of age; for she believed him true, that had promised.
11:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因著信，連撒拉自己，即使過了年齡，還得了能力，懷孕生子，因她認為那應許她的是信實的。
11:12|ASV|wherefore also there sprang of one, and him as good as dead, so many as the stars of heaven in multitude, and as the sand, which is by the sea-shore, innumerable.
11:12|Darby|Wherefore also there have been born of one, and that of  one become dead, even as the stars of heaven in multitude, and  as the countless sand which [is] by the sea shore.
11:12|KJV|Therefore sprang there even of one, and him as good as dead, so many as the stars of the sky in multitude, and as the sand which is by the sea shore innumerable.
11:12<version name="WYC">For which thing of one, and yet nigh dead, there were born as stars of heaven in multitude, and as gravel that is at the seaside out of number. [For which thing, and of one, and him nigh dead, <i>men</i> be born as stars of heaven in multitude, and as gravel, <i>or</i> <i>sand</i>, that is at the seaside unnumerable.]</version>
11:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以從一個彷彿已死的人，生出子孫來，如同天上的星那樣眾多，海邊的沙那樣無數。
11:13|ASV|These all died in faith, not having received the promises, but having seen them and greeted them from afar, and having confessed that they were strangers and pilgrims on the earth.
11:13|Darby|All these died in faith, not having received the promises,  but having seen them from afar off and embraced [them], and  confessed that they were strangers and sojourners on the earth.
11:13|KJV|These all died in faith, not having received the promises, but having seen them afar off, and were persuaded of them, and embraced them, and confessed that they were strangers and pilgrims on the earth.
11:13|WYC|By faith all these be dead, when the promises were not taken, but they beheld them afar [but they beholding them afar], and greeting them well, and acknowledged that they were pilgrims, and harboured men on the earth.
11:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些人都是存著信心死的，並沒有得著所應許的，卻從遠處望見，且歡喜迎接，又承認自己在地上是客旅，是寄居的。
11:14|ASV|For they that say such things make it manifest that they are seeking after a country of their own.
11:14|Darby|For they who say such things shew clearly that they seek  [their] country.
11:14|KJV|For they that say such things declare plainly that they seek a country.
11:14|WYC|And they that say these things, signify that they seek a country.
11:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|說這樣話的人，是顯明自己在尋找一個家鄉。
11:15|ASV|And if indeed they had been mindful of that country from which they went out, they would have had opportunity to return.
11:15|Darby|And if they had called to mind that from whence they went  out, they had had opportunity to have returned;
11:15|KJV|And truly, if they had been mindful of that country from whence they came out, they might have had opportunity to have returned.
11:15|WYC|If they had had mind of that [And forsooth if they had mind of that], of which they went out, [soothly] they had time of turning again;
11:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們若真是想念著所離開的家鄉，還有折回的機會；
11:16|ASV|But now they desire a better country, that is, a heavenly: wherefore God is not ashamed of them, to be called their God; for he hath prepared for them a city.
11:16|Darby|but now they seek a better, that is, a heavenly; wherefore  God is not ashamed of them, to be called their God; for he has  prepared for them a city.
11:16|KJV|But now they desire a better country, that is, an heavenly: wherefore God is not ashamed to be called their God: for he hath prepared for them a city.
11:16<version name="WYC">but now they desire a better, that is to say, heavenly.   Therefore God is not confounded to be called the God of them [Therefore God is not confounded, <i>or shamed</i>, to be called the God of them]; for he made ready to them a city.</version>
11:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們卻羨慕一個更美、屬天的家鄉；所以神稱為他們的神，並不以為恥，因為祂已經給他們豫備了一座城。
11:17|ASV|By faith Abraham, being tried, offered up Isaac: yea, he that had gladly received the promises was offering up his only begotten  son;
11:17|Darby|By faith Abraham, [when] tried, offered up Isaac, and he  who had received to himself the promises offered up his only  begotten [son],
11:17|KJV|By faith Abraham, when he was tried, offered up Isaac: and he that had received the promises offered up his only begotten son,
11:17<version name="WYC">By faith Abraham offered Isaac, when he was tempted; and he offered the one begotten [<i>son</i>], which had taken the promises [which had taken repromissions];</version>
11:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞伯拉罕因著信，被試驗的時候，就把以撒獻上；這正是那歡喜領受應許的，將自己獨生的兒子獻上。
11:18|ASV|even he to whom it was said, In Isaac shall thy seed be called:
11:18|Darby|as to whom it had been said, In Isaac shall thy seed be  called:
11:18|KJV|Of whom it was said, That in Isaac shall thy seed be called:
11:18|WYC|to whom it was said, For in Isaac the seed shall be called to thee.
11:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|論到這兒子，曾有話說，“從以撒生的，纔要稱為你的後裔。”
11:19|ASV|accounting that God  is able to raise up, even from the dead; from whence he did also in a figure receive him back.
11:19|Darby|counting that God [was] able to raise [him] even from  among [the] dead, whence also he received him in a figure.
11:19|KJV|Accounting that God was able to raise him up, even from the dead; from whence also he received him in a figure.
11:19<version name="WYC">For he deemed, that God is mighty to raise him, yea, from death <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23208b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup>; wherefore he took him also into a parable.</version>
11:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他算定神甚至能叫人從死人中復活；就表樣說，他也實在從死人中得回了他的兒子。
11:20|ASV|By faith Isaac blessed Jacob and Esau, even concerning things to come.
11:20|Darby|By faith Isaac blessed Jacob and Esau concerning things to  come.
11:20|KJV|By faith Isaac blessed Jacob and Esau concerning things to come.
11:20|WYC|By faith also of things to coming [By faith and of things to come], Isaac blessed Jacob and Esau.
11:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以撒因著信，指著要來的事，給雅各、以掃祝福。
11:21|ASV|By faith Jacob, when he was dying, blessed each of the sons of Joseph; and worshipped, leaning upon the top of his staff.
11:21|Darby|By faith Jacob [when] dying blessed each of the sons of  Joseph, and worshipped on the top of his staff.
11:21|KJV|By faith Jacob, when he was a dying, blessed both the sons of Joseph; and worshipped, leaning upon the top of his staff.
11:21|WYC|By faith Jacob dying blessed all the sons of Joseph, and honoured the highness of his staff [and honoured the highness of his rod].
11:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|雅各因著信，臨死的時候，給約瑟的兩個兒子各自祝福，並且扶著杖頭敬拜神。
11:22|ASV|By faith Joseph, when his end was nigh, made mention of the departure of the children of Israel; and gave commandment concerning his bones.
11:22|Darby|By faith Joseph [when] dying called to mind the going  forth of the sons of Israel, and gave commandment concerning  his bones.
11:22|KJV|By faith Joseph, when he died, made mention of the departing of the children of Israel; and gave commandment concerning his bones.
11:22|WYC|By faith Joseph dying had mind of the passing forth of the children of Israel, and commanded of his bones.
11:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|約瑟因著信，臨終的時候，題到以色列子孫出埃及的事，並為自己的骸骨留下遺囑。
11:23|ASV|By faith Moses, when he was born, was hid three months by his parents, because they saw he was a goodly child; and they were not afraid of the king's commandment.
11:23|Darby|By faith Moses, being born, was hid three months by his  parents, because they saw the child beautiful; and they did not  fear the injunction of the king.
11:23|KJV|By faith Moses, when he was born, was hid three months of his parents, because they saw he was a proper child; and they were not afraid of the king's commandment.
11:23<version name="WYC">By faith Moses born, was hid three months of his father and mother, for that they saw the young child fair [for that they saw the young child fair, <i>or seemly</i>]; and they dreaded not the commandment of the king.</version>
11:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|摩西生下來的時候，他的父母因見他是個俊美的孩子，就因著信，把他藏了三個月，並不怕王命。
11:24|ASV|By faith Moses, when he was grown up, refused to be called the son of Pharaoh's daughter;
11:24|Darby|By faith Moses, when he had become great, refused to be  called son of Pharaoh's daughter;
11:24|KJV|By faith Moses, when he was come to years, refused to be called the son of Pharaoh's daughter;
11:24|WYC|By faith Moses was made great, and denied that he was the son of Pharaoh's daughter, [By faith Moses made great, denied him to be the son of Pharaoh's daughter,]
11:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|摩西因著信，長大了就拒絕稱為法老女兒之子；
11:25|ASV|choosing rather to share ill treatment with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleasures of sin for a season;
11:25|Darby|choosing rather to suffer affliction along with the people  of God than to have [the] temporary pleasure of sin;
11:25|KJV|Choosing rather to suffer affliction with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleasures of sin for a season;
11:25|WYC|and chose more to be tormented with the people of God [choosing rather for to be tormented with the people of God], than to have mirth of temporal sin;
11:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他寧可選擇和神的百姓同受苦害，也不願有罪的短暫享受；
11:26|ASV|accounting the reproach of Christ greater riches than the treasures of Egypt: for he looked unto the recompense of reward.
11:26|Darby|esteeming the reproach of the Christ greater riches than  the treasures of Egypt, for he had respect to the recompense.
11:26|KJV|Esteeming the reproach of Christ greater riches than the treasures in Egypt: for he had respect unto the recompence of the reward.
11:26|WYC|deeming the reproof of Christ more riches than the treasures of [the]  Egyptians; for he beheld into the rewarding.
11:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他算為基督受的凌辱，比埃及的財物更寶貴，因他望斷以及於那賞賜。
11:27|ASV|By faith he forsook Egypt, not fearing the wrath of the king: for he endured, as seeing him who is invisible.
11:27|Darby|By faith he left Egypt, not fearing the wrath of the king;  for he persevered, as seeing him who is invisible.
11:27|KJV|By faith he forsook Egypt, not fearing the wrath of the king: for he endured, as seeing him who is invisible.
11:27|WYC|By faith he forsook Egypt, and dreaded not the hardness of the king; for he abode, as seeing him that was invisible. [By faith he forsook Egypt, not dreading the hardness of the king; forsooth he as seeing sustained the invisible.]
11:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他因著信，離開埃及，不怕王怒；因他堅定不移，如同看見那不能看見的主；
11:28|ASV|By faith he kept the passover, and the sprinkling of the blood, that the destroyer of the firstborn should not touch them.
11:28|Darby|By faith he celebrated the passover and the sprinkling of  the blood, that the destroyer of the firstborn might not touch  them.
11:28|KJV|Through faith he kept the passover, and the sprinkling of blood, lest he that destroyed the firstborn should touch them.
11:28<version name="WYC">By faith he hallowed pask, and the shedding out of blood, that he that destroyed the first things <i>of Egyptians</i>, should not touch them. [By faith he hallowed pask, and shedding of blood, lest he that destroyed the first things <i>of</i> <i>the</i> <i>Egyptians</i>, should touch them.]</version>
11:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他因著信，就立了逾越節並塗血的事，免得那滅長子的臨及以色列人。
11:29|ASV|By faith they passed through the Red sea as by dry land: which the Egyptians assaying to do were swallowed up.
11:29|Darby|By faith they passed through the Red sea as through dry  land; of which the Egyptians having made trial were swallowed  up.
11:29|KJV|By faith they passed through the Red sea as by dry land: which the Egyptians assaying to do were drowned.
11:29<version name="WYC">By faith they passed the red sea, as by dry land, which thing Egyptians assaying were devoured [<i>in waters</i>].</version>
11:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們因著信，過紅海如過乾地；埃及人試著要過去，就被吞滅了。
11:30|ASV|By faith the walls of Jericho fell down, after they had been compassed about for seven days.
11:30|Darby|By faith the walls of Jericho fell, having been encircled  for seven days.
11:30|KJV|By faith the walls of Jericho fell down, after they were compassed about seven days.
11:30|WYC|By faith the walls of Jericho felled down [fell down], by compassing of seven days.
11:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因著信，耶利哥的城牆被圍繞七日，就倒塌了。
11:31|ASV|By faith Rahab the harlot perished not with them that were disobedient, having received the spies with peace.
11:31|Darby|By faith Rahab the harlot did not perish along with the  unbelieving, having received the spies in peace.
11:31|KJV|By faith the harlot Rahab perished not with them that believed not, when she had received the spies with peace.
11:31<version name="WYC">By faith Rahab the whore received the spies with peace, and perished not with unbelieveful men. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23220c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup></version>
11:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|妓女喇合因著信，和和平平的接待探子，就不與那些不信從的人一同滅亡。
11:32|ASV|And what shall I more say? for the time will fail me if I tell of Gideon, Barak, Samson, Jephthah; of David and Samuel and the prophets:
11:32|Darby|And what more do I say? For the time would fail me telling  of Gideon, and Barak, and Samson, and Jephthah, and David and  Samuel, and of the prophets:
11:32|KJV|And what shall I more say? for the time would fail me to tell of Gedeon, and of Barak, and of Samson, and of Jephthae; of David also, and Samuel, and of the prophets:
11:32|WYC|And what yet shall I say?  For time shall fail to me [Soothly time shall fail me] telling of Gedeon, Barak, Samson, Jephthae, David, and Samuel, and of other prophets;
11:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|此外，我還要再說甚麼？若要一一細說基甸、巴拉、參孫、耶弗他、大衛、撒母耳和眾申言者的事，時間就不彀我用了。
11:33|ASV|who through faith subdued kingdoms, wrought righteousness, obtained promises, stopped the mouths of lions,
11:33|Darby|who by faith overcame kingdoms, wrought righteousness,  obtained promises, stopped lions' mouths,
11:33|KJV|Who through faith subdued kingdoms, wrought righteousness, obtained promises, stopped the mouths of lions.
11:33|WYC|which by faith overcame realms, wrought rightwiseness, got repromissions; they stopped the mouths of lions,
11:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們藉著信，制伏了列國，行了公義，得了應許，堵了獅子的口，
11:34|ASV|quenched the power of fire, escaped the edge of the sword, from weakness were made strong, waxed mighty in war, turned to flight armies of aliens.
11:34|Darby|quenched [the] power of fire, escaped [the] edge of the  sword, became strong out of weakness, became mighty in war,  made [the] armies of strangers give way.
11:34|KJV|Quenched the violence of fire, escaped the edge of the sword, out of weakness were made strong, waxed valiant in fight, turned to flight the armies of the aliens.
11:34|WYC|they quenched the fierceness of fire, they drove away the edge of sword,  they recovered of sickness, they were made strong in battle, they turned the hosts of aliens.
11:34|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|滅了烈火的猛勢，脫了刀劍的鋒刃，軟弱得著加力，爭戰顯出大能，打退外邦的軍隊。
11:35|ASV|Women received their dead by a resurrection: and others were tortured, not accepting their deliverance; that they might obtain a better resurrection:
11:35|Darby|Women received their dead again by resurrection; and  others were tortured, not having accepted deliverance, that  they might get a better resurrection;
11:35|KJV|Women received their dead raised to life again: and others were tortured, not accepting deliverance; that they might obtain a better resurrection:
11:35<version name="WYC">Women received their dead <i>children </i>from death to life; but others were held forth, not taking redemption [Women received their dead of again-rising; forsooth others were holden forth, <i>or dead</i>, not taking redemption], that they should find a better again-rising.</version>
11:35|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有婦人得自己的死人復活；另有人受嚴刑至死，不肯接受釋放，為要得著更美的復活；
11:36|ASV|and others had trial of mockings and scourgings, yea, moreover of bonds and imprisonment:
11:36|Darby|and others underwent trial of mockings and scourgings,  yea, and of bonds and imprisonment.
11:36|KJV|And others had trial of cruel mockings and scourgings, yea, moreover of bonds and imprisonment:
11:36|WYC|And others assayed scornings and beatings, moreover and bonds and prisons.
11:36|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又另有人受了戲弄和鞭打，甚至捆鎖和監禁的試煉；
11:37|ASV|they were stoned, they were sawn asunder, they were tempted, they were slain with the sword: they went about in sheepskins, in goatskins; being destitute, afflicted, ill-treated
11:37|Darby|They were stoned, were sawn asunder, were tempted, died by  the death of the sword; they went about in sheepskins, in  goatskins, destitute, afflicted, evil treated,
11:37|KJV|They were stoned, they were sawn asunder, were tempted, were slain with the sword: they wandered about in sheepskins and goatskins; being destitute, afflicted, tormented;
11:37|WYC|They were stoned, they were sawed, they were tempted, they were dead in slaying of sword.  They went about in badger skins [They went about in brock skins], and in skins of goats, needy, anguished, tormented;
11:37|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們被石頭打死，被鋸鋸死，受到試探，被刀殺死；披著綿羊山羊的皮各處奔走，受窮乏，受患難，受苦害；
11:38|ASV|(of whom the world was not worthy), wandering in deserts and mountains and caves, and the holes of the earth.
11:38|Darby|(of whom the world was not worthy,) wandering in deserts  and mountains, and [in] dens and caverns of the earth.
11:38|KJV|(Of whom the world was not worthy:) they wandered in deserts, and in mountains, and in dens and caves of the earth.
11:38|WYC|to which the world was not worthy.  They wandered in wildernesses [They erring in wildernesses], and in mountains and dens, and [in] caves of the earth.
11:38|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在曠野、山嶺、山洞、地穴，飄流無定，是世界不配有的。
11:39|ASV|And these all, having had witness borne to them through their faith, received not the promise,
11:39|Darby|And these all, having obtained witness through faith, did  not receive the promise,
11:39|KJV|And these all, having obtained a good report through faith, received not the promise:
11:39|WYC|And all these, approved by witnessing of faith [proved by witnessing of faith], took not repromission;
11:39|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些人都藉著信得了美好的見證，卻沒有得著所應許的；
11:40<version name="ASV">God having provided some better thing concerning us, that apart from us they should not be made perfect. </p><p /><br /></version>
11:40<version name="Darby">God having foreseen some better thing for us, that they  should not be made perfect without us. </p><p /><br /></version>
11:40<version name="KJV">God having provided some better thing for us, that they without us should not be made perfect.</p><p /><br /></version>
11:40|WYC|for God provided some better thing for us, that they should not be made perfect without us.
11:40|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神為我們豫備了更美的事，叫他們若沒有我們，就不能完全。
12:1|ASV|Therefore let us also, seeing we are compassed about with so great a cloud of witnesses, lay aside every weight, and the sin which doth so easily beset us, and let us run with patience the race that is set before us,
12:1|Darby|Let *us* also therefore, having so great a cloud of  witnesses surrounding us, laying aside every weight, and sin  which so easily entangles us, run with endurance the race that  lies before us,
12:1|KJV|Wherefore seeing we also are compassed about with so great a cloud of witnesses, let us lay aside every weight, and the sin which doth so easily beset us, and let us run with patience the race that is set before us,
12:1|WYC|Therefore [and] we that have so great a cloud of witnesses put to [us], do we away all charge, and sin standing about us, and by patience run we to the battle purposed to us,
12:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，我們既有這許多的見證人，如同雲彩圍著我們，就當脫去各樣的重擔，和容易纏累我們的罪，憑著忍耐奔那擺在我們前頭的賽程，
12:2|ASV|looking unto Jesus the author and perfecter of our faith, who for the joy that was set before him endured the cross, despising shame, and hath sat down at the right hand of the throne of God.
12:2|Darby|looking stedfastly on Jesus the leader and completer of  faith: who, in view of the joy lying before him, endured [the]  cross, having despised [the] shame, and is set down at the  right hand of the throne of God.
12:2|KJV|Looking unto Jesus the author and finisher of our faith; who for the joy that was set before him endured the cross, despising the shame, and is set down at the right hand of the throne of God.
12:2|WYC|beholding into the maker of faith, and the perfect ender, Jesus; which when joy was purposed to him, he suffered the cross [suffered the cross], and despised confusion, and sitteth on the right half of the seat of God.
12:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|望斷以及於耶穌，就是我們信心的創始者與成終者；祂為那擺在前面的喜樂，就輕看羞辱，忍受了十字架，便坐在神寶座的右邊。
12:3|ASV|For consider him that hath endured such gainsaying of sinners against himself, that ye wax not weary, fainting in your souls.
12:3|Darby|For consider well him who endured so great contradiction  from sinners against himself, that ye be not weary, fainting in  your minds.
12:3|KJV|For consider him that endured such contradiction of sinners against himself, lest ye be wearied and faint in your minds.
12:3|WYC|And bethink ye on him that suffered such gainsaying of sinful men against himself [Forsooth bethink ye on him that sustained such against-saying of sinful men against himself], that ye be not made weary, failing in your souls.
12:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那忍受罪人這樣頂撞自己的，你們要考量比較，免得疲倦灰心。
12:4|ASV|Ye have not yet resisted unto blood, striving against sin:
12:4|Darby|Ye have not yet resisted unto blood, wrestling against sin.
12:4|KJV|Ye have not yet resisted unto blood, striving against sin.
12:4|WYC|For ye against-stood not yet unto blood, fighting against sin.
12:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們與罪爭鬥，還沒有抵擋到流血；
12:5|ASV|and ye have forgotten the exhortation which reasoneth with you as with sons, My son, regard not lightly the chastening of the Lord, Nor faint when thou art reproved of him;
12:5|Darby|And ye have quite forgotten the exhortation which speaks to  you as to sons: My son, despise not [the] chastening of [the]  Lord, nor faint [when] reproved by him;
12:5|KJV|And ye have forgotten the exhortation which speaketh unto you as unto children, My son, despise not thou the chastening of the Lord, nor faint when thou art rebuked of him:
12:5|WYC|And ye have forgotten the comfort that speaketh to you as to sons, and saith, My son, do not thou despise the teaching of the Lord [saying, My son, do not thou despise the discipline of the Lord], neither be thou made weary, the while thou art chastised of him.
12:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們竟全然忘了那勸勉的話，就是對你們如同對兒子所講論的，說，“我兒，你不可輕看主的管教，被祂責備的時候，也不可灰心；
12:6|ASV|For whom the Lord loveth he chasteneth, And scourgeth every son whom he receiveth.
12:6|Darby|for whom [the] Lord loves he chastens, and scourges every  son whom he receives.
12:6|KJV|For whom the Lord loveth he chasteneth, and scourgeth every son whom he receiveth.
12:6<version name="WYC">For the Lord chastiseth him that he loveth; he beateth every son that he receiveth. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23235a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
12:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為主所愛的，祂必管教，又鞭打凡所收納的兒子。”
12:7|ASV|It is for chastening that ye endure; God dealeth with you as with sons; for what son is there whom his father chasteneth not?
12:7|Darby|Ye endure for chastening, God conducts himself towards you  as towards sons; for who is the son that the father chastens  not?
12:7|KJV|If ye endure chastening, God dealeth with you as with sons; for what son is he whom the father chasteneth not?
12:7<version name="WYC">Abide ye still in chastising; God proffereth him(self) to you as to sons <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23236b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup>.  For what son is it, whom the father chastiseth not?</version>
12:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|為了受管教，你們要忍受。神待你們如同待兒子；那有兒子是父親不管教的？
12:8|ASV|But if ye are without chastening, whereof all have been made partakers, then are ye bastards, and not sons.
12:8|Darby|But if ye are without chastening, of which all have been  made partakers, then are ye bastards, and not sons.
12:8|KJV|But if ye be without chastisement, whereof all are partakers, then are ye bastards, and not sons.
12:8|WYC|That if ye be out of chastising, whose partners be ye all made [That if ye be out of discipline, of which all be made partners], then ye be adulterers, and not sons.
12:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只是你們若不受眾子所共受的管教，就是私生子，不是兒子了。
12:9|ASV|Furthermore, we had the fathers of our flesh to chasten us, and we gave them reverence: shall we not much rather be in subjection unto the Father of spirits, and live?
12:9|Darby|Moreover we have had the fathers of our flesh as  chasteners, and we reverenced [them]; shall we not much rather  be in subjection to the Father of spirits, and live?
12:9|KJV|Furthermore we have had fathers of our flesh which corrected us, and we gave them reverence: shall we not much rather be in subjection unto the Father of spirits, and live?
12:9|WYC|And afterward we had fathers of our flesh, teachers, and we with reverence dreaded them.  Whether not much more we shall obey to the Father of spirits, and we shall live?
12:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|再者，我們曾有肉身的父管教我們，我們尚且敬重他們，何況萬靈的父，我們豈不更當服從祂而得活著麼？
12:10|ASV|For they indeed for a few days chastened us as seemed good to them; but he for our profit, that we may be partakers of his holiness.
12:10|Darby|For they indeed chastened for a few days, as seemed good  to them; but he for profit, in order to the partaking of his  holiness.
12:10|KJV|For they verily for a few days chastened us after their own pleasure; but he for our profit, that we might be partakers of his holiness.
12:10|WYC|And they [soothly] in time of few days taught us by their will; but this Father teacheth to that thing that is profitable [forsooth this Father to that thing that is profitable], in receiving the hallowing of him.
12:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|肉身的父是在短暫的日子裡，照自己以為好的管教我們，惟有萬靈的父管教我們，是為了我們的益處，使我們有分於祂的聖別。
12:11|ASV|All chastening seemeth for the present to be not joyous but grievous; yet afterward it yieldeth peaceable fruit unto them that have been exercised thereby, even the fruit of righteousness.
12:11|Darby|But no chastening at the time seems to be [matter] of joy,  but of grief; but afterwards yields [the] peaceful fruit of  righteousness to those exercised by it.
12:11|KJV|Now no chastening for the present seemeth to be joyous, but grievous: nevertheless afterward it yieldeth the peaceable fruit of righteousness unto them which are exercised thereby.
12:11<version name="WYC">And each chastising in [this] present <i>time</i> seemeth to be not of joy, but of sorrow; but afterward it shall yield fruit of rightwiseness most peaceable to men exercised by it.</version>
12:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|一切的管教，當時固然不覺得喜樂，反覺得愁苦；後來卻給那藉此受過操練的人，結出平安的義果。
12:12|ASV|Wherefore lift up the hands that hang down, and the palsied knees;
12:12|Darby|Wherefore lift up the hands that hang down, and the  failing knees;
12:12|KJV|Wherefore lift up the hands which hang down, and the feeble knees;
12:12|WYC|For which thing raise ye [up] slow hands, and knees unbound,
12:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以你們要把下垂的手，癱弱的膝挺起來；
12:13|ASV|and make straight paths for your feet, that that which is lame be not turned out of the way, but rather be healed.
12:13|Darby|and make straight paths for your feet, that that which is  lame be not turned aside; but that rather it may be healed.
12:13|KJV|And make straight paths for your feet, lest that which is lame be turned out of the way; but let it rather be healed.
12:13<version name="WYC">and make ye rightful steps to your feet [and make rightful goings, <i>or steps</i>, to your feet]; that no man halting err, but more be healed.</version>
12:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|也要為自己的腳把路徑修直了，使瘸子不至脫臼，反得醫治。
12:14|ASV|Follow after peace with all men, and the sanctification without which no man shall see the Lord:
12:14|Darby|Pursue peace with all, and holiness, without which no one  shall see the Lord:
12:14|KJV|Follow peace with all men, and holiness, without which no man shall see the Lord:
12:14|WYC|Follow ye peace with all men, and holiness, without which no man shall see God.
12:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要追求與眾人和睦，並要追求聖別，非聖別沒有人能見主；
12:15|ASV|looking carefully lest there be any man that falleth short of the grace of God; lest any root of bitterness springing up trouble you, and thereby the many be defiled;
12:15|Darby|watching lest [there be] any one who lacks the grace of  God; lest any root of bitterness springing up trouble [you],  and many be defiled by it;
12:15|KJV|Looking diligently lest any man fail of the grace of God; lest any root of bitterness springing up trouble you, and thereby many be defiled;
12:15<version name="WYC">Behold ye, that no man fail to the grace of God [Beholding that no man fail to the grace of God], that no root of bitterness burrowing upward hinder [us], and many be defouled by it [and by it be many <i>men</i> defouled];</version>
12:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|要監察，免得有人墜落離開神的恩典；免得有苦根長起來纏擾你們，許多人便因此沾染污穢；
12:16|ASV|lest there be any fornication, or profane person, as Esau, who for one mess of meat sold his own birthright.
12:16|Darby|lest [there be] any fornicator, or profane person, as  Esau, who for one meal sold his birthright;
12:16|KJV|Lest there be any fornicator, or profane person, as Esau, who for one morsel of meat sold his birthright.
12:16<version name="WYC">that no man be lecher, either unholy, as Esau, which for one meat sold his first things. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23245c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup></version>
12:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|免得有淫亂的、或貪戀世俗如以掃的，他因一口食物把自己長子的名分賣了。
12:17|ASV|For ye know that even when he afterward desired to inherit the blessing, he was rejected; for he found no place for a change of mind in his father, though he sought is diligently with tears.
12:17|Darby|for ye know that also afterwards, desiring to inherit the  blessing, he was rejected, (for he found no place for  repentance) although he sought it earnestly with tears.
12:17|KJV|For ye know how that afterward, when he would have inherited the blessing, he was rejected: for he found no place of repentance, though he sought it carefully with tears.
12:17|WYC|For know ye, that afterward he coveting to inherit blessing, was reproved.  For he found not place of penance, though he sought it with tears.
12:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|後來他也想要承受祝福，竟被拒絕；雖然帶著淚苦求，還是沒有反悔的餘地，這是你們知道的。
12:18|ASV|For ye are not come unto a mount that might be touched, and that burned with fire, and unto blackness, and darkness, and tempest,
12:18|Darby|For ye have not come to [the mount] that might be touched  and was all on fire, and to obscurity, and darkness, and  tempest,
12:18|KJV|For ye are not come unto the mount that might be touched, and that burned with fire, nor unto blackness, and darkness, and tempest,
12:18|WYC|But ye have not come [Forsooth ye have not come] to the fire able to be touched, and able to come to, and to the whirlwind, and mist, and tempest,
12:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們原不是來到那可摸、有火燒著的山，和黑暗、幽暗、旋風、
12:19|ASV|and the sound of a trumpet, and the voice of words; which voice they that heard entreated that no word more should be spoken unto them;
12:19|Darby|and trumpet's sound, and voice of words; which they that  heard, excusing themselves, declined [the] word being addressed  to them any more:
12:19|KJV|And the sound of a trumpet, and the voice of words; which voice they that heard intreated that the word should not be spoken to them any more:
12:19|WYC|and sound of trumpet [and sound of the trump], and voice of words; which they that heard, excused them(selves), that the word should not be made to them.
12:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|角聲、與說話的聲音那裡；那些聽見這聲音的，都懇求不要再對他們多說話；
12:20|ASV|for they could not endure that which was enjoined, If even a beast touch the mountain, it shall be stoned;
12:20|Darby|(for they were not able to bear what was enjoined: And if  a beast should touch the mountain, it shall be stoned;
12:20|KJV|(For they could not endure that which was commanded, And if so much as a beast touch the mountain, it shall be stoned, or thrust through with a dart:
12:20|WYC|For they bare not that that was said, And if a beast touched the hill, it was stoned [it shall be stoned].
12:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為他們擔當不起所囑咐他們的話：“即使是走獸摸了這山，也要用石頭打死。”
12:21|ASV|and so fearful was the appearance, that Moses said, I exceedingly fear and quake:
12:21|Darby|and, so fearful was the sight, Moses said, I am  exceedingly afraid and full of trembling;)
12:21|KJV|And so terrible was the sight, that Moses said, I exceedingly fear and quake:)
12:21|WYC|And so dreadful it was that was seen, that Moses said, I am afeared, and full of trembling.
12:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且所顯現的是如此可怕，甚至摩西說，“我甚是恐懼戰兢。”
12:22|ASV|but ye are come unto mount Zion, and unto the city of the living God, the heavenly Jerusalem, and to innumerable hosts of angels,
12:22|Darby|but ye have come to mount Zion; and to [the] city of [the]  living God, heavenly Jerusalem; and to myriads of angels,
12:22|KJV|But ye are come unto mount Sion, and unto the city of the living God, the heavenly Jerusalem, and to an innumerable company of angels,
12:22|WYC|But ye have come nigh to the hill Sion, and to the city of God living [and to the city of living God], the heavenly Jerusalem, and to the multitude of many thousand angels,
12:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但你們乃是來到錫安山，來到活神的城，屬天的耶路撒冷，來到千萬天使整體的聚集，
12:23|ASV|to the general assembly and church of the firstborn who are enrolled in heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and to the spirits of just men made perfect,
12:23|Darby|the universal gathering; and to [the] assembly of the  firstborn [who are] registered in heaven; and to God, judge of  all; and to [the] spirits of just [men] made perfect;
12:23|KJV|To the general assembly and church of the firstborn, which are written in heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and to the spirits of just men made perfect,
12:23|WYC|and to the church of the first men, which be written in heavens, and to God, doomsman of all, and to the spirit of just perfect men [and to the spirits of just perfect men],
12:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|來到名字記錄在諸天之上眾長子的召會，來到審判眾人的神這裡，來到被成全之義人的靈這裡，
12:24|ASV|and to Jesus the mediator of a new covenant, and to the blood of sprinkling that speaketh better than that of Abel.
12:24|Darby|and to Jesus, mediator of a new covenant; and to [the]  blood of sprinkling, speaking better than Abel.
12:24|KJV|And to Jesus the mediator of the new covenant, and to the blood of sprinkling, that speaketh better things than that of Abel.
12:24<version name="WYC">and to Jesus, mediator of the new testament, and to the sprinkling of blood, speaking better than Abel [better speaking than Abel's <i>blood</i>].</version>
12:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|來到新約的中保耶穌這裡，並來到所灑的血這裡，這血所說的比亞伯的血所說的更美。
12:25|ASV|See that ye refuse not him that speaketh. For if they escaped not when they refused him that warned them on earth, much more shall not we escape who turn away from him that  warneth from heaven:
12:25|Darby|See that ye refuse not him that speaks. For if those did  not escape who had refused him who uttered the oracles on  earth, much more we who turn away from him [who does so] from  heaven:
12:25|KJV|See that ye refuse not him that speaketh. For if they escaped not who refused him that spake on earth, much more shall not we escape, if we turn away from him that speaketh from heaven:
12:25|WYC|See ye, that ye forsake [refuse] not the speaker; for if they that forsake him that spake on the earth, escaped not [if forsooth they escaped not (that) refused him that spake on earth], much more we that turn away from him that speaketh to us from heavens.
12:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要謹慎，不可棄絕那說話的，因為那些棄絕那在地上警戒他們者的，尚且不能逃罪，何況我們這轉離那從諸天之上警戒我們者的？
12:26|ASV|whose voice then shook the earth: but now he hath promised, saying, Yet once more will I make to tremble not the earth only, but also the heaven.
12:26|Darby|whose voice then shook the earth; but now he has promised,  saying, Yet once will *I* shake not only the earth, but also  the heaven.
12:26|KJV|Whose voice then shook the earth: but now he hath promised, saying, Yet once more I shake not the earth only, but also heaven.
12:26|WYC|Whose voice then moved the earth, but now he again promiseth, and saith [saying], Yet once and I shall move not only the earth, but also heaven.
12:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當時祂的聲音震動了地；但如今祂應許說，“再一次我不單要震動地，還要震動天。”
12:27|ASV|And this word, Yet once more, signifieth the removing of those things that are shaken, as of things that have been made, that those things which are not shaken may remain.
12:27|Darby|But this Yet once, signifies the removing of what is  shaken, as being made, that what is not shaken may remain.
12:27|KJV|And this word, Yet once more, signifieth the removing of those things that are shaken, as of things that are made, that those things which cannot be shaken may remain.
12:27|WYC|And that he saith, Yet once, he declareth the translation of moveable things, as of made things, that those things dwell, that be unmoveable.
12:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這“再一次，”指明那被震動的，就是受造之物，都要挪去，使那不被震動的常存。
12:28|ASV|Wherefore, receiving a kingdom that cannot be shaken, let us have grace, whereby we may offer service well-pleasing to God with reverence and awe:
12:28|Darby|Wherefore let us, receiving a kingdom not to be shaken,  have grace, by which let us serve God acceptably with reverence  and fear.
12:28|KJV|Wherefore we receiving a kingdom which cannot be moved, let us have grace, whereby we may serve God acceptably with reverence and godly fear:
12:28|WYC|Therefore we receiving the kingdom unmoveable, have we grace, by which serve we pleasing to God with dread and reverence.
12:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我們既領受了不能震動的國，就當接受恩典，藉此得以照神所喜悅的，以虔誠和畏懼事奉神；
12:29<version name="ASV">for our God is a consuming fire. </p><p /><br /></version>
12:29<version name="Darby">For also our God [is] a consuming fire. </p><p /><br /></version>
12:29<version name="KJV">For our God is a consuming fire.</p><p /><br /></version>
12:29|WYC|For our God is fire that wasteth [For why our God is fire wasting].
12:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們的神乃是烈火。
13:1|ASV|Let love of the brethren continue.
13:1|Darby|Let brotherly love abide.
13:1|KJV|Let brotherly love continue.
13:1|WYC|The charity of brotherhood dwell in you,
13:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄相愛要持久。
13:2|ASV|Forget not to show love unto strangers: for thereby some have entertained angels unawares.
13:2|Darby|Be not forgetful of hospitality; for by it some have  unawares entertained angels.
13:2|KJV|Be not forgetful to entertain strangers: for thereby some have entertained angels unawares.
13:2|WYC|and do not ye forget hospitality; for by this some men pleased to angels, that were received to harbour [for by this some pleased to angels received to harbour].
13:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不可忘記用愛接待客旅；因為有人藉此不知不覺的款待了天使。
13:3|ASV|Remember them that are in bonds, as bound with them; them that are illtreated, as being yourselves also in the body.
13:3|Darby|Remember prisoners, as bound with [them]; those that are  evil-treated, as being yourselves also in [the] body.
13:3|KJV|Remember them that are in bonds, as bound with them; and them which suffer adversity, as being yourselves also in the body.
13:3|WYC|Think ye on bound men, as ye were together bound [Be ye mindful of bound men, as ye together bound], and of travailing men, as [and] yourselves dwelling in the body.
13:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要顧念被捆綁的人，好像與他們同受捆綁；也要顧念遭苦害的人，因為自己也在肉身之內。
13:4|ASV|Let marriage be had in honor among all, and let the bed be undefiled: for fornicators and adulterers God will judge.
13:4|Darby|[Let] marriage [be held] every way in honour, and the bed  [be] undefiled; for fornicators and adulterers will God judge.
13:4|KJV|Marriage is honourable in all, and the bed undefiled: but whoremongers and adulterers God will judge.
13:4<version name="WYC">Wedding <i>is</i> in all things honourable, and [the] bed unwemmed [and the bed undefouled]; for God shall deem fornicators and adulterers.</version>
13:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|婚姻當在眾人中間受尊重，床也不可污穢，因為淫亂和姦淫的人，神必審判。
13:5|ASV|Be ye free from the love of money; content with such things as ye have: for himself hath said, I will in no wise fail thee, neither will I in any wise forsake thee.
13:5|Darby|[Let your] conversation [be] without love of money,  satisfied with [your] present circumstances; for *he* has said,  I will not leave thee, neither will I forsake thee.
13:5|KJV|Let your conversation be without covetousness; and be content with such things as ye have: for he hath said, I will never leave thee, nor forsake thee.
13:5<version name="WYC">Be <i>your</i> manners without covetousness, satisfied with present things [satisfied with things being]; for he said, I shall not leave thee, neither forsake,</version>
13:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們生活為人不可貪愛錢財，要以現有的為足；因為主曾說，“我絕不撇下你，也絕不丟棄你。”
13:6|ASV|So that with good courage we say, The Lord is my helper; I will not fear: What shall man do unto me?
13:6|Darby|So that, taking courage, we may say, The Lord [is] my  helper, and I will not be afraid: what will man do unto me?
13:6|KJV|So that we may boldly say, The Lord is my helper, and I will not fear what man shall do unto me.
13:6|WYC|so that we say trustily [so that we trustily say], The Lord is an helper to me; I shall not dread, what a man shall do to me.
13:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我們放膽說，“主是幫助我的，我必不懼怕；人能把我怎麼樣？”
13:7|ASV|Remember them that had the rule over you, men that spake unto you the word of God; and considering the issue of their life, imitate their faith.
13:7|Darby|Remember your leaders who have spoken to you the word of  God; and considering the issue of their conversation, imitate  their faith.
13:7|KJV|Remember them which have the rule over you, who have spoken unto you the word of God: whose faith follow, considering the end of their conversation.
13:7<version name="WYC">Have ye mind of your sovereigns, that have spoken to you the word of God; of whom behold ye the going out of living, and follow ye the faith of them, <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23265a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
13:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|要記念那些帶領你們，對你們講過神話語的人，要效法他們的信心，留心看他們為人的結局。
13:8|ASV|Jesus Christ is the same yesterday and to-day, yea and for ever.
13:8|Darby|Jesus Christ [is] the same yesterday, and to-day, and to  the ages [to come].
13:8|KJV|Jesus Christ the same yesterday, and to day, and for ever.
13:8<version name="WYC">Jesus Christ, yesterday, and to day, he <i>is</i> also into worlds.</version>
13:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶穌基督，昨日、今日、直到永遠，是一樣的。
13:9|ASV|Be not carried away by divers and strange teachings: for it is good that the heart be established by grace; not by meats, wherein they that occupied themselves were not profited.
13:9|Darby|Be not carried away with various and strange doctrines; for  [it is] good that the heart be confirmed with grace, not meats;  those who have walked in which have not been profited by  [them].
13:9|KJV|Be not carried about with divers and strange doctrines. For it is a good thing that the heart be established with grace; not with meats, which have not profited them that have been occupied therein.
13:9|WYC|Do not ye be led away with diverse and strange teachings.  For it is best to stable the heart with grace, not with meats, which profited not to men wandering in them.
13:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們不要被各樣怪異的教訓帶入歧途，因為心靠恩典得堅固，不靠祭物作食物，纔是好的；那靠祭物作食物而行的，從來沒有得著益處。
13:10|ASV|We have an altar, whereof they have no right to eat that serve the tabernacle.
13:10|Darby|We have an altar of which they have no right to eat who  serve the tabernacle;
13:10|KJV|We have an altar, whereof they have no right to eat which serve the tabernacle.
13:10<version name="WYC">We have an altar, of which they that serve to the tabernacle, have not power [have not power, <i>or leave</i>,] to eat.</version>
13:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們有一祭壇，其上的祭物，是那些事奉帳幕的人沒有權利喫的。
13:11|ASV|For the bodies of those beasts whose blood is brought into the holy place by the high priest as an offering for sin, are burned without the camp.
13:11|Darby|for of those beasts whose blood is carried [as sacrifices  for sin] into the [holy of] holies by the high priest, of these  the bodies are burned outside the camp.
13:11|KJV|For the bodies of those beasts, whose blood is brought into the sanctuary by the high priest for sin, are burned without the camp.
13:11|WYC|For of which beasts the blood is borne in for sin into holy things by the bishop, the bodies of them be burnt without the castles.
13:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|原來祭牲的血，由大祭司為著罪帶進至聖所，祭牲的身體，被燒在營外。
13:12|ASV|Wherefore Jesus also, that he might sanctify the people through his own blood, suffered without the gate.
13:12|Darby|Wherefore also Jesus, that he might sanctify the people by  his own blood, suffered without the gate:
13:12|KJV|Wherefore Jesus also, that he might sanctify the people with his own blood, suffered without the gate.
13:12|WYC|For which thing Jesus, that he should hallow the people by his blood, suffered without the gate.
13:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以耶穌為要藉自己的血聖別百姓，也就在城門外受苦。
13:13|ASV|Let us therefore go forth unto him without the camp, bearing his reproach.
13:13|Darby|therefore let us go forth to him without the camp, bearing  his reproach:
13:13|KJV|Let us go forth therefore unto him without the camp, bearing his reproach.
13:13<version name="WYC">Therefore go we out to him without the castles, bearing his reproof. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23271b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
13:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我們也當出到營外就了祂去，忍受祂所受的凌辱。
13:14|ASV|For we have not here an abiding city, but we seek after the city which is to come.
13:14|Darby|for we have not here an abiding city, but we seek the  coming one.
13:14|KJV|For here have we no continuing city, but we seek one to come.
13:14<version name="WYC">For we have not here a city dwelling, but we seek a city to coming. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23272c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup></version>
13:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們在這裡本沒有常存的城，乃是尋求那要來的城。
13:15|ASV|Through him then let us offer up a sacrifice of praise to God continually, that is, the fruit of lips which make confession to his name.
13:15|Darby|By him therefore let us offer [the] sacrifice of praise  continually to God, that is, [the] fruit of [the] lips  confessing his name.
13:15|KJV|By him therefore let us offer the sacrifice of praise to God continually, that is, the fruit of our lips giving thanks to his name.
13:15|WYC|Therefore by him offer we a sacrifice of praising evermore to God [By him therefore offer we an host of praising allway to God], that is to say, the fruit of lips acknowledging to his name.
13:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我們應當藉著耶穌，常常向神獻上讚美的祭，這就是承認主名之嘴脣的果子。
13:16|ASV|But to do good and to communicate forget not: for with such sacrifices God is well pleased.
13:16|Darby|But of doing good and communicating [of your substance] be  not forgetful, for with such sacrifices God is well pleased.
13:16|KJV|But to do good and to communicate forget not: for with such sacrifices God is well pleased.
13:16<version name="WYC">And do not ye forget well-doing, and communing; for by such sacrifices God is well served <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23274d" title="See footnote d">d</a>]</sup>.</version>
13:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只是不可忘記行善和供輸，因為這樣的祭物是神所喜悅的。
13:17|ASV|Obey them that have the rule over you, and submit to them: for they watch in behalf of your souls, as they that shall give account; that they may do this with joy, and not with grief: for this were unprofitable for you.
13:17|Darby|Obey your leaders, and be submissive; for *they* watch  over your souls as those that shall give account; that they may  do this with joy, and not groaning, for this [would be]  unprofitable for you.
13:17|KJV|Obey them that have the rule over you, and submit yourselves: for they watch for your souls, as they that must give account, that they may do it with joy, and not with grief: for that is unprofitable for you.
13:17<version name="WYC">Obey ye to your sovereigns, and be ye subject to them; for they perfectly wake <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23275e" title="See footnote e">e</a>]</sup>, as to yielding reason for your souls, that they do this thing with joy, and not sorrowing; for this thing speedeth not to you.</version>
13:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要信從那些帶領你們的，且要服從；因他們為你們的魂儆醒，好像要交賬的人；你們要使他們歡樂的作這事，不至歎息；若歎息，就與你們無益了。
13:18|ASV|Pray for us: for we are persuaded that we have a good conscience, desiring to live honorably in all things.
13:18|Darby|Pray for us: for we persuade ourselves that we have a good  conscience, in all things desirous to walk rightly.
13:18|KJV|Pray for us: for we trust we have a good conscience, in all things willing to live honestly.
13:18|WYC|Pray ye for us, and we trust that we have good conscience in all things, willing to live well.
13:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|請你們為我們禱告，因我們深信自己良心無虧，願意凡事都行得好。
13:19|ASV|And I exhort you the more exceedingly to do this, that I may be restored to you the sooner.
13:19|Darby|But I much more beseech [you] to do this, that I may the  more quickly be restored to you.
13:19|KJV|But I beseech you the rather to do this, that I may be restored to you the sooner.
13:19<version name="WYC">Moreover I beseech you to do [<i>this thing</i>], that I be restored the sooner to you.</version>
13:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我更加求你們為我禱告，使我能快些回到你們那裡去。
13:20|ASV|Now the God of peace, who brought again from the dead the great shepherd of the sheep with the blood of an eternal covenant, even our Lord Jesus,
13:20|Darby|But the God of peace, who brought again from among [the]  dead our Lord Jesus, the great shepherd of the sheep, in [the  power of the] blood of [the] eternal covenant,
13:20|KJV|Now the God of peace, that brought again from the dead our Lord Jesus, that great shepherd of the sheep, through the blood of the everlasting covenant,
13:20<version name="WYC">And God of peace, that led out from death the great shepherd of sheep, in the blood of [the] everlasting testament, our Lord Jesus Christ, <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23278f" title="See footnote f">f</a>]</sup></version>
13:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但願平安的神，就是那憑永約之血，領群羊的大牧人我們的主耶穌，從死人中上來的，
13:21|ASV|make you perfect in every good thing to do his will, working in us that which is well-pleasing in his sight, through Jesus Christ; to whom be the glory for ever and ever. Amen.
13:21|Darby|perfect you in every good work to the doing of his will,  doing in you what is pleasing before him through Jesus Christ;  to whom [be] glory for the ages of ages. Amen.
13:21|KJV|Make you perfect in every good work to do his will, working in you that which is wellpleasing in his sight, through Jesus Christ; to whom be glory for ever and ever. Amen.
13:21<version name="WYC">shape you in all good thing, that ye do the will of him; and he do in you that thing that shall please before him, by Jesus Christ <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23279g" title="See footnote g">g</a>]</sup>, to whom be glory into worlds of worlds.  Amen.</version>
13:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在各樣善事上成全你們，好實行祂的旨意；祂是在我們裡面，藉著耶穌基督，行祂看為可喜悅的事。願榮耀歸與祂，直到永永遠遠。阿們。
13:22|ASV|But I exhort you, brethren, bear with the word of exhortation, for I have written unto you in few words.
13:22|Darby|But I beseech you, brethren, bear the word of exhortation,  for it is but in few words that I have written to you.
13:22|KJV|And I beseech you, brethren, suffer the word of exhortation: for I have written a letter unto you in few words.
13:22|WYC|And, brethren, I pray you, that ye suffer a word of solace; for by full few things I have written to you [and soothly by few I have written to you].
13:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，我懇求你們容納這勸勉的話，因我不過是簡短的寫給你們。
13:23|ASV|Know ye that our brother Timothy hath been set at liberty; with whom, if he come shortly, I will see you.
13:23|Darby|Know that our brother Timotheus is set at liberty; with  whom, if he should come soon, I will see you.
13:23|KJV|Know ye that our brother Timothy is set at liberty; with whom, if he come shortly, I will see you.
13:23|WYC|Know ye our brother Timothy, that is sent forth, with whom if he shall come more hastily, I shall see you.
13:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們該知道，我們的弟兄提摩太已經釋放了；他若快來，我必同他去見你們。
13:24|ASV|Salute all them that have the rule over you, and all the saints. They of Italy salute you.
13:24|Darby|Salute all your leaders, and all the saints. They from  Italy salute you.
13:24|KJV|Salute all them that have the rule over you, and all the saints. They of Italy salute you.
13:24|WYC|Greet ye well all your sovereigns, and all holy men [Greet well all your provosts, and all saints].  The brethren of Italy greet you well.
13:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|請問帶領你們的諸位和眾聖徒安。從義大利來的人也問你們安。
13:25<version name="ASV">Grace be with you all. Amen. </p><p /><br /></version>
13:25<version name="Darby">Grace [be] with you all. Amen. </p><p /><br /></version>
13:25<version name="KJV">Grace be with you all. Amen.</p><p /><br /></version>
13:25<version name="WYC">The grace of God <i>be</i> with you all.  Amen. [Grace with you.  Amen.]</version>
13:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願恩典與你們眾人同在。阿們。
