1:1|Darby|The word of Jehovah that came unto Hosea, the son of Beeri,  in the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, Hezekiah, kings of Judah,  and in the days of Jeroboam the son of Joash, king of Israel.
1:1|KJV|The word of the LORD that came unto Hosea, the son of Beeri, in the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam the son of Joash, king of Israel.
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當烏西雅、約坦、亞哈斯、希西家作猶大王，約阿施的兒子耶羅波安作以色列王的日子，耶和華的話臨到備利的兒子何西阿。
1:2|Darby|The beginning of the word of Jehovah through Hosea. And  Jehovah said to Hosea, Go, take unto thee a wife of whoredoms,  and children of whoredoms; for the land is entirely given up to  whoredom, away from Jehovah.
1:2|KJV|The beginning of the word of the LORD by Hosea. And the LORD said to Hosea, Go, take unto thee a wife of whoredoms and children of whoredoms: for the land hath committed great whoredom, departing from the LORD.
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華初次與何西阿說話，對他說，你去娶淫婦為妻，也收那從淫亂所生的兒女，因為這地大行淫亂，離棄耶和華。
1:3|Darby|And he went and took Gomer the daughter of Diblaim; and she  conceived and bore him a son.
1:3|KJV|So he went and took Gomer the daughter of Diblaim; which conceived, and bare him a son.
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是何西阿去娶了滴拉音的女兒歌篾；這婦人懷孕，給他生了一個兒子。
1:4|Darby|And Jehovah said unto him, Call his name Jizreel; for yet a  little, and I will visit the blood of Jizreel upon the house of  Jehu, and will cause the kingdom of the house of Israel to  cease.
1:4|KJV|And the LORD said unto him, Call his name Jezreel; for yet a little while, and I will avenge the blood of Jezreel upon the house of Jehu, and will cause to cease the kingdom of the house of Israel.
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華對何西阿說，給他起名叫耶斯列，因為再過片時，我必追討耶戶家在耶斯列殺人流血的罪，也必使以色列家的國滅絕。
1:5|Darby|And it shall come to pass in that day, that I will break the  bow of Israel in the valley of Jizreel.
1:5|KJV|And it shall come to pass at that day, that I will break the bow of Israel, in the valley of Jezreel.
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|到那日，我必在耶斯列山谷折斷以色列的弓。
1:6|Darby|And she conceived again, and bore a daughter. And he said  unto him, Call her name Lo-ruhamah; for I will no more have  mercy upon the house of Israel, so that I should pardon them.
1:6|KJV|And she conceived again, and bare a daughter. And God said unto him, Call her name Loruhamah: for I will no more have mercy upon the house of Israel; but I will utterly take them away.
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|歌篾又懷孕生了一個女兒；耶和華對何西阿說，給她起名叫羅路哈瑪，因為我必不再憐恤以色列家，決不赦免他們。
1:7|Darby|But I will have mercy upon the house of Judah, and will save  them by Jehovah their God; and I will not save them by bow, or  by sword, or by battle, [or] by horses, or by horsemen.
1:7|KJV|But I will have mercy upon the house of Judah, and will save them by the LORD their God, and will not save them by bow, nor by sword, nor by battle, by horses, nor by horsemen.
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我卻要憐恤猶大家，我必憑耶和華他們的神拯救他們，必不憑弓、刀、爭戰、馬匹、與馬兵拯救他們。
1:8|Darby|And she weaned Lo-ruhamah; and she conceived and bore a son;
1:8|KJV|Now when she had weaned Loruhamah, she conceived, and bare a son.
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|歌篾給羅路哈瑪斷奶以後，又懷孕生了一個兒子。
1:9|Darby|and he said, Call his name Lo-ammi; for ye are not my  people, and I will not be for you.
1:9|KJV|Then said God, Call his name Loammi: for ye are not my people, and I will not be your God.
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華說，給他起名叫羅阿米，因為你們不是我的子民，我也不屬於你們。
1:10|Darby|Yet the number of the children of Israel shall be as the  sand of the sea which cannot be measured or numbered; and it  shall come to pass, [that] in the place where it was said unto  them, Ye are not my people, it shall be said unto them, Sons of  the living ???’???’?????????God.
1:10|KJV|Yet the number of the children of Israel shall be as the sand of the sea, which cannot be measured nor numbered; and it shall come to pass, that in the place where it was said unto them, Ye are not my people, there it shall be said unto them, Ye are the sons of the living God.
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而以色列的人數必如海沙，不可量，不可數；從前在甚麼地方對他們說，你們不是我的子民，將來在那堨硃鴷L們說，你們是活神的兒子。
1:11<version name="Darby">And the children of Judah and the children of Israel shall  be gathered together, and they shall appoint themselves one  head, and shall go up out of the land: for great is the day of  Jizreel. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:11<version name="KJV">Then shall the children of Judah and the children of Israel be gathered together, and appoint themselves one head, and they shall come up out of the land: for great shall be the day of Jezreel.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|猶大人和以色列人必一同聚集，為自己立一個首領，從這地上去，因為耶斯列的日子必為大日。
2:1|Darby|Say unto your brethren Ammi; and to your sisters, Ruhamah.
2:1|KJV|Say ye unto your brethren, Ammi; and to your sisters, Ruhamah.
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要對你們的弟兄說，阿米；要對你們的姊妹說，路哈瑪。
2:2|Darby|Plead with your mother, plead; for she is not my wife,  neither am I her husband: and let her put away her whoredoms  from her face, and her adulteries from between her breasts;
2:2|KJV|Plead with your mother, plead: for she is not my wife, neither am I her husband: let her therefore put away her whoredoms out of her sight, and her adulteries from between her breasts;
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要與你們的母親大大爭辯，因為她不是我的妻子，我也不是她的丈夫；叫她除掉臉上的淫亂，和胸間的姦淫，
2:3|Darby|lest I strip her naked, and set her as in the day that she  was born, and make her as a wilderness, and set her as a dry  land, and slay her with thirst.
2:3|KJV|Lest I strip her naked, and set her as in the day that she was born, and make her as a wilderness, and set her like a dry land, and slay her with thirst.
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|免得我剝去她的衣服，使她赤身像纔生的日子一樣，使她如曠野，如乾旱之地，以乾渴殺死她。
2:4|Darby|And I will not have mercy upon her children; for they are  the children of whoredoms.
2:4|KJV|And I will not have mercy upon her children; for they be the children of whoredoms.
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必不憐恤她的兒女，因為他們是從淫亂生的兒女。
2:5|Darby|For their mother hath played the harlot; she that conceived  them hath done shamefully: for she said, I will go after my  lovers, that give [me] my bread and my water, my wool and my  flax, mine oil and my drink.
2:5|KJV|For their mother hath played the harlot: she that conceived them hath done shamefully: for she said, I will go after my lovers, that give me my bread and my water, my wool and my flax, mine oil and my drink.
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們的母親行了淫亂，懷他們的母作了可羞恥的事，因為她說，我要隨從所愛的人，他們給我餅和水，羊毛和麻，油和酒。
2:6|Darby|Therefore behold, I will hedge up thy way with thorns; and I  will fence [her] in with a wall, that she shall not find her  paths.
2:6|KJV|Therefore, behold, I will hedge up thy way with thorns, and make a wall, that she shall not find her paths.
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此，我必用荊棘堵塞她的道，築牆擋住她，使她找不著路。
2:7|Darby|And she shall pursue after her lovers, and shall not  overtake them; and she shall seek them, and shall not find  them: and she shall say, I will go and return to my first  husband, for then was it better with me than now.
2:7|KJV|And she shall follow after her lovers, but she shall not overtake them; and she shall seek them, but shall not find them: then shall she say, I will go and return to my first husband; for then was it better with me than now.
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|她必追隨所愛的人，卻追不上，她必尋找他們，卻尋不見；便說，我要歸回前夫，因我那時的光景比如今還好。
2:8|Darby|And she did not know that I had given her the corn and the  new wine and the oil, and had multiplied to her the silver and  gold, which they employed for Baal.
2:8|KJV|For she did not know that I gave her corn, and wine, and oil, and multiplied her silver and gold, which they prepared for Baal.
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|她不知道是我給她五穀、新酒和新油；又加增她的金銀；他們卻用於巴力。
2:9|Darby|Therefore will I return, and take away my corn in the time  thereof, and my new wine in its season, and will withdraw my  wool and my flax which should have covered her nakedness.
2:9|KJV|Therefore will I return, and take away my corn in the time thereof, and my wine in the season thereof, and will recover my wool and my flax given to cover her nakedness.
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此到了收割的時候，出酒的季節，我必將我的五穀新酒收回，也必將她應當遮體的羊毛和麻奪去。
2:10|Darby|And now will I discover her impiety in the sight of her  lovers, and none shall deliver her out of my hand.
2:10|KJV|And now will I discover her lewdness in the sight of her lovers, and none shall deliver her out of mine hand.
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|如今我必在她所愛的人眼前，顯露她的淫蕩，必無人能救她脫離我的手。
2:11|Darby|And I will cause all her mirth to cease: her feasts, her  new moons, and her sabbaths! and all her solemnities.
2:11|KJV|I will also cause all her mirth to cease, her feast days, her new moons, and her sabbaths, and all her solemn feasts.
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必使她一切的歡樂，她的節期、月朔、安息日、並她所定一切的會，都止息了。
2:12|Darby|And I will make desolate her vine and her fig-tree, whereof  she hath said, These are my rewards which my lovers have given  me; and I will make them a forest, and the beasts of the field  shall eat them.
2:12|KJV|And I will destroy her vines and her fig trees, whereof she hath said, These are my rewards that my lovers have given me: and I will make them a forest, and the beasts of the field shall eat them.
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我也必使她的葡萄樹和無花果樹荒蕪，就是她說，這是我所愛的人給我為代價的；我必使這些樹變為叢林，為田野的走獸所喫。
2:13|Darby|And I will visit upon her the days of the Baals, wherein  she burned incense to them, and decked herself with her rings  and jewels, and went after her lovers, and forgot me, saith  Jehovah.
2:13|KJV|And I will visit upon her the days of Baalim, wherein she burned incense to them, and she decked herself with her earrings and her jewels, and she went after her lovers, and forgat me, saith the LORD.
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必在她身上追討她素日給諸巴力燒香的罪，那時她佩帶鼻環和珠寶，隨從她所愛的人，卻忘記了我；這是耶和華說的。
2:14|Darby|Therefore behold, I will allure her, and bring her into the  wilderness, and speak to her heart.
2:14|KJV|Therefore, behold, I will allure her, and bring her into the wilderness, and speak comfortably unto her.
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此我必誘導她，領她到曠野，對她的心說話；
2:15|Darby|And I will give her her vineyards from thence, and the  valley of Achor for a door of hope; and she shall sing there,  as in the days of her youth and as in the day when she came up  out of the land of Egypt.
2:15|KJV|And I will give her her vineyards from thence, and the valley of Achor for a door of hope: and she shall sing there, as in the days of her youth, and as in the day when she came up out of the land of Egypt.
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|從那塈琤祭蝳o葡萄園，又賜她亞割谷作為指望的門；她必在那媕麥n，與她幼年的日子一樣，與她從埃及地上來的日子相同。
2:16|Darby|And it shall be in that day, saith Jehovah, [that] thou  shalt call me, My husband, and shalt call me no more, Baali;
2:16|KJV|And it shall be at that day, saith the LORD, that thou shalt call me Ishi; and shalt call me no more Baali.
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華說，那日你必稱呼我：我的丈夫，不再稱呼我：巴力。
2:17|Darby|for I will take away the names of the Baals out of her  mouth, and they shall no more be remembered by their name.
2:17|KJV|For I will take away the names of Baalim out of her mouth, and they shall no more be remembered by their name.
2:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我必從她口中除掉諸巴力的名號，他們的名號不再被記念。
2:18|Darby|And I will make a covenant for them in that day with the  beasts of the field, and with the fowl of the heavens, and the  creeping things of the ground; and I will break bow and sword  and battle out of the land; and I will make them to lie down  safely.
2:18|KJV|And in that day will I make a covenant for them with the beasts of the field and with the fowls of heaven, and with the creeping things of the ground: and I will break the bow and the sword and the battle out of the earth, and will make them to lie down safely.
2:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當那日我必為我的民，與田野的走獸、空中的飛鳥、並地上的爬物立約；又必從那地折斷弓刀，止息爭戰，使他們安然躺臥。
2:19|Darby|And I will betroth thee unto me for ever; and I will  betroth thee unto me in righteousness, and in judgment, and in  loving-kindness, and in mercies;
2:19|KJV|And I will betroth thee unto me for ever; yea, I will betroth thee unto me in righteousness, and in judgment, and in lovingkindness, and in mercies.
2:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必聘你永遠歸我為妻，以公義和公平，以慈愛和憐恤聘你歸我；
2:20|Darby|and I will betroth thee unto me in faithfulness: and thou  shalt know Jehovah.
2:20|KJV|I will even betroth thee unto me in faithfulness: and thou shalt know the LORD.
2:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|也必以信實聘你歸我，你就必認識我耶和華。
2:21|Darby|And it shall come to pass in that day, I will hear, saith  Jehovah, I will hear the heavens, and they shall hear the  earth;
2:21|KJV|And it shall come to pass in that day, I will hear, saith the LORD, I will hear the heavens, and they shall hear the earth;
2:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華說，那日我必應允；我必應允天，天必應允地，
2:22|Darby|and the earth shall hear the corn, and the new wine, and  the oil; and they shall hear Jizreel.
2:22|KJV|And the earth shall hear the corn, and the wine, and the oil; and they shall hear Jezreel.
2:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|地必應允五穀、新酒和新油，這些必應允耶斯列民。
2:23<version name="Darby">And I will sow her unto me in the land; and I will have  mercy upon Lo-ruhamah; and I will say to Lo-ammi, Thou art my  people; and they shall say, My God. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:23<version name="KJV">And I will sow her unto me in the earth; and I will have mercy upon her that had not obtained mercy; and I will say to them which were not my people, Thou art my people; and they shall say, Thou art my God.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必將她播種在這地歸我，我必憐恤羅路哈瑪；我必對羅阿米說，你是我的民；他們必說，你是我的神。
3:1|Darby|And Jehovah said unto me, Go again, love a woman beloved of  a friend, and an adulteress, according to the love of Jehovah  for the children of Israel, though they turn to other gods, and  love raisin-cakes.
3:1|KJV|Then said the LORD unto me, Go yet, love a woman beloved of her friend, yet an adulteress, according to the love of the LORD toward the children of Israel, who look to other gods, and love flagons of wine.
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華對我說，你再去愛一個婦人，就是為她友伴所愛、卻又犯姦淫的，好像以色列人，雖然轉向別神，喜愛葡萄餅，耶和華還是愛他們。
3:2|Darby|So I bought her to me for fifteen silver [pieces], and for a  homer of barley, and a half-homer of barley.
3:2|KJV|So I bought her to me for fifteen pieces of silver, and for an homer of barley, and an half homer of barley:
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我便用十五錠銀子，一賀梅珥半大麥，買她歸我。
3:3|Darby|And I said unto her, Thou shalt abide for me many days; thou  shalt not play the harlot, and thou shalt not be [another]  man's, and I will also be for thee.
3:3|KJV|And I said unto her, Thou shalt abide for me many days; thou shalt not play the harlot, and thou shalt not be for another man: so will I also be for thee.
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我對她說，你當多日為我靜居，不可行淫亂，不可歸別人為妻；我向你也必這樣。
3:4|Darby|For the children of Israel shall abide many days without  king, and without prince, and without sacrifice, and without  statue, and without ephod and teraphim.
3:4|KJV|For the children of Israel shall abide many days without a king, and without a prince, and without a sacrifice, and without an image, and without an ephod, and without teraphim:
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為以色列人也必多日獨居，無君王，無首領，無祭祀，無柱像，無以弗得，無家中的神像。
3:5<version name="Darby">Afterwards shall the children of Israel return, and seek  Jehovah their God, and David their king; and shall turn with  fear toward Jehovah and toward his goodness, at the end of the  days. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:5<version name="KJV">Afterward shall the children of Israel return, and seek the LORD their God, and David their king; and shall fear the LORD and his goodness in the latter days.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|後來以色列人必歸回，尋求他們的神耶和華，和他們的王大衛；在末後的日子，必心存敬畏歸向耶和華，領受祂的美善。
4:1|Darby|Hear the word of Jehovah, ye children of Israel; for Jehovah  hath a controversy with the inhabitants of the land; for there  is no truth, nor goodness, nor knowledge of God in the land.
4:1|KJV|Hear the word of the LORD, ye children of Israel: for the LORD hath a controversy with the inhabitants of the land, because there is no truth, nor mercy, nor knowledge of God in the land.
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列人哪，你們當聽耶和華的話；耶和華要與這地的居民爭辯，因這地上無忠信，無恩慈，無人認識神。
4:2|Darby|Swearing, and lying, and killing, and stealing, and  committing adultery, -- they break out; and blood toucheth  blood.
4:2|KJV|By swearing, and lying, and killing, and stealing, and committing adultery, they break out, and blood toucheth blood.
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|卻有詛咒、欺騙、兇殺、偷盜、姦淫；他們行強暴，殺人流血接連不斷。
4:3|Darby|For this shall the land mourn, and every one that dwelleth  therein shall languish, with the beasts of the field, and with  the fowl of the heavens, yea, the fishes of the sea also shall  be taken away.
4:3|KJV|Therefore shall the land mourn, and every one that dwelleth therein shall languish, with the beasts of the field, and with the fowls of heaven; yea, the fishes of the sea also shall be taken away.
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此，這地悲哀，其中的一切居民、田野的獸、空中的鳥必都衰微，連海中的魚也必除去。
4:4|Darby|Yet let no man strive, and let no man reprove; for thy  people are as they that strive with the priest.
4:4|KJV|Yet let no man strive, nor reprove another: for thy people are as they that strive with the priest.
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而人都不必爭辯，也不必指責；因為你的民與那些跟祭司爭辯的人一樣。
4:5|Darby|And thou shalt stumble by day; and the prophet also shall  stumble with thee by night: and I will destroy thy mother.
4:5|KJV|Therefore shalt thou fall in the day, and the prophet also shall fall with thee in the night, and I will destroy thy mother.
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你必在日間絆跌，申言者也必在夜間與你一同絆跌；我必滅絕你的母親。
4:6|Darby|My people are destroyed for lack of knowledge; for thou hast  rejected knowledge, and I will reject thee, that thou shalt be  no priest to me; seeing thou hast forgotten the law of thy God,  I also will forget thy children.
4:6|KJV|My people are destroyed for lack of knowledge: because thou hast rejected knowledge, I will also reject thee, that thou shalt be no priest to me: seeing thou hast forgotten the law of thy God, I will also forget thy children.
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的民因無那樣的認識而滅絕；你棄掉那樣的認識，我也必棄掉你，使你不再給我作祭司；你既忘了你神的律法，我也必忘記你的兒女。
4:7|Darby|As they were multiplied, so they sinned against me: I will  change their glory into shame.
4:7|KJV|As they were increased, so they sinned against me: therefore will I change their glory into shame.
4:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祭司越發增多，就越發得罪我；我必使他們的榮耀變為羞辱。
4:8|Darby|They eat the sin of my people, and their soul longeth for  their iniquity.
4:8|KJV|They eat up the sin of my people, and they set their heart on their iniquity.
4:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們喫我民的贖罪祭，滿心願望我的民行罪孽。
4:9|Darby|And it shall be as the people so the priest; and I will  visit their ways upon them, and recompense to them their  doings;
4:9|KJV|And there shall be, like people, like priest: and I will punish them for their ways, and reward them their doings.
4:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|將來民如何，祭司也必如何；我必因他們所行的懲罰他們，照他們所作的報應他們。
4:10|Darby|and they shall eat, and not have enough; they shall commit  whoredom, and shall not increase: for they have left off taking  heed to Jehovah.
4:10|KJV|For they shall eat, and not have enough: they shall commit whoredom, and shall not increase: because they have left off to take heed to the LORD.
4:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們喫，卻不得飽；行淫，而不得增多；因為他們離棄耶和華，不遵從祂。
4:11|Darby|Fornication, and wine, and new wine take away the heart.
4:11|KJV|Whoredom and wine and new wine take away the heart.
4:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|淫亂和酒並新酒，奪去他們的心。
4:12|Darby|My people ask counsel of their stock, and their staff  declareth unto them; for the spirit of whoredoms causeth [them]  to err, and they have gone a whoring from under their God:
4:12|KJV|My people ask counsel at their stocks, and their staff declareth unto them: for the spirit of whoredoms hath caused them to err, and they have gone a whoring from under their God.
4:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的民求問木頭柱像，以為木杖能指示他們，因為淫亂的靈使他們失迷，他們就行淫離棄了他們的神。
4:13|Darby|they sacrifice upon the tops of the mountains, and burn  incense upon the hills, under oak and poplar and terebinth,  because the shade thereof is good; therefore your daughters  play the harlot and your daughters-in-law commit adultery.
4:13|KJV|They sacrifice upon the tops of the mountains, and burn incense upon the hills, under oaks and poplars and elms, because the shadow thereof is good: therefore your daughters shall commit whoredom, and your spouses shall commit adultery.
4:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們在各山頂獻祭，在各高岡的橡樹、楊樹、栗樹之下燒香，因為樹影美好。所以你們的女兒行淫亂，你們的新婦犯姦淫。
4:14|Darby|I will not punish your daughters when they play the harlot,  nor your daughters-in-law for their committing adultery; for  they themselves go aside with harlots, and they sacrifice with  prostitutes: and the people that doth not understand shall come  to ruin.
4:14|KJV|I will not punish your daughters when they commit whoredom, nor your spouses when they commit adultery: for themselves are separated with whores, and they sacrifice with harlots: therefore the people that doth not understand shall fall.
4:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們的女兒行淫亂，你們的新婦犯姦淫，我卻不懲罰她們；因為你們男人自己離群與娼妓同居，與妓女一同獻祭；這無知的民，必至傾倒。
4:15|Darby|Though thou, Israel, play the harlot, let not Judah  trespass; and come ye not unto Gilgal, neither go up to  Beth-aven, nor swear [As] Jehovah liveth!
4:15|KJV|Though thou, Israel, play the harlot, yet let not Judah offend; and come not ye unto Gilgal, neither go ye up to Bethaven, nor swear, The LORD liveth.
4:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列阿，你雖然行淫亂，猶大卻不可犯罪；不要往吉甲去，不要上到伯亞文，也不要指著永活的耶和華起誓。
4:16|Darby|For Israel is refractory as an untractable heifer; now will  Jehovah feed them as a lamb in a wide [pasture].
4:16|KJV|For Israel slideth back as a backsliding heifer: now the LORD will feed them as a lamb in a large place.
4:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為以色列倔強，猶如倔強的母牛；現在耶和華要牧放他們，如同牧放羊羔在寬闊之地麼？
4:17|Darby|-- Ephraim is joined to idols: leave him alone.
4:17|KJV|Ephraim is joined to idols: let him alone.
4:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以法蓮與偶像聯合，任憑他們罷。
4:18|Darby|Their drink is sour; they give themselves up to whoredom;  her great men passionately love [their] shame.
4:18|KJV|Their drink is sour: they have committed whoredom continually: her rulers with shame do love, Give ye.
4:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們的酒已經喝盡；他們放縱自己行淫，他們的官長最愛羞恥的事。
4:19<version name="Darby">The wind hath wrapped her up in its wings, and they shall  be ashamed because of their sacrifices. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:19<version name="KJV">The wind hath bound her up in her wings, and they shall be ashamed because of their sacrifices.</p><p /><br /></version>
4:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|風把他們裹在翅膀堙A他們必因所獻的祭蒙羞。
5:1|Darby|Hear this, ye priests; and hearken, ye house of Israel; and  give ear, O house of the king: for this judgment is for you;  for ye have been a snare at Mizpah, and a net spread upon  Tabor.
5:1|KJV|Hear ye this, O priests; and hearken, ye house of Israel; and give ye ear, O house of the king; for judgment is toward you, because ye have been a snare on Mizpah, and a net spread upon Tabor.
5:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|眾祭司阿，要聽這話；以色列家阿，要留心聽；王家阿，要側耳聽。審判要臨到你們，因你們曾是米斯巴的網羅，是他泊山上鋪張的網。
5:2|Darby|And they have plunged themselves in the corruption of  apostasy, but I will be a chastiser of them all.
5:2|KJV|And the revolters are profound to make slaughter, though I have been a rebuker of them all.
5:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|悖逆的人肆行殺戮，罪孽極深，我卻懲治他們眾人。
5:3|Darby|I know Ephraim, and Israel is not hid from me; for now,  Ephraim, thou hast committed whoredom; Israel is defiled.
5:3|KJV|I know Ephraim, and Israel is not hid from me: for now, O Ephraim, thou committest whoredom, and Israel is defiled.
5:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以法蓮為我所知，以色列不能向我隱藏；以法蓮哪，你行了淫亂，以色列被玷污了。
5:4|Darby|Their doings do not allow them to return unto their God; for  the spirit of whoredoms is in the midst of them, and they know  not Jehovah.
5:4|KJV|They will not frame their doings to turn unto their God: for the spirit of whoredoms is in the midst of them, and they have not known the LORD.
5:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們所行的不容他們歸向神；因有淫亂的靈在他們堶情A他們也不認識耶和華。
5:5|Darby|And Israel's pride doth testify to his face; and Israel and  Ephraim shall fall by their iniquity: Judah also shall fall  with them.
5:5|KJV|And the pride of Israel doth testify to his face: therefore shall Israel and Ephraim fall in their iniquity: Judah also shall fall with them.
5:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列的驕傲當面見證自己，以色列和以法蓮必因自己的罪孽絆跌；猶大也必與他們一同絆跌。
5:6|Darby|They shall go with their flocks and with their herds to seek  Jehovah; but they shall not find [him]: he hath withdrawn  himself from them.
5:6|KJV|They shall go with their flocks and with their herds to seek the LORD; but they shall not find him; he hath withdrawn himself from them.
5:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們必牽著牛羊去尋求耶和華，卻尋不見；祂已經退去離開他們。
5:7|Darby|They have dealt treacherously against Jehovah; for they have  begotten strange children: now shall the new moon devour them,  with their allotted possessions.
5:7|KJV|They have dealt treacherously against the LORD: for they have begotten strange children: now shall a month devour them with their portions.
5:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們向耶和華行事詭詐，因為他們生了私子；到了月朔，他們與他們所得的分必被吞滅。
5:8|Darby|Blow the horn in Gibeah, the trumpet in Ramah; cry aloud  [at] Beth-aven: behind thee, O Benjamin!
5:8|KJV|Blow ye the cornet in Gibeah, and the trumpet in Ramah: cry aloud at Bethaven, after thee, O Benjamin.
5:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們當在基比亞吹角，在拉瑪吹號，在伯亞文吹出大聲，說，便雅憫哪，當心你的後頭！
5:9|Darby|Ephraim shall be a desolation in the day of rebuke: among  the tribes of Israel have I made known that which is sure.
5:9|KJV|Ephraim shall be desolate in the day of rebuke: among the tribes of Israel have I made known that which shall surely be.
5:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在責罰的日子，以法蓮必變為荒場；我在以色列支派中，已指示確定必成的事。
5:10|Darby|The princes of Judah are become like them that remove the  landmark: I will pour out my wrath upon them like water.
5:10|KJV|The princes of Judah were like them that remove the bound: therefore I will pour out my wrath upon them like water.
5:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|猶大的首領如同挪移地界的人；我必將盛怒倒在他們身上，如水一樣。
5:11|Darby|Ephraim is oppressed, crushed in judgment, because in  selfwill he walked after the commandment [of man].
5:11|KJV|Ephraim is oppressed and broken in judgment, because he willingly walked after the commandment.
5:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以法蓮因定意隨從人的命令，就受欺壓，被審判壓碎。
5:12|Darby|And I will be unto Ephraim as a moth, and to the house of  Judah as rottenness.
5:12|KJV|Therefore will I be unto Ephraim as a moth, and to the house of Judah as rottenness.
5:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我向以法蓮如蛀蟲，向猶大家如朽木。
5:13|Darby|When Ephraim saw his sickness, and Judah his sore, then  went Ephraim to the Assyrian, and sent to king Jareb; but he  was unable to heal you, nor hath he removed your sore.
5:13|KJV|When Ephraim saw his sickness, and Judah saw his wound, then went Ephraim to the Assyrian, and sent to king Jareb: yet could he not heal you, nor cure you of your wound.
5:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以法蓮見自己有病，猶大見自己有傷，以法蓮就打發人往亞述去見耶雷布王；他卻不能醫治你們，你們的傷必不能離身。
5:14|Darby|For I will be unto Ephraim as a lion, and as a young lion  to the house of Judah. I, I will tear and go away; I will carry  off, and there shall be none to deliver.
5:14|KJV|For I will be unto Ephraim as a lion, and as a young lion to the house of Judah: I, even I, will tear and go away; I will take away, and none shall rescue him.
5:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必向以法蓮如獅子，向猶大家如少壯獅子。我必撕裂他們而去；我必奪去他們，無人搭救。
5:15<version name="Darby">I will go away, I will return to my place, till they  acknowledge their trespass, and seek my face: in their  affliction they will seek me early. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:15<version name="KJV">I will go and return to my place, till they acknowledge their offence, and seek my face: in their affliction they will seek me early.</p><p /><br /></version>
5:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我要去，回到我自己的地方，等他們承認自己的罪過，尋求我的面；他們在急難的時候，必切切的尋求我。
6:1|Darby|Come and let us return unto Jehovah: for he hath torn, and  he will heal us; he hath smitten, and he will bind us up.
6:1|KJV|Come, and let us return unto the LORD: for he hath torn, and he will heal us; he hath smitten, and he will bind us up.
6:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|來罷，我們歸向耶和華；祂撕裂我們，也必醫治；祂打傷我們，也必纏裹。
6:2|Darby|After two days will he revive us; on the third day he will  raise us up, and we shall live before his face;
6:2|KJV|After two days will he revive us: in the third day he will raise us up, and we shall live in his sight.
6:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|過兩天祂必使我們活過來，第三天祂必使我們興起，我們就在祂面前活著。
6:3|Darby|and we shall know, -- we shall follow on to know Jehovah:  his going forth is assured as the morning dawn; and he will  come unto us as the rain, as the latter rain which watereth the  earth.
6:3|KJV|Then shall we know, if we follow on to know the LORD: his going forth is prepared as the morning; and he shall come unto us as the rain, as the latter and former rain unto the earth.
6:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們務要認識耶和華，竭力追求認識祂；祂出現確定如晨光，祂必臨到我們像甘雨，像滋潤大地的春雨。
6:4|Darby|What shall I do unto thee, Ephraim? What shall I do unto  thee, Judah? For your goodness is as a morning cloud, and as  the dew that early passeth away.
6:4|KJV|O Ephraim, what shall I do unto thee? O Judah, what shall I do unto thee? for your goodness is as a morning cloud, and as the early dew it goeth away.
6:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主說，以法蓮哪，我可向你怎樣行呢？猶大阿，我可向你怎樣作呢？因為你們的慈愛如同早晨的雲霧，又如速散的甘露。
6:5|Darby|Therefore have I hewed [them] by the prophets; I have slain  them by the words of my mouth: and my judgment goeth forth as  the light.
6:5|KJV|Therefore have I hewed them by the prophets; I have slain them by the words of my mouth: and thy judgments are as the light that goeth forth.
6:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此，我藉申言者砍伐他們，以我口中的話殺戮他們，我的審判如光發出。
6:6|Darby|For I delight in loving-kindness, and not sacrifice; and the  knowledge of God more than burnt-offerings.
6:6|KJV|For I desired mercy, and not sacrifice; and the knowledge of God more than burnt offerings.
6:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我喜悅慈愛，不喜悅祭祀，喜悅認識神，勝於燔祭。
6:7|Darby|But they like Adam have transgressed the covenant: there  have they dealt treacherously against me.
6:7|KJV|But they like men have transgressed the covenant: there have they dealt treacherously against me.
6:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們卻如亞當背約，在那埵V我行事詭詐。
6:8|Darby|Gilead is a city of them that work iniquity; it is tracked  with blood.
6:8|KJV|Gilead is a city of them that work iniquity, and is polluted with blood.
6:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|基列是行罪孽之人的城，被血沾染。
6:9|Darby|And as troops of robbers lie in wait for a man, so the  company of priests murder in the way of Shechem; yea, they  commit lewdness.
6:9|KJV|And as troops of robbers wait for a man, so the company of priests murder in the way by consent: for they commit lewdness.
6:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|強盜成群，怎樣埋伏殺人；祭司結黨，也照樣在示劍的路上殺戮行邪惡。
6:10|Darby|In the house of Israel have I seen a horrible thing: the  whoredom of Ephraim is there; Israel is defiled.
6:10|KJV|I have seen an horrible thing in the house of Israel: there is the whoredom of Ephraim, Israel is defiled.
6:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在以色列家，我見了可怕的事：以法蓮在那埵陴]行；以色列玷污了自己。
6:11<version name="Darby">Also, for thee, Judah, is a harvest appointed, when I shall  turn again the captivity of my people. </p><p /><br /></version>
6:11<version name="KJV">Also, O Judah, he hath set an harvest for thee, when I returned the captivity of my people.</p><p /><br /></version>
6:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|猶大阿，我使被擄之民歸回的時候，必有為你所命定的收成。
7:1|Darby|When I would heal Israel, then the iniquity of Ephraim is  discovered, and the wickedness of Samaria: for they practise  falsehood; and the thief entereth in, [and] the troop of  robbers assaileth without.
7:1|KJV|When I would have healed Israel, then the iniquity of Ephraim was discovered, and the wickedness of Samaria: for they commit falsehood; and the thief cometh in, and the troop of robbers spoileth without.
7:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我想醫治以色列的時候，以法蓮的罪孽和撒瑪利亞的惡行就顯露出來；因為他們行事虛謊。內有賊人入室偷竊，外有強盜成群搶劫。
7:2|Darby|And they say not in their hearts [that] I remember all their  wickedness: now do their own doings encompass them; they are  before my face.
7:2|KJV|And they consider not in their hearts that I remember all their wickedness: now their own doings have beset them about; they are before my face.
7:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們心堥瓣˙﹛A我記得他們的一切惡。他們所行的現在纏繞他們，都在我面前。
7:3|Darby|They make the king glad with their wickedness, and the  princes with their lies.
7:3|KJV|They make the king glad with their wickedness, and the princes with their lies.
7:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們以邪惡使君王歡喜，以謊言使首領喜樂。
7:4|Darby|They all practise adultery, as an oven heated by the baker:  he ceaseth from stirring [the fire] after he hath kneaded the  dough, until it be leavened.
7:4|KJV|They are all adulterers, as an oven heated by the baker, who ceaseth from raising after he hath kneaded the dough, until it be leavened.
7:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們都是行姦淫的，像火爐被烤餅者燒熱：從摶麵到發麵的時候，他暫不使火發旺。
7:5|Darby|In the day of our king, the princes made themselves sick  with the heat of wine: he stretched out his hand to scorners.
7:5|KJV|In the day of our king the princes have made him sick with bottles of wine; he stretched out his hand with scorners.
7:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在我們王宴樂的日子，首領因酒的烈性成病；王與褻慢人拉手。
7:6|Darby|For they have applied their heart like an oven to their  lying in wait: their baker sleepeth all the night; in the  morning it burneth like a flaming fire.
7:6|KJV|For they have made ready their heart like an oven, whiles they lie in wait: their baker sleepeth all the night; in the morning it burneth as a flaming fire.
7:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們埋伏的時候，心中熱如火爐：就如烤餅者整夜睡臥，到了早晨，火爐燒旺，火氣炎炎。
7:7|Darby|They are all hot as an oven, and devour their judges; all  their kings are fallen: there is none among them that calleth  unto me.
7:7|KJV|They are all hot as an oven, and have devoured their judges; all their kings are fallen: there is none among them that calleth unto me.
7:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|眾人也熱如火爐，吞滅他們的審判官；他們的君王都仆倒而死；他們中間無一人呼求我。
7:8|Darby|Ephraim, he mixeth himself with the peoples; Ephraim is a  cake not turned.
7:8|KJV|Ephraim, he hath mixed himself among the people; Ephraim is a cake not turned.
7:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以法蓮與列邦人攙雜；以法蓮是沒有翻過的餅。
7:9|Darby|Strangers have devoured his strength, and he knoweth [it]  not; yea, gray hairs are here and there upon him, and he  knoweth [it] not.
7:9|KJV|Strangers have devoured his strength, and he knoweth it not: yea, gray hairs are here and there upon him, yet he knoweth not.
7:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|外邦人吞喫他力量得來的，他自己卻不知道；滿頭白髮，他自己也不曉得。
7:10|Darby|And the pride of Israel testifieth to his face; and they do  not return to Jehovah their God, nor seek him for all this.
7:10|KJV|And the pride of Israel testifieth to his face: and they do not return to the LORD their God, nor seek him for all this.
7:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列的驕傲當面見證自己；雖遭遇這一切，他們仍不歸向耶和華他們的神，也不尋求祂。
7:11|Darby|And Ephraim is become like a silly dove without  understanding: they call to Egypt, they go to Assyria.
7:11|KJV|Ephraim also is like a silly dove without heart: they call to Egypt, they go to Assyria.
7:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以法蓮好像鴿子愚蠢無知：他們呼求埃及，投奔亞述。
7:12|Darby|When they go, I will spread my net upon them; I will bring  them down as the fowl of the heavens; I will chastise them,  according as their assembly hath heard.
7:12|KJV|When they shall go, I will spread my net upon them; I will bring them down as the fowls of the heaven; I will chastise them, as their congregation hath heard.
7:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們去的時候，我必將我的網撒在他們身上；我要打下他們，如同空中的鳥；我必按他們會眾所聽見的，管教他們。
7:13|Darby|Woe unto them! for they have wandered from me; destruction  unto them! for they have transgressed against me. And I would  redeem them; but they speak lies against me.
7:13|KJV|Woe unto them! for they have fled from me: destruction unto them! because they have transgressed against me: though I have redeemed them, yet they have spoken lies against me.
7:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們有禍了！因他們飄離了我。他們必遭毀滅，因他們違背我。我雖要救贖他們，他們卻向我說謊。
7:14|Darby|And they cried not unto me in their heart, when they howled  upon their beds; they assemble themselves for corn and new  wine; they have turned aside from me.
7:14|KJV|And they have not cried unto me with their heart, when they howled upon their beds: they assemble themselves for corn and wine, and they rebel against me.
7:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們心中並不哀求我，乃在床上呼號。他們為求五穀新酒聚集，仍然悖逆我。
7:15|Darby|I have indeed trained, I have strengthened their arms, but  they imagine mischief against me.
7:15|KJV|Though I have bound and strengthened their arms, yet do they imagine mischief against me.
7:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我雖訓練他們，堅固他們的膀臂，他們竟圖謀惡事抗拒我。
7:16<version name="Darby">They return, [but] not to the [Most] High: they are like a  deceitful bow. Their princes shall fall by the sword for the  rage of their tongue: this shall be their derision in the land  of Egypt. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:16<version name="KJV">They return, but not to the most High: they are like a deceitful bow: their princes shall fall by the sword for the rage of their tongue: this shall be their derision in the land of Egypt.</p><p /><br /></version>
7:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們歸向，卻不歸向至上者；他們如同詭詐的弓。他們的首領，必因舌頭的狂傲倒在刀下。這在埃及地必為人所譏笑。
8:1|Darby|Set the trumpet to thy mouth. [He cometh] as an eagle  against the house of Jehovah, because they have transgressed my  covenant, and rebelled against my law.
8:1|KJV|Set the trumpet to thy mouth. He shall come as an eagle against the house of the LORD, because they have transgressed my covenant, and trespassed against my law.
8:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你用口吹角罷！敵人如鷹來攻打耶和華的家，因為這民違背了我的約，干犯了我的律法。
8:2|Darby|They shall cry unto me, My God, we know thee; [we], Israel.
8:2|KJV|Israel shall cry unto me, My God, we know thee.
8:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們必呼叫我說，我的神阿，我們以色列認識你了。
8:3|Darby|Israel hath cast off good: the enemy shall pursue him.
8:3|KJV|Israel hath cast off the thing that is good: the enemy shall pursue him.
8:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列丟棄良善，仇敵必追逼他。
8:4|Darby|They have set up kings, but not by me; they have made  princes, and I knew it not; of their silver and their gold have  they made them idols, that they may be cut off.
8:4|KJV|They have set up kings, but not by me: they have made princes, and I knew it not: of their silver and their gold have they made them idols, that they may be cut off.
8:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們立君王，卻不是由於我；他們立首領，我卻不承認。他們用金銀為自己製造偶像，以致被剪除。
8:5|Darby|Thy calf, O Samaria, hath cast [thee] off; mine anger is  kindled against them: how long will they be incapable of  purity?
8:5|KJV|Thy calf, O Samaria, hath cast thee off; mine anger is kindled against them: how long will it be ere they attain to innocency?
8:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|撒瑪利亞阿，你的牛犢已經丟棄你！我的怒氣向拜牛犢的人發作。他們到幾時纔能無罪呢？
8:6|Darby|For from Israel is this also: -- a workman made it, and it  is no God: for the calf of Samaria shall be [broken in] pieces.
8:6|KJV|For from Israel was it also: the workman made it; therefore it is not God: but the calf of Samaria shall be broken in pieces.
8:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這牛犢竟然出於以色列！是匠人所造的，並不是神；撒瑪利亞的牛犢，必被打碎。
8:7|Darby|For they have sown the wind, and they shall reap the  whirlwind: it hath no stalk; should it sprout, it would yield  no meal; if so be it yield, strangers shall swallow it up.
8:7|KJV|For they have sown the wind, and they shall reap the whirlwind: it hath no stalk; the bud shall yield no meal: if so be it yield, the strangers shall swallow it up.
8:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們所種的是風，所收的是旋風。所種的不成禾稼，就是發苗也產不出麵，即便產出，外人也必吞喫。
8:8|Darby|Israel is swallowed up: now are they become among the  nations as a vessel wherein is no pleasure.
8:8|KJV|Israel is swallowed up: now shall they be among the Gentiles as a vessel wherein is no pleasure.
8:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列被吞喫；他們現今在列國中，好像人不喜悅的器皿。
8:9|Darby|For they are gone up [to] Assyria [as] a wild ass alone by  himself: Ephraim hath hired lovers.
8:9|KJV|For they are gone up to Assyria, a wild ass alone by himself: Ephraim hath hired lovers.
8:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為他們上亞述去，如同獨行的野驢；以法蓮有雇來的愛人。
8:10|Darby|Although they hire among the nations, now will I gather  them, and they shall begin to be straitened under the burden of  the king of princes.
8:10|KJV|Yea, though they have hired among the nations, now will I gather them, and they shall sorrow a little for the burden of the king of princes.
8:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們雖在列邦中雇了這樣的人，現在我卻要聚集他們；他們因君王和首領所加的重擔，必漸漸衰微。
8:11|Darby|Because Ephraim hath multiplied altars to sin, altars shall  be unto him to sin.
8:11|KJV|Because Ephraim hath made many altars to sin, altars shall be unto him to sin.
8:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以法蓮築了許多祭壇取罪，因此，祭壇使他犯罪。
8:12|Darby|I have prescribed unto him the manifold things of my law:  they are counted [as] a strange thing.
8:12|KJV|I have written to him the great things of my law, but they were counted as a strange thing.
8:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我為他寫了律法萬條，卻被看如外人的事。
8:13|Darby|They sacrifice flesh [for] the sacrifices of mine  offerings, and eat it; Jehovah hath no delight in them. Now  will he remember their iniquity, and visit their sins: they  shall return to Egypt.
8:13|KJV|They sacrifice flesh for the sacrifices of mine offerings, and eat it; but the LORD accepteth them not; now will he remember their iniquity, and visit their sins: they shall return to Egypt.
8:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於獻給我的祭物，他們雖然宰獻祭牲並喫祭肉，耶和華卻不悅納他們。現在祂必想起他們的罪孽，懲罰他們的罪；他們必歸回埃及。
8:14<version name="Darby">For Israel hath forgotten his Maker, and buildeth temples;  and Judah hath multiplied fenced cities: but I will send a fire  upon his cities, and it shall devour the palaces thereof. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:14<version name="KJV">For Israel hath forgotten his Maker, and buildeth temples; and Judah hath multiplied fenced cities: but I will send a fire upon his cities, and it shall devour the palaces thereof.</p><p /><br /></version>
8:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列忘記造他的主，建造宮殿，猶大多造堅固城；我卻要降火焚燒他的城邑，燒滅其中的宮殿。
9:1|Darby|Rejoice not, Israel, exultingly, as the peoples; for thou  hast gone a whoring from thy God, thou hast loved harlot's hire  upon every corn-floor.
9:1|KJV|Rejoice not, O Israel, for joy, as other people: for thou hast gone a whoring from thy God, thou hast loved a reward upon every cornfloor.
9:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列阿，不要喜樂，不要像外邦人歡騰，因為你行淫亂離棄了你的神，在各穀場上如妓女喜愛酬價。
9:2|Darby|The floor and the winepress shall not feed them, and the new  wine shall fail her.
9:2|KJV|The floor and the winepress shall not feed them, and the new wine shall fail in her.
9:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|穀場和酒醡，都不彀餧養他們，新酒也必使他們失望。
9:3|Darby|They shall not dwell in Jehovah's land; but Ephraim shall  return to Egypt, and in Assyria shall they eat that which is  unclean.
9:3|KJV|They shall not dwell in the LORD's land; but Ephraim shall return to Egypt, and they shall eat unclean things in Assyria.
9:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們必不得住耶和華的地，以法蓮卻要歸回埃及，必在亞述喫不潔淨的食物。
9:4|Darby|They shall pour out no [offerings of] wine to Jehovah,  neither shall their sacrifices be pleasing unto him: they shall  be unto them as the bread of mourners; all that eat thereof  shall be defiled: for their bread shall be for themselves; it  shall not come into the house of Jehovah.
9:4|KJV|They shall not offer wine offerings to the LORD, neither shall they be pleasing unto him: their sacrifices shall be unto them as the bread of mourners; all that eat thereof shall be polluted: for their bread for their soul shall not come into the house of the LORD.
9:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們必不得向耶和華奠酒，所獻的祭也不蒙悅納。他們的祭物，必如居喪者的食物，凡喫的必被玷污，因他們的食物，只為他們自己，必不奉入耶和華的殿。
9:5|Darby|What will ye do in the day of assembly, and in the day of  the feast of Jehovah?
9:5|KJV|What will ye do in the solemn day, and in the day of the feast of the LORD?
9:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在大會的日子，到耶和華的節期，你們要怎樣行呢？
9:6|Darby|For behold, they are gone away because of destruction: Egypt  shall gather them up, Moph shall bury them: their pleasant  things of silver, nettles shall possess them; thorns shall be  in their tents.
9:6|KJV|For, lo, they are gone because of destruction: Egypt shall gather them up, Memphis shall bury them: the pleasant places for their silver, nettles shall possess them: thorns shall be in their tabernacles.
9:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們因逃避災難離去；埃及人必收殮他們，摩弗人必葬埋他們。他們用銀子作的美物上必長蒺藜；他們的帳棚中必生荊棘。
9:7|Darby|The days of visitation are come; the days of recompence are  come: Israel shall know [it]: the prophet is a fool, the  inspired man is mad, because of the greatness of thine  iniquity, and the great enmity.
9:7|KJV|The days of visitation are come, the days of recompence are come; Israel shall know it: the prophet is a fool, the spiritual man is mad, for the multitude of thine iniquity, and the great hatred.
9:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列人必知道，懲罰的日子臨近，報應的時候來到。申言者愚昧，受靈感者瘋狂；皆因你罪孽極多，大懷仇恨。
9:8|Darby|Is Ephraim a watchman with my God? [nay] the prophet is a  fowler's snare on all his ways, enmity in the house of his God.
9:8|KJV|The watchman of Ephraim was with my God: but the prophet is a snare of a fowler in all his ways, and hatred in the house of his God.
9:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以法蓮曾作我神的守望者。至於申言者，在他一切的道路上有捕鳥人的網羅，在他神的家中有仇恨。
9:9|Darby|They have deeply corrupted themselves as in the days of  Gibeah. He will remember their iniquity, he will visit their  sins.
9:9|KJV|They have deeply corrupted themselves, as in the days of Gibeah: therefore he will remember their iniquity, he will visit their sins.
9:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們深深的敗壞了自己，如在基比亞的日子一樣；耶和華必記得他們的罪孽，必追討他們的罪。
9:10|Darby|I found Israel as grapes in the wilderness; as first-ripe  fruit on the fig-tree, I saw your fathers at the beginning:  they went to Baal-Peor, and separated themselves unto that  shame, and became abominations like their lover.
9:10|KJV|I found Israel like grapes in the wilderness; I saw your fathers as the firstripe in the fig tree at her first time: but they went to Baalpeor, and separated themselves unto that shame; and their abominations were according as they loved.
9:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主說，我遇見以色列如葡萄在曠野；我看見你們的列祖如無花果樹上首先初熟的果子。他們卻來到巴力毗珥，分別自己歸與那可羞恥的，就成為可憎惡的，與他們所愛的人一樣。
9:11|Darby|As for Ephraim, their glory shall fly away as a bird, -- no  birth, no pregnancy, no conception!
9:11|KJV|As for Ephraim, their glory shall fly away like a bird, from the birth, and from the womb, and from the conception.
9:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於以法蓮人，他們的榮耀必如鳥飛去－必不生產，不懷胎，不成孕！
9:12|Darby|For even should they bring up their children, yet will I  bereave them, [that] not a man [remain]: for woe also to them  when I shall have departed from them!
9:12|KJV|Though they bring up their children, yet will I bereave them, that there shall not be a man left: yea, woe also to them when I depart from them!
9:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|縱然養大兒女，我卻必使他們喪子，甚至不留一人。我離棄他們的時候，他們就有禍了。
9:13|Darby|Ephraim, as I saw [him], was a Tyre planted in a beautiful  place; but Ephraim shall bring forth his children to the  slayer.
9:13|KJV|Ephraim, as I saw Tyrus, is planted in a pleasant place: but Ephraim shall bring forth his children to the murderer.
9:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我看以法蓮如推羅栽於草地；以法蓮卻要將自己的兒女帶出來，交與行殺戮的人。
9:14|Darby|Give them, Jehovah -- what wilt thou give? -- give them a  miscarrying womb and dry breasts.
9:14|KJV|Give them, O LORD: what wilt thou give? give them a miscarrying womb and dry breasts.
9:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華阿，求你加給他們－你要加給他們甚麼呢？求你使他們胎墜乳乾。
9:15|Darby|All their wickedness is in Gilgal; for there I hated them:  because of the wickedness of their doings, I will drive them  out of my house, I will love them no more: all their princes  are rebellious.
9:15|KJV|All their wickedness is in Gilgal: for there I hated them: for the wickedness of their doings I will drive them out of mine house, I will love them no more: all their princes are revolters.
9:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華說，他們一切的邪惡都在吉甲，我在那媦迄c他們。因他們所行的惡，我必從我家中趕他們出去，不再憐愛他們；他們的首領都是悖逆的。
9:16|Darby|Ephraim is smitten: their root is dried up, they shall bear  no fruit; yea, though they should bring forth, yet will I slay  the beloved [fruit] of their womb.
9:16|KJV|Ephraim is smitten, their root is dried up, they shall bear no fruit: yea, though they bring forth, yet will I slay even the beloved fruit of their womb.
9:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以法蓮受責打；他們的根枯乾，不結果子；即或生產，我必殺他們腹中所出的愛子。
9:17<version name="Darby">My God hath rejected them, because they hearkened not unto  him; and they shall be wanderers among the nations. </p><p /><br /></version>
9:17<version name="KJV">My God will cast them away, because they did not hearken unto him: and they shall be wanderers among the nations.</p><p /><br /></version>
9:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的神棄絕了他們，因為他們不聽從祂；他們也必飄流在列國中。
10:1|Darby|Israel is an unpruned vine, he bringeth forth fruit unto  himself: according to the abundance of his fruit he hath  multiplied altars; according to the goodness of his land they  have made goodly statues.
10:1|KJV|Israel is an empty vine, he bringeth forth fruit unto himself: according to the multitude of his fruit he hath increased the altars; according to the goodness of his land they have made goodly images.
10:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列是茂盛的葡萄樹，結果繁多。他的果子越多，就越增添祭壇；地土越肥美，就越造美好的柱像。
10:2|Darby|Their heart is divided; now shall they be found guilty: he  will break down their altars, he will destroy their statues.
10:2|KJV|Their heart is divided; now shall they be found faulty: he shall break down their altars, he shall spoil their images.
10:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們心懷二意，現今要定為有罪。耶和華必拆毀他們的祭壇，毀壞他們的柱像。
10:3|Darby|For now they will say, We have no king, for we feared not  Jehovah; and a king, what can he do for us?
10:3|KJV|For now they shall say, We have no king, because we feared not the LORD; what then should a king do to us?
10:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現今他們必說，我們沒有王，因為我們不敬畏耶和華；王能為我們作甚麼呢？
10:4|Darby|They speak [mere] words, swearing falsely in making a  covenant; therefore shall judgment spring up as hemlock in the  furrows of the fields.
10:4|KJV|They have spoken words, swearing falsely in making a covenant: thus judgment springeth up as hemlock in the furrows of the field.
10:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們在立約時說空話，起假誓，因此，審判如毒草滋生在田間的犁溝中。
10:5|Darby|The inhabitants of Samaria shall fear because of the calf  of Beth-aven; for the people thereof shall mourn over it, and  the idolatrous priests thereof shall tremble for it, for its  glory, because it is departed from it.
10:5|KJV|The inhabitants of Samaria shall fear because of the calves of Bethaven: for the people thereof shall mourn over it, and the priests thereof that rejoiced on it, for the glory thereof, because it is departed from it.
10:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|撒瑪利亞的居民必因伯亞文的牛犢驚恐，拜它的民為它悲哀，拜它為偶像的祭司為它戰兢，都因榮耀離開它去了。
10:6|Darby|Yea, it shall be carried unto Assyria [as] a present for  king Jareb: Ephraim shall be seized with shame, and Israel  shall be ashamed of his own counsel.
10:6|KJV|It shall be also carried unto Assyria for a present to king Jareb: Ephraim shall receive shame, and Israel shall be ashamed of his own counsel.
10:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人必將牛犢帶到亞述，當作禮物獻給耶雷布王。以法蓮必蒙羞，以色列必因自己的計謀慚愧。
10:7|Darby|As for Samaria her king is cut off as chips upon the face  of the waters.
10:7|KJV|As for Samaria, her king is cut off as the foam upon the water.
10:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|撒瑪利亞和她的王必被剪除，如水面的枯枝一樣。
10:8|Darby|And the high places of Aven, the sin of Israel, shall be  destroyed: the thorn and the thistle shall come up upon their  altars; and they shall say to the mountains, Cover us! and to  the hills, Fall on us!
10:8|KJV|The high places also of Aven, the sin of Israel, shall be destroyed: the thorn and the thistle shall come up on their altars; and they shall say to the mountains, Cover us; and to the hills, Fall on us.
10:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|伯亞文的邱壇，就是以色列的罪，必被毀滅。荊棘和蒺藜必長在他們的祭壇上；他們必對大山說，遮蓋我們！對小山說，倒在我們身上！
10:9|Darby|From the days of Gibeah hast thou sinned, O Israel: there  they stood: the battle in Gibeah against the children of  iniquity did not overtake them.
10:9|KJV|O Israel, thou hast sinned from the days of Gibeah: there they stood: the battle in Gibeah against the children of iniquity did not overtake them.
10:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列阿，你從基比亞的日子以來，時常犯罪。他們仍然站在那堙F攻擊罪孽之輩的戰事，豈不是在基比亞追上他們麼？
10:10|Darby|At my pleasure will I chastise them; and the peoples shall  be assembled against them, when they are bound for their two  iniquities.
10:10|KJV|It is in my desire that I should chastise them; and the people shall be gathered against them, when they shall bind themselves in their two furrows.
10:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在願意的時候必管教他們；他們為兩樣的罪孽所纏的時候，列邦的民必聚集攻擊他們。
10:11|Darby|And Ephraim is a trained heifer, that loveth to tread out  [the corn]; I have passed over upon her fair neck: I will make  Ephraim to draw; Judah shall plough, Jacob shall break his  clods.
10:11|KJV|And Ephraim is as an heifer that is taught, and loveth to tread out the corn; but I passed over upon her fair neck: I will make Ephraim to ride; Judah shall plow, and Jacob shall break his clods.
10:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以法蓮是馴良的母牛犢，喜愛踹穀，我卻將軛加在牠肥美的頸項上：我要使以法蓮拉犁，猶大必耕田，雅各必耙地。
10:12|Darby|Sow to yourselves in righteousness, reap according to  mercy; break up your fallow ground: for it is time to seek  Jehovah, till he come and rain righteousness upon you.
10:12|KJV|Sow to yourselves in righteousness, reap in mercy; break up your fallow ground: for it is time to seek the LORD, till he come and rain righteousness upon you.
10:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要為自己向公義撒種，就能照著慈愛收割；你們要開墾自己的休耕地，因為現今正是尋求耶和華的時候，等祂臨到，使公義如雨降在你們身上。
10:13|Darby|Ye have ploughed wickedness, reaped iniquity, eaten the  fruit of lies; for thou didst confide in thy way, in the  multitude of thy mighty men.
10:13|KJV|Ye have plowed wickedness, ye have reaped iniquity; ye have eaten the fruit of lies: because thou didst trust in thy way, in the multitude of thy mighty men.
10:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們耕種的是奸惡，收割的是不義，喫的是謊言的果子。因你倚靠自己的道路，仰賴自己的勇士眾多。
10:14|Darby|And a tumult shall arise among thy peoples, and all thy  fortresses shall be spoiled, as Shalman spoiled Beth-arbel in  the day of battle: the mother was dashed in pieces with the  children.
10:14|KJV|Therefore shall a tumult arise among thy people, and all thy fortresses shall be spoiled, as Shalman spoiled Betharbel in the day of battle: the mother was dashed in pieces upon her children.
10:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以在你民中必起鬨嚷之聲，你一切的保障必被拆毀，就如沙勒幔在爭戰的日子拆毀伯亞比勒，將其中的母子一同摔死。
10:15<version name="Darby">So shall Bethel do unto you because of the wickedness of  your wickedness: at day-break shall the king of Israel utterly  be cut off. </p><p /><br /></version>
10:15<version name="KJV">So shall Bethel do unto you because of your great wickedness: in a morning shall the king of Israel utterly be cut off.</p><p /><br /></version>
10:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因你們的大惡，伯特利必使你們遭遇如此：到了黎明，以色列的王必全然滅絕。
11:1|Darby|When Israel was a child, then I loved him, and out of Egypt  I called my son.
11:1|KJV|When Israel was a child, then I loved him, and called my son out of Egypt.
11:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列年幼的時候我愛他，就從埃及召出我的兒子來。
11:2|Darby|As they called them, so they went from them: they  sacrificed unto the Baals, and burned incense to graven images.
11:2|KJV|As they called them, so they went from them: they sacrificed unto Baalim, and burned incense to graven images.
11:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|申言者越發招呼他們，他們越發走開，向諸巴力獻祭，給眾偶像燒香。
11:3|Darby|And I it was that taught Ephraim to walk, -- He took them  upon his arms, -- but they knew not that I healed them.
11:3|KJV|I taught Ephraim also to go, taking them by their arms; but they knew not that I healed them.
11:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我原教導以法蓮行走，用雙臂抱著他們，他們卻不知道是我醫治了他們。
11:4|Darby|I drew them with bands of a man, with cords of love; and I  was to them as they that take off the yoke on their jaws, and I  gently caused them to eat.
11:4|KJV|I drew them with cords of a man, with bands of love: and I was to them as they that take off the yoke on their jaws, and I laid meat unto them.
11:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我用慈繩愛索牽引他們；我待他們如人鬆開他們腮上的軛，溫和的餧養他們。
11:5|Darby|He shall not return into the land of Egypt, but the  Assyrian shall be his king; for they refused to return [to me];
11:5|KJV|He shall not return into the land of Egypt, and the Assyrian shall be his king, because they refused to return.
11:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們必不歸回埃及地，亞述人卻要作他們的王，因他們不肯歸向我。
11:6|Darby|and the sword shall turn about in his cities, and shall  consume his bars, and devour [them], because of their own  counsels.
11:6|KJV|And the sword shall abide on his cities, and shall consume his branches, and devour them, because of their own counsels.
11:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|刀劍必在他們的城中揮動，毀壞門閂，把人吞滅，都因他們隨從自己的計謀。
11:7|Darby|Yea, my people are bent upon backsliding from me: though  they call them to the Most High, none at all exalteth [him].
11:7|KJV|And my people are bent to backsliding from me: though they called them to the most High, none at all would exalt him.
11:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的民偏要背道離開我，眾申言者雖然招呼他們歸向至上的主，卻無人尊崇祂。
11:8|Darby|How shall I give thee over, Ephraim? [how] shall I deliver  thee up, Israel? how shall I make thee as Admah? [how] shall I  set thee as Zeboim? My heart is turned within me, my repentings  are kindled together.
11:8|KJV|How shall I give thee up, Ephraim? how shall I deliver thee, Israel? how shall I make thee as Admah? how shall I set thee as Zeboim? mine heart is turned within me, my repentings are kindled together.
11:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以法蓮哪，我怎能捨棄你？以色列阿，我怎能將你交出？我怎能使你如押瑪？怎能使你如洗扁？我回心轉意，我的憐恤大大發動。
11:9|Darby|I will not execute the fierceness of mine anger, I will not  again destroy Ephraim; for I am ???’???’?????????God, and not man, -- the Holy  One in the midst of thee: and I will not come in anger.
11:9|KJV|I will not execute the fierceness of mine anger, I will not return to destroy Ephraim: for I am God, and not man; the Holy One in the midst of thee: and I will not enter into the city.
11:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必不發猛烈的怒氣，也不再毀滅以法蓮；因我是神，並非人，是你們中間的聖者，我必不在怒中臨到你們。
11:10|Darby|They shall walk after Jehovah; he shall roar like a lion;  when he shall roar, then the children shall hasten from the  west:
11:10|KJV|They shall walk after the LORD: he shall roar like a lion: when he shall roar, then the children shall tremble from the west.
11:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們必跟隨耶和華。祂必如獅子吼叫；祂一吼叫，祂的兒女就從西方戰兢而來。
11:11|Darby|they shall hasten as a bird out of Egypt, and as a dove  out of the land of Assyria; and I will cause them to dwell in  their houses, saith Jehovah.
11:11|KJV|They shall tremble as a bird out of Egypt, and as a dove out of the land of Assyria: and I will place them in their houses, saith the LORD.
11:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們必如雀鳥從埃及戰兢而來，又如鴿子從亞述地來到。我必使他們住自己的房屋，這是耶和華說的。
11:12<version name="Darby">Ephraim encompasseth me about with lies, and the house of  Israel with deceit; but Judah yet walketh with ???’???’?????????God, and with  the holy things of truth. </p><p /><br /></version>
11:12<version name="KJV">Ephraim compasseth me about with lies, and the house of Israel with deceit: but Judah yet ruleth with God, and is faithful with the saints.</p><p /><br /></version>
11:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以法蓮用謊言，以色列家用詭計圍繞我；猶大向神，向忠信的聖者，仍然猶疑不定。
12:1|Darby|Ephraim feedeth on wind, and pursueth after the east wind:  all day long he multiplieth lies and desolation; and they make  a covenant with Assyria, and oil is carried into Egypt.
12:1|KJV|Ephraim feedeth on wind, and followeth after the east wind: he daily increaseth lies and desolation; and they do make a covenant with the Assyrians, and oil is carried into Egypt.
12:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以法蓮喫風，終日追趕東風；他增添虛謊和強暴；與亞述立約，把油送到埃及。
12:2|Darby|Jehovah hath also a controversy with Judah, and he will  punish Jacob according to his ways; according to his doings  will he recompense him.
12:2|KJV|The LORD hath also a controversy with Judah, and will punish Jacob according to his ways; according to his doings will he recompense him.
12:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華又與猶大爭辯，必照雅各所行的懲罰他，按他所作的報應他。
12:3|Darby|He took his brother by the heel in the womb, and in his  strength he wrestled with God.
12:3|KJV|He took his brother by the heel in the womb, and by his strength he had power with God:
12:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他在母腹中抓住哥哥的腳跟，壯年的時候與神較力。
12:4|Darby|Yea, he wrestled with the Angel, and prevailed; he wept,  and made supplication unto him: he found him in Bethel, and  there he spoke with us,
12:4|KJV|Yea, he had power over the angel, and prevailed: he wept, and made supplication unto him: he found him in Bethel, and there he spake with us;
12:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他與天使較力並且得勝；他哭泣懇求，在伯特利遇見耶和華；祂在那婸P我們說話，
12:5|Darby|-- even Jehovah, the God of hosts, -- Jehovah is his  memorial.
12:5|KJV|Even the LORD God of hosts; the LORD is his memorial.
12:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂是耶和華萬軍之神；耶和華是祂可記念的名。
12:6|Darby|And thou, return unto thy God: keep loving-kindness and  judgment, and wait on thy God continually.
12:6|KJV|Therefore turn thou to thy God: keep mercy and judgment and wait on thy God continually.
12:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你當歸向你的神，謹守慈愛、公平，常常等候你的神。
12:7|Darby|[He is] a merchant, balances of deceit are in his hand; he  loveth to oppress.
12:7|KJV|He is a merchant, the balances of deceit are in his hand: he loveth to oppress.
12:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以法蓮是商人，手埵雩瑗B的天平，喜愛欺詐。
12:8|Darby|And Ephraim saith, Nevertheless I am become rich, I have  found me out substance; in all my labours they shall find none  iniquity in me that were sin.
12:8|KJV|And Ephraim said, Yet I am become rich, I have found me out substance: in all my labours they shall find none iniquity in me that were sin.
12:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以法蓮說，我果然成了富足，為自己得了財富；我一切勞碌得來的，人必不見有甚麼不義，可算為罪的。
12:9|Darby|But I [that am] Jehovah thy God from the land of Egypt will  again make thee to dwell in tents, as in the days of the solemn  feast.
12:9|KJV|And I that am the LORD thy God from the land of Egypt will yet make thee to dwell in tabernacles, as in the days of the solemn feast.
12:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|自從在埃及地以來，我就是耶和華你的神；我必使你再住帳棚，如在所定節期的日子一樣。
12:10|Darby|And I have spoken to the prophets, and I have multiplied  visions, and by means of the prophets have I used similitudes.
12:10|KJV|I have also spoken by the prophets, and I have multiplied visions, and used similitudes, by the ministry of the prophets.
12:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我已曉諭眾申言者，並且加增異象，藉申言者使用比喻。
12:11|Darby|If Gilead is iniquity, surely they are but vanity: they  sacrifice bullocks in Gilgal; yea, their altars are as heaps in  the furrows of the fields.
12:11|KJV|Is there iniquity in Gilead? surely they are vanity: they sacrifice bullocks in Gilgal; yea, their altars are as heaps in the furrows of the fields.
12:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|基列人有罪孽麼？他們全然是虛假的。他們在吉甲獻牛為祭，他們的祭壇好像田間犁溝中的亂堆。
12:12|Darby|And Jacob fled into the country of Syria, and Israel  served for a wife, and for a wife he kept [sheep].
12:12|KJV|And Jacob fled into the country of Syria, and Israel served for a wife, and for a wife he kept sheep.
12:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|從前雅各逃到亞蘭地，以色列為得妻子服事人，為得妻子替人放羊。
12:13|Darby|And by a prophet Jehovah brought Israel out of Egypt, and  by a prophet was he preserved.
12:13|KJV|And by a prophet the LORD brought Israel out of Egypt, and by a prophet was he preserved.
12:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華藉申言者領以色列從埃及上來，以色列也藉申言者而得保存。
12:14<version name="Darby">Ephraim provoked [him] to anger most bitterly; and his  Lord shall leave his blood upon him, and recompense unto him  his reproach. </p><p /><br /></version>
12:14<version name="KJV">Ephraim provoked him to anger most bitterly: therefore shall he leave his blood upon him, and his reproach shall his LORD return unto him.</p><p /><br /></version>
12:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以法蓮大大惹動主怒，所以他的主必使他流血的罪歸在他身上，必將他自己的羞辱還報他。
13:1|Darby|When Ephraim spoke, there was trembling; he exalted himself  in Israel: but he trespassed through Baal, and he died.
13:1|KJV|When Ephraim spake trembling, he exalted himself in Israel; but when he offended in Baal, he died.
13:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|從前以法蓮說話，人都戰兢。他在以色列中高舉自己；但他因事奉巴力而犯罪，就死了。
13:2|Darby|And now they sin more and more, and have made them molten  images of their silver, idols according to their own  understanding, all of it the work of the craftsmen: they say of  them, Let the men that sacrifice kiss the calves.
13:2|KJV|And now they sin more and more, and have made them molten images of their silver, and idols according to their own understanding, all of it the work of the craftsmen: they say of them, Let the men that sacrifice kiss the calves.
13:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現今他們越發犯罪，用銀子為自己造鑄像，就是照自己的聰明製造的偶像，都是匠人的工作。他們論到那些偶像，說，獻祭的人可以向牛犢親嘴。
13:3|Darby|Therefore they shall be as the morning cloud, and as the  early dew that passeth away, as the chaff driven with the  whirlwind out of the threshing-floor, and as the smoke out of  the lattice.
13:3|KJV|Therefore they shall be as the morning cloud and as the early dew that passeth away, as the chaff that is driven with the whirlwind out of the floor, and as the smoke out of the chimney.
13:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此，他們必如早晨的雲霧，又如速散的甘露，像禾場上的糠秕被狂風吹去，又像煙氣從窗口騰散。
13:4|Darby|Yet I [am] Jehovah thy God from the land of Egypt, and thou  hast known no God but me; and there is no saviour besides me.
13:4|KJV|Yet I am the LORD thy God from the land of Egypt, and thou shalt know no god but me: for there is no saviour beside me.
13:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|自從在埃及地以來，我就是耶和華你的神；在我以外，你不可認識別神，除我以外並沒有救主。
13:5|Darby|I knew thee in the wilderness, in the land of drought.
13:5|KJV|I did know thee in the wilderness, in the land of great drought.
13:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我曾在曠野極其乾旱之地認識你。
13:6|Darby|According to their pasture, they became full; they became  full, and their heart was exalted: therefore have they  forgotten me.
13:6|KJV|According to their pasture, so were they filled; they were filled, and their heart was exalted; therefore have they forgotten me.
13:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們照我所賜的草場得了飽足；既得飽足，心就高傲，忘記了我。
13:7|Darby|And I will be unto them as a lion; as a leopard I will lurk  for them by the way;
13:7|KJV|Therefore I will be unto them as a lion: as a leopard by the way will I observe them:
13:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此，我要向他們如獅子，又如豹伏在道旁窺視。
13:8|Darby|I will meet them as a bear bereaved of her [whelps], and  will rend the covering of their heart, and there will I devour  them like a lioness: the beast of the field shall tear them.
13:8|KJV|I will meet them as a bear that is bereaved of her whelps, and will rend the caul of their heart, and there will I devour them like a lion: the wild beast shall tear them.
13:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我遇見他們必像丟崽子的母熊，撕裂他們的心膜；在那塈琤硃野懋鄑]喫他們；田野的走獸必撕碎他們。
13:9|Darby|It is thy destruction, O Israel, that [thou art] against  me, against thy help.
13:9|KJV|O Israel, thou hast destroyed thyself; but in me is thine help.
13:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列阿，你反對我，就是反對幫助你的，自取毀壞。
13:10|Darby|Where then is thy king, that he may save thee in all thy  cities? and thy judges of whom thou saidst, Give me a king and  princes? --
13:10|KJV|I will be thy king: where is any other that may save thee in all thy cities? and thy judges of whom thou saidst, Give me a king and princes?
13:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現在你的王在那堜O？讓他在你所有的城中拯救你罷。審理你的在那堜O？論到他們，你曾說，把王和首領賜給我。
13:11|Darby|I gave thee a king in mine anger, and took him away in my  wrath.
13:11|KJV|I gave thee a king in mine anger, and took him away in my wrath.
13:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在怒氣中將王賜給你，又在盛怒中將王廢去。
13:12|Darby|The iniquity of Ephraim is bound up; his sin is laid by in  store.
13:12|KJV|The iniquity of Ephraim is bound up; his sin is hid.
13:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以法蓮的罪孽是包裹著的，他的罪是收藏著的。
13:13|Darby|The pangs of a woman in travail shall come upon him: he is  a son not wise; for at the time of the breaking forth of  children, he was not there.
13:13|KJV|The sorrows of a travailing woman shall come upon him: he is an unwise son; for he should not stay long in the place of the breaking forth of children.
13:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|產婦的疼痛必臨到他身上。他是無智慧之子，到了產期，他不應當遲延。
13:14|Darby|I will ransom them from the power of Sheol. I will redeem  them from death: where, O death, are thy plagues? where, O  Sheol, is thy destruction? Repentance shall be hid from mine  eyes.
13:14|KJV|I will ransom them from the power of the grave; I will redeem them from death: O death, I will be thy plagues; O grave, I will be thy destruction: repentance shall be hid from mine eyes.
13:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必救贖他們脫離陰間的權勢，救贖他們脫離死亡。死亡阿，你的災害在那堙H陰間哪，你的毀滅在那堙H在我眼前絕無後悔。
13:15|Darby|Though he be fruitful among [his] brethren, an east wind  shall come, a wind of Jehovah [that] cometh up from the  wilderness, and his spring shall become dry, and his fountain  shall be dried up: he shall spoil the treasure of all pleasant  vessels.
13:15|KJV|Though he be fruitful among his brethren, an east wind shall come, the wind of the LORD shall come up from the wilderness, and his spring shall become dry, and his fountain shall be dried up: he shall spoil the treasure of all pleasant vessels.
13:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他在弟兄中雖然茂盛，必有東風颳來，就是耶和華的風從曠野上來，他的泉源必乾涸，他的源頭必枯竭。仇敵必擄掠他所積蓄的一切寶器。
13:16<version name="Darby">Samaria shall bear her guilt; for she hath rebelled  against her God: they shall fall by the sword; their infants  shall be dashed in pieces, and their women with child shall be  ripped up. </p><p /><br /></version>
13:16<version name="KJV">Samaria shall become desolate; for she hath rebelled against her God: they shall fall by the sword: their infants shall be dashed in pieces, and their women with child shall be ripped up.</p><p /><br /></version>
13:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|撒瑪利亞必有罪，因為悖逆她的神。他們必倒在刀下，嬰孩必被摔死，孕婦必被剖開。
14:1|Darby|O Israel, return unto Jehovah thy God; for thou hast fallen  by thine iniquity.
14:1|KJV|O israel, return unto the LORD thy God; for thou hast fallen by thine iniquity.
14:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列阿，你要歸向耶和華你的神；你是因自己的罪孽絆跌了。
14:2|Darby|Take with you words, and turn to Jehovah; say unto him,  Forgive all iniquity, and receive [us] graciously; so will we  render the calves of our lips.
14:2|KJV|Take with you words, and turn to the LORD: say unto him, Take away all iniquity, and receive us graciously: so will we render the calves of our lips.
14:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當帶著禱告的話歸向耶和華，對祂說，求你赦免一切罪孽，恩慈的收納我們；這樣，我們就把嘴脣的祭，如同牛犢獻上。
14:3|Darby|Assyria shall not save us; we will not ride upon horses:  neither will we say any more to the work of our hands, [Thou  art] our God; because in thee the fatherless findeth mercy.
14:3|KJV|Asshur shall not save us; we will not ride upon horses: neither will we say any more to the work of our hands, Ye are our gods: for in thee the fatherless findeth mercy.
14:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞述不能拯救我們；我們不再騎馬；也不再對我們手所造的說，你是我們的神，因為孤兒在你那堭o蒙憐恤。
14:4|Darby|I will heal their backsliding, I will love them freely; for  mine anger is turned away from him.
14:4|KJV|I will heal their backsliding, I will love them freely: for mine anger is turned away from him.
14:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必醫治他們的背道，甘心愛他們；因為我的怒氣已從他們轉消。
14:5|Darby|I will be as the dew unto Israel: he shall blossom as the  lily, and cast forth his roots as Lebanon.
14:5|KJV|I will be as the dew unto Israel: he shall grow as the lily, and cast forth his roots as Lebanon.
14:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必向以色列如甘露，他必如百合花開放，如利巴嫩的樹木扎根。
14:6|Darby|His shoots shall spread, and his beauty shall be as the  olive-tree, and his smell as Lebanon.
14:6|KJV|His branches shall spread, and his beauty shall be as the olive tree, and his smell as Lebanon.
14:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他的枝條必延伸，他的榮華如橄欖樹，他的香氣如利巴嫩的香柏樹。
14:7|Darby|They shall return and sit under his shadow; they shall  revive [as] corn, and blossom as the vine: the renown thereof  shall be as the wine of Lebanon.
14:7|KJV|They that dwell under his shadow shall return; they shall revive as the corn, and grow as the vine: the scent thereof shall be as the wine of Lebanon.
14:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|曾坐在他蔭下的必歸回，發旺如五穀，開花如葡萄樹；他的名聲如利巴嫩的酒。
14:8|Darby|Ephraim [shall say], What have I to do any more with idols?  (I answer [him], and I will observe him.) I am like a green  fir-tree. -- From me is thy fruit found.
14:8|KJV|Ephraim shall say, What have I to do any more with idols? I have heard him, and observed him: I am like a green fir tree. From me is thy fruit found.
14:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以法蓮必說，我與偶像還有甚麼相干呢？我耶和華必回答他，也必顧念他。我如青翠的松樹，你的果子從我而得。
14:9<version name="Darby">Who is wise, and he shall understand these things?  intelligent, and he shall know them? For the ways of Jehovah  are right, and the just shall walk in them; but the  transgressors shall fall therein. </p><p /><br /></version>
14:9<version name="KJV">Who is wise, and he shall understand these things? prudent, and he shall know them? for the ways of the LORD are right, and the just shall walk in them: but the transgressors shall fall therein.</p><p /><br /></version>
14:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|誰是智慧人？他可以明白這些事。誰是通達人？他可以知道這一切。因為耶和華的道路是正直的，義人必在其中行走，有過犯的人卻在其上絆跌。
