1:1|ASV|James, a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ, to the twelve tribes which are of the Dispersion, greeting.
1:1|Darby|James, bondman of God and of [the] Lord Jesus Christ, to the  twelve tribes which [are] in the dispersion, greeting.
1:1|KJV|James, a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ, to the twelve tribes which are scattered abroad, greeting.
1:1|WYC|James, the servant of God, and of our Lord Jesus Christ, to the twelve kindreds, that be in scattering abroad, health.
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神和主耶穌基督的奴僕雅各，寫信給散居的十二個支派：願你們喜樂。
1:2|ASV|Count it all joy, my brethren, when ye fall into manifold temptations;
1:2|Darby|Count it all joy, my brethren, when ye fall into various  temptations,
1:2|KJV|My brethren, count it all joy when ye fall into divers temptations;
1:2|WYC|My brethren, deem ye all joy [guess ye all joy], when ye fall into diverse temptations,
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的弟兄們，無論何時你們落在諸般的試煉中，都要以為大喜樂；
1:3|ASV|Knowing that the proving of your faith worketh patience.
1:3|Darby|knowing that the proving of your faith works endurance.
1:3|KJV|Knowing this, that the trying of your faith worketh patience.
1:3|WYC|witting, that the proving of your faith worketh patience;
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|知道你們信心所受的試驗，產生忍耐。
1:4|ASV|And let patience have its perfect work, that ye may be perfect and entire, lacking in nothing.
1:4|Darby|But let endurance have [its] perfect work, that ye may be  perfect and complete, lacking in nothing.
1:4|KJV|But let patience have her perfect work, that ye may be perfect and entire, wanting nothing.
1:4|WYC|and patience hath a perfect work, that ye be perfect and whole, and fail in nothing. [soothly patience hath a perfect work, that ye be perfect and whole, in nothing failing.]
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但忍耐也當成功，好使你們齊備完整，毫無缺欠。
1:5|ASV|But if any of you lacketh wisdom, let him ask of God, who giveth to all liberally and upbraideth not; and it shall be given him.
1:5|Darby|But if any one of you lack wisdom, let him ask of God, who  gives to all freely and reproaches not, and it shall be given  to him:
1:5|KJV|If any of you lack wisdom, let him ask of God, that giveth to all men liberally, and upbraideth not; and it shall be given him.
1:5|WYC|And if any of you needeth wisdom, ask he of God, which giveth to all men largely [that giveth to all men largely], and upbraideth not; and it shall be given to him.
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們中間若有缺少智慧的，就當求那厚賜眾人，也不斥責人的神，就必有賜給他的。
1:6|ASV|But let him ask in faith, nothing doubting: for he that doubteth is like the surge of the sea driven by the wind and tossed.
1:6|Darby|but let him ask in faith, nothing doubting. For he that  doubts is like a wave of the sea driven by the wind and tossed  about;
1:6|KJV|But let him ask in faith, nothing wavering. For he that wavereth is like a wave of the sea driven with the wind and tossed.
1:6|WYC|But ask he in faith, and doubt nothing [nothing doubting]; for he that doubteth, is like to a wave of the sea, which is moved and borne about of the wind [the which of wind is moved and borne about].
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只是要憑著信心求，一點不疑惑；因為那疑惑的人，就像海中的波浪，被風吹動翻騰。
1:7|ASV|For let not that man think that he shall receive anything of the Lord;
1:7|Darby|for let not that man think that he shall receive anything  from the Lord;
1:7|KJV|For let not that man think that he shall receive any thing of the Lord.
1:7|WYC|Therefore guess not that man, that he shall take any thing of the Lord.
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣的人，不要想從主那裡得到甚麼；
1:8|ASV|a doubleminded man, unstable in all his ways.
1:8|Darby|[he is] a double-minded man, unstable in all his ways.
1:8|KJV|A double minded man is unstable in all his ways.
1:8|WYC|A man double in soul is unstable in all his ways.
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|心懷二意的人，在他一切的路上，都是搖蕩不定的。
1:9|ASV|But let the brother of low degree glory in his high estate:
1:9|Darby|But let the brother of low degree glory in his elevation,
1:9|KJV|Let the brother of low degree rejoice in that he is exalted:
1:9|WYC|And a meek brother have glory in his enhancing. [Forsooth a meek brother glory in his enhancing.]
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|卑微的弟兄升高，就該誇耀；
1:10|ASV|and the rich, in that he is made low: because as the flower of the grass he shall pass away.
1:10|Darby|and the rich in his humiliation, because as [the] grass's  flower he will pass away.
1:10|KJV|But the rich, in that he is made low: because as the flower of the grass he shall pass away.
1:10|WYC|and a rich man in his lowness; for as the flower of grass he shall pass.
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|富足的降卑，也該如此，因為他必要過去，如同草上的花一樣。
1:11|ASV|For the sun ariseth with the scorching wind, and withereth the grass: and the flower thereof falleth, and the grace of the fashion of it perisheth: so also shall the rich man fade away in his goings.
1:11|Darby|For the sun has risen with its burning heat, and has  withered the grass, and its flower has fallen, and the  comeliness of its look has perished: thus the rich also shall  wither in his goings.
1:11|KJV|For the sun is no sooner risen with a burning heat, but it withereth the grass, and the flower thereof falleth, and the grace of the fashion of it perisheth: so also shall the rich man fade away in his ways.
1:11<version name="WYC">The sun rose up with heat, and dried the grass, and the flower of it felled down, and the fairness of his face perished; and so a rich man withereth in his ways. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23294a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|太陽升起，熱氣薰烤，草就枯乾，花也凋謝，美容就消沒了；那富足的人在他所行的事上，也要這樣衰殘。
1:12|ASV|Blessed is the man that endureth temptation; for when he hath been approved, he shall receive the crown of life, which  the Lord promised to them that love him.
1:12|Darby|Blessed [is the] man who endures temptation; for, having  been proved, he shall receive the crown of life, which He has  promised to them that love him.
1:12|KJV|Blessed is the man that endureth temptation: for when he is tried, he shall receive the crown of life, which the Lord hath promised to them that love him.
1:12<version name="WYC">Blessed <i>is</i> the man, that suffereth temptation; for when he shall be proved, he shall receive the crown of life, which God promised to men that love him.</version>
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|忍受試煉的人有福了，因為他既受試驗得了稱許，就必得著生命的冠冕，這是主應許給那些愛祂之人的。
1:13|ASV|Let no man say when he is tempted, I am tempted of God; for God cannot be tempted with evil, and he himself tempteth no man:
1:13|Darby|Let no man, being tempted, say, I am tempted of God. For  God cannot be tempted by evil things, and himself tempts no  one.
1:13|KJV|Let no man say when he is tempted, I am tempted of God: for God cannot be tempted with evil, neither tempteth he any man:
1:13|WYC|No man when he is tempted, say, that he is tempted of God; for why God is not a tempter of evil things, for he tempteth no man.
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人被試誘，不可說，我是被神試誘，因為神不被惡試誘，祂也不試誘人。
1:14|ASV|but each man is tempted, when he is drawn away by his own lust, and enticed.
1:14|Darby|But every one is tempted, drawn away, and enticed by his  own lust;
1:14|KJV|But every man is tempted, when he is drawn away of his own lust, and enticed.
1:14<version name="WYC">But each man is tempted, drawn and stirred of his own coveting. [Soothly each man is tempted of his own coveting, drawn <i>from reason</i>, and snared, <i>or deceived</i>.]</version>
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但各人被試誘，乃是被自己的私慾勾引誘惑的；
1:15|ASV|Then the lust, when it hath conceived, beareth sin: and the sin, when it is fullgrown, bringeth forth death.
1:15|Darby|then lust, having conceived, gives birth to sin; but sin  fully completed brings forth death.
1:15|KJV|Then when lust hath conceived, it bringeth forth sin: and sin, when it is finished, bringeth forth death.
1:15|WYC|Afterward coveting [Then coveting], when it hath conceived, bringeth forth sin; but sin, when it is filled, engendereth death [soothly sin, when it is fulfilled, gendereth death].
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然後私慾懷了胎，就生出罪；罪既長成，就產生死。
1:16|ASV|Be not deceived, my beloved brethren.
1:16|Darby|Do not err, my beloved brethren.
1:16|KJV|Do not err, my beloved brethren.
1:16|WYC|Therefore [And so], my most dear-worthy brethren, do not ye err.
1:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我親愛的弟兄們，不要看錯了。
1:17|ASV|Every good gift and every perfect gift is from above, coming down from the Father of lights, with whom can be no variation, neither shadow that is cast by turning.
1:17|Darby|Every good gift and every perfect gift comes down from  above, from the Father of lights, with whom is no variation nor  shadow of turning.
1:17|KJV|Every good gift and every perfect gift is from above, and cometh down from the Father of lights, with whom is no variableness, neither shadow of turning.
1:17<version name="WYC">Each good gift, and each perfect gift is from above, and cometh down from the Father of lights, with whom is none other changing, nor overshadowing of reward. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23300b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
1:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|一切美善的賜與、和各樣完備的恩賜，都是從上頭，從眾光之父降下來的，在祂並沒有變動，或轉動的影兒。
1:18|ASV|Of his own will he brought us forth by the word of truth, that we should be a kind of firstfruits of his creatures.
1:18|Darby|According to his own will begat he us by the word of truth,  that we should be a certain first-fruits of *his* creatures.
1:18|KJV|Of his own will begat he us with the word of truth, that we should be a kind of firstfruits of his creatures.
1:18|WYC|For willfully he begat us by the word of truth [Forsooth willfully he gendered us with the word of truth], that we be a beginning of his creature.
1:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂照自己的定意，用真理的話生了我們，叫我們在祂所造的萬物中，成為初熟的果子。
1:19|ASV|Ye know this, my beloved brethren. But let every man be swift to hear, slow to speak, slow to wrath:
1:19|Darby|So that, my beloved brethren, let every man be swift to  hear, slow to speak, slow to wrath;
1:19|KJV|Wherefore, my beloved brethren, let every man be swift to hear, slow to speak, slow to wrath:
1:19|WYC|Know ye, my brethren most loved, be each man swift to hear, but slow to speak, and slow to wrath;
1:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我親愛的弟兄們，這是你們所知道的，但你們各人要快快的聽，慢慢的說，慢慢的動怒；
1:20|ASV|for the wrath of man worketh not the righteousness of God.
1:20|Darby|for man's wrath does not work God's righteousness.
1:20|KJV|For the wrath of man worketh not the righteousness of God.
1:20|WYC|for the wrath of man worketh not the rightwiseness of God.
1:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為人的忿怒並不成就神的義。
1:21|ASV|Wherefore putting away all filthiness and overflowing of wickedness, receive with meekness the implanted word, which is able to save your souls.
1:21|Darby|Wherefore, laying aside all filthiness and abounding of  wickedness, accept with meekness the implanted word, which is  able to save your souls.
1:21|KJV|Wherefore lay apart all filthiness and superfluity of naughtiness, and receive with meekness the engrafted word, which is able to save your souls.
1:21<version name="WYC">For which thing cast ye away all uncleanness, and plenty of malice, and in mildness receive ye the word that is planted <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23304c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup>, that may save your souls.</version>
1:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以你們既脫去一切的污穢，和盈餘的惡毒，就該用溫柔領受那栽種的話，就是能救你們魂的話。
1:22|ASV|But be ye doers of the word, and not hearers only, deluding your own selves.
1:22|Darby|But be ye doers of [the] word and not hearers only,  beguiling yourselves.
1:22|KJV|But be ye doers of the word, and not hearers only, deceiving your own selves.
1:22|WYC|But be ye doers of the word, and not hearers only, deceiving yourselves.
1:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只是你們要作行道者，不要單作聽道者，自己欺哄自己。
1:23|ASV|For if any one is a hearer of the word and not a doer, he is like unto a man beholding his natural face in a mirror:
1:23|Darby|For if any man be a hearer of [the] word and not a doer,  *he* is like to a man considering his natural face in a mirror:
1:23|KJV|For if any be a hearer of the word, and not a doer, he is like unto a man beholding his natural face in a glass:
1:23<version name="WYC">For if any man is an hearer of the word, and not a doer, this shall be likened to a man that beholdeth the face of his birth in a mirror [this shall be comparisoned, <i>or</i> <i>likened</i>, to a man beholding the cheer of his birth in a mirror];</version>
1:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為人若是聽道者，而不是行道者，就像人對著鏡子看自己本來的面目；
1:24|ASV|for he beholdeth himself, and goeth away, and straightway forgetteth what manner of man he was.
1:24|Darby|for he has considered himself and is gone away, and  straightway he has forgotten what he was like.
1:24|KJV|For he beholdeth himself, and goeth his way, and straightway forgetteth what manner of man he was.
1:24|WYC|for he beheld himself, and went away, and at once he forgot which he was. [for he beheld himself, and went away, and anon he forgot what manner man he was.]
1:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|看過走開以後，隨即忘了自己是甚麼樣子。
1:25|ASV|But he that looketh into the perfect law, the law of liberty, and so continueth, being not a hearer that forgetteth but a doer that worketh, this man shall be blessed in his doing.
1:25|Darby|But *he* that fixes his view on [the] perfect law, that of  liberty, and abides in [it], being not a forgetful hearer but a  doer of [the] work, *he* shall be blessed in his doing.
1:25|KJV|But whoso looketh into the perfect law of liberty, and continueth therein, he being not a forgetful hearer, but a doer of the work, this man shall be blessed in his deed.
1:25|WYC|But he that beholdeth into the law of perfect freedom, and dwelleth in it, and is not made a forgetful hearer, but a doer of work, this shall be blessed in his deed.
1:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|惟有詳細察看那完備自由的律法，並且時常如此的，他不是聽了就忘，乃是實在行出來，就在他所行的事上必然得福。
1:26|ASV|If any man thinketh himself to be religious, while he bridleth not his tongue but deceiveth his heart, this man's religion is vain.
1:26|Darby|If any one think himself to be religious, not bridling his  tongue, but deceiving his heart, this man's religion is vain.
1:26|KJV|If any man among you seem to be religious, and bridleth not his tongue, but deceiveth his own heart, this man's religion is vain.
1:26|WYC|And if any man guesseth himself to be religious, and refraineth not his tongue, but deceiveth his heart, the religion of him is vain.
1:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若有人自以為是虔敬的，卻不勒住他的舌頭，反欺騙自己的心，這人的虔敬是虛空的。
1:27<version name="ASV">Pure religion and undefiled before our God and Father is this, to visit the fatherless and widows in their affliction, and to keep oneself unspotted from the world. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:27<version name="Darby">Pure and undefiled religion before God and the Father is  this: to visit orphans and widows in their affliction, to keep  oneself unspotted from the world. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:27<version name="KJV">Pure religion and undefiled before God and the Father is this, To visit the fatherless and widows in their affliction, and to keep himself unspotted from the world.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:27|WYC|A clean religion, and unwemmed with God and the Father, is this, to visit fatherless and motherless children, and widows in their tribulation, and to keep himself undefouled from this world [and to keep himself undefouled from the world].
1:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在神與父面前，那清潔沒有玷污的虔敬，就是看顧在患難中的孤兒寡婦，保守自己不受世界玷污。
2:1|ASV|My brethren, hold not the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Lord of glory, with respect of persons.
2:1|Darby|My brethren, do not have the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ,  [Lord] of glory, with respect of persons:
2:1|KJV|My brethren, have not the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Lord of glory, with respect of persons.
2:1<version name="WYC">My brethren, do not ye have the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ of glory, in acception of persons [in acception, <i>or taking</i>, of persons].</version>
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的弟兄們，你們既相信我們榮耀的主耶穌基督，便不可按著外貌待人。
2:2|ASV|For if there come into your synagogue a man with a gold ring, in fine clothing, and there come in also a poor man in vile clothing;
2:2|Darby|for if there come unto your synagogue a man with a gold ring  in splendid apparel, and a poor man also come in in vile  apparel,
2:2|KJV|For if there come unto your assembly a man with a gold ring, in goodly apparel, and there come in also a poor man in vile raiment;
2:2<version name="WYC">For if a man that hath a golden ring, and in a fair clothing, cometh in your company, and a poor man entereth in a foul clothing, [Forsooth if there shall enter into your covent, <i>or</i> <i>gathering together</i>, a man having a gold ring, in white, <i>or fair</i>, cloth, forsooth and a poor man shall enter in foul habit, <i>or cloth</i>,]</version>
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若有一個人戴著金戒指，穿著華麗衣服，進你們的會堂去，又有一個窮人，穿著骯髒衣服也進去；
2:3|ASV|and ye have regard to him that weareth the fine clothing, and say, Sit thou here in a good place; and ye say to the poor man, Stand thou there, or sit under my footstool;
2:3|Darby|and ye look upon him who wears the splendid apparel, and  say, Do thou sit here well, and say to the poor, Do thou stand  there, or sit here under my footstool:
2:3|KJV|And ye have respect to him that weareth the gay clothing, and say unto him, Sit thou here in a good place; and say to the poor, Stand thou there, or sit here under my footstool:
2:3|WYC|and if ye behold into him [and ye behold into him] that is clothed with clear clothing, and if ye say to him, Sit thou here well; but to the poor man ye say, Stand thou there, either sit under the stool of my feet [Stand thou there, or sit under the stool of my feet];
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們就重看那穿華麗衣服的人，說，請你坐在這好位上；又對那窮人說，你站在那裡，或坐在我腳凳下邊。
2:4|ASV|Do ye not make distinctions among yourselves, and become judges with evil thoughts?
2:4|Darby|have ye not made a difference among yourselves, and become  judges having evil thoughts?
2:4|KJV|Are ye not then partial in yourselves, and are become judges of evil thoughts?
2:4|WYC|whether ye deem not with yourselves, and be made doomsmen of wicked thoughts?
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這豈不是你們中間有了歧視，用惡意判斷人麼？
2:5|ASV|Hearken, my beloved brethren; did not God choose them that are poor as to the world to be rich in faith, and heirs of the kingdom which he promised to them that love him?
2:5|Darby|Hear, my beloved brethren: Has not God chosen the poor as to  the world, rich in faith, and heirs of the kingdom, which he  has promised to them that love him?
2:5|KJV|Hearken, my beloved brethren, Hath not God chosen the poor of this world rich in faith, and heirs of the kingdom which he hath promised to them that love him?
2:5|WYC|Hear ye, my most dear-worthy brethren, whether God chose not poor men in this world, rich in faith, and heirs of the kingdom, that God promised to men that love him?
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我親愛的弟兄們，請聽，神豈不是揀選了世上貧窮的人，叫他們在信上富足，並承受祂所應許給那些愛祂之人的國麼？
2:6|ASV|But ye have dishonored the poor man. Do not the rich oppress you, and themselves drag you before the judgment-seats?
2:6|Darby|But *ye* have despised the poor [man]. Do not the rich  oppress you, and [do not] *they* drag you before [the]  tribunals?
2:6|KJV|But ye have despised the poor. Do not rich men oppress you, and draw you before the judgment seats?
2:6|WYC|But ye have despised the poor man.  Whether rich men oppress not you by power, and they draw you to dooms [and draw you to dooms]?
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們反倒羞辱貧窮的人。那富足的人豈不是欺壓你們，拉你們到法庭去麼？
2:7|ASV|Do not they blaspheme the honorable name by which ye are called?
2:7|Darby|And [do not] *they* blaspheme the excellent name which has  been called upon you?
2:7|KJV|Do not they blaspheme that worthy name by the which ye are called?
2:7|WYC|Whether they blaspheme not the good name, that is called to help on you [that is in-called of you]?
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們不是褻瀆那在你們身上被稱呼的尊名麼？
2:8|ASV|Howbeit if ye fulfil the royal law, according to the scripture, Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself, ye do well:
2:8|Darby|If indeed ye keep [the] royal law according to the  scripture, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself, ye do  well.
2:8|KJV|If ye fulfil the royal law according to the scripture, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself, ye do well:
2:8<version name="WYC">Nevertheless if ye perform the king's law, by scriptures <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23318a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself, ye do well.</version>
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們若照著經上“要愛鄰舍如同自己”的話，成全這君尊的律法，你們就作得好了；
2:9|ASV|but if ye have respect of persons, ye commit sin, being convicted by the law as transgressors.
2:9|Darby|But if ye have respect of persons, ye commit sin, being  convicted by the law as transgressors.
2:9|KJV|But if ye have respect to persons, ye commit sin, and are convinced of the law as transgressors.
2:9|WYC|But if ye take persons, ye work sin, and be reproved of the law, as trespassers [as transgressors].
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但你們若按外貌待人，便是犯罪，給律法定為犯法的。
2:10|ASV|For whosoever shall keep the whole law, and yet stumble in one point, he is become guilty of all.
2:10|Darby|For whoever shall keep the whole law and shall offend in  one [point], he has come under the guilt of [breaking] all.
2:10|KJV|For whosoever shall keep the whole law, and yet offend in one point, he is guilty of all.
2:10|WYC|And whoever keepeth all the law, but offendeth in one [Forsooth whoever shall keep all the law, soothly offend in one], he is made guilty of all.
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為凡遵守全律法，卻在一條上失腳的，他就是犯了眾條。
2:11|ASV|For he that said, Do not commit adultery, said also, Do not kill. Now if thou dost not commit adultery, but killest, thou art become a transgressor of the law.
2:11|Darby|For he who said, Thou shalt not commit adultery, said also,  Thou shalt not kill. Now if thou dost not commit adultery, but  killest, thou art become transgressor of [the] law.
2:11|KJV|For he that said, Do not commit adultery, said also, Do not kill. Now if thou commit no adultery, yet if thou kill, thou art become a transgressor of the law.
2:11|WYC|For he that said, Thou shalt do no lechery [Thou shalt not do lechery], said also, Thou shalt not slay; that if thou doest no lechery, but thou slayest, thou art made [a] trespasser of the law.
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|原來那說不可姦淫的，也說不可殺人。你若是不姦淫，卻殺人，還是成了犯律法的。
2:12|ASV|So speak ye, and so do, as men that are to be judged by a law of liberty.
2:12|Darby|So speak ye, and so act, as those that are to be judged by  [the] law of liberty;
2:12|KJV|So speak ye, and so do, as they that shall be judged by the law of liberty.
2:12|WYC|Thus speak ye, and thus do ye, as beginning to be deemed by the law of freedom.
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們既然要按自由的律法受審判，就該照這律法說話行事。
2:13|ASV|For judgment is without mercy to him that hath showed no mercy: mercy glorieth against judgment.
2:13|Darby|for judgment [will be] without mercy to him that has shewn  no mercy. Mercy glories over judgment.
2:13|KJV|For he shall have judgment without mercy, that hath shewed no mercy; and mercy rejoiceth against judgment.
2:13<version name="WYC">For why doom without mercy <i>is</i> to him, that doeth no mercy; but mercy above raiseth doom.</version>
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為那不憐憫人的，也要受無憐憫的審判；憐憫原是向審判誇勝。
2:14|ASV|What doth it profit, my brethren, if a man say he hath faith, but have not works? can that faith save him?
2:14|Darby|What [is] the profit, my brethren, if any one say he have  faith, but have not works? can faith save him?
2:14|KJV|What doth it profit, my brethren, though a man say he hath faith, and have not works? can faith save him?
2:14|WYC|My brethren, what shall it profit, if any man say that he hath faith, but he hath not works? whether faith shall be able to save him?
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的弟兄們，若有人說自己有信心，卻沒有行為，有甚麼益處？難道這信心能救他麼？
2:15|ASV|If a brother or sister be naked and in lack of daily food,
2:15|Darby|Now if a brother or a sister is naked and destitute of  daily food,
2:15|KJV|If a brother or sister be naked, and destitute of daily food,
2:15|WYC|And if a brother or sister be naked, and have need of each day's livelode [of each day's lifelode],
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若有弟兄或姊妹經常是赤身露體的，又缺了日用的食物，
2:16|ASV|and one of you say unto them, Go in peace, be ye warmed and filled; and yet ye give them not the things needful to the body; what doth it profit?
2:16|Darby|and one from amongst you say to them, Go in peace, be  warmed and filled; but give not to them the needful things for  the body, what [is] the profit?
2:16|KJV|And one of you say unto them, Depart in peace, be ye warmed and filled; notwithstanding ye give them not those things which are needful to the body; what doth it profit?
2:16|WYC|and if any of you say to them, Go ye in peace [Go in peace], be ye made hot, and be ye filled; but if ye give not to them those things that be necessary to the body, what shall it profit?
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|而你們中間有人對他們說，平平安安的去罷，願你們穿得暖，喫得飽；卻不給他們身體所需用的，有甚麼益處？
2:17|ASV|Even so faith, if it have not works, is dead in itself.
2:17|Darby|So also faith, if it have not works, is dead by itself.
2:17|KJV|Even so faith, if it hath not works, is dead, being alone.
2:17|WYC|So also faith, if it hath not works, is dead in itself.
2:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|信心也是這樣，若沒有行為，就是死的。
2:18|ASV|Yea, a man will say, Thou hast faith, and I have works: show me thy faith apart from thy works, and I by my works will show thee my faith.
2:18|Darby|But some one will say, *Thou* hast faith and *I* have  works. Shew me thy faith without works, and *I* from my works  will shew thee my faith.
2:18|KJV|Yea, a man may say, Thou hast faith, and I have works: shew me thy faith without thy works, and I will shew thee my faith by my works.
2:18|WYC|But some man shall say, Thou hast faith, and I have works; show thou to me thy faith without works [show thou me thy faith without works], and I shall show to thee my faith of works.
2:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有人會說，你有信心，我有行為；你將你沒有行為的信心指給我看，我便由我的行為，將我的信心指給你看。
2:19|ASV|Thou believest that God is one; thou doest well: the demons also believe, and shudder.
2:19|Darby|*Thou* believest that God is one. Thou doest well. The  demons even believe, and tremble.
2:19|KJV|Thou believest that there is one God; thou doest well: the devils also believe, and tremble.
2:19|WYC|Thou believest, that one God is; thou doest well; and devils believe, and [together] tremble.
2:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你信神只有一位；你信的不錯；鬼也信，卻是戰驚。
2:20|ASV|But wilt thou know, O vain man, that faith apart from works is barren?
2:20|Darby|But wilt thou know, O vain man, that faith without works is  dead?
2:20|KJV|But wilt thou know, O vain man, that faith without works is dead?
2:20|WYC|But wilt thou know, thou vain man, that faith without works is idle?
2:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|虛浮的人哪，你願意知道沒有行為的信心是無用的麼？
2:21|ASV|Was not Abraham our father justified by works, in that he offered up Isaac his son upon the altar?
2:21|Darby|Was not Abraham our father justified by works when he had  offered Isaac his son upon the altar?
2:21|KJV|Was not Abraham our father justified by works, when he had offered Isaac his son upon the altar?
2:21|WYC|Whether Abraham, our father, was not justified of works [Abraham, our father, whether he was not justified of works], offering Isaac, his son, on the altar?
2:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們的祖宗亞伯拉罕，把他兒子以撒獻在壇上，豈不是本於行為得稱義麼？
2:22|ASV|Thou seest that faith wrought with his works, and by works was faith made perfect;
2:22|Darby|Thou seest that faith wrought with his works, and that by  works faith was perfected.
2:22|KJV|Seest thou how faith wrought with his works, and by works was faith made perfect?
2:22|WYC|Therefore thou seest, that faith wrought with his works, and his faith was filled of works [and his faith was fulfilled of works].
2:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你看，信心是與他的行為同工，而且信心本於行為纔得完全；
2:23|ASV|and the scripture was fulfilled which saith, And Abraham believed God, and it was reckoned unto him for righteousness; and he was called the friend of God.
2:23|Darby|And the scripture was fulfilled which says, Abraham  believed God, and it was reckoned to him as righteousness, and  he was called Friend of God.
2:23|KJV|And the scripture was fulfilled which saith, Abraham believed God, and it was imputed unto him for righteousness: and he was called the Friend of God.
2:23<version name="WYC">And the scripture was filled, saying, Abraham believed to God, and it was areckoned to him to rightwiseness <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23333b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup>, and he was called the friend of God.</version>
2:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這就應驗經上所說的：“亞伯拉罕信神，這就算為他的義。”他又得稱為神的朋友。
2:24|ASV|Ye see that by works a man is justified, and not only by faith.
2:24|Darby|Ye see that a man is justified on the principle of works,  and not on the principle of faith only.
2:24|KJV|Ye see then how that by works a man is justified, and not by faith only.
2:24|WYC|Ye see that a man is justified of works, and not of faith only.
2:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|可見人得稱義是本於行為，不是單本於信。
2:25|ASV|And in like manner was not also Rahab the harlot justified by works, in that she received the messengers, and sent them out another way?
2:25|Darby|But was not in like manner also Rahab the harlot justified  on the principle of works, when she had received the messengers  and put [them] forth by another way?
2:25|KJV|Likewise also was not Rahab the harlot justified by works, when she had received the messengers, and had sent them out another way?
2:25|WYC|In like manner, whether also Rahab, the whore, was not justified of works, and received the messengers, and sent them out by another way?
2:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|妓女喇合接待使者，又放他們從別的路上出去，不也是一樣本於行為得稱義麼？
2:26<version name="ASV">For as the body apart from the spirit is dead, even so faith apart from works is dead. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:26<version name="Darby">For as the body without a spirit is dead, so also faith  without works is dead. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:26<version name="KJV">For as the body without the spirit is dead, so faith without works is dead also.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:26|WYC|For as the body without spirit is dead, so also faith without works is dead.
2:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|身體沒有靈是死的，照樣，信心沒有行為也是死的。
3:1|ASV|Be not many of you teachers, my brethren, knowing that we shall receive heavier judgment.
3:1|Darby|Be not many teachers, my brethren, knowing that we shall  receive greater judgment.
3:1|KJV|My brethren, be not many masters, knowing that we shall receive the greater condemnation.
3:1|WYC|My brethren, do not ye be made many masters, witting that ye take the more doom.
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的弟兄們，不要多人作教師，因為知道我們要受更重的審判。
3:2|ASV|For in many things we all stumble. If any stumbleth not in word, the same is a perfect man, able to bridle the whole body also.
3:2|Darby|For we all often offend. If any one offend not in word, *he*  [is] a perfect man, able to bridle the whole body too.
3:2|KJV|For in many things we offend all. If any man offend not in word, the same is a perfect man, and able also to bridle the whole body.
3:2|WYC|For all we offend in many things.  If any man offendeth not in word, this is a perfect man; for also he may lead about all the body with a bridle [forsooth he may with a bridle lead about all the body].
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們在許多事上都有過失，若有人在話語上沒有過失，他就是完全人，也能勒住全身。
3:3|ASV|Now if we put the horses' bridles into their mouths that they may obey us, we turn about their whole body also.
3:3|Darby|Behold, we put the bits in the mouths of the horses, that  they may obey us, and we turn round their whole bodies.
3:3|KJV|Behold, we put bits in the horses' mouths, that they may obey us; and we turn about their whole body.
3:3|WYC|For if we put bridles into horses' mouths, for to consent to us, and we lead about all the body of them.
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們若把嚼環放在馬嘴裡，叫牠們服從我們，就能調動牠們的全身。
3:4|ASV|Behold, the ships also, though they are so great and are driven by rough winds, are yet turned about by a very small rudder, whither the impulse of the steersman willeth.
3:4|Darby|Behold also the ships, which are so great, and driven by  violent winds, are turned about by a very small rudder,  wherever the pleasure of the helmsman will.
3:4|KJV|Behold also the ships, which though they be so great, and are driven of fierce winds, yet are they turned about with a very small helm, whithersoever the governor listeth.
3:4|WYC|And lo! ships, when they be great, and be driven of strong winds, yet they be borne about of a little rudder, where the moving of the governor will.
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|看哪，船隻雖然那麼大，又被狂風催逼，無論掌舵者的意思要往那裡去，都能被小小的舵調動。
3:5|ASV|So the tongue also is a little member, and boasteth great things. Behold, how much wood is kindled by how small a fire!
3:5|Darby|Thus also the tongue is a little member, and boasts great  things. See how little a fire, how large a wood it kindles!
3:5|KJV|Even so the tongue is a little member, and boasteth great things. Behold, how great a matter a little fire kindleth!
3:5|WYC|So also the tongue is but a little member, and raiseth great things.  Lo! how little fire burneth a full great wood [Lo! how much fire kindleth how great a wood].
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|舌頭也是這樣，雖是個小肢體，卻能說誇大的話。看哪，多麼小的火，能點著多麼大的樹林。
3:6|ASV|And the tongue is a fire: the world of iniquity among our members is the tongue, which defileth the whole body, and setteth on fire the wheel of nature, and is set on fire by hell.
3:6|Darby|and the tongue [is] fire, the world of unrighteousness; the  tongue is set in our members, the defiler of the whole body,  and which sets fire to the course of nature, and is set on fire  of hell.
3:6|KJV|And the tongue is a fire, a world of iniquity: so is the tongue among our members, that it defileth the whole body, and setteth on fire the course of nature; and it is set on fire of hell.
3:6<version name="WYC">And our tongue is fire, the university of wickedness.  The tongue is ordained in our members, which defouleth all the body; and it is inflamed of hell [and it is inflamed, <i>or set afire</i>, of hell], and inflameth the wheel of our birth.</version>
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|舌頭就是火，在我們百體中，是個不義的世界，污穢全身，也把生命的輪子點起來，且是給火坑的火點著的。
3:7|ASV|For every kind of beasts and birds, of creeping things and things in the sea, is tamed, and hath been tamed by mankind.
3:7|Darby|For every species both of beasts and of birds, both of  creeping things and of sea animals, is tamed and has been tamed  by the human species;
3:7|KJV|For every kind of beasts, and of birds, and of serpents, and of things in the sea, is tamed, and hath been tamed of mankind:
3:7<version name="WYC">And all the kind of beasts, and of fowls, and of serpents, and of others is chastised, and those be made tame of man's kind; [Soothly all kind of beasts, and fowls, and serpents, and of others, be overcome, <i>or</i> <i>under-yoked</i>, and be made tame, of mankind];</version>
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|原來各類走獸、飛禽、爬物和水族的性情，都可以制伏，也已經被人的性情制伏了；
3:8|ASV|But the tongue can no man tame; it is a restless evil, it is full of deadly poison.
3:8|Darby|but the tongue can no one among men tame; [it is] an  unsettled evil, full of death-bringing poison.
3:8|KJV|But the tongue can no man tame; it is an unruly evil, full of deadly poison.
3:8<version name="WYC">but no man may chastise the tongue, for it is an unpeaceable evil [soothly it is an unquiet, <i>or unpeaceable</i>, evil thing], and full of deadly venom.</version>
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|惟獨舌頭沒有人能制伏，是不止息的惡物，滿了致死的毒氣。
3:9|ASV|Therewith bless we the Lord and Father; and therewith curse we men, who are made after the likeness of God:
3:9|Darby|Therewith bless we the Lord and Father, and therewith curse  we men made after [the] likeness of God.
3:9|KJV|Therewith bless we God, even the Father; and therewith curse we men, which are made after the similitude of God.
3:9|WYC|In it we bless God, the Father, and in it we curse men, that be made to the likeness of God.
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們用舌頭頌讚那為主為父的，又用舌頭咒詛那照著神樣式受造的人。
3:10|ASV|out of the same mouth cometh forth blessing and cursing. My brethren, these things ought not so to be.
3:10|Darby|Out of the same mouth goes forth blessing and cursing. It  is not right, my brethren, that these things should be thus.
3:10|KJV|Out of the same mouth proceedeth blessing and cursing. My brethren, these things ought not so to be.
3:10|WYC|Of the same mouth passeth forth blessing and cursing [Of the same mouth cometh forth blessing and cursing].  My brethren, it behooveth not that these things be done so.
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|頌讚和咒詛從同一個口裡出來，我的弟兄們，這是不應當的。
3:11|ASV|Doth the fountain send forth from the same opening sweet water and bitter?
3:11|Darby|Does the fountain, out of the same opening, pour forth  sweet and bitter?
3:11|KJV|Doth a fountain send forth at the same place sweet water and bitter?
3:11|WYC|Whether a well of the same hole bringeth forth [bring forth] sweet and salt water?
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|泉源從同一個眼裡能湧出甜水和苦水麼？
3:12|ASV|Can a fig tree, my brethren, yield olives, or a vine figs? Neither can salt water yield sweet.
3:12|Darby|Can, my brethren, a fig produce olives, or a vine figs?  Neither [can] salt [water] make sweet water.
3:12|KJV|Can the fig tree, my brethren, bear olive berries? either a vine, figs? so can no fountain both yield salt water and fresh.
3:12|WYC|My brethren, whether a fig tree may make grapes, either a vine figs [or a vine figs]?  So neither salt water may make sweet water.
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的弟兄們，無花果樹能生橄欖麼？葡萄樹能結無花果麼？鹹水也不能發出甜水來。
3:13|ASV|Who is wise and understanding among you? let him show by his good life his works in meekness of wisdom.
3:13|Darby|Who [is] wise and understanding among you; let him shew out  of a good conversation his works in meekness of wisdom;
3:13|KJV|Who is a wise man and endued with knowledge among you? let him shew out of a good conversation his works with meekness of wisdom.
3:13<version name="WYC">Who <i>is</i> wise, and taught among you? show he of good living his working, in mildness of his wisdom [show he of good living his work, in mildness of wisdom].</version>
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們中間誰是有智慧有見識的？他就當用智慧的溫柔，憑他美好的品行，顯出他所作所為的。
3:14|ASV|But if ye have bitter jealousy and faction in your heart, glory not and lie not against the truth.
3:14|Darby|but if ye have bitter emulation and strife in your hearts,  do not boast and lie against the truth.
3:14|KJV|But if ye have bitter envying and strife in your hearts, glory not, and lie not against the truth.
3:14<version name="WYC">That if ye have bitter envy, and strivings be in your hearts, do not ye have glory [That if ye have bitter zeal, <i>or envy</i>, and strives be in your hearts, do not ye glory], and be liars against the truth.</version>
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但你們心裡若懷著苦毒的嫉妒和私圖好爭，就不要再誇口，也不要再說謊抵擋真理了。
3:15|ASV|This wisdom is not a wisdom that cometh down from above, but is earthly, sensual, devilish.
3:15|Darby|This is not the wisdom which comes down from above, but  earthly, natural, devilish.
3:15|KJV|This wisdom descendeth not from above, but is earthly, sensual, devilish.
3:15|WYC|For this wisdom is not from above coming down, but earthly, and beastly, and fiendly [but earthly, beastly, fiendly].
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣的智慧，不是從上頭下來的，乃是屬地的、屬魂的、出於鬼且像鬼的。
3:16|ASV|For where jealousy and faction are, there is confusion and every vile deed.
3:16|Darby|For where emulation and strife [are], there [is] disorder  and every evil thing.
3:16|KJV|For where envying and strife is, there is confusion and every evil work.
3:16<version name="WYC">For where is envy and strife, there <i>is</i> unsteadfastness and all depraved work [and all shrewd work].</version>
3:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為何處有嫉妒和私圖好爭，何處就有擾亂和各樣的壞事。
3:17|ASV|But the wisdom that is from above is first pure, then peaceable, gentle, easy to be entreated, full of mercy and good fruits, without variance, without hypocrisy.
3:17|Darby|But the wisdom from above first is pure, then peaceful,  gentle, yielding, full of mercy and good fruits, unquestioning,  unfeigned.
3:17|KJV|But the wisdom that is from above is first pure, then peaceable, gentle, and easy to be intreated, full of mercy and good fruits, without partiality, and without hypocrisy.
3:17<version name="WYC">But wisdom that is from above, first it is chaste, afterward peaceable, mild, able to be counseled [persuadable, <i>that is</i>,<i> easy to treat</i>,<i> and to be treated</i>], consenting to good things, full of mercy and of good fruits, deeming without feigning.</version>
3:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|惟獨從上頭來的智慧，先是純潔的，後是和平的、和藹的、柔順的，滿有憐憫和善果，沒有偏見，沒有假冒。
3:18<version name="ASV">And the fruit of righteousness is sown in peace for them that make peace. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:18<version name="Darby">But [the] fruit of righteousness in peace is sown for them  that make peace. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:18<version name="KJV">And the fruit of righteousness is sown in peace of them that make peace.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:18|WYC|And the fruit of rightwiseness is sown in peace, to men that make peace.
3:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且義的果子，乃是由那些製造和平的人，在和平中所種植的。
4:1|ASV|Whence come wars and whence come fightings among you? come they not hence, even of your pleasures that war in your members?
4:1|Darby|Whence [come] wars and whence fightings among you? [Is it]  not thence, -- from your pleasures, which war in your members?
4:1|KJV|From whence come wars and fightings among you? come they not hence, even of your lusts that war in your members?
4:1<version name="WYC">Whereof <i>be</i> battles and chidings among you?  Whether not of your covetings, that fight in your members?</version>
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們中間的爭戰是從那裡來的？鬥毆是從那裡來的？豈不是從你們肢體中交戰的私慾來的麼？
4:2|ASV|Ye lust, and have not: ye kill, and covet, and cannot obtain: ye fight and war; ye have not, because ye ask not.
4:2|Darby|Ye lust and have not: ye kill and are full of envy, and  cannot obtain; ye fight and war; ye have not because ye ask  not.
4:2|KJV|Ye lust, and have not: ye kill, and desire to have, and cannot obtain: ye fight and war, yet ye have not, because ye ask not.
4:2|WYC|Ye covet, and ye have not; ye slay, and ye have envy, and ye be not able to get [ye slay, and have envy, and ye be not able to get].  Ye chide, and make battle; and ye have not, for that ye ask not.
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們縱任貪慾，仍無所有；你們殺害嫉妒，也不能得，你們就鬥毆爭戰。你們沒有，是因為你們不求；
4:3|ASV|Ye ask, and receive not, because ye ask amiss, that ye may spend  it in your pleasures.
4:3|Darby|Ye ask and receive not, because ye ask evilly, that ye may  consume [it] in your pleasures.
4:3|KJV|Ye ask, and receive not, because ye ask amiss, that ye may consume it upon your lusts.
4:3|WYC|Ye ask, and ye receive not; for that ye ask evil, as ye show openly in your covetings.
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們求也無所得，是因為你們妄求，為要耗費在你們的宴樂中。
4:4|ASV|Ye adulteresses, know ye not that the friendship of the world is enmity with God? Whosoever therefore would be a friend of the world maketh himself an enemy of God.
4:4|Darby|Adulteresses, know ye not that friendship with the world is  enmity with God? Whoever therefore is minded to be [the] friend  of the world is constituted enemy of God.
4:4|KJV|Ye adulterers and adulteresses, know ye not that the friendship of the world is enmity with God? whosoever therefore will be a friend of the world is the enemy of God.
4:4|WYC|Adulterers, know not ye, that the friendship of this world is enemy to God?  Therefore whoever will be the friend of this world, is made the enemy of God.
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們這些淫亂的人，豈不知與世界為友，就是與神為敵麼？所以凡想要與世界為友的，就成了神的仇敵。
4:5|ASV|Or think ye that the scripture speaketh in vain? Doth the spirit which he made to dwell in us long unto envying?
4:5|Darby|Think ye that the scripture speaks in vain? Does the Spirit  which has taken his abode in us desire enviously?
4:5|KJV|Do ye think that the scripture saith in vain, The spirit that dwelleth in us lusteth to envy?
4:5|WYC|Whether ye guess [Whether ween ye], that the scripture saith vainly, The spirit that dwelleth in you, coveteth to envy?
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|經上說，“祂使其居住在我們裡面的那靈，戀慕以至於嫉妒。”你們想，這話是徒然的麼？
4:6|ASV|But he giveth more grace. Wherefore the scripture saith, God resisteth the proud, but giveth grace to the humble.
4:6|Darby|But he gives more grace. Wherefore he says, God sets himself  against [the] proud, but gives grace to [the] lowly.
4:6|KJV|But he giveth more grace. Wherefore he saith, God resisteth the proud, but giveth grace unto the humble.
4:6|WYC|But he giveth the more grace [Forsooth he giveth more grace]; for which thing he saith, God withstandeth proud men, but to meek men he giveth grace.
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但祂賜更大的恩典；所以經上說，“神敵擋狂傲的人，賜恩給謙卑的人。”
4:7|ASV|Be subject therefore unto God; but resist the devil, and he will flee from you.
4:7|Darby|Subject yourselves therefore to God. Resist the devil, and  he will flee from you.
4:7|KJV|Submit yourselves therefore to God. Resist the devil, and he will flee from you.
4:7|WYC|Therefore be ye subject to God; but withstand ye the devil, and he shall flee from you.
4:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以你們要服從神，抵擋魔鬼，魔鬼就必離開你們逃跑了。
4:8|ASV|Draw nigh to God, and he will draw nigh to you. Cleanse your hands, ye sinners; and purify your hearts, ye doubleminded.
4:8|Darby|Draw near to God, and he will draw near to you. Cleanse  [your] hands, sinners, and purify [your] hearts, ye  double-minded.
4:8|KJV|Draw nigh to God, and he will draw nigh to you. Cleanse your hands, ye sinners; and purify your hearts, ye double minded.
4:8<version name="WYC">Approach ye to God, and he shall approach to you.  Ye sinners, cleanse ye the hands, and ye double in soul, purge ye the hearts. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23362a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
4:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要親近神，神就必親近你們。有罪的人哪，要潔淨你們的手。心懷二意的人哪，要純潔你們的心。
4:9|ASV|Be afflicted, and mourn, and weep: let your laughter be turned to mourning, and your joy to heaviness.
4:9|Darby|Be wretched, and mourn, and weep: let your laughter be  turned to mourning, and [your] joy to heaviness.
4:9|KJV|Be afflicted, and mourn, and weep: let your laughter be turned to mourning, and your joy to heaviness.
4:9|WYC|Be ye wretches, and wail ye [and weep ye]; your laughing be [it] turned into weeping, and [your] joy into sorrow of heart.
4:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要愁苦、哀慟、哭泣；你們的喜笑要變作哀慟，歡樂要變作憂鬱。
4:10|ASV|Humble yourselves in the sight of the Lord, and he shall exalt you.
4:10|Darby|Humble yourselves before [the] Lord, and he shall exalt  you.
4:10|KJV|Humble yourselves in the sight of the Lord, and he shall lift you up.
4:10|WYC|Be ye meeked in the sight of the Lord, and he shall enhance you.
4:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要在主面前降卑，主就必叫你們升高。
4:11|ASV|Speak not one against another, brethren. He that speaketh against a brother, or judgeth his brother, speaketh against the law, and judgeth the law: but if thou judgest the law, thou art not a doer of the law, but a judge.
4:11|Darby|Speak not against one another, brethren. He that speaks  against [his] brother, or judges his brother, speaks against  [the] law and judges [the] law. But if thou judgest [the] law,  thou art not doer of [the] law, but judge.
4:11|KJV|Speak not evil one of another, brethren. He that speaketh evil of his brother, and judgeth his brother, speaketh evil of the law, and judgeth the law: but if thou judge the law, thou art not a doer of the law, but a judge.
4:11|WYC|My brethren, do not ye backbite each other.  He that backbiteth his brother, either that deemeth his brother [or that deemeth his brother], backbiteth the law, and deemeth the law.  And if thou deemest the law, thou art not a doer of the law, but a doomsman.
4:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，你們不可彼此批評；那批評弟兄，或審判弟兄的，就是批評律法，審判律法。你若審判律法，就不是行律法者，乃是審判者。
4:12|ASV|One only is the lawgiver and judge, even he who is able to save and to destroy: but who art thou that judgest thy neighbor?
4:12|Darby|One is the lawgiver and judge, who is able to save and to  destroy: but who art *thou* who judgest thy neighbour?
4:12|KJV|There is one lawgiver, who is able to save and to destroy: who art thou that judgest another?
4:12|WYC|But one is maker of the law, and judge, that may destroy, and deliver [that may lose, and deliver].  And who art thou, that deemest thy neighbour?
4:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|設立律法者和審判者只有一位，就是那能救人，也能滅人的。你這審判鄰舍的，你是誰？
4:13|ASV|Come now, ye that say, To-day or to-morrow we will go into this city, and spend a year there, and trade, and get gain:
4:13|Darby|Go to now, ye who say, To-day or to-morrow will we go into  such a city and spend a year there, and traffic and make gain,
4:13|KJV|Go to now, ye that say, To day or to morrow we will go into such a city, and continue there a year, and buy and sell, and get gain:
4:13|WYC|Lo! now ye, that say, To day either to morrow [To day or to morrow] we shall go into that city, and there we shall dwell a year, and we shall make merchandise, and we shall make winning;
4:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|嗐，你們說，今天或明天，我們要往某城去，在那裡住一年，作買賣得利；
4:14|ASV|whereas ye know not what shall be on the morrow. What is your life? For ye are a vapor, that appeareth for a little time, and then vanisheth away.
4:14|Darby|ye who do not know what will be on the morrow, ([for] what  [is] your life? It is even a vapour, appearing for a little  while, and then disappearing,)
4:14|KJV|Whereas ye know not what shall be on the morrow. For what is your life? It is even a vapour, that appeareth for a little time, and then vanisheth away.
4:14<version name="WYC">which know not [that know not], what is to you in the morrow.  For what is your life?  A smoke [A vapour, <i>or</i> <i>smoke</i>,] appearing at a little time, and afterward it shall be wasted.</version>
4:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其實明天的事你們並不知道。你們的生命是甚麼？你們原是一團霧氣，出現少時，隨後就不見了。
4:15|ASV|For that ye ought to say, If the Lord will, we shall both live, and do this or that.
4:15|Darby|instead of your saying, If the Lord should [so] will and we  should live, we will also do this or that.
4:15|KJV|For that ye ought to say, If the Lord will, we shall live, and do this, or that.
4:15|WYC|Therefore that ye say, If the Lord will, and if we [shall] live, we shall do this thing, either that thing [or that thing].
4:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們倒應當說，主若願意，我們就可以活著，也可以作這事，或作那事。
4:16|ASV|But now ye glory in your vauntings: all such glorying is evil.
4:16|Darby|But now ye glory in your vauntings: all such glorying is  evil.
4:16|KJV|But now ye rejoice in your boastings: all such rejoicing is evil.
4:16|WYC|And now ye make full out joy in your prides; every such joying is wicked.
4:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現今你們竟以張狂誇口；凡這樣誇口都是惡的。
4:17<version name="ASV">To him therefore that knoweth to do good, and doeth it not, to him it is sin. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:17<version name="Darby">To him therefore who knows how to do good, and does it not,  to him it is sin. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:17<version name="KJV">Therefore to him that knoweth to do good, and doeth it not, to him it is sin.</p><p /><br /></version>
4:17|WYC|Therefore it is sin to him, that knoweth to do good, and doeth not. [Therefore to a man knowing to do good, and not doing, sin is to him.]
4:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此，人若知道行善，卻不去行，這對他就是罪了。
5:1|ASV|Come now, ye rich, weep and howl for your miseries that are coming upon you.
5:1|Darby|Go to now, ye rich, weep, howling over your miseries that  [are] coming upon [you].
5:1|KJV|Go to now, ye rich men, weep and howl for your miseries that shall come upon you.
5:1|WYC|Do now, ye rich men, weep ye, yelling in your wretchednesses that shall come to you.
5:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|嗐，你們富足的人，應當為那將要臨到你們的悲慘哭泣號咷。
5:2|ASV|Your riches are corrupted, and your garments are moth-eaten.
5:2|Darby|Your wealth is become rotten, and your garments moth-eaten.
5:2|KJV|Your riches are corrupted, and your garments are motheaten.
5:2|WYC|Your riches be rotten, and your clothes be eaten of moths.
5:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們的財物壞了，衣服也被蟲子咬了。
5:3|ASV|Your gold and your silver are rusted; and their rust shall be for a testimony against you, and shall eat your flesh as fire. Ye have laid up your treasure in the last days.
5:3|Darby|Your gold and silver is eaten away, and their canker shall  be for a witness against you, and shall eat your flesh as fire.  Ye have heaped up treasure in [the] last days.
5:3|KJV|Your gold and silver is cankered; and the rust of them shall be a witness against you, and shall eat your flesh as it were fire. Ye have heaped treasure together for the last days.
5:3|WYC|Your gold and silver hath rusted, and the rust of them shall be to you into witnessing, and shall eat your fleshes, as fire.  Ye have treasured to you wrath in the last days.
5:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們的金銀都袘k了，這蚼n作見證，定你們的罪，又要像火一樣，喫你們的肉。你們在末後的日子積蓄財寶。
5:4|ASV|Behold, the hire of the laborers who mowed your fields, which is of you kept back by fraud, crieth out: and the cries of them that reaped have entered into the ears of the Lord of Sabaoth.
5:4|Darby|Behold, the wages of your labourers, who have harvested your  fields, wrongfully kept back by you, cry, and the cries of  those that have reaped are entered into the ears of [the] Lord  of sabaoth.
5:4|KJV|Behold, the hire of the labourers who have reaped down your fields, which is of you kept back by fraud, crieth: and the cries of them which have reaped are entered into the ears of the Lord of sabaoth.
5:4|WYC|Lo! the hire of your workmen, that reaped your fields, which is defrauded of you [which is frauded of you], crieth; and the cry of them hath entered into the ears of the Lord of hosts.
5:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|看哪，工人收割你們的田地，你們扣下他們的工錢，這工錢為他們喊冤；並且那收割之人的呼聲，已經入了萬軍之主的耳中。
5:5|ASV|Ye have lived delicately on the earth, and taken your pleasure; ye have nourished your hearts in a day of slaughter.
5:5|Darby|Ye have lived luxuriously on the earth and indulged  yourselves; ye have nourished your hearts [as] in a day of  slaughter;
5:5|KJV|Ye have lived in pleasure on the earth, and been wanton; ye have nourished your hearts, as in a day of slaughter.
5:5|WYC|Ye have eaten on the earth, and in your lecheries ye have nourished your hearts.  In the day of slaying
5:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們活在地上奢華宴樂；當宰殺的日子，竟養肥了你們的心。
5:6|ASV|Ye have condemned, ye have killed the righteous one; he doth not resist you.
5:6|Darby|ye have condemned, ye have killed the just; he does not  resist you.
5:6|KJV|Ye have condemned and killed the just; and he doth not resist you.
5:6|WYC|ye brought, and slew the just man, and he against-stood not you [and he withstood you not].
5:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們定了義人的罪，把他殺害，他沒有敵擋你們。
5:7|ASV|Be patient therefore, brethren, until the coming of the Lord. Behold, the husbandman waiteth for the precious fruit of the earth, being patient over it, until it receive the early and latter rain.
5:7|Darby|Have patience, therefore, brethren, till the coming of the  Lord. Behold, the labourer awaits the precious fruit of the  earth, having patience for it until it receive [the] early and  [the] latter rain.
5:7|KJV|Be patient therefore, brethren, unto the coming of the Lord. Behold, the husbandman waiteth for the precious fruit of the earth, and hath long patience for it, until he receive the early and latter rain.
5:7<version name="WYC">Therefore, brethren, be ye patient, till to the coming of the Lord.  Lo! an earth-tiller abideth [the] precious fruit of the earth, patiently suffering, till he receive timeful and lateful <i>fruit</i>.</version>
5:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，弟兄們，你們要恆忍，直到主的來臨。看哪，農夫等候地裡寶貴的出產，為此恆忍，直到得了秋雨春雨。
5:8|ASV|Be ye also patient; establish your hearts: for the coming of the Lord is at hand.
5:8|Darby|*Ye* also have patience: stablish your hearts, for the  coming of the Lord is drawn nigh.
5:8|KJV|Be ye also patient; stablish your hearts: for the coming of the Lord draweth nigh.
5:8|WYC|And be ye patient, and confirm ye your hearts, for the coming of the Lord shall approach. [And be ye patient, and confirm your hearts, for the coming of the Lord shall nigh.]
5:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們也當恆忍，堅固你們的心，因為主的來臨近了。
5:9|ASV|Murmur not, brethren, one against another, that ye be not judged: behold, the judge standeth before the doors.
5:9|Darby|Complain not one against another, brethren, that ye be not  judged. Behold, the judge stands before the door.
5:9|KJV|Grudge not one against another, brethren, lest ye be condemned: behold, the judge standeth before the door.
5:9|WYC|Brethren, do not ye be sorrowful each to other [Brethren, do not ye be scornful each to other], that ye be not deemed.  Lo! the judge standeth nigh before the gate.
5:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，你們不要彼此埋怨，免得受審判；看哪，那審判者站在門前了。
5:10|ASV|Take, brethren, for an example of suffering and of patience, the prophets who spake in the name of the Lord.
5:10|Darby|Take [as] an example, brethren, of suffering and having  patience, the prophets, who have spoken in the name of [the]  Lord.
5:10|KJV|Take, my brethren, the prophets, who have spoken in the name of the Lord, for an example of suffering affliction, and of patience.
5:10|WYC|Brethren, take ye ensample of evil going out, and of long abiding, and travail [Brethren, take ye example of evil going out, and of long abiding of travail], and of patience, the prophets, that spake to you in the name of the Lord.
5:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，你們要把那曾在主名裡說話的眾申言者，當作受苦和恆忍的榜樣。
5:11|ASV|Behold, we call them blessed that endured: ye have heard of the patience of Job, and have seen the end of the Lord, how that the Lord is full of pity, and merciful.
5:11|Darby|Behold, we call them blessed who have endured. Ye have  heard of the endurance of Job, and seen the end of the Lord;  that the Lord is full of tender compassion and pitiful.
5:11|KJV|Behold, we count them happy which endure. Ye have heard of the patience of Job, and have seen the end of the Lord; that the Lord is very pitiful, and of tender mercy.
5:11|WYC|Lo! we bless them that suffered.  Ye have heard the patience of Job, and ye saw the end of the Lord, for the Lord is merciful, and doing mercy.
5:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|看哪，我們稱那忍耐的人是有福的。你們聽見過約伯的忍耐，也看見過主給他的結局，明顯主是滿有慈心，且有憐恤。
5:12|ASV|But above all things, my brethren, swear not, neither by the heaven, nor by the earth, nor by any other oath: but let your yea be yea, and your nay, nay; that ye fall not under judgment.
5:12|Darby|But before all things, my brethren, swear not, neither by  heaven, nor by the earth, nor by any other oath; but let your  yea be yea, and your nay, nay, that ye do not fall under  judgment.
5:12|KJV|But above all things, my brethren, swear not, neither by heaven, neither by the earth, neither by any other oath: but let your yea be yea; and your nay, nay; lest ye fall into condemnation.
5:12|WYC|Before all things, my brethren, do not ye swear, neither by heaven, neither by earth, neither by whatever other oath.  But be your word Yea, yea, Nay, nay, that ye fall not under doom.
5:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的弟兄們，最要緊的是不可起誓；不可指著天起誓，也不可指著地起誓，無論何誓都不可起；你們的話，是，就說是，不是，就說不是，免得你們落在審判之下。
5:13|ASV|Is any among you suffering? Let him pray. Is any cheerful? Let him sing praise.
5:13|Darby|Does any one among you suffer evil? let him pray. Is any  happy? let him sing psalms.
5:13|KJV|Is any among you afflicted? let him pray. Is any merry? let him sing psalms.
5:13<version name="WYC">And if any of you is sorrowful [Soothly if any of you is sorrowful, <i>or</i> <i>heavy</i>], pray he with patient soul, and say he a psalm.</version>
5:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們中間有受苦的麼？他該禱告。有愉快的麼？他該歌頌。
5:14|ASV|Is any among you sick? Let him call for the elders of the church; and let them pray over him, anointing him with oil in the name of the Lord:
5:14|Darby|Is any sick among you? let him call to [him] the elders of  the assembly, and let them pray over him, anointing him with  oil in the name of [the] Lord;
5:14|KJV|Is any sick among you? let him call for the elders of the church; and let them pray over him, anointing him with oil in the name of the Lord:
5:14|WYC|If any of you is sick, lead he in priests of the church, and pray they for him, and anoint him with oil in the name of the Lord [anointing with oil in the name of the Lord];
5:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們中間有病弱的麼？他該請召會的長老來，在主的名裡用油抹他，為他禱告。
5:15|ASV|and the prayer of faith shall save him that is sick, and the Lord shall raise him up; and if he have committed sins, it shall be forgiven him.
5:15|Darby|and the prayer of faith shall heal the sick, and the Lord  shall raise him up; and if he be one who has committed sins, it  shall be forgiven him.
5:15|KJV|And the prayer of faith shall save the sick, and the Lord shall raise him up; and if he have committed sins, they shall be forgiven him.
5:15<version name="WYC">and the prayer of faith shall save the sick <i>man</i>, and the Lord shall make him light <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23386a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>; and if he be in sins, they shall be forgiven to him.</version>
5:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|信心的祈禱要救那病人，主必叫他起來；他若犯了罪，也必蒙赦免。
5:16|ASV|Confess therefore your sins one to another, and pray one for another, that ye may be healed. The supplication of a righteous man availeth much in its working.
5:16|Darby|Confess therefore your offences to one another, and pray  for one another, that ye may be healed. [The] fervent  supplication of the righteous [man] has much power.
5:16|KJV|Confess your faults one to another, and pray one for another, that ye may be healed. The effectual fervent prayer of a righteous man availeth much.
5:16|WYC|Therefore acknowledge ye each to other your sins, and pray ye each for other, that ye be saved [Therefore acknowledge ye one to another your sins, and pray ye for each other, that ye be saved].  For the continual prayer of a just man is much worth.
5:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以你們要彼此認罪，互相代禱，使你們可以得醫治。義人的祈求發動起來，是大有能力的。
5:17|ASV|Elijah was a man of like passions with us, and he prayed fervently that it might not rain; and it rained not on the earth for three years and six months.
5:17|Darby|Elias was a man of like passions to us, and he prayed with  prayer that it should not rain; and it did not rain upon the  earth three years and six months;
5:17|KJV|Elias was a man subject to like passions as we are, and he prayed earnestly that it might not rain: and it rained not on the earth by the space of three years and six months.
5:17<version name="WYC">Elias was a deadly man like us [Elias was a man like to us passible, <i>or able to suffer</i>], and in prayer he prayed, that it should not rain on the earth, and it rained not three years and six months.</version>
5:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以利亞是與我們性情相同的人，他懇切禱告，求不要降雨，雨就三年零六個月不降在地上。
5:18|ASV|And he prayed again; and the heaven gave rain, and the earth brought forth her fruit.
5:18|Darby|and again he prayed, and the heaven gave rain, and the  earth caused its fruit to spring forth.
5:18|KJV|And he prayed again, and the heaven gave rain, and the earth brought forth her fruit.
5:18|WYC|And again he prayed, and heaven gave rain, and the earth gave his fruit.
5:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他又禱告，天就賜下雨水，地也生出土產。
5:19|ASV|My brethren, if any among you err from the truth, and one convert him;
5:19|Darby|My brethren, if any one among you err from the truth, and  one bring him back,
5:19|KJV|Brethren, if any of you do err from the truth, and one convert him;
5:19|WYC|And, brethren, if any of you erreth from truth, and any converteth him, [Brethren, forsooth if any of you shall err from the truth, and any shall convert him,]
5:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的弟兄們，你們中間若有人受迷惑離開真理，有人使他回轉，
5:20<version name="ASV">let him know, that he who converteth a sinner from the error of his way shall save a soul from death, and shall cover a multitude of sins. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:20<version name="Darby">let him know that he that brings back a sinner from [the]  error of his way shall save a soul from death and shall cover a  multitude of sins. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:20<version name="KJV">Let him know, that he which converteth the sinner from the error of his way shall save a soul from death, and shall hide a multitude of sins.</p><p /><br /></version>
5:20|WYC|he oweth to know, that he that maketh a sinner to be turned from the error of his way, shall save the soul of him from death, and covereth the multitude of sins.  [Amen.]
5:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這人該知道，那叫一個罪人從他錯謬的路上轉回的，必救他的魂脫離死亡，也必遮蓋眾多的罪。
