1:1|ASV|Jude, a servant of Jesus Christ, and brother of James, to them that are called, beloved in God the Father, and kept for Jesus Christ:
1:1|Darby|Jude, bondman of Jesus Christ, and brother of James, to the  called ones beloved in God [the] Father and preserved in Jesus  Christ:
1:1|KJV|Jude, the servant of Jesus Christ, and brother of James, to them that are sanctified by God the Father, and preserved in Jesus Christ, and called:
1:1|WYC|Judas, the servant of Jesus Christ, and brother of James, to these that be loved, that be in God the Father, and to them that be called and kept of Jesus Christ [and of Jesus Christ kept and called],
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶穌基督的奴僕，雅各的兄弟猶大，寫信給那蒙召，在父神裡蒙愛，並蒙耶穌基督保守的人：
1:2|ASV|Mercy unto you and peace and love be multiplied.
1:2|Darby|Mercy to you, and peace, and love be multiplied.
1:2|KJV|Mercy unto you, and peace, and love, be multiplied.
1:2|WYC|mercy, and peace, and charity be filled to you. [mercy to you, and peace, and charity be full-filled.]
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願憐憫、平安與愛，繁增的歸與你們。
1:3|ASV|Beloved, while I was giving all diligence to write unto you of our common salvation, I was constrained to write unto you exhorting you to contend earnestly for the faith which was once for all delivered unto the saints.
1:3|Darby|Beloved, using all diligence to write to you of our common  salvation, I have been obliged to write to you exhorting [you]  to contend earnestly for the faith once delivered to the  saints.
1:3|KJV|Beloved, when I gave all diligence to write unto you of the common salvation, it was needful for me to write unto you, and exhort you that ye should earnestly contend for the faith which was once delivered unto the saints.
1:3<version name="WYC">Most dear <i>brethren </i>[Most dear], I doing all busyness to write to you of your common health, had need to write to you, and pray to strive strongly for the faith that is once taken to saints [for the faith once betaken to saints].</version>
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|親愛的，我盡心竭力要寫信給你們，論到我們共享之救恩的時候，就不得不寫信勸你們，要為那一次永遠交付聖徒的信仰竭力爭辯。
1:4|ASV|For there are certain men crept in privily, even they who were of old written of beforehand unto this condemnation, ungodly men, turning the grace of our God into lasciviousness, and denying our only Master and Lord, Jesus Christ.
1:4|Darby|For certain men have got in unnoticed, they who of old were  marked out beforehand to this sentence, ungodly [persons],  turning the grace of our God into dissoluteness, and denying  our only Master and Lord Jesus Christ.
1:4|KJV|For there are certain men crept in unawares, who were before of old ordained to this condemnation, ungodly men, turning the grace of our God into lasciviousness, and denying the only Lord God, and our Lord Jesus Christ.
1:4|WYC|For some unfaithful men privily entered, that sometime were before-written into this doom, and overturn the grace of our God into lechery, and deny him that is only a Lord, our Lord Jesus Christ. [Forsooth some men privily entered, that sometime were before-written into this doom, unpious men, overturning the grace of our God into lechery, and denying the alone lordshipper and our Lord Jesus Christ.]
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為有些人偷著進來，就是自古豫先所記載要受審判的不敬虔之人，將我們神的恩典變作放縱情慾的機會，並且否認我們獨一的主人和主，耶穌基督。
1:5|ASV|Now I desire to put you in remembrance, though ye know all things once for all, that the Lord, having saved a people out of the land of Egypt, afterward destroyed them that believed not.
1:5|Darby|But I would put you in remembrance, you who once knew all  things, that the Lord, having saved a people out of [the] land  of Egypt, in the second place destroyed those who had not  believed.
1:5|KJV|I will therefore put you in remembrance, though ye once knew this, how that the Lord, having saved the people out of the land of Egypt, afterward destroyed them that believed not.
1:5|WYC|But I will admonish you once, that know all things, that Jesus saved his people from the land of Egypt, and the second time destroyed them that believed not. [Forsooth I will together admonish you, witting once all things, for Jesus saving his people of the land of Egypt, the second time lost them that believed not.]
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|雖然你們一次永遠知道了一切的事，我仍要題醒你們：從前主救了祂的百姓出埃及地，後來卻把那些不信的毀滅了；
1:6|ASV|And angels that kept not their own principality, but left their proper habitation, he hath kept in everlasting bonds under darkness unto the judgment of the great day.
1:6|Darby|And angels who had not kept their own original state, but  had abandoned their own dwelling, he keeps in eternal chains  under gloomy darkness, to [the] judgment of [the] great day;
1:6|KJV|And the angels which kept not their first estate, but left their own habitation, he hath reserved in everlasting chains under darkness unto the judgment of the great day.
1:6|WYC|And he reserved under darkness angels, that kept not their princehood, but forsook their house, into the doom of the great God, into everlasting bonds. [Soothly angels that kept not his princehood, but forsook his house, he reserved into the doom of great God, in everlasting bonds under darkness.]
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又有不守自己權位，離棄自己住處的天使，主用永遠的鎖鍊把他們拘留在幽冥裡，等候大日的審判；
1:7|ASV|Even as Sodom and Gomorrah, and the cities about them, having in like manner with these given themselves over to fornication and gone after strange flesh, are set forth as an example, suffering the punishment of eternal fire.
1:7|Darby|as Sodom and Gomorrha, and the cities around them,  committing greedily fornication, in like manner with them, and  going after other flesh, lie there as an example, undergoing  the judgment of eternal fire.
1:7|KJV|Even as Sodom and Gomorrha, and the cities about them in like manner, giving themselves over to fornication, and going after strange flesh, are set forth for an example, suffering the vengeance of eternal fire.
1:7<version name="WYC">As Sodom, and Gomorrha, and the nigh coasted cities, that in like manner did fornication, and went away after other flesh, and be made ensample, suffering pain of everlasting fire. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23696a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又如所多瑪、蛾摩拉和周圍城邑的人，也照他們的樣子一味的行淫，隨從相異的肉體，就受永火的刑罰，立為鑑戒。
1:8|ASV|Yet in like manner these also in their dreamings defile the flesh, and set at nought dominion, and rail at dignities.
1:8|Darby|Yet in like manner these dreamers also defile [the] flesh,  and despise lordship, and speak railingly against dignities.
1:8|KJV|Likewise also these filthy dreamers defile the flesh, despise dominion, and speak evil of dignities.
1:8|WYC|In like manner also these that defoul the flesh, and despise lordship, and blaspheme majesty.
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而，這些作夢的人，還是照樣玷污肉體，輕慢主治者，毀謗在尊位的。
1:9|ASV|But Michael the archangel, when contending with the devil he disputed about the body of Moses, durst not bring against him a railing judgment, but said, The Lord rebuke thee.
1:9|Darby|But Michael the archangel, when disputing with the devil he  reasoned about the body of Moses, did not dare to bring a  railing judgment against [him], but said, [The] Lord rebuke  thee.
1:9|KJV|Yet Michael the archangel, when contending with the devil he disputed about the body of Moses, durst not bring against him a railing accusation, but said, The Lord rebuke thee.
1:9|WYC|When Michael, archangel, disputed with the devil, and strove of Moses' body [When Michael, the archangel, disputing with the devil, strove of Moses' body], he was not hardy to bring in doom of blasphemy, but said, The Lord command to thee.
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|天使長米迦勒與魔鬼爭辯，為摩西的身體爭論的時候，尚且不敢以神對他的判辭毀謗他，只說，主責備你罷。
1:10|ASV|But these rail at whatsoever things they know not: and what they understand naturally, like the creatures without reason, in these things are they destroyed.
1:10|Darby|But these, whatever things they know not, they speak  railingly against; but what even, as the irrational animals,  they understand by mere nature, in these things they corrupt  themselves.
1:10|KJV|But these speak evil of those things which they know not: but what they know naturally, as brute beasts, in those things they corrupt themselves.
1:10|WYC|But these men blaspheme [Forsooth these blaspheme], whatever things they know not.  For whatever things they know naturally as dumb beasts [Forsooth whatever things they know by kind as dumb beasts], in these they be corrupt.
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但這些人毀謗他們所不認識的；他們本性所知道的，與那沒有理性的畜類一樣，在這些事上正被敗壞。
1:11|ASV|Woe unto them! For they went in the way of Cain, and ran riotously in the error of Balaam for hire, and perished in the gainsaying of Korah.
1:11|Darby|Woe to them! because they have gone in the way of Cain, and  given themselves up to the error of Balaam for reward, and  perished in the gainsaying of Core.
1:11|KJV|Woe unto them! for they have gone in the way of Cain, and ran greedily after the error of Balaam for reward, and perished in the gainsaying of Core.
1:11|WYC|Woe to them that went the way of Cain, and that be shed out by error of Balaam for meed, and perished in the gainsaying of Core [and perished in the again-saying of Core].
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們有禍了！因為走了該隱的道路，又為工價向著巴蘭的錯謬直闖，並在可拉的背叛中滅亡了。
1:12|ASV|These are they who are hidden rocks in your love-feasts when they feast with you, shepherds that without fear feed themselves; clouds without water, carried along by winds; autumn leaves without fruit, twice dead, plucked up by the roots;
1:12|Darby|These are spots in your love-feasts, feasting together  [with you] without fear, pasturing themselves; clouds without  water, carried along by [the] winds; autumnal trees, without  fruit, twice dead, rooted up;
1:12|KJV|These are spots in your feasts of charity, when they feast with you, feeding themselves without fear: clouds they are without water, carried about of winds; trees whose fruit withereth, without fruit, twice dead, plucked up by the roots;
1:12<version name="WYC">These be in their meats, feasting together to filth [These be in their meats filths, <i>or defoulings</i>, feasting together], without dread feeding themselves.  <i>These be</i> clouds without water, that be borne about of winds; harvest trees without fruit, twice dead, drawn up by the root;</version>
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣的人，在你們的愛筵上乃是暗礁，與你們同喫的時候，無所懼怕；他們是只餧養自己的牧人；是沒有雨水的雲彩，被風飄蕩；是秋天沒有果子的樹，死而又死，連根被拔出來；
1:13|ASV|Wild waves of the sea, foaming out their own shame; wandering stars, for whom the blackness of darkness hath been reserved forever.
1:13|Darby|raging waves of the sea, foaming out their own shames;  wandering stars, to whom has been reserved the gloom of  darkness for eternity.
1:13|KJV|Raging waves of the sea, foaming out their own shame; wandering stars, to whom is reserved the blackness of darkness for ever.
1:13<version name="WYC">waves of the mad sea, foaming out their confusions; erring stars, to which the tempest of darknesses is kept without end. [waves of the wild, <i>or mad</i>, sea, frothing out their confusions; erring stars, to whom the tempest of darknesses is kept into without end.]</version>
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|是海裡的狂浪，湧出自己可恥的泡沫；是流蕩的星，有黑暗的幽冥為他們永遠存留。
1:14|ASV|And to these also Enoch, the seventh from Adam, prophesied, saying, Behold, the Lord came with ten thousands of his holy ones,
1:14|Darby|And Enoch, [the] seventh from Adam, prophesied also as to  these, saying, Behold, [the] Lord has come amidst his holy  myriads,
1:14|KJV|And Enoch also, the seventh from Adam, prophesied of these, saying, Behold, the Lord cometh with ten thousands of his saints,
1:14|WYC|But Enoch, the seventh from Adam, prophesied of these, and said [saying], Lo! the Lord cometh with his holy thousands,
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞當的七世孫以諾，也曾豫言這些人說，看哪，主帶著祂的千萬聖者來臨，
1:15|ASV|to execute judgment upon all, and to convict all the ungodly of all their works of ungodliness which they have ungodly wrought, and of all the hard things which ungodly sinners have spoken against him.
1:15|Darby|to execute judgment against all; and to convict all the  ungodly of them of all their works of ungodliness, which they  have wrought ungodlily, and of all the hard [things] which  ungodly sinners have spoken against him.
1:15|KJV|To execute judgment upon all, and to convince all that are ungodly among them of all their ungodly deeds which they have ungodly committed, and of all their hard speeches which ungodly sinners have spoken against him.
1:15<version name="WYC">to do doom against all men, and to reprove all unfaithful men of all the works of the wickedness of them, by which they did wickedly, and of all the hard words, that wicked sinners have spoken against God. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23704b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|要在眾人身上行審判，定罪那一切不敬虔的人，憑不敬虔所行一切不敬虔的事，又定罪不敬虔之罪人所說一切頂撞祂的剛愎話。
1:16|ASV|These are murmurers, complainers, walking after their lusts (and their mouth speaketh great swelling words), showing respect of persons for the sake of advantage.
1:16|Darby|These are murmurers, complainers, walking after their  lusts; and their mouth speaks swelling words, admiring persons  for the sake of profit.
1:16|KJV|These are murmurers, complainers, walking after their own lusts; and their mouth speaketh great swelling words, having men's persons in admiration because of advantage.
1:16<version name="WYC">These be grumblers full of plaints [These be grutchers plaining, <i>or full of plaints</i>], wandering after their desires; and the mouth of them speaketh pride, worshipping persons, because of winning [by cause of winning].</version>
1:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些人是牢騷求疵、怨尤不平的，隨從自己的情慾而行，口中說矜誇的大話，為了利益奉承人。
1:17|ASV|But ye, beloved, remember ye the words which have been spoken before by the apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ;
1:17|Darby|But *ye*, beloved, remember the words spoken before by the  apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ,
1:17|KJV|But, beloved, remember ye the words which were spoken before of the apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ;
1:17<version name="WYC">And ye, most dear <i>brethren</i>, be mindful of the words [Forsooth, ye most dear, be ye mindful of the words], which be before-said of [the] apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ;</version>
1:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|親愛的，你們卻要記念我們主耶穌基督的使徒從前所說的話；
1:18|ASV|That they said to you, In the last time there shall be mockers, walking after their own ungodly lusts.
1:18|Darby|that they said to you, that at [the] end of the time there  should be mockers, walking after their own lusts of  ungodlinesses.
1:18|KJV|How that they told you there should be mockers in the last time, who should walk after their own ungodly lusts.
1:18|WYC|which said to you, that in the last times there shall come beguilers [there shall come scorners], wandering after their own desires, not in piety.
1:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們曾對你們說過，末後的時期必有好譏誚的人，隨從自己不敬虔的私慾而行。
1:19|ASV|These are they who make separations, sensual, having not the Spirit.
1:19|Darby|These are they who set [themselves] apart, natural [men],  not having [the] Spirit.
1:19|KJV|These be they who separate themselves, sensual, having not the Spirit.
1:19|WYC|These be, which separate themselves, beastly men, not having Spirit. [These be, the which separate themselves, beastly, not having Spirit.]
1:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這就是那些製造分裂，屬魂而沒有靈的人。
1:20|ASV|But ye, beloved, building up yourselves on your most holy faith, praying in the Holy Spirit,
1:20|Darby|But *ye*, beloved, building yourselves up on your most holy  faith, praying in the Holy Spirit,
1:20|KJV|But ye, beloved, building up yourselves on your most holy faith, praying in the Holy Ghost,
1:20<version name="WYC">But ye, most dear <i>brethren</i>, above build yourselves on your most holy faith, and pray ye in the Holy Ghost, <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23709c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup></version>
1:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|親愛的，你們卻要在至聖的信仰上建造自己，在聖靈裡禱告，
1:21|ASV|keep yourselves in the love of God, looking for the mercy of our Lord Jesus Christ unto eternal life.
1:21|Darby|keep yourselves in the love of God, awaiting the mercy of  our Lord Jesus Christ unto eternal life.
1:21|KJV|Keep yourselves in the love of God, looking for the mercy of our Lord Jesus Christ unto eternal life.
1:21|WYC|and keep yourselves in the love of God, and abide ye the mercy of our Lord Jesus Christ into life everlasting. [keep yourselves in the love of God, abiding the mercy of our Lord Jesus Christ into life everlasting.]
1:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|保守自己在神的愛中，等候我們主耶穌基督的憐憫，以至於永遠的生命。
1:22|ASV|And on some have mercy, who are in doubt;
1:22|Darby|And of some have compassion, making a difference,
1:22|KJV|And of some have compassion, making a difference:
1:22|WYC|And reprove ye these men that be deemed,
1:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有些人疑惑不定，你們要憐憫他們，
1:23|ASV|and some save, snatching them out of the fire; and on some have mercy with fear; hating even the garment spotted by the flesh.
1:23|Darby|but others save with fear, snatching [them] out of the  fire; hating even the garment spotted by the flesh.
1:23|KJV|And others save with fear, pulling them out of the fire; hating even the garment spotted by the flesh.
1:23<version name="WYC">but save ye them, and take ye them from the fire.  And do ye mercy to other men, in the dread of God, and hate ye also that defouled coat, which is fleshly. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-23712d" title="See footnote d">d</a>]</sup></version>
1:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|要把他們從火中搶出來，搭救他們；有些人你們要存畏懼的心憐憫他們，連那被肉體玷污的裡衣也當憎惡。
1:24|ASV|Now unto him that is able to guard you from stumbling, and to set you before the presence of his glory without blemish in exceeding joy,
1:24|Darby|But to him that is able to keep you without stumbling, and  to set [you] with exultation blameless before his glory,
1:24|KJV|Now unto him that is able to keep you from falling, and to present you faultless before the presence of his glory with exceeding joy,
1:24|WYC|But to him that is mighty to keep you without sin, and to ordain before the sight of his glory you unwemmed in full out joy,
1:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但願榮耀、尊大、權能和權柄，藉著我們的主耶穌基督，歸與那能保守你們不失腳，並使你們無瑕無疵，歡歡樂樂站在祂榮耀之前的，獨一的神我們的救主，
1:25<version name="ASV">to the only God our Saviour, through Jesus Christ our Lord, be glory, majesty, dominion and power, before all time, and now, and for evermore. Amen. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:25<version name="Darby">to the only God our Saviour, through Jesus Christ our Lord,  [be] glory, majesty, might, and authority, from before the  whole age, and now, and to all the ages. Amen. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:25<version name="KJV">To the only wise God our Saviour, be glory and majesty, dominion and power, both now and ever. Amen.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:25<version name="WYC">in the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, to God alone our Saviour, by Jesus Christ our Lord, <i>be</i> glory, and magnifying, empire, and power, before all worlds, and now, and into all worlds of worlds.  Amen.</version>
1:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|從萬世之前，並現今，直到永永遠遠。阿們。
