1:1|Darby|How doth the city sit solitary [that] was full of people!  She that was great among the nations is become as a widow; the  princess among the provinces is become tributary!
1:1|KJV|How doth the city sit solitary, that was full of people! how is she become as a widow! she that was great among the nations, and princess among the provinces, how is she become tributary!
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|先前滿有人民的城，現在何竟獨坐！先前在列國中為大的，現在竟如寡婦；先前在諸省中為王后的，現在成了進貢的。
1:2|Darby|She weepeth sore in the night, and her tears are on her  cheeks; among all her lovers she hath no comforter; all her  friends have dealt treacherously with her, they are become her  enemies.
1:2|KJV|She weepeth sore in the night, and her tears are on her cheeks: among all her lovers she hath none to comfort her: all her friends have dealt treacherously with her, they are become her enemies.
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|她夜間痛哭，淚流滿腮。在她一切所愛的人中間，沒有一個安慰她的；她的朋友，都以詭詐待她，成了她的仇敵。
1:3|Darby|Judah is gone into captivity because of affliction, and  because of great servitude; she dwelleth among the nations, she  findeth no rest: all her pursuers have overtaken her within the  straits.
1:3|KJV|Judah is gone into captivity because of affliction, and because of great servitude: she dwelleth among the heathen, she findeth no rest: all her persecutors overtook her between the straits.
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|猶大遭遇苦難，多服勞役，被遷到外邦；她住在列國中，尋不著安息；在急難中，一切追逼她的人將她追上了。
1:4|Darby|The ways of Zion do mourn, because none come to the solemn  assembly: all her gates are desolate; her priests sigh, her  virgins are in grief; and as for her, she is in bitterness.
1:4|KJV|The ways of Zion do mourn, because none come to the solemn feasts: all her gates are desolate: her priests sigh, her virgins are afflicted, and she is in bitterness.
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|錫安的路徑，因無人來守所定的節期就悲傷；她的城門淒涼，她的祭司歎息；她的處女受艱難，自己也在愁苦中。
1:5|Darby|Her adversaries have become the head, her enemies prosper;  for Jehovah hath afflicted her for the multitude of her  transgressions: her children are gone into captivity before the  adversary.
1:5|KJV|Her adversaries are the chief, her enemies prosper; for the LORD hath afflicted her for the multitude of her transgressions: her children are gone into captivity before the enemy.
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|她的敵人為首；她的仇敵亨通；因為她的過犯眾多，耶和華使她受苦；她的孩童在敵人面前被擄去。
1:6|Darby|And from the daughter of Zion all her splendour is departed:  her princes are become like harts that find no pasture; and  they are gone without strength before the pursuer.
1:6|KJV|And from the daughter of Zion all her beauty is departed: her princes are become like harts that find no pasture, and they are gone without strength before the pursuer.
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|錫安女子的威榮，全都離去；她的首領，像找不著草場的鹿，在追趕的人面前，無力行走。
1:7|Darby|In the days of her affliction and of her wanderings, since  her people fell into the hand of an adversary, and none did  help her, Jerusalem remembereth all her precious things which  she had in the days of old: the adversaries have seen her, they  mock at her ruin.
1:7|KJV|Jerusalem remembered in the days of her affliction and of her miseries all her pleasant things that she had in the days of old, when her people fell into the hand of the enemy, and none did help her: the adversaries saw her, and did mock at her sabbaths.
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶路撒冷在困苦流離之時，就追想古時一切的美事；她百姓落在敵人手中，無人救助；敵人看見她，就嗤笑她的衰敗。
1:8|Darby|Jerusalem hath grievously sinned; therefore is she removed  as an impurity: all that honoured her despise her because they  have seen her nakedness; and she sigheth, and turneth backward.
1:8|KJV|Jerusalem hath grievously sinned; therefore she is removed: all that honoured her despise her, because they have seen her nakedness: yea, she sigheth, and turneth backward.
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶路撒冷大大的犯罪，所以成了不潔之物。素來尊敬她的，見她赤露就都藐視她；她自己也歎息，轉身退後。
1:9|Darby|Her impurity was in her skirts, she remembered not her  latter end; and she came down wonderfully: she hath no  comforter. Jehovah, behold my affliction; for the enemy hath  magnified himself.
1:9|KJV|Her filthiness is in her skirts; she remembereth not her last end; therefore she came down wonderfully: she had no comforter. O LORD, behold my affliction: for the enemy hath magnified himself.
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|她的污穢是在衣裙上；她不思想自己末後的結局；所以她令人驚奇的敗落，無人安慰她。她說，耶和華阿，求你看我的苦難，因為仇敵自誇為大。
1:10|Darby|The adversary hath spread out his hand upon all her  precious things; for she hath seen the nations enter into her  sanctuary, concerning whom thou didst command that they should  not enter into thy congregation.
1:10|KJV|The adversary hath spread out his hand upon all her pleasant things: for she hath seen that the heathen entered into her sanctuary, whom thou didst command that they should not enter into thy congregation.
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|敵人伸手，奪取她的一切美物；她眼見外邦人進入她的聖所；論到這外邦人，你曾吩咐不可入你的會中。
1:11|Darby|All her people sigh, they seek bread; they have given their  precious things for food to revive [their] soul. See, Jehovah,  and consider, for I am become vile.
1:11|KJV|All her people sigh, they seek bread; they have given their pleasant things for meat to relieve the soul: see, O LORD, and consider; for I am become vile.
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|她的民都歎息，尋求食物；他們用美物換糧食，要救回性命。他們說，耶和華阿，求你觀看，因為我成了被藐視的。
1:12|Darby|Is it nothing to you, all ye that pass by? Behold, and see  if there be any sorrow like unto my sorrow, which is done unto  me, whom Jehovah hath afflicted in the day of his fierce anger.
1:12|KJV|Is it nothing to you, all ye that pass by? behold, and see if there be any sorrow like unto my sorrow, which is done unto me, wherewith the LORD hath afflicted me in the day of his fierce anger.
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們一切過路的人哪，這事你們不介意麼？你們要觀看，有甚麼痛苦像我所遭受的痛苦，就是耶和華在祂發烈怒的日子，使我所受的苦。
1:13|Darby|From on high hath he sent fire into my bones, and it  prevaileth against them; he hath spread a net for my feet; he  hath turned me back; he hath made me desolate [and] faint all  the day.
1:13|KJV|From above hath he sent fire into my bones, and it prevaileth against them: he hath spread a net for my feet, he hath turned me back: he hath made me desolate and faint all the day.
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂從高天使火進入我的骨頭，勝過了我；祂鋪下網羅，絆我的腳，使我轉回退後；祂使我終日淒涼發昏。
1:14|Darby|The yoke of my transgressions is bound by his hand: they  are wreathed, they are come up upon my neck; he hath made my  strength to fail; the Lord hath delivered me into hands out of  which I am not able to rise up.
1:14|KJV|The yoke of my transgressions is bound by his hand: they are wreathed, and come up upon my neck: he hath made my strength to fall, the LORD hath delivered me into their hands, from whom I am not able to rise up.
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我過犯的軛，是祂手所綁的，都糾纏在一起，上到我的頸項；祂使我的力量衰敗。主將我交在我所不能敵擋的人手中。
1:15|Darby|The Lord hath cast down all my mighty men in the midst of  me; he hath called an assembly against me to crush my young  men; the Lord hath trodden as a winepress the virgin daughter  of Judah.
1:15|KJV|The LORD hath trodden under foot all my mighty men in the midst of me: he hath called an assembly against me to crush my young men: the LORD hath trodden the virgin, the daughter of Judah, as in a winepress.
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主輕棄我中間的一切勇士；祂招聚會眾攻擊我，要壓碎我的少年人。主將猶大的處女踹踏，像在酒醡中一樣。
1:16|Darby|For these things I weep; mine eye, mine eye runneth down  with water: for the comforter that should revive my soul is far  from me; my children are desolate, for the enemy hath  prevailed.
1:16|KJV|For these things I weep; mine eye, mine eye runneth down with water, because the comforter that should relieve my soul is far from me: my children are desolate, because the enemy prevailed.
1:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我因這些事哭泣；我的眼睛淚水直流，因為那當安慰我，救回我性命的，離我甚遠；我的兒女淒苦，因為仇敵已經得勝。
1:17|Darby|Zion spreadeth forth her hands; there is none to comfort  her; Jehovah hath commanded concerning Jacob, [that] his  adversaries [should be] round about him; Jerusalem is as an  impurity among them.
1:17|KJV|Zion spreadeth forth her hands, and there is none to comfort her: the LORD hath commanded concerning Jacob, that his adversaries should be round about him: Jerusalem is as a menstruous woman among them.
1:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|錫安伸出雙手，無人安慰；論到雅各，耶和華已經出令，使四圍的人作他仇敵；耶路撒冷在他們中間，成了不潔之物。
1:18|Darby|Jehovah is righteous; for I have rebelled against his  commandment. Hear, I pray you, all ye peoples, and behold my  sorrow. My virgins and my young men are gone into captivity.
1:18|KJV|The LORD is righteous; for I have rebelled against his commandment: hear, I pray you, all people, and behold my sorrow: my virgins and my young men are gone into captivity.
1:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華是公義的，因我違背了祂的命令。眾民哪，請聽我的話，看我的痛苦；我的處女和少年人，都被擄去了。
1:19|Darby|I called for my lovers, they have deceived me; my priests  and mine elders have expired in the city, while they sought  them food to revive their soul.
1:19|KJV|I called for my lovers, but they deceived me: my priests and mine elders gave up the ghost in the city, while they sought their meat to relieve their souls.
1:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我招呼我所愛的人，他們卻愚弄我；我的祭司和長老，正尋求食物要救回性命的時候，就在城中滅亡。
1:20|Darby|See, Jehovah, for I am in distress, my bowels are troubled;  my heart is turned within me, for I have grievously rebelled:  without, the sword hath bereaved [me], within, it is as death.
1:20|KJV|Behold, O LORD; for I am in distress: my bowels are troubled; mine heart is turned within me; for I have grievously rebelled: abroad the sword bereaveth, at home there is as death.
1:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華阿，求你觀看，因為我在急難中，我的心腸翻騰；我的心在我堶授蝓遄A因我曾經大大的悖逆。在街上刀劍使人喪子，在屋媯S如死亡。
1:21|Darby|They have heard that I sigh: I have no comforter: all mine  enemies have heard of my calamity; they are glad that thou hast  done it. Thou wilt bring the day that thou hast called, and  they shall be like unto me.
1:21|KJV|They have heard that I sigh: there is none to comfort me: all mine enemies have heard of my trouble; they are glad that thou hast done it: thou wilt bring the day that thou hast called, and they shall be like unto me.
1:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們聽見我歎息，卻無人安慰我；我的仇敵都聽見我的患難；因你作了這事，他們就都歡喜。你必使你宣告的日子來到，他們就要像我一樣。
1:22<version name="Darby">Let all their wickedness come before thee; and do unto  them, as thou hast done unto me for all my transgressions: for  my sighs are many, and my heart is faint. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:22<version name="KJV">Let all their wickedness come before thee; and do unto them, as thou hast done unto me for all my transgressions: for my sighs are many, and my heart is faint.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願他們的惡，都呈到你面前；你怎樣因我的一切過犯待我，求你照樣待他們；因我歎息甚多，我的心發昏。
2:1|Darby|How hath the Lord in his anger covered the daughter of Zion  with a cloud! He hath cast down from the heavens unto the earth  the beauty of Israel, and remembered not his footstool in the  day of his anger.
2:1|KJV|How hath the LORD covered the daughter of Zion with a cloud in his anger, and cast down from heaven unto the earth the beauty of Israel, and remembered not his footstool in the day of his anger!
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主何竟發怒，使烏雲遮蔽錫安的女子！祂將以色列的華美，從天扔在地上，在祂發怒的日子，並不記念自己的腳凳。
2:2|Darby|The Lord hath swallowed up all the dwellings of Jacob, and  hath not spared; he hath thrown down in his wrath the  strongholds of the daughter of Judah: he hath brought [them]  down to the ground; he hath profaned the kingdom and the  princes thereof.
2:2|KJV|The LORD hath swallowed up all the habitations of Jacob, and hath not pitied: he hath thrown down in his wrath the strong holds of the daughter of Judah; he hath brought them down to the ground: he hath polluted the kingdom and the princes thereof.
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主吞滅雅各一切的住處，並不顧惜；祂在盛怒中拆毀了猶大女子的保障，使這保障坍倒在地；祂辱沒這國和其首領。
2:3|Darby|He hath cut off in fierce anger all the horn of Israel: he  hath withdrawn his right hand from before the enemy; and he  burned up Jacob like a flaming fire, devouring round about.
2:3|KJV|He hath cut off in his fierce anger all the horn of Israel: he hath drawn back his right hand from before the enemy, and he burned against Jacob like a flaming fire, which devoureth round about.
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂在烈怒中，把以色列的角全然砍斷。祂在仇敵面前收回右手。祂像火焰四圍吞滅，在雅各中間焚燒。
2:4|Darby|He hath bent his bow like an enemy; he stood with his right  hand as an adversary, and hath slain all that was pleasant to  the eye: in the tent of the daughter of Zion, he hath poured  out his fury like fire.
2:4|KJV|He hath bent his bow like an enemy: he stood with his right hand as an adversary, and slew all that were pleasant to the eye in the tabernacle of the daughter of Zion: he poured out his fury like fire.
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂張弓，好像仇敵；祂站著舉起右手，如同敵人，將悅人眼目的盡行殺戮。在錫安女子的帳棚上，倒出祂的忿怒像火一樣。
2:5|Darby|The Lord is become as an enemy: he hath swallowed up Israel;  he hath swallowed up all her palaces; he hath destroyed his  strongholds, and hath multiplied in the daughter of Judah  mourning and lamentation.
2:5|KJV|The LORD was as an enemy: he hath swallowed up Israel, he hath swallowed up all her palaces: he hath destroyed his strong holds, and hath increased in the daughter of Judah mourning and lamentation.
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主如仇敵吞滅以色列，吞滅她的一切宮殿；主毀壞她的保障，在猶大女子中，加增悲傷哀號。
2:6|Darby|And he hath violently cast down his enclosure as a garden;  he hath destroyed his place of assembly: Jehovah hath caused  set feast and sabbath to be forgotten in Zion, and hath  despised in the indignation of his anger king and priest.
2:6|KJV|And he hath violently taken away his tabernacle, as if it were of a garden: he hath destroyed his places of the assembly: the LORD hath caused the solemn feasts and sabbaths to be forgotten in Zion, and hath despised in the indignation of his anger the king and the priest.
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂強力拆毀自己的帷幕，好像拆毀園子；祂毀壞自己的聚會之處；耶和華使所定的節期和安息日，在錫安都被忘記；祂在怒氣的憤恨中，藐視君王和祭司。
2:7|Darby|The Lord hath cast off his altar, he hath rejected his  sanctuary; he hath given up into the hand of the enemy the  walls of her palaces: they have made a noise in the house of  Jehovah, as on the day of a set feast.
2:7|KJV|The LORD hath cast off his altar, he hath abhorred his sanctuary, he hath given up into the hand of the enemy the walls of her palaces; they have made a noise in the house of the LORD, as in the day of a solemn feast.
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主丟棄了祂的祭壇，憎惡祂的聖所，將宮殿的牆垣交在仇敵手中。他們在耶和華的殿中喧嚷，像在所定節期之日一樣。
2:8|Darby|Jehovah hath purposed to destroy the wall of the daughter of  Zion: he hath stretched out the line, he hath not withdrawn his  hand from destroying; and he hath made the rampart and the wall  to lament: they languish together.
2:8|KJV|The LORD hath purposed to destroy the wall of the daughter of Zion: he hath stretched out a line, he hath not withdrawn his hand from destroying: therefore he made the rampart and the wall to lament; they languished together.
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華想要拆毀錫安女子的城牆；祂拉了準繩，不將手收回，定要毀滅；祂使外郭和城牆都悲哀，一同衰敗。
2:9|Darby|Her gates are sunk into the ground; he hath destroyed and  broken her bars. Her king and her princes are among the  nations: the law is no [more]; her prophets also find no vision  from Jehovah.
2:9|KJV|Her gates are sunk into the ground; he hath destroyed and broken her bars: her king and her princes are among the Gentiles: the law is no more; her prophets also find no vision from the LORD.
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|錫安的門陷入地內；耶和華將她的門閂毀壞、折斷；她的君王和首領落在沒有律法的列國中；她的申言者也不得見耶和華的異象。
2:10|Darby|The elders of the daughter of Zion sit upon the ground,  they keep silence; they have cast dust upon their heads, they  have girded themselves with sackcloth: the virgins of Jerusalem  hang down their head to the ground.
2:10|KJV|The elders of the daughter of Zion sit upon the ground, and keep silence: they have cast up dust upon their heads; they have girded themselves with sackcloth: the virgins of Jerusalem hang down their heads to the ground.
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|錫安女子的長老坐在地上，默默無聲；他們把塵土撒在頭上，腰束麻布；耶路撒冷的處女，垂頭至地。
2:11|Darby|Mine eyes are consumed with tears, my bowels are troubled;  my liver is poured upon the earth, because of the ruin of the  daughter of my people; because infant and suckling swoon in the  streets of the city.
2:11|KJV|Mine eyes do fail with tears, my bowels are troubled, my liver is poured upon the earth, for the destruction of the daughter of my people; because the children and the sucklings swoon in the streets of the city.
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的眼流淚，以致失明；我的心腸翻騰，肝膽塗地，都因我的民遭毀滅，又因孩童和喫奶的在城內街上發昏。
2:12|Darby|They say to their mothers, Where is corn and wine? when  they swoon as the wounded in the streets of the city; when they  pour out their soul into their mothers' bosom.
2:12|KJV|They say to their mothers, Where is corn and wine? when they swooned as the wounded in the streets of the city, when their soul was poured out into their mothers' bosom.
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時他們在城內街上發昏，好像受傷的，在母親的懷堭N要喪命，對母親說，穀和酒在那堜O？
2:13|Darby|What shall I take to witness for thee? what shall I liken  unto thee, daughter of Jerusalem? What shall I equal to thee,  that I may comfort thee, virgin daughter of Zion? For thy ruin  is great as the sea: who will heal thee?
2:13|KJV|What thing shall I take to witness for thee? what thing shall I liken to thee, O daughter of Jerusalem? what shall I equal to thee, that I may comfort thee, O virgin daughter of Zion? for thy breach is great like the sea: who can heal thee?
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶路撒冷的女子阿，我可用甚麼向你證明呢？我可把你比作甚麼呢？錫安的處女阿，我可拿甚麼和你比較，好安慰你呢？因為你的裂口大如海，誰能醫治你呢？
2:14|Darby|Thy prophets have seen vanity and folly for thee; and they  have not revealed thine iniquity, to turn away thy captivity;  but have seen for thee burdens of falsehood and causes of  expulsion.
2:14|KJV|Thy prophets have seen vain and foolish things for thee: and they have not discovered thine iniquity, to turn away thy captivity; but have seen for thee false burdens and causes of banishment.
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你的申言者為你看見虛幻和愚妄的異象，並沒有揭露你的罪孽，使你被擄的歸回；卻為你看見虛假的默示，和使你被趕逐的緣故。
2:15|Darby|All that pass by clap [their] hands at thee; they hiss and  shake their head at the daughter of Jerusalem: Is this the city  which they called, The perfection of beauty, The joy of the  whole earth?
2:15|KJV|All that pass by clap their hands at thee; they hiss and wag their head at the daughter of Jerusalem, saying, Is this the city that men call The perfection of beauty, The joy of the whole earth?
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡過路的，都向你拍掌；他們向耶路撒冷的女子嗤笑搖頭，說，難道這城就是人所稱為全美的，稱為全地所喜悅的麼？
2:16|Darby|All thine enemies open their mouth against thee, they hiss  and gnash the teeth: they say, We have swallowed [her] up; this  is forsooth the day that we looked for: we have found, we have  seen [it].
2:16|KJV|All thine enemies have opened their mouth against thee: they hiss and gnash the teeth: they say, We have swallowed her up: certainly this is the day that we looked for; we have found, we have seen it.
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你的仇敵都張口攻擊你；他們嗤笑切齒，說，我們把她吞滅了。這真是我們所盼望的日子；我們得著了，我們看見了。
2:17|Darby|Jehovah hath done what he had devised; he hath fulfilled  his word which he had commanded from the days of old: he hath  thrown down, and hath not spared, and he hath caused the enemy  to rejoice over thee; he hath set up the horn of thine  adversaries.
2:17|KJV|The LORD hath done that which he had devised; he hath fulfilled his word that he had commanded in the days of old: he hath thrown down, and hath not pitied: and he hath caused thine enemy to rejoice over thee, he hath set up the horn of thine adversaries.
2:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華成就了祂所定意的，應驗了祂從古時所吩咐的話；祂傾覆了，並不顧惜，使你的仇敵因勝過你而喜樂；祂使你敵人的角被高舉。
2:18|Darby|Their heart cried unto the Lord. O wall of the daughter of  Zion, let tears run down like a torrent day and night: give  thyself no respite; let not the apple of thine eye rest.
2:18|KJV|Their heart cried unto the LORD, O wall of the daughter of Zion, let tears run down like a river day and night: give thyself no rest; let not the apple of thine eye cease.
2:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|錫安民的心哀求主：錫安女子的城牆阿，願你晝夜流淚如河，不得歇息；願你眼中的瞳人，淚流不止。
2:19|Darby|Arise, cry out in the night, in the beginning of the  watches; pour out thy heart like water before the face of the  Lord: lift up thy hands toward him for the life of thy young  children, who faint from hunger at the top of all the streets.
2:19|KJV|Arise, cry out in the night: in the beginning of the watches pour out thine heart like water before the face of the LORD: lift up thy hands toward him for the life of thy young children, that faint for hunger in the top of every street.
2:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|夜間每逢交更的時候，你要起來呼喊，在主面前傾心如水；你的孩童在各街頭挨餓發昏，你要為他們的性命向主舉手禱告。
2:20|Darby|See, Jehovah, and consider to whom thou hast done this!  Shall the women eat their fruit, the infants that they nursed?  Shall priest and prophet be slain in the sanctuary of the Lord?
2:20|KJV|Behold, O LORD, and consider to whom thou hast done this. Shall the women eat their fruit, and children of a span long? shall the priest and the prophet be slain in the sanctuary of the Lord?
2:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華阿，求你觀看，見你向誰這樣行？婦人豈可喫自己所生育，就是自己所撫弄的嬰孩麼？祭司和申言者，豈可在主的聖所中被殺戮麼？
2:21|Darby|The child and the old man lie on the ground in the streets;  my virgins and my young men are fallen by the sword: thou hast  slain [them] in the day of thine anger; thou hast killed, thou  hast not spared.
2:21|KJV|The young and the old lie on the ground in the streets: my virgins and my young men are fallen by the sword; thou hast slain them in the day of thine anger; thou hast killed, and not pitied.
2:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|少年人和老年人，都在街上躺臥；我的處女和壯丁，都倒在刀下；你在發怒的日子，殺死他們；你殺戮了，並不顧惜。
2:22<version name="Darby">Thou hast called up, as on the day of a set feast, my  terrors on every side; and in the day of Jehovah's anger there  was none that escaped or remained: those that I have nursed and  brought up hath mine enemy consumed. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:22<version name="KJV">Thou hast called as in a solemn day my terrors round about, so that in the day of the LORD's anger none escaped nor remained: those that I have swaddled and brought up hath mine enemy consumed.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你呼召四圍驚嚇我的人，像在所定節期的日子呼召人一樣；耶和華發怒的日子，無人逃脫，無人存留；我所撫弄所養育的，仇敵都殺淨了。
3:1|Darby|I am the man that hath seen affliction by the rod of his  wrath.
3:1|KJV|I AM the man that hath seen affliction by the rod of his wrath.
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我是因耶和華忿怒的杖，遇見困苦的人。
3:2|Darby|Me hath he led, and brought into darkness, and not into  light.
3:2|KJV|He hath led me, and brought me into darkness, but not into light.
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂驅趕我，使我行在黑暗中，不行在光明堙C
3:3|Darby|Surely against me hath he turned again and again his hand  all the day.
3:3|KJV|Surely against me is he turned; he turneth his hand against me all the day.
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂真是終日再三反手攻擊我。
3:4|Darby|My flesh and my skin hath he wasted away, he hath broken my  bones.
3:4|KJV|My flesh and my skin hath he made old; he hath broken my bones.
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂使我的皮肉消損；祂折斷了我的骨頭。
3:5|Darby|He hath built against me, and encompassed [me] with gall and  toil.
3:5|KJV|He hath builded against me, and compassed me with gall and travail.
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂築壘攻擊我，用苦膽和艱難圍困我。
3:6|Darby|He hath made me to dwell in dark places as those that have  been long dead.
3:6|KJV|He hath set me in dark places, as they that be dead of old.
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂使我住在幽暗之處，像死了許久的人一樣。
3:7|Darby|He hath hedged me about that I cannot get out: he hath made  my chain heavy.
3:7|KJV|He hath hedged me about, that I cannot get out: he hath made my chain heavy.
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂築牆圍住我，使我不能出去；祂使我的銅鍊沉重。
3:8|Darby|Even when I cry and shout, he shutteth out my prayer.
3:8|KJV|Also when I cry and shout, he shutteth out my prayer.
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我哀號求救時，祂塞閉不聽我的禱告。
3:9|Darby|He hath inclosed my ways with hewn stone, he hath made my  paths crooked.
3:9|KJV|He hath inclosed my ways with hewn stone, he hath made my paths crooked.
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂用鑿過的石頭，築牆擋住我的道路；祂使我的路徑彎曲。
3:10|Darby|He is unto me [as] a bear lying in wait, a lion in secret  places.
3:10|KJV|He was unto me as a bear lying in wait, and as a lion in secret places.
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂向我如熊埋伏，如獅子在隱密處。
3:11|Darby|He hath turned aside my ways, and pulled me in pieces; he  hath made me desolate.
3:11|KJV|He hath turned aside my ways, and pulled me in pieces: he hath made me desolate.
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂使我轉離正路，將我撕碎，使我淒涼。
3:12|Darby|He hath bent his bow, and set me as a mark for the arrow.
3:12|KJV|He hath bent his bow, and set me as a mark for the arrow.
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂張弓將我當作箭靶。
3:13|Darby|He hath caused the arrows of his quiver to enter into my  reins.
3:13|KJV|He hath caused the arrows of his quiver to enter into my reins.
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂把箭袋中的箭，射入我的肺腑。
3:14|Darby|I am become a derision to all my people; their song all the  day.
3:14|KJV|I was a derision to all my people; and their song all the day.
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我成了眾民的笑話，成了他們終日嘲笑的歌曲。
3:15|Darby|He hath sated me with bitterness, he hath made me drunk  with wormwood.
3:15|KJV|He hath filled me with bitterness, he hath made me drunken with wormwood.
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂使苦楚充滿我，使我喝足茵蔯。
3:16|Darby|He hath also broken my teeth with gravel stones, he hath  covered me with ashes.
3:16|KJV|He hath also broken my teeth with gravel stones, he hath covered me with ashes.
3:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂又用沙石磣斷我的牙，用灰塵將我蒙蓋。
3:17|Darby|And thou hast removed my soul far off from peace: I have  forgotten prosperity.
3:17|KJV|And thou hast removed my soul far off from peace: I forgat prosperity.
3:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你使我的魂遠離平安；我忘記了好處。
3:18|Darby|And I said, My strength is perished, and my hope in  Jehovah.
3:18|KJV|And I said, My strength and my hope is perished from the LORD:
3:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我就說，我的力量衰敗，我在耶和華那堙A毫無指望。
3:19|Darby|Remember thou mine affliction and my wandering, the  wormwood and the gall.
3:19|KJV|Remembering mine affliction and my misery, the wormwood and the gall.
3:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華阿，求你記念我如茵蔯和苦膽的困苦流離。
3:20|Darby|My soul hath [them] constantly in remembrance, and is  humbled in me.
3:20|KJV|My soul hath them still in remembrance, and is humbled in me.
3:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的魂反覆想念這些，就在堶戛屭I。
3:21|Darby|-- This I recall to heart, therefore have I hope.
3:21|KJV|This I recall to my mind, therefore have I hope.
3:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的心回想這事，我就有指望。
3:22|Darby|It is of Jehovah's loving-kindness we are not consumed,  because his compassions fail not;
3:22|KJV|It is of the LORD's mercies that we are not consumed, because his compassions fail not.
3:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們不至消滅，是出於耶和華的慈愛，因祂的憐恤不至斷絕；
3:23|Darby|they are new every morning: great is thy faithfulness.
3:23|KJV|They are new every morning: great is thy faithfulness.
3:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|每早晨這些都是新的；你的信實，極其廣大。
3:24|Darby|Jehovah is my portion, saith my soul; therefore will I hope  in him.
3:24|KJV|The LORD is my portion, saith my soul; therefore will I hope in him.
3:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的魂說，耶和華是我的分；因此，我要仰望祂。
3:25|Darby|Jehovah is good unto them that wait for him, to the soul  [that] seeketh him.
3:25|KJV|The LORD is good unto them that wait for him, to the soul that seeketh him.
3:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|等候耶和華，心奡M求祂的，耶和華必善待他。
3:26|Darby|It is good that one should both wait, and that in silence,  for the salvation of Jehovah.
3:26|KJV|It is good that a man should both hope and quietly wait for the salvation of the LORD.
3:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人仰望且靜默等候耶和華的救恩，這原是好的。
3:27|Darby|It is good for a man that he bear the yoke in his youth:
3:27|KJV|It is good for a man that he bear the yoke in his youth.
3:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人在幼年負軛，這原是好的。
3:28|Darby|He sitteth solitary and keepeth silence, because he hath  laid it upon him;
3:28|KJV|He sitteth alone and keepeth silence, because he hath borne it upon him.
3:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他當獨坐靜默，因為這是耶和華加在他身上的。
3:29|Darby|he putteth his mouth in the dust, if so be there may be  hope;
3:29|KJV|He putteth his mouth in the dust; if so be there may be hope.
3:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他當口貼塵埃，或者還有指望。
3:30|Darby|he giveth his cheek to him that smiteth him; he is filled  full with reproach.
3:30|KJV|He giveth his cheek to him that smiteth him: he is filled full with reproach.
3:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他當由人打他的腮頰；他當滿受凌辱。
3:31|Darby|For the Lord will not cast off for ever;
3:31|KJV|For the LORD will not cast off for ever:
3:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為主必不永遠丟棄人。
3:32|Darby|but if he have caused grief, he will have compassion  according to the multitude of his loving-kindnesses:
3:32|KJV|But though he cause grief, yet will he have compassion according to the multitude of his mercies.
3:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主雖使人憂愁，還要照祂諸般的慈愛發憐恤。
3:33|Darby|for he doth not willingly afflict or grieve the children of  men.
3:33|KJV|For he doth not afflict willingly nor grieve the children of men.
3:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為祂並不存心使人受苦，使世人憂愁。
3:34|Darby|To crush under foot all the prisoners of the earth,
3:34|KJV|To crush under his feet all the prisoners of the earth.
3:34|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人將地上一切被囚的，都壓在腳下，
3:35|Darby|to turn aside the right of a man before the face of the  Most High,
3:35|KJV|To turn aside the right of a man before the face of the most High,
3:35|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在至高者面前屈枉人，
3:36|Darby|to wrong a man in his cause, -- will not the Lord see it?
3:36|KJV|To subvert a man in his cause, the LORD approveth not.
3:36|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在人的訟事上，顛倒是非－主豈不看這些麼？
3:37|Darby|Who is he that saith, and there cometh to pass, what the  Lord hath not commanded?
3:37|KJV|Who is he that saith, and it cometh to pass, when the Lord commandeth it not?
3:37|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主未曾命令的，誰能說了就成呢？
3:38|Darby|Out of the mouth of the Most High doth not there proceed  evil and good?
3:38|KJV|Out of the mouth of the most High proceedeth not evil and good?
3:38|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|禍福不都出於至高者的口麼？
3:39|Darby|Wherefore doth a living man complain, a man for the  punishment of his sins?
3:39|KJV|Wherefore doth a living man complain, a man for the punishment of his sins?
3:39|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|活人為何抱怨？人為何因自己的罪受罰發怨言？
3:40|Darby|Let us search and try our ways, and turn again to Jehovah.
3:40|KJV|Let us search and try our ways, and turn again to the LORD.
3:40|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們當探究察驗自己的道路，再歸向耶和華。
3:41|Darby|Let us lift up our heart with [our] hands unto ???’???’?????????God in the  heavens.
3:41|KJV|Let us lift up our heart with our hands unto God in the heavens.
3:41|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們當舉起心，向天上的神舉手禱告。
3:42|Darby|We have transgressed and have rebelled: thou hast not  pardoned.
3:42|KJV|We have transgressed and have rebelled: thou hast not pardoned.
3:42|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們犯罪背叛，你並不饒恕。
3:43|Darby|Thou hast covered thyself with anger, and pursued us; thou  hast slain, thou hast not spared.
3:43|KJV|Thou hast covered with anger, and persecuted us: thou hast slain, thou hast not pitied.
3:43|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你以怒氣遮蔽自己，追趕我們。你施行殺戮，並不顧惜。
3:44|Darby|Thou hast covered thyself with a cloud, that prayer should  not pass through.
3:44|KJV|Thou hast covered thyself with a cloud, that our prayer should not pass through.
3:44|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你用雲遮蔽自己，以致禱告不得透過。
3:45|Darby|Thou hast made us the offscouring and refuse in the midst  of the peoples.
3:45|KJV|Thou hast made us as the offscouring and refuse in the midst of the people.
3:45|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你使我們在眾民中成為污穢和渣滓。
3:46|Darby|All our enemies have opened their mouth against us.
3:46|KJV|All our enemies have opened their mouths against us.
3:46|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們的仇敵，都張口攻擊我們。
3:47|Darby|Fear and the pit are come upon us, devastation and ruin.
3:47|KJV|Fear and a snare is come upon us, desolation and destruction.
3:47|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|恐懼和陷坑，殘害和毀滅，都臨及我們。
3:48|Darby|Mine eye runneth down with streams of water for the ruin of  the daughter of my people.
3:48|KJV|Mine eye runneth down with rivers of water for the destruction of the daughter of my people.
3:48|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因我民被毀滅，我就眼淚流下如河。
3:49|Darby|Mine eye poureth down, and ceaseth not, without any  intermission,
3:49|KJV|Mine eye trickleth down, and ceaseth not, without any intermission.
3:49|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的眼淚傾流不停，總不止息，
3:50|Darby|till Jehovah look down and behold from the heavens.
3:50|KJV|Till the LORD look down, and behold from heaven.
3:50|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|直等耶和華垂顧，從天觀看。
3:51|Darby|Mine eye affecteth my soul, because of all the daughters of  my city.
3:51|KJV|Mine eye affecteth mine heart because of all the daughters of my city.
3:51|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因我本城的民，我的眼使我的魂傷痛。
3:52|Darby|They that are mine enemies without cause have chased me  sore like a bird.
3:52|KJV|Mine enemies chased me sore, like a bird, without cause.
3:52|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|無故與我為敵的追捕我，像追捕雀鳥一樣。
3:53|Darby|They have cut off my life in a pit, and cast a stone upon  me.
3:53|KJV|They have cut off my life in the dungeon, and cast a stone upon me.
3:53|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們使我的命在坑中斷絕，又拋石頭在我身上。
3:54|Darby|Waters streamed over my head; I said, I am cut off.
3:54|KJV|Waters flowed over mine head; then I said, I am cut off.
3:54|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|水流過我的頭；我說，我被剪除了。
3:55|Darby|I called upon thy name, Jehovah, out of the lowest pit.
3:55|KJV|I called upon thy name, O LORD, out of the low dungeon.
3:55|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華阿，我從極深的坑堜I求你的名。
3:56|Darby|Thou hast heard my voice: hide not thine ear at my sighing,  at my cry.
3:56|KJV|Thou hast heard my voice: hide not thine ear at my breathing, at my cry.
3:56|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你曾聽見我的聲音；求你不要掩耳不聽我的呼吸，我的呼籲。
3:57|Darby|Thou drewest near in the day that I called upon thee; thou  saidst, Fear not.
3:57|KJV|Thou drewest near in the day that I called upon thee: thou saidst, Fear not.
3:57|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我呼求你的日子，你臨近我，說，不要懼怕。
3:58|Darby|Lord, thou hast pleaded the cause of my soul, thou hast  redeemed my life.
3:58|KJV|O LORD, thou hast pleaded the causes of my soul; thou hast redeemed my life.
3:58|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主阿，你伸明了我魂堛滬煄F你救贖了我的命。
3:59|Darby|Jehovah, thou hast seen my wrong: judge thou my cause.
3:59|KJV|O LORD, thou hast seen my wrong: judge thou my cause.
3:59|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華阿，你見了我受的委屈；求你為我伸冤。
3:60|Darby|Thou hast seen all their vengeance, all their imaginations  against me.
3:60|KJV|Thou hast seen all their vengeance and all their imaginations against me.
3:60|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們向我報仇，設謀害我，你都看見了。
3:61|Darby|Thou hast heard their reproach, O Jehovah, all their  imaginations against me;
3:61|KJV|Thou hast heard their reproach, O LORD, and all their imaginations against me;
3:61|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華阿，你聽見他們辱罵我的話，知道他們向我所設的一切計謀，
3:62|Darby|the lips of those that rise up against me and their  meditation against me all the day.
3:62|KJV|The lips of those that rose up against me, and their device against me all the day.
3:62|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並那些起來攻擊我的人口中所說的話，以及終日所默想害我的計謀。
3:63|Darby|Behold thou their sitting down and their rising up: I am  their song.
3:63|KJV|Behold their sitting down, and their rising up; I am their musick.
3:63|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|求你觀看：他們坐下、起來；我成了他們嘲笑的歌曲。
3:64|Darby|Render unto them a recompence, O Jehovah, according to the  work of their hands;
3:64|KJV|Render unto them a recompence, O LORD, according to the work of their hands.
3:64|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華阿，你要按著他們手所作的，向他們施行報應。
3:65|Darby|give them obduracy of heart, thy curse unto them;
3:65|KJV|Give them sorrow of heart, thy curse unto them.
3:65|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要使他們的心剛硬，使你的咒詛臨到他們。
3:66<version name="Darby">pursue them in anger, and destroy them from under the  heavens of Jehovah. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:66<version name="KJV">Persecute and destroy them in anger from under the heavens of the LORD.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:66|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要在怒中追趕他們，從耶和華的天下除滅他們。
4:1|Darby|How is the gold become dim! the most pure gold changed! the  stones of the sanctuary poured out at the top of all the  streets!
4:1|KJV|How is the gold become dim! how is the most fine gold changed! the stones of the sanctuary are poured out in the top of every street.
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|黃金何竟失光！極純的金何竟變色！聖所的石頭倒在各街頭上。
4:2|Darby|The sons of Zion, so precious, comparable to fine gold, how  are they esteemed as earthen pitchers, the work of the hands of  the potter!
4:2|KJV|The precious sons of Zion, comparable to fine gold, how are they esteemed as earthen pitchers, the work of the hands of the potter!
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|錫安寶貴的眾子，好比精金，現在何竟算為窯匠的手所作的瓦瓶。
4:3|Darby|Even the jackals offer the breast, they give suck to their  young; the daughter of my people is become cruel, like the  ostriches in the wilderness.
4:3|KJV|Even the sea monsters draw out the breast, they give suck to their young ones: the daughter of my people is become cruel, like the ostriches in the wilderness.
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|野狗尚且把奶乳哺崽子，我民的女子倒成為殘忍，好像曠野的鴕鳥一般。
4:4|Darby|The tongue of the sucking child cleaveth to the roof of his  mouth for thirst; the young children ask bread, no man breaketh  it unto them.
4:4|KJV|The tongue of the sucking child cleaveth to the roof of his mouth for thirst: the young children ask bread, and no man breaketh it unto them.
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|喫奶孩子的舌頭，因乾渴貼住上膛；孩童求餅，無人擘給他們。
4:5|Darby|They that fed delicately are desolate in the streets; they  that were brought up in scarlet embrace dung-hills.
4:5|KJV|They that did feed delicately are desolate in the streets: they that were brought up in scarlet embrace dunghills.
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|素來喫美好食物的，現今在街上變為淒涼；素來在朱紅褥子中養大的，現今抱臥糞堆；
4:6|Darby|And the punishment of the iniquity of the daughter of my  people is greater than the reward of the sin of Sodom, which  was overthrown as in a moment, and no hands were violently laid  upon her.
4:6|KJV|For the punishment of the iniquity of the daughter of my people is greater than the punishment of the sin of Sodom, that was overthrown as in a moment, and no hands stayed on her.
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我民的罪孽，比所多瑪的罪還大；所多瑪雖然無人加手於她，還是轉眼之間被傾覆。
4:7|Darby|Her Nazarites were purer than snow, whiter than milk; they  were more ruddy in body than rubies, their figure was as  sapphire.
4:7|KJV|Her Nazarites were purer than snow, they were whiter than milk, they were more ruddy in body than rubies, their polishing was of sapphire:
4:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|錫安的貴冑素來比雪純淨，比奶更白；他們的身體比珊瑚更紅，樣貌像藍寶石一樣。
4:8|Darby|Their visage is darker than blackness, they are not known in  the streets; their skin cleaveth to their bones, it is  withered, it is become like a stick.
4:8|KJV|Their visage is blacker than a coal; they are not known in the streets: their skin cleaveth to their bones; it is withered, it is become like a stick.
4:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現在他們的面貌比黑炭更黑，以致在街上無人認識；他們的皮膚緊貼骨頭，枯乾如同木柴。
4:9|Darby|The slain with the sword are happier than the slain with  hunger; for these pine away, stricken through for want of the  fruits of the field.
4:9|KJV|They that be slain with the sword are better than they that be slain with hunger: for these pine away, stricken through for want of the fruits of the field.
4:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|餓死的不如被刀殺的，因為他們缺乏田間的出產，就受折磨，漸漸消瘦死亡。
4:10|Darby|The hands of pitiful women have boiled their own children:  they were their meat in the ruin of the daughter of my people.
4:10|KJV|The hands of the pitiful women have sodden their own children: they were their meat in the destruction of the daughter of my people.
4:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|慈憐的婦人親手煮自己的兒女；當我民被毀滅的時候，他們的兒女成了自己的食物。
4:11|Darby|Jehovah hath accomplished his fury; he hath poured out his  fierce anger, and hath kindled a fire in Zion, which hath  consumed the foundations thereof.
4:11|KJV|The LORD hath accomplished his fury; he hath poured out his fierce anger, and hath kindled a fire in Zion, and it hath devoured the foundations thereof.
4:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華發盡祂的怒氣，倒出祂的烈怒。祂在錫安使火著起，燒燬錫安的根基。
4:12|Darby|The kings of the earth, and all the inhabitants of the  world, would not have believed that the adversary and the enemy  should enter into the gates of Jerusalem.
4:12|KJV|The kings of the earth, and all the inhabitants of the world, would not have believed that the adversary and the enemy should have entered into the gates of Jerusalem.
4:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|地上的君王和世上的居民，都不信敵人和仇敵能進耶路撒冷的城門。
4:13|Darby|[It is] for the sins of her prophets, [and] the iniquities  of her priests, who have shed the blood of the righteous in the  midst of her.
4:13|KJV|For the sins of her prophets, and the iniquities of her priests, that have shed the blood of the just in the midst of her,
4:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這都因她申言者的罪，和祭司的罪孽；他們在城中流了義人的血。
4:14|Darby|They wandered about blind in the streets; they were  polluted with blood, so that men could not touch their  garments.
4:14|KJV|They have wandered as blind men in the streets, they have polluted themselves with blood, so that men could not touch their garments.
4:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們在街上瞎闖亂走，又被血玷污，以致人不能摸他們的衣服。
4:15|Darby|They cried unto them, Depart! Unclean! Depart! depart,  touch not! When they fled away, and wandered about, it was said  among the nations, They shall no more sojourn [there].
4:15|KJV|They cried unto them, Depart ye; it is unclean; depart, depart, touch not: when they fled away and wandered, they said among the heathen, They shall no more sojourn there.
4:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人向他們喊著說，走開！不潔淨的！走開，走開，不要碰我！他們逃走飄流的時候，列國中有人說，他們不可仍在這堭H居。
4:16|Darby|The face of Jehovah hath divided them; he will no more  regard them. They respected not the persons of the priests,  they favoured not the aged.
4:16|KJV|The anger of the LORD hath divided them; he will no more regard them: they respected not the persons of the priests, they favoured not the elders.
4:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華的怒氣將他們分散，不再眷顧他們；人不重看祭司，也不厚待長老。
4:17|Darby|Our eyes still failed for our vain help; in our watching,  we have watched for a nation that did not save.
4:17|KJV|As for us, our eyes as yet failed for our vain help: in our watching we have watched for a nation that could not save us.
4:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們仍在仰望幫助，以致眼目昏花，還是枉然；我們所盼望的，竟是一個不能救人的國。
4:18|Darby|They hunted our steps, that we could not go in our streets:  our end is near, our days are fulfilled; for our end is come.
4:18|KJV|They hunt our steps, that we cannot go in our streets: our end is near, our days are fulfilled; for our end is come.
4:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們像打獵的追蹤我們的腳步，以致我們不能在自己的街上行走；我們的結局臨近，我們的日子滿足，因為我們的結局來到了。
4:19|Darby|Our pursuers were swifter than the eagles of the heavens;  they chased us hotly upon the mountains, they laid wait for us  in the wilderness.
4:19|KJV|Our persecutors are swifter than the eagles of the heaven: they pursued us upon the mountains, they laid wait for us in the wilderness.
4:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|追趕我們的比空中的鷹更快；他們在山上追逼我們，在曠野埋伏等候我們。
4:20|Darby|The breath of our nostrils, the anointed of Jehovah, was  taken in their pits; of whom we said, Under his shadow we shall  live among the nations.
4:20|KJV|The breath of our nostrils, the anointed of the LORD, was taken in their pits, of whom we said, Under his shadow we shall live among the heathen.
4:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華的受膏者好比我們鼻中的氣，在他們的坑中被捉住；我們曾論到他說，我們必在他蔭下，在列國中存活。
4:21|Darby|Rejoice and be glad, daughter of Edom, that dwellest in the  land of Uz: the cup shall pass also unto thee; thou shalt be  drunken, and make thyself naked.
4:21|KJV|Rejoice and be glad, O daughter of Edom, that dwellest in the land of Uz; the cup also shall pass through unto thee: thou shalt be drunken, and shalt make thyself naked.
4:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|住在烏斯地的以東女子阿，只管歡喜快樂；這杯也必傳到你那堙F你必喝醉，以致露體。
4:22<version name="Darby">The punishment of thine iniquity is accomplished, O  daughter of Zion; he will no more carry thee away into  captivity. He will visit thine iniquity, O daughter of Edom; he  will discover thy sins. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:22<version name="KJV">The punishment of thine iniquity is accomplished, O daughter of Zion; he will no more carry thee away into captivity: he will visit thine iniquity, O daughter of Edom; he will discover thy sins.</p><p /><br /></version>
4:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|錫安的女子阿，你為罪孽所受的懲罰已經足彀了；耶和華必不使你再被遷徙。以東的女子阿，祂必追討你的罪孽，揭露你的罪。
5:1|Darby|Remember, O Jehovah, what is come upon us; consider, and see  our reproach.
5:1|KJV|Remember, O LORD, what is come upon us: consider, and behold our reproach.
5:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華阿，求你記念我們所遭遇的事；注視觀看我們所受的凌辱。
5:2|Darby|Our inheritance is turned to strangers, our houses to  aliens.
5:2|KJV|Our inheritance is turned to strangers, our houses to aliens.
5:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們的產業，轉歸異族人；我們的房屋，轉歸外地人。
5:3|Darby|We are orphans and fatherless, our mothers are as widows.
5:3|KJV|We are orphans and fatherless, our mothers are as widows.
5:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們成了無父的孤兒；我們的母親，好像寡婦。
5:4|Darby|Our water have we to drink for money, our wood cometh unto  us for a price.
5:4|KJV|We have drunken our water for money; our wood is sold unto us.
5:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們出錢纔得水喝；我們的柴是出了代價買來的。
5:5|Darby|Our pursuers are on our necks: we are weary, we have no  rest.
5:5|KJV|Our necks are under persecution: we labour, and have no rest.
5:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|追趕我們的，到了我們的頸項上；我們疲乏，不得歇息。
5:6|Darby|We have given the hand to Egypt, [and] to Asshur, to be  satisfied with bread.
5:6|KJV|We have given the hand to the Egyptians, and to the Assyrians, to be satisfied with bread.
5:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們投降埃及人和亞述人，為要得糧喫飽。
5:7|Darby|Our fathers have sinned, [and] they are not; and we bear  their iniquities.
5:7|KJV|Our fathers have sinned, and are not; and we have borne their iniquities.
5:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們列祖犯罪，而今不在了，我們卻擔當他們的罪孽。
5:8|Darby|Bondmen rule over us: there is no deliverer out of their  hand.
5:8|KJV|Servants have ruled over us: there is none that doth deliver us out of their hand.
5:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|奴僕轄制我們；無人救我們脫離他們的手。
5:9|Darby|We have to get our bread at the risk of our lives, because  of the sword of the wilderness.
5:9|KJV|We gat our bread with the peril of our lives because of the sword of the wilderness.
5:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為曠野的刀劍，我們冒性命的危險，纔得糧食。
5:10|Darby|Our skin gloweth like an oven, because of the burning heat  of the famine.
5:10|KJV|Our skin was black like an oven because of the terrible famine.
5:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因飢餓的燥熱，我們的皮膚黝黑如爐。
5:11|Darby|They have ravished the women in Zion, the maids in the  cities of Judah.
5:11|KJV|They ravished the women in Zion, and the maids in the cities of Judah.
5:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們在錫安玷污婦人，在猶大的城邑玷污處女。
5:12|Darby|Princes were hanged up by their hand; the faces of elders  were not honoured.
5:12|KJV|Princes are hanged up by their hand: the faces of elders were not honoured.
5:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|首領被他們吊起，老人的面也不受尊敬。
5:13|Darby|The young men have borne the mill, and the youths have  stumbled under the wood.
5:13|KJV|They took the young men to grind, and the children fell under the wood.
5:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|少年人扛磨石，孩童背木柴而絆跌。
5:14|Darby|The elders have ceased from the gate, the young men from  their music.
5:14|KJV|The elders have ceased from the gate, the young men from their musick.
5:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|老年人在城門口絕跡，少年人不再奏樂。
5:15|Darby|The joy of our heart hath ceased; our dance is turned into  mourning.
5:15|KJV|The joy of our heart is ceased; our dance is turned into mourning.
5:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們心中的歡樂止息，跳舞轉為悲哀。
5:16|Darby|The crown is fallen from our head: woe unto us, for we have  sinned!
5:16|KJV|The crown is fallen from our head: woe unto us, that we have sinned!
5:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|冠冕從我們的頭上落下；我們有禍了，因我們犯了罪。
5:17|Darby|For this our heart is faint; for these things our eyes have  grown dim,
5:17|KJV|For this our heart is faint; for these things our eyes are dim.
5:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|為這事我們的心發昏；為這些事我們的眼昏花。
5:18|Darby|Because of the mountain of Zion, which is desolate: foxes  walk over it.
5:18|KJV|Because of the mountain of Zion, which is desolate, the foxes walk upon it.
5:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為錫安山荒涼，狐狸行在其上。
5:19|Darby|Thou, Jehovah, dwellest for ever; thy throne is from  generation to generation.
5:19|KJV|Thou, O LORD, remainest for ever; thy throne from generation to generation.
5:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華阿，你存到永遠，你的寶座，存到萬代。
5:20|Darby|Wherefore dost thou forget us for ever, dost thou forsake  us so long time?
5:20|KJV|Wherefore dost thou forget us for ever, and forsake us so long time?
5:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你為何永遠忘記我們，為何長久離棄我們？
5:21|Darby|Turn thou us unto thee, Jehovah, and we shall be turned;  renew our days as of old.
5:21|KJV|Turn thou us unto thee, O LORD, and we shall be turned; renew our days as of old.
5:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華阿，求你使我們回轉，我們便得回轉；求你更新我們的日子，像古時一樣。
5:22<version name="Darby">Or is it that thou hast utterly rejected us? Wouldest thou  be exceeding wroth against us? </p><p /><br /></version>
5:22<version name="KJV">But thou hast utterly rejected us; thou art very wroth against us.</p><p /><br /></version>
5:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|或是你已經全然棄絕我們，向我們大發烈怒？
