1:1|ASV|The burden of the word of Jehovah to Israel by Malachi.
1:1|Darby|The burden of the word of Jehovah to Israel by Malachi.
1:1|KJV|The burden of the word of the LORD to Israel by Malachi.
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華藉瑪拉基傳給以色列之話語的默示。
1:2|ASV|I have loved you, saith Jehovah. Yet ye say, Wherein hast thou loved us? Was not Esau Jacob's brother, saith Jehovah: yet I loved Jacob;
1:2|Darby|I have loved you, saith Jehovah; but ye say, Wherein hast  thou loved us? Was not Esau Jacob's brother? saith Jehovah, and  I loved Jacob,
1:2|KJV|I have loved you, saith the LORD. Yet ye say, Wherein hast thou loved us? Was not Esau Jacob's brother? saith the LORD: yet I loved Jacob,
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華說，我愛了你們；你們卻說，你在何事上愛了我們呢？耶和華說，以掃不是雅各的哥哥麼？我卻愛雅各，
1:3|ASV|but Esau I hated, and made his mountains a desolation, and gave his heritage to the jackals of the wilderness.
1:3|Darby|and I hated Esau; and made his mountains a desolation, and  [gave] his inheritance to the jackals of the wilderness.
1:3|KJV|And I hated Esau, and laid his mountains and his heritage waste for the dragons of the wilderness.
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|惡以掃，使他的山嶺荒涼，把他的地業交給曠野的野狗。
1:4|ASV|Whereas Edom saith, We are beaten down, but we will return and build the waste places; thus saith Jehovah of hosts, They shall build, but I will throw down; and men shall call them The border of wickedness, and The people against whom Jehovah hath indignation for ever.
1:4|Darby|If Edom say, We are broken down, but we will build again the  ruined places, -- thus saith Jehovah of hosts: They shall  build, but I will throw down; and [men] shall call them the  territory of wickedness, and the people against whom Jehovah  hath indignation for ever.
1:4|KJV|Whereas Edom saith, We are impoverished, but we will return and build the desolate places; thus saith the LORD of hosts, They shall build, but I will throw down; and they shall call them, The border of wickedness, and, The people against whom the LORD hath indignation for ever.
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以東人說，我們現在雖被擊倒，卻要重建荒廢之處；萬軍之耶和華如此說，任他們建造，我必拆毀；他們必稱為罪惡之境，為耶和華永遠惱怒之民。
1:5|ASV|And your eyes shall see, and ye shall say, Jehovah be magnified beyond the border of Israel.
1:5|Darby|And your eyes shall see [it], and ye shall say, Jehovah is  magnified beyond the border of Israel.
1:5|KJV|And your eyes shall see, and ye shall say, The LORD will be magnified from the border of Israel.
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們必親眼看見，也必親自說，耶和華在以色列境地之上，被尊為大。
1:6|ASV|A son honoreth his father, and a servant his master: if then I am a father, where is mine honor? and if I am a master, where is my fear? saith Jehovah of hosts unto you, O priests, that despise my name. And ye say, Wherein have we despised thy name?
1:6|Darby|A son honoureth [his] father, and a servant his master: if  then I be a father, where is mine honour? and if I be a master,  where is my fear? saith Jehovah of hosts unto you, priests,  that despise my name. But ye say, Wherein have we despised thy  name?
1:6|KJV|A son honoureth his father, and a servant his master: if then I be a father, where is mine honour? and if I be a master, where is my fear? saith the LORD of hosts unto you, O priests, that despise my name. And ye say, Wherein have we despised thy name?
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|藐視我名的祭司阿，萬軍之耶和華對你們說，兒子尊敬父親，僕人敬畏主人。我既為父親，我該受的尊敬在那堜O？我既為主人，我該得的敬畏在那堜O？你們卻說，我們在何事上藐視你的名呢？
1:7|ASV|Ye offer polluted bread upon mine altar. And ye say, Wherein have we polluted thee? In that ye say, The table of Jehovah is contemptible.
1:7|Darby|Ye offer polluted bread upon mine altar; and ye say, Wherein  have we polluted thee? In that ye say, The table of Jehovah is  contemptible.
1:7|KJV|Ye offer polluted bread upon mine altar; and ye say, Wherein have we polluted thee? In that ye say, The table of the LORD is contemptible.
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們將污穢的食物獻在我的壇上，且說，我們在何事上污穢你呢？你們竟說，耶和華的桌子是可藐視的。
1:8|ASV|And when ye offer the blind for sacrifice, it is no evil! and when ye offer the lame and sick, it is no evil! Present it now unto thy governor; will he be pleased with thee? or will he accept thy person? saith Jehovah of hosts.
1:8|Darby|And if ye offer the blind for sacrifice, is it not evil? And  if ye offer the lame and sick, is it not evil? Present it now  unto thy governor: will he be pleased with thee? or will he  accept thy person? saith Jehovah of hosts.
1:8|KJV|And if ye offer the blind for sacrifice, is it not evil? and if ye offer the lame and sick, is it not evil? offer it now unto thy governor; will he be pleased with thee, or accept thy person? saith the LORD of hosts.
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們將瞎眼的獻為祭物，這不是惡麼？將瘸腿的、有病的獻上，這不是惡麼？你且把這些獻給你的省長。他豈喜悅你，豈能看你的情面麼？這是萬軍之耶和華說的。
1:9|ASV|And now, I pray you, entreat the favor of God, that he may be gracious unto us: this hath been by your means: will he accept any of your persons? saith Jehovah of hosts.
1:9|Darby|And now, I pray you, beseech ???’???’?????????God that he will be gracious  unto us. This hath been of your hand: will he accept any of  your persons? saith Jehovah of hosts.
1:9|KJV|And now, I pray you, beseech God that he will be gracious unto us: this hath been by your means: will he regard your persons? saith the LORD of hosts.
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現在我勸你們懇求神的恩惠，祂好施恩與我們。這妄獻的事，既是出於你們的手，祂豈能看你們的情面麼？這是萬軍之耶和華說的。
1:10|ASV|Oh that there were one among you that would shut the doors, that ye might not kindle fire on mine altar in vain! I have no pleasure in you, saith Jehovah of hosts, neither will I accept an offering at your hand.
1:10|Darby|Who is there among you that would even shut the doors? and  ye would not kindle [fire] on mine altar for nothing. I have no  delight in you, saith Jehovah of hosts, neither will I accept  an oblation at your hand.
1:10|KJV|Who is there even among you that would shut the doors for nought? neither do ye kindle fire on mine altar for nought. I have no pleasure in you, saith the LORD of hosts, neither will I accept an offering at your hand.
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|甚願你們中間有一人關上殿門，免得你們徒然在我壇上燒火！萬軍之耶和華說，我不喜悅你們，也不從你們手中收納供物。
1:11|ASV|For from the rising of the sun even unto the going down of the same my name shall be great among the Gentiles; and in every place incense shall be offered unto my name, and a pure offering: for my name shall be great among the Gentiles, saith Jehovah of hosts.
1:11|Darby|For from the rising of the sun even unto its setting my  name shall be great among the nations; and in every place  incense shall be offered unto my name, and a pure oblation: for  my name shall be great among the nations, saith Jehovah of  hosts.
1:11|KJV|For from the rising of the sun even unto the going down of the same my name shall be great among the Gentiles; and in every place incense shall be offered unto my name, and a pure offering: for my name shall be great among the heathen, saith the LORD of hosts.
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬軍之耶和華說，從日出之地到日落之處，我的名在列國中必尊為大。在各處，人必向我的名燒香，獻潔淨的供物；因為我的名在列國中必尊為大。
1:12|ASV|But ye profane it, in that ye say, The table of Jehovah is polluted, and the fruit thereof, even its food, is contemptible.
1:12|Darby|But ye profane it, in that ye say, The table of the Lord is  polluted; and the fruit thereof, his food, is contemptible.
1:12|KJV|But ye have profaned it, in that ye say, The table of the LORD is polluted; and the fruit thereof, even his meat, is contemptible.
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們卻褻瀆我的名，說，耶和華的桌子是污穢的，其上的食物是可藐視的。
1:13|ASV|Ye say also, Behold, what a weariness is it! and ye have snuffed at it, saith Jehovah of hosts; and ye have brought that which was taken by violence, and the lame, and the sick; thus ye bring the offering: should I accept this at your hand? saith Jehovah.
1:13|Darby|And ye say, Behold, what a weariness! And ye have puffed at  it, saith Jehovah of hosts, and ye bring [that which was] torn,  and the lame, and the sick; thus ye bring the oblation: should  I accept this of your hand? saith Jehovah.
1:13|KJV|Ye said also, Behold, what a weariness is it! and ye have snuffed at it, saith the LORD of hosts; and ye brought that which was torn, and the lame, and the sick; thus ye brought an offering: should I accept this of your hand? saith the LORD.
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們又說，這些事何等煩瑣！並嗤之以鼻。這是萬軍之耶和華說的。你們把搶來的、瘸腿的、有病的，拿來獻上為供物；我豈能從你們手中收納這些呢？這是耶和華說的。
1:14<version name="ASV">But cursed be the deceiver, who hath in his flock a male, and voweth, and sacrificeth unto the Lord a blemished thing; for I am a great King, saith Jehovah of hosts, and my name is terrible among the Gentiles. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:14<version name="Darby">Yea, cursed be the deceiver, who hath in his flock a male,  and voweth and sacrificeth unto the Lord a corrupt thing; for I  am a great King, saith Jehovah of hosts, and my name is  terrible among the nations. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:14<version name="KJV">But cursed be the deceiver, which hath in his flock a male, and voweth, and sacrificeth unto the LORD a corrupt thing: for I am a great King, saith the LORD of hosts, and my name is dreadful among the heathen.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|行詭詐的在群中有公羊，他許願卻用有殘疾的獻給主，這人是可咒詛的；因為我是大君王，我的名在列國中是可畏的；這是萬軍之耶和華說的。
2:1|ASV|And now, O ye priests, this commandment is for you.
2:1|Darby|And now, ye priests, this commandment is for you.
2:1|KJV|And now, O ye priests, this commandment is for you.
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|眾祭司阿，現今這誡命是給你們的。
2:2|ASV|If ye will not hear, and if ye will not lay it to heart, to give glory unto my name, saith Jehovah of hosts, then will I send the curse upon you, and I will curse your blessings; yea, I have cursed them already, because ye do not lay it to heart.
2:2|Darby|If ye do not hear, and if ye do not lay [it] to heart, to  give glory unto my name, saith Jehovah of hosts, I will even  send the curse among you, and I will curse your blessings: yea,  I have already cursed them, because ye do not lay [it] to  heart.
2:2|KJV|If ye will not hear, and if ye will not lay it to heart, to give glory unto my name, saith the LORD of hosts, I will even send a curse upon you, and I will curse your blessings: yea, I have cursed them already, because ye do not lay it to heart.
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬軍之耶和華說，你們若不聽從，也不放在心上，將榮耀歸與我的名，我就要差咒詛到你們中間，咒詛你們的福分；因你們不把誡命放在心上，我已經咒詛這些福分了。
2:3|ASV|Behold, I will rebuke your seed, and will spread dung upon your faces, even the dung of your feasts; and ye shall be taken away with it.
2:3|Darby|Behold, I will rebuke your seed, and spread dung upon your  faces, the dung of your feasts; and they shall take you away  with it.
2:3|KJV|Behold, I will corrupt your seed, and spread dung upon your faces, even the dung of your solemn feasts; and one shall take you away with it.
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必斥責你們的種子，又把糞，就是你們節期祭牲的糞，潑在你們的臉上；人要把你們與糞一同除掉。
2:4|ASV|And ye shall know that I have sent this commandment unto you, that my covenant may be with Levi, saith Jehovah of hosts.
2:4|Darby|And ye shall know that I have sent this commandment unto  you, that my covenant might be with Levi, saith Jehovah of  hosts.
2:4|KJV|And ye shall know that I have sent this commandment unto you, that my covenant might be with Levi, saith the LORD of hosts.
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們就知道我傳這誡命給你們，使我與利未所立的約，可以常存；這是萬軍之耶和華說的。
2:5|ASV|My covenant was with him of life and peace; and I gave them to him that he might fear; and he feared me, and stood in awe of my name.
2:5|Darby|My covenant with him was of life and peace, and I gave them  to him that he might fear; and he feared me, and trembled  before my name.
2:5|KJV|My covenant was with him of life and peace; and I gave them to him for the fear wherewith he feared me, and was afraid before my name.
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我曾與他立生命和平安的約；我將這兩樣賜給他，使他心存敬畏；他就敬畏我，懼怕我的名。
2:6|ASV|The law of truth was in his mouth, and unrighteousness was not found in his lips: he walked with me in peace and uprightness, and turned many away from iniquity.
2:6|Darby|The law of truth was in his mouth, and unrighteousness was  not found in his lips: he walked with me in peace and  uprightness, and he turned many from iniquity.
2:6|KJV|The law of truth was in his mouth, and iniquity was not found in his lips: he walked with me in peace and equity, and did turn many away from iniquity.
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|真理的律法在他口中，他嘴堥S有不義；他在平安和正直婸P我同行，使多人回頭離開罪孽。
2:7|ASV|For the priest's lips should keep knowledge, and they should seek the law at his mouth; for he is the messenger of Jehovah of hosts.
2:7|Darby|For the priest's lips should keep knowledge, and at his  mouth they seek the law; for he is the messenger of Jehovah of  hosts.
2:7|KJV|For the priest's lips should keep knowledge, and they should seek the law at his mouth: for he is the messenger of the LORD of hosts.
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祭司的嘴當謹守知識，人也當由他口中尋求訓誨，因為他是萬軍之耶和華的使者。
2:8|ASV|But ye are turned aside out of the way; ye have caused many to stumble in the law; ye have corrupted the covenant of Levi, saith Jehovah of hosts.
2:8|Darby|But ye are departed out of the way; ye have caused many to  stumble at the law; ye have corrupted the covenant of Levi,  saith Jehovah of hosts.
2:8|KJV|But ye are departed out of the way; ye have caused many to stumble at the law; ye have corrupted the covenant of Levi, saith the LORD of hosts.
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們卻偏離正道，使許多人在律法上跌倒；你們廢棄我與利未所立的約；這是萬軍之耶和華說的。
2:9|ASV|Therefore have I also made you contemptible and base before all the people, according as ye have not kept my ways, but have had respect of persons in the law.
2:9|Darby|And I also have made you contemptible and base before all  the people, because ye have not kept my ways, but have respect  of persons in [administering] the law.
2:9|KJV|Therefore have I also made you contemptible and base before all the people, according as ye have not kept my ways, but have been partial in the law.
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我也使你們在眾人面前被藐視，看為下賤，因你們不遵行我的道路，竟在律法上偏袒人。
2:10|ASV|Have we not all one father? hath not one God created us? why do we deal treacherously every man against his brother, profaning the covenant of our fathers?
2:10|Darby|Have we not all one father? Hath not one ???’???’?????????God created us?  Why do we deal unfaithfully every man against his brother, by  profaning the covenant of our fathers?
2:10|KJV|Have we not all one father? hath not one God created us? why do we deal treacherously every man against his brother, by profaning the covenant of our fathers?
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們豈不都有一位父麼？豈不是一位神所造的麼？我們各人怎麼以詭詐待弟兄，瀆犯了神與我們列祖所立的約呢？
2:11|ASV|Judah hath dealt treacherously, and an abomination is committed in Israel and in Jerusalem; for Judah hath profaned the holiness of Jehovah which he loveth, and hath married the daughter of a foreign god.
2:11|Darby|Judah hath dealt unfaithfully, and an abomination is  committed in Israel and in Jerusalem; for Judah hath profaned  the sanctuary of Jehovah which he loved, and hath married the  daughter of a strange ???’???’?????????god.
2:11|KJV|Judah hath dealt treacherously, and an abomination is committed in Israel and in Jerusalem; for Judah hath profaned the holiness of the LORD which he loved, and hath married the daughter of a strange god.
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|猶大人行事詭詐，並且在以色列和耶路撒冷中，行了一件可憎的事；因為猶大人褻瀆耶和華所愛的聖所，娶事奉外邦神的女子為妻。
2:12|ASV|Jehovah will cut off, to the man that doeth this, him that waketh and him that answereth, out of the tents of Jacob, and him that offereth an offering unto Jehovah of hosts.
2:12|Darby|Jehovah will cut off from the tents of Jacob the man that  doeth this, him that calleth and him that answereth; and him  that offereth an oblation unto Jehovah of hosts.
2:12|KJV|The LORD will cut off the man that doeth this, the master and the scholar, out of the tabernacles of Jacob, and him that offereth an offering unto the LORD of hosts.
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡行這事的，無論是叫醒的、答應的、或是獻供物給萬軍之耶和華的，耶和華也必從雅各的帳棚中剪除他。
2:13|ASV|And this again ye do: ye cover the altar of Jehovah with tears, with weeping, and with sighing, insomuch that he regardeth not the offering any more, neither receiveth it with good will at your hand.
2:13|Darby|And further ye do this: ye cover the altar of Jehovah with  tears, with weeping, and with sighing, insomuch that he  regardeth not the oblation any more, nor receiveth [it] with  satisfaction at your hand.
2:13|KJV|And this have ye done again, covering the altar of the LORD with tears, with weeping, and with crying out, insomuch that he regardeth not the offering any more, or receiveth it with good will at your hand.
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們又行了一件這樣的事，使眼淚，使哭泣和歎息遮蓋耶和華的祭壇，以致耶和華不再垂看那供物，也不樂意從你們手中收納。
2:14|ASV|Yet ye say, Wherefore? Because Jehovah hath been witness between thee and the wife of thy youth, against whom thou hast dealt treacherously, though she is thy companion, and the wife of thy covenant.
2:14|Darby|Yet ye say, Wherefore? Because Jehovah hath been a witness  between thee and the wife of thy youth, against whom thou hast  dealt unfaithfully: yet is she thy companion, and the wife of  thy covenant.
2:14|KJV|Yet ye say, Wherefore? Because the LORD hath been witness between thee and the wife of thy youth, against whom thou hast dealt treacherously: yet is she thy companion, and the wife of thy covenant.
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們還說，這是為甚麼呢？因耶和華在你和你幼年所娶的妻子中間作證人；她雖是你的伴侶，又是你盟約的妻子，你卻以詭詐待她。
2:15|ASV|And did he not make one, although he had the residue of the Spirit? And wherefore one? He sought a godly seed. Therefore take heed to your spirit, and let none deal treacherously against the wife of his youth.
2:15|Darby|And did not one make [them]? and the remnant of the Spirit  was his. And wherefore the one? He sought a seed of God. Take  heed then to your spirit, and let none deal unfaithfully  against the wife of his youth,
2:15|KJV|And did not he make one? Yet had he the residue of the spirit. And wherefore one? That he might seek a godly seed. Therefore take heed to your spirit, and let none deal treacherously against the wife of his youth.
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而神豈不是使二人成為一麼？祂靈的餘裔是屬祂的。為何成為一呢？乃是要得著屬神的後裔。所以當謹守你們的靈，誰也不可以詭詐待自己幼年所娶的妻子。
2:16|ASV|For I hate putting away, saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, and him that covereth his garment with violence, saith Jehovah of hosts: therefore take heed to your spirit, that ye deal not treacherously.
2:16|Darby|(for I hate putting away, saith Jehovah the God of Israel;)  and he covereth with violence his garment, saith Jehovah of  hosts: take heed then to your spirit, that ye deal not  unfaithfully.
2:16|KJV|For the LORD, the God of Israel, saith that he hateth putting away: for one covereth violence with his garment, saith the LORD of hosts: therefore take heed to your spirit, that ye deal not treacherously.
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華以色列的神說，休妻是我所恨惡的，休妻的人是以強暴行事；所以當謹守你們的靈，不可行詭詐；這是萬軍之耶和華說的。
2:17<version name="ASV">Ye have wearied Jehovah with your words. Yet ye say, Wherein have we wearied him? In that ye say, Every one that doeth evil is good in the sight of Jehovah, and he delighteth in them; or where is the God of justice? </p><p /><br /></version>
2:17<version name="Darby">Ye have wearied Jehovah with your words, and ye say,  Wherein have we wearied [him]? In that ye say, Every one that  doeth evil is good in the sight of Jehovah, and he delighteth  in them; or, Where is the God of judgment? </p><p /><br /></version>
2:17<version name="KJV">Ye have wearied the LORD with your words. Yet ye say, Wherein have we wearied him? When ye say, Every one that doeth evil is good in the sight of the LORD, and he delighteth in them; or, Where is the God of judgment?</p><p /><br /></version>
2:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們用言語使耶和華厭煩；你們還說，我們在何事上使祂厭煩呢？因為你們說，凡行惡的，耶和華眼看為善，並且祂喜悅他們；或說，公平的神在那堜O？
3:1|ASV|Behold, I send my messenger, and he shall prepare the way before me: and the Lord, whom ye seek, will suddenly come to his temple; and the messenger of the covenant, whom ye desire, behold, he cometh, saith Jehovah of hosts.
3:1|Darby|Behold, I send my messenger, and he shall prepare the way  before me; and the Lord whom ye seek will suddenly come to his  temple, and the Angel of the covenant, whom ye delight in:  behold, he cometh, saith Jehovah of hosts.
3:1|KJV|Behold, I will send my messenger, and he shall prepare the way before me: and the LORD, whom ye seek, shall suddenly come to his temple, even the messenger of the covenant, whom ye delight in: behold, he shall come, saith the LORD of hosts.
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬軍之耶和華說，我要差遣我的使者，在我前面豫備道路；你們所尋求的主，必忽然來到祂的殿；立約的使者，就是你們所羨慕的，快要來到。
3:2|ASV|But who can abide the day of his coming? and who shall stand when he appeareth? for he is like a refiner's fire, and like fuller's soap:
3:2|Darby|But who shall endure the day of his coming? and who shall  stand when he appeareth? For he will be like a refiner's fire,  and like fullers' lye.
3:2|KJV|But who may abide the day of his coming? and who shall stand when he appeareth? for he is like a refiner's fire, and like fullers' soap:
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂來的日子，誰能當得起呢？祂顯現的時候，誰能立得住呢？因為祂如煉金之人的火，如漂布之人的鹼。
3:3|ASV|and he will sit as a refiner and purifier of silver, and he will purify the sons of Levi, and refine them as gold and silver; and they shall offer unto Jehovah offerings in righteousness.
3:3|Darby|And he shall sit [as] a refiner and purifier of silver; and  he will purify the children of Levi, and purge them as gold and  silver; and they shall offer unto Jehovah an oblation in  righteousness.
3:3|KJV|And he shall sit as a refiner and purifier of silver: and he shall purify the sons of Levi, and purge them as gold and silver, that they may offer unto the LORD an offering in righteousness.
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂必坐下如煉淨銀子的，必潔淨利未人，熬煉他們像金銀一樣，他們就必在公義中獻供物給耶和華。
3:4|ASV|Then shall the offering of Judah and Jerusalem be pleasant unto Jehovah, as in the days of old, and as in ancient years.
3:4|Darby|Then shall the oblation of Judah and Jerusalem be pleasant  unto Jehovah, as in the days of old, and as in former years.
3:4|KJV|Then shall the offering of Judah and Jerusalem be pleasant unto the LORD, as in the days of old, and as in former years.
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時，猶大和耶路撒冷所獻的供物，必蒙耶和華悅納，彷彿古時之日，往昔之年。
3:5|ASV|And I will come near to you to judgment; and I will be a swift witness against the sorcerers, and against the adulterers, and against the false swearers, and against those that oppress the hireling in his wages, the widow, and the fatherless, and that turn aside the sojourner from his right, and fear not me, saith Jehovah of hosts.
3:5|Darby|And I will come near to you to judgment; and I will be a  swift witness against the sorcerers, and against the  adulterers, and against the false swearers, and against those  that oppress the hired servant in [his] wages, the widow and  the fatherless, and that turn aside the stranger [from his  right], and fear not me, saith Jehovah of hosts.
3:5|KJV|And I will come near to you to judgment; and I will be a swift witness against the sorcerers, and against the adulterers, and against false swearers, and against those that oppress the hireling in his wages, the widow, and the fatherless, and that turn aside the stranger from his right, and fear not me, saith the LORD of hosts.
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬軍之耶和華說，我必臨近你們，施行審判；我必速速作見證，攻擊行邪術的、犯姦淫的、起假誓的、虧負雇工之工價的、欺壓寡婦孤兒的、屈枉寄居的、和不敬畏我的。
3:6|ASV|For I, Jehovah, change not; therefore ye, O sons of Jacob, are not consumed.
3:6|Darby|For I Jehovah change not, and ye, sons of Jacob, are not  consumed.
3:6|KJV|For I am the LORD, I change not; therefore ye sons of Jacob are not consumed.
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因我耶和華是不改變的；所以雅各的子孫哪，你們沒有滅亡。
3:7|ASV|From the days of your fathers ye have turned aside from mine ordinances, and have not kept them. Return unto me, and I will return unto you, saith Jehovah of hosts. But ye say, Wherein shall we return?
3:7|Darby|Since the days of your fathers have ye departed from my  statutes, and have not kept them. Return unto me, and I will  return unto you, saith Jehovah of hosts. But ye say, Wherein  shall we return?
3:7|KJV|Even from the days of your fathers ye are gone away from mine ordinances, and have not kept them. Return unto me, and I will return unto you, saith the LORD of hosts. But ye said, Wherein shall we return?
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬軍之耶和華說，從你們列祖的日子以來，你們常常偏離我的律例而不遵守。現在你們要轉向我，我就轉向你們；你們卻問說，我們如何轉向呢？
3:8|ASV|Will a man rob God? yet ye rob me. But ye say, Wherein have we robbed thee? In tithes and offerings.
3:8|Darby|Will a man rob God? But ye rob me. And ye say, Wherein do we  rob thee? [In] tithes and heave-offerings.
3:8|KJV|Will a man rob God? Yet ye have robbed me. But ye say, Wherein have we robbed thee? In tithes and offerings.
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人豈可奪取神之物呢？你們竟奪取我的物，你們卻說，我們在何事上奪取你的物呢？你們奪取了當納的十分之一，和當獻的供物。
3:9|ASV|Ye are cursed with the curse; for ye rob me, even this whole nation.
3:9|Darby|Ye are cursed with a curse; and me ye rob, [even] this whole  nation.
3:9|KJV|Ye are cursed with a curse: for ye have robbed me, even this whole nation.
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們為咒詛所咒詛，但你們通國的人，仍奪取我的物。
3:10|ASV|Bring ye the whole tithe into the store-house, that there may be food in my house, and prove me now herewith, saith Jehovah of hosts, if I will not open you the windows of heaven, and pour you out a blessing, that there shall not be room enough to receive it.
3:10|Darby|Bring the whole tithe into the treasure-house, that there  may be food in my house, and prove me now herewith, saith  Jehovah of hosts, if I open not to you the windows of the  heavens, and pour you out a blessing, till there be no place  for it.
3:10|KJV|Bring ye all the tithes into the storehouse, that there may be meat in mine house, and prove me now herewith, saith the LORD of hosts, if I will not open you the windows of heaven, and pour you out a blessing, that there shall not be room enough to receive it.
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬軍之耶和華說，你們要將當納的十分之一，全然送入倉庫，使我家有糧，以此試試我，是否為你們敞開天上的窗戶，傾福與你們，甚至無處可容。
3:11|ASV|And I will rebuke the devourer for your sakes, and he shall not destroy the fruits of your ground; neither shall your vine cast its fruit before the time in the field, saith Jehovah of hosts.
3:11|Darby|And I will rebuke the devourer for your sakes, and he shall  not destroy the fruits of your ground; neither shall your vine  cast its fruit before the time in the field, saith Jehovah of  hosts.
3:11|KJV|And I will rebuke the devourer for your sakes, and he shall not destroy the fruits of your ground; neither shall your vine cast her fruit before the time in the field, saith the LORD of hosts.
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬軍之耶和華說，我必為你們斥責那吞喫者，他就不毀壞你們地的出產；你們田間的葡萄樹在未熟之先，也不掉果子。
3:12|ASV|And all nations shall call you happy; for ye shall be a delightsome land, saith Jehovah of hosts.
3:12|Darby|And all nations shall call you blessed; for ye shall be a  delightsome land, saith Jehovah of hosts.
3:12|KJV|And all nations shall call you blessed: for ye shall be a delightsome land, saith the LORD of hosts.
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬軍之耶和華說，萬國必稱你們為有福的，因你們的地必成為喜樂之地。
3:13|ASV|Your words have been stout against me, saith Jehovah. Yet ye say, What have we spoken against thee?
3:13|Darby|Your words have been stout against me, saith Jehovah; but  ye say, What have we been speaking against thee?
3:13|KJV|Your words have been stout against me, saith the LORD. Yet ye say, What have we spoken so much against thee?
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華說，你們用話語頂撞我；你們還說，我們用甚麼話頂撞了你呢？
3:14|ASV|Ye have said, It is vain to serve God; and what profit is it that we have kept his charge, and that we have walked mournfully before Jehovah of hosts?
3:14|Darby|Ye say, It is vain to serve God; and what profit is it that  we keep his charge, and that we walk mournfully before Jehovah  of hosts?
3:14|KJV|Ye have said, It is vain to serve God: and what profit is it that we have kept his ordinance, and that we have walked mournfully before the LORD of hosts?
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們說，事奉神是徒然的；遵守神所吩咐的，在萬軍之耶和華面前哀痛而行，有甚麼益處呢？
3:15|ASV|And now we call the proud happy; yea, they that work wickedness are built up; yea, they tempt God, and escape.
3:15|Darby|And now we hold the proud for happy; yea, they that work  wickedness are built up; yea, they tempt God, and they escape.
3:15|KJV|And now we call the proud happy; yea, they that work wickedness are set up; yea, they that tempt God are even delivered.
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|如今我們稱狂傲的人為有福；行惡的人非但得建立，並且雖然試探神，卻得以逃罪。
3:16|ASV|Then they that feared Jehovah spake one with another; and Jehovah hearkened, and heard, and a book of remembrance was written before him, for them that feared Jehovah, and that thought upon his name.
3:16|Darby|Then they that feared Jehovah spoke often one to another;  and Jehovah observed [it], and heard, and a book of remembrance  was written before him for them that feared Jehovah, and that  thought upon his name.
3:16|KJV|Then they that feared the LORD spake often one to another: and the LORD hearkened, and heard it, and a book of remembrance was written before him for them that feared the LORD, and that thought upon his name.
3:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時，敬畏耶和華的彼此談論；耶和華側耳而聽，且有記念冊在祂面前，記錄那些敬畏耶和華並留意祂名的人。
3:17|ASV|And they shall be mine, saith Jehovah of hosts, even mine own possession, in the day that I make; and I will spare them, as a man spareth his own son that serveth him.
3:17|Darby|And they shall be unto me a peculiar treasure, saith  Jehovah of hosts, in the day that I prepare; and I will spare  them as a man spareth his own son that serveth him.
3:17|KJV|And they shall be mine, saith the LORD of hosts, in that day when I make up my jewels; and I will spare them, as a man spareth his own son that serveth him.
3:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬軍之耶和華說，在我所豫備的日子，他們必屬我，作我自己的珍寶；我必顧惜他們，如同人顧惜那服事自己的兒子。
3:18<version name="ASV">Then shall ye return and discern between the righteous and the wicked, between him that serveth God and him that serveth him not. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:18<version name="Darby">And ye shall return and discern between the righteous and  the wicked, between him that serveth God and him that serveth  him not. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:18<version name="KJV">Then shall ye return, and discern between the righteous and the wicked, between him that serveth God and him that serveth him not.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時你們必歸回，將義人和惡人，事奉神和不事奉神的人，分別出來。
4:1|ASV|For, behold, the day cometh, it burneth as a furnace; and all the proud, and all that work wickedness, shall be stubble; and the day that cometh shall burn them up, saith Jehovah of hosts, that it shall leave them neither root nor branch.
4:1|Darby|For behold, the day cometh, burning as a furnace; and all  the proud and all that work wickedness shall be stubble; and  the day that cometh shall burn them up, saith Jehovah of hosts,  so that it shall leave them neither root nor branch.
4:1|KJV|For, behold, the day cometh, that shall burn as an oven; and all the proud, yea, and all that do wickedly, shall be stubble: and the day that cometh shall burn them up, saith the LORD of hosts, that it shall leave them neither root nor branch.
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬軍之耶和華說，那日子來到，如燒著的火爐；凡狂傲的和行惡的，必如碎秸；那要來之日必將他們燒盡，不給他們留下根和枝條。
4:2|ASV|But unto you that fear my name shall the sun of righteousness arise with healing in its wings; and ye shall go forth, and gambol as calves of the stall.
4:2|Darby|And unto you that fear my name shall the Sun of  righteousness arise with healing in his wings; and ye shall go  forth and leap like fatted calves.
4:2|KJV|But unto you that fear my name shall the Sun of righteousness arise with healing in his wings; and ye shall go forth, and grow up as calves of the stall.
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但向你們敬畏我名的人，必有公義的日頭升起，其翅膀有醫治之能；你們必如圈堛漯峇犢出來跳躍。
4:3|ASV|And ye shall tread down the wicked; for they shall be ashes under the soles of your feet in the day that I make, saith Jehovah of hosts.
4:3|Darby|And ye shall tread down the wicked; for they shall be ashes  under the soles of your feet in the day that I prepare, saith  Jehovah of hosts.
4:3|KJV|And ye shall tread down the wicked; for they shall be ashes under the soles of your feet in the day that I shall do this, saith the LORD of hosts.
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們必踐踏惡人；因為在我所豫備的日子，他們必如灰塵在你們腳掌之下；這是萬軍之耶和華說的。
4:4|ASV|Remember ye the law of Moses my servant, which I commanded unto him in Horeb for all Israel, even statutes and ordinances.
4:4|Darby|Remember the law of Moses my servant, which I commanded unto  him in Horeb for all Israel, the statutes and ordinances.
4:4|KJV|Remember ye the law of Moses my servant, which I commanded unto him in Horeb for all Israel, with the statutes and judgments.
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們當記念我僕人摩西的律法，就是我在何烈山為以色列眾人所吩咐他的律例和典章。
4:5|ASV|Behold, I will send you Elijah the prophet before the great and terrible day of Jehovah come.
4:5|Darby|Behold, I send unto you Elijah the prophet, before the  coming of the great and terrible day of Jehovah.
4:5|KJV|Behold, I will send you Elijah the prophet before the coming of the great and dreadful day of the LORD:
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|看哪，耶和華大而可畏之日未到以前，我必差遣申言者以利亞到你們那堨h。
4:6<version name="ASV">And he shall turn the heart of the fathers to the children, and the heart of the children to their fathers; lest I come and smite the earth with a curse. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:6<version name="Darby">And he shall turn the heart of the fathers to the children,  and the heart of the children to their fathers, lest I come and  smite the earth with a curse. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:6<version name="KJV">And he shall turn the heart of the fathers to the children, and the heart of the children to their fathers, lest I come and smite the earth with a curse.</p><p /><br /></version>
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他必使父親的心轉向兒女，兒女的心轉向父親，免得我來，用咒詛擊打這地。
