1:1|ASV|The burden of Nineveh. The book of the vision of Nahum the Elkoshite.
1:1|Darby|The burden of Nineveh. The book of the vision of Nahum the  Elkoshite.
1:1|KJV|The burden of Nineveh. The book of the vision of Nahum the Elkoshite.
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|關於尼尼微的默示，就是伊勒歌斯人那鴻的異象書。
1:2|ASV|Jehovah is a jealous God and avengeth; Jehovah avengeth and is full of wrath; Jehovah taketh vengeance on his adversaries, and he reserveth wrath for his enemies.
1:2|Darby|A jealous and avenging ???’???’?????????God is Jehovah: an avenger is  Jehovah, and full of fury: Jehovah taketh vengeance on his  adversaries, and he reserveth [wrath] for his enemies.
1:2|KJV|God is jealous, and the LORD revengeth; the LORD revengeth, and is furious; the LORD will take vengeance on his adversaries, and he reserveth wrath for his enemies.
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華是忌邪施報的神；耶和華施報，且滿有忿怒；耶和華向祂的敵人施報，向祂的仇敵懷怒。
1:3|ASV|Jehovah is slow to anger, and great in power, and will by no means clear the guilty: Jehovah hath his way in the whirlwind and in the storm, and the clouds are the dust of his feet.
1:3|Darby|Jehovah is slow to anger, and great in power, and doth not  at all clear [the guilty]: Jehovah, -- his way is in the  whirlwind and in the storm, and the clouds are the dust of his  feet.
1:3|KJV|The LORD is slow to anger, and great in power, and will not at all acquit the wicked: the LORD hath his way in the whirlwind and in the storm, and the clouds are the dust of his feet.
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華不輕易發怒，大有能力，絕不以有罪的為無罪；耶和華的道路在旋風和暴風中，雲彩是祂腳下的塵土。
1:4|ASV|He rebuketh the sea, and maketh it dry, and drieth up all the rivers: Bashan languisheth, and Carmel; and the flower of Lebanon languisheth.
1:4|Darby|He rebuketh the sea, and maketh it dry, and drieth up all  the rivers: Bashan languisheth, and Carmel, and the flower of  Lebanon languisheth.
1:4|KJV|He rebuketh the sea, and maketh it dry, and drieth up all the rivers: Bashan languisheth, and Carmel, and the flower of Lebanon languisheth.
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂斥責海，使海乾了，使一切江河乾涸。巴珊和迦密的樹林衰殘，利巴嫩的花草也衰殘了。
1:5|ASV|The mountains quake at him, and the hills melt; and the earth is upheaved at his presence, yea, the world, and all that dwell therein.
1:5|Darby|The mountains quake before him, and the hills melt, and the  earth is upheaved at his presence, and the world, and all that  dwell therein.
1:5|KJV|The mountains quake at him, and the hills melt, and the earth is burned at his presence, yea, the world, and all that dwell therein.
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|大山因祂震動，小山也都鎔化；大地在祂面前突起，世界和住在其間的也都如此。
1:6|ASV|Who can stand before his indignation? and who can abide in the fierceness of his anger? his wrath is poured out like fire, and the rocks are broken asunder by him.
1:6|Darby|Who shall stand before his indignation? and who shall abide  in the fierceness of his anger? His fury is poured out like  fire, and the rocks are broken asunder by him.
1:6|KJV|Who can stand before his indignation? and who can abide in the fierceness of his anger? his fury is poured out like fire, and the rocks are thrown down by him.
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在祂的惱怒前，誰能站得住呢？祂發烈怒，誰能當得起呢？祂的忿怒如火傾倒，磐石因祂崩裂。
1:7|ASV|Jehovah is good, a stronghold in the day of trouble; and he knoweth them that take refuge in him.
1:7|Darby|Jehovah is good, a stronghold in the day of trouble; and he  knoweth them that trust in him.
1:7|KJV|The LORD is good, a strong hold in the day of trouble; and he knoweth them that trust in him.
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華本為善，在急難的日子作人的保障；祂認得那些投奔於祂的人。
1:8|ASV|But with an over-running flood he will make a full end of her place, and will pursue his enemies into darkness.
1:8|Darby|But with an overrunning flood he will make a full end of the  place thereof, and darkness shall pursue his enemies.
1:8|KJV|But with an overrunning flood he will make an utter end of the place thereof, and darkness shall pursue his enemies.
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但祂必以氾濫的洪水將尼尼微滅絕淨盡，又將祂的仇敵趕入黑暗。
1:9|ASV|What do ye devise against Jehovah? he will make a full end; affliction shall not rise up the second time.
1:9|Darby|What do ye imagine against Jehovah? He will make a full end:  trouble shall not rise up the second time.
1:9|KJV|What do ye imagine against the LORD? he will make an utter end: affliction shall not rise up the second time.
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|尼尼微人哪，你們設何謀攻擊耶和華呢？祂必將你們滅絕淨盡；災難必不再次興起。
1:10|ASV|For entangled like thorns, and drunken as with their drink, they are consumed utterly as dry stubble.
1:10|Darby|Though they be tangled together [as] thorns, and be as  drenched from their drink, they shall be devoured as dry  stubble, completely.
1:10|KJV|For while they be folden together as thorns, and while they are drunken as drunkards, they shall be devoured as stubble fully dry.
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們雖像纏結的荊棘，像喝醉了的人，卻必如枯乾的碎秸全然燒滅。
1:11|ASV|There is one gone forth out of thee, that deviseth evil against Jehovah, that counselleth wickedness.
1:11|Darby|Out of thee is gone forth one that imagineth evil against  Jehovah, a wicked counsellor.
1:11|KJV|There is one come out of thee, that imagineth evil against the LORD, a wicked counsellor.
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有一人從你那堨X來，圖謀邪惡，設惡計攻擊耶和華。
1:12|ASV|Thus saith Jehovah: Though they be in full strength, and likewise many, even so shall they be cut down, and he shall pass away. Though I have afflicted thee, I will afflict thee no more.
1:12|Darby|Thus saith Jehovah: Though they be complete in number, and  many as they be, even so shall they be cut down, and he shall  pass away; and though I have afflicted thee, I will afflict  thee no more.
1:12|KJV|Thus saith the LORD; Though they be quiet, and likewise many, yet thus shall they be cut down, when he shall pass through. Though I have afflicted thee, I will afflict thee no more.
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華如此說，他們雖然人數充足繁多，也必被剪除消逝。猶大阿，我雖然使你受苦，卻不再使你受苦。
1:13|ASV|And now will I break his yoke from off thee, and will burst thy bonds in sunder.
1:13|Darby|And now will I break his yoke from off thee, and will burst  thy bonds asunder.
1:13|KJV|For now will I break his yoke from off thee, and will burst thy bonds in sunder.
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現在我必從你頸項上折斷他的軛，扭開你的繩索。
1:14|ASV|And Jehovah hath given commandment concerning thee, that no more of thy name be sown: out of the house of thy gods will I cut off the graven image and the molten image; I will make thy grave; for thou art vile.
1:14|Darby|And Jehovah hath given commandment concerning thee, that no  more of thy name be sown: out of the house of thy god will I  cut off the graven image, and the molten image: I will prepare  thy grave; for thou art vile.
1:14|KJV|And the LORD hath given a commandment concerning thee, that no more of thy name be sown: out of the house of thy gods will I cut off the graven image and the molten image: I will make thy grave; for thou art vile.
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|尼尼微阿，耶和華已經出令，指著你說，你的名必不再散播；我必從你神的廟中，除滅雕製的偶像，和鑄造的偶像；我必因你的卑劣，為你豫備墳墓。
1:15<version name="ASV">Behold, upon the mountains the feet of him that bringeth good tidings, that publisheth peace! Keep thy feasts, O Judah, perform thy vows; for the wicked one shall no more pass through thee; he is utterly cut off. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:15<version name="Darby">Behold upon the mountains the feet of him that bringeth  glad tidings, that publisheth peace! Celebrate thy feasts,  Judah, perform thy vows: for the wicked one shall no more pass  through thee; he is utterly cut off. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:15<version name="KJV">Behold upon the mountains the feet of him that bringeth good tidings, that publisheth peace! O Judah, keep thy solemn feasts, perform thy vows: for the wicked shall no more pass through thee; he is utterly cut off.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|看哪，報好信傳平安之人的腳登山，說，猶大阿，當守你的節期，還你所許的願；因為那惡人必不再從你中間經過；他已全然被剪除了。
2:1|ASV|He that dasheth in pieces is come up against thee: keep the fortress, watch the way, make thy loins strong, fortify thy power mightily.
2:1|Darby|He that dasheth in pieces is come up against thy face: keep  the fortress, watch the way, make [thy] loins strong, fortify  [thy] power mightily.
2:1|KJV|He that dasheth in pieces is come up before thy face: keep the munition, watch the way, make thy loins strong, fortify thy power mightily.
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|尼尼微阿，那打散邦國的上到你面前；你要看守保障，謹防道路，使腰強壯，大大勉力。
2:2|ASV|For Jehovah restoreth the excellency of Jacob, as the excellency of Israel; for the emptiers have emptied them out, and destroyed their vine-branches.
2:2|Darby|For Jehovah hath brought again the glory of Jacob, as the  glory of Israel; for the wasters have wasted them, and marred  their vine-branches.
2:2|KJV|For the LORD hath turned away the excellency of Jacob, as the excellency of Israel: for the emptiers have emptied them out, and marred their vine branches.
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為耶和華復興雅各所誇耀的，好像以色列所誇耀的一樣；因為劫掠者已經把他們劫掠一空，將他們的葡萄枝毀壞了。
2:3|ASV|The shield of his mighty men is made red, the valiant men are in scarlet: the chariots flash with steel in the day of his preparation, and the cypress spears are brandished.
2:3|Darby|The shield of his mighty men is made red, the valiant men  are in scarlet: the chariots [glitter] with the sheen of steel,  in the day of his preparation, and the spears are brandished.
2:3|KJV|The shield of his mighty men is made red, the valiant men are in scarlet: the chariots shall be with flaming torches in the day of his preparation, and the fir trees shall be terribly shaken.
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂勇士的盾牌是紅的，精兵都穿朱紅衣服；在祂豫備爭戰的日子，戰車上的鋼鐵閃爍如火，槍矛也掄起來了；
2:4|ASV|The chariots rage in the streets; they rush to and fro in the broad ways: the appearance of them is like torches; they run like the lightnings.
2:4|Darby|The chariots rush madly in the streets, they justle one  against another in the broad ways: the appearance of them is  like torches, they run like lightnings.
2:4|KJV|The chariots shall rage in the streets, they shall justle one against another in the broad ways: they shall seem like torches, they shall run like the lightnings.
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|戰車在街上急行，在寬闊處奔來奔去，形狀如火把，飛跑如閃電。
2:5|ASV|He remembereth his nobles: they stumble in their march; they make haste to the wall thereof, and the mantelet is prepared.
2:5|Darby|He bethinketh him of his nobles: they stumble in their  march; they make haste to the wall thereof, and the shelter is  prepared.
2:5|KJV|He shall recount his worthies: they shall stumble in their walk; they shall make haste to the wall thereof, and the defence shall be prepared.
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞述王招聚他的貴冑：他們顛躓而行，奔上城牆，但攻城者的防障已經備妥。
2:6|ASV|The gates of the rivers are opened, and the palace is dissolved.
2:6|Darby|The gates of the rivers are opened, and the palace melteth  away.
2:6|KJV|The gates of the rivers shall be opened, and the palace shall be dissolved.
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|河閘開放，宮殿摧毀。
2:7|ASV|And it is decreed: she is uncovered, she is carried away; and her handmaids moan as with the voice of doves, beating upon their breasts.
2:7|Darby|And it is decreed: she shall be uncovered, she shall be led  away, and her maids shall moan as with the voice of doves,  drumming upon their breasts.
2:7|KJV|And Huzzab shall be led away captive, she shall be brought up, and her maids shall lead her as with the voice of doves, tabering upon their breasts.
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王后赤身，被人擄去；宮女捶胸，哀鳴如鴿；此乃命定之事。
2:8|ASV|But Nineveh hath been from of old like a pool of water: yet they flee away. Stand, stand, they cry; but none looketh back.
2:8|Darby|Nineveh hath been like a pool of water, since the day she  existed, yet they flee away. ... Stand! Stand! But none looketh  back.
2:8|KJV|But Nineveh is of old like a pool of water: yet they shall flee away. Stand, stand, shall they cry; but none shall look back.
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|尼尼微自古以來充滿人民，如同聚水的池子；現在他們卻都逃跑；雖有人呼喊說，站住！站住！卻無人回顧。
2:9|ASV|Take ye the spoil of silver, take the spoil of gold; for there is no end of the store, the glory of all goodly furniture.
2:9|Darby|Plunder the silver, plunder the gold; for there is no end of  the splendid store of all precious vessels.
2:9|KJV|Take ye the spoil of silver, take the spoil of gold: for there is none end of the store and glory out of all the pleasant furniture.
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們搶掠銀子，搶掠金子罷！因為所儲備的無窮，一切的寶器何等榮耀！
2:10|ASV|She is empty, and void, and waste; and the heart melteth, and the knees smite together, and anguish is in all loins, and the faces of them all are waxed pale.
2:10|Darby|She is empty, and void, and waste; and the heart melteth,  and the knees smite together, and writhing pain is in all  loins, and all their faces grow pale.
2:10|KJV|She is empty, and void, and waste: and the heart melteth, and the knees smite together, and much pain is in all loins, and the faces of them all gather blackness.
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現在卻空虛、荒涼、曠廢！人心融化，雙膝相碰，腰都疼痛，臉都變暗。
2:11|ASV|Where is the den of the lions, and the feeding-place of the young lions, where the lion and the lioness walked, the lion's whelp, and none made them afraid?
2:11|Darby|Where is [now] the den of the lions, and the feeding-place  of the young lions, where the lion, the lioness, [and] the  lion's whelp walked, and none made them afraid?
2:11|KJV|Where is the dwelling of the lions, and the feedingplace of the young lions, where the lion, even the old lion, walked, and the lion's whelp, and none made them afraid?
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|獅子的洞和少壯獅子餧養之處在那堜O？公獅、母獅、小獅遊行，無人驚嚇之處在那堜O？
2:12|ASV|The lion did tear in pieces enough for his whelps, and strangled for his lionesses, and filled his caves with prey, and his dens with ravin.
2:12|Darby|The lion tore in pieces enough for his whelps, and  strangled for his lionesses, and filled his holes with prey,  and his dens with ravin.
2:12|KJV|The lion did tear in pieces enough for his whelps, and strangled for his lionesses, and filled his holes with prey, and his dens with ravin.
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|公獅為小獅撕碎足彀的食物，為母獅掐死活物，把獵物充滿牠的洞，把撕碎的充滿牠的穴。
2:13<version name="ASV">Behold, I am against thee, saith Jehovah of hosts, and I will burn her chariots in the smoke, and the sword shall devour thy young lions; and I will cut off thy prey from the earth, and the voice of thy messengers shall no more be heard. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:13<version name="Darby">Behold, I am against thee, saith Jehovah of hosts: and I  will burn her chariots into smoke; and the sword shall devour  thy young lions, and I will cut off thy prey from the earth;  and the voice of thy messengers shall no more be heard. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:13<version name="KJV">Behold, I am against thee, saith the LORD of hosts, and I will burn her chariots in the smoke, and the sword shall devour thy young lions: and I will cut off thy prey from the earth, and the voice of thy messengers shall no more be heard.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬軍之耶和華說，看哪，我與你為敵，必將你的戰車焚燒成煙，刀劍也必吞滅你的少壯獅子；我必從地上除滅你的獵物；你使者的聲音，必不再聽見。
3:1|ASV|Woe to the bloody city! it is all full of lies and rapine; the prey departeth not.
3:1|Darby|Woe to the bloody city! It is all full of lies [and]  violence; the prey departeth not.
3:1|KJV|Woe to the bloody city! it is all full of lies and robbery; the prey departeth not;
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|禍哉，這流人血的城！充滿謊詐和強暴，搶奪的事總不止息。
3:2|ASV|The noise of the whip, and the noise of the rattling of wheels, and prancing horses, and bounding chariots,
3:2|Darby|The crack of the whip, and the noise of the rattling of the  wheels, and of the prancing horses, and of the bounding  chariots!
3:2|KJV|The noise of a whip, and the noise of the rattling of the wheels, and of the pransing horses, and of the jumping chariots.
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|鞭聲響亮，車輪轟轟；馬匹快跑，車輛奔騰，
3:3|ASV|the horseman mounting, and the flashing sword, and the glittering spear, and a multitude of slain, and a great heap of corpses, and there is no end of the bodies; they stumble upon their bodies;-
3:3|Darby|The horseman springing up, and the glitter of the sword, and  the flash of the spear, and a multitude of slain, and a mass of  carcases, and no end of corpses: they stumble over their  corpses.
3:3|KJV|The horseman lifteth up both the bright sword and the glittering spear: and there is a multitude of slain, and a great number of carcases; and there is none end of their corpses; they stumble upon their corpses:
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|騎兵躍馬，刀劍發光，槍矛閃爍；被殺的甚多，屍首成堆，屍骸無數，人碰著而跌倒。
3:4|ASV|because of the multitude of the whoredoms of the well-favored harlot, the mistress of witchcrafts, that selleth nations through her whoredoms, and families through her witchcrafts.
3:4|Darby|-- Because of the multitude of the fornications of the  well-favoured harlot, mistress of sorceries, that selleth  nations through her fornications, and families through her  sorceries,
3:4|KJV|Because of the multitude of the whoredoms of the wellfavoured harlot, the mistress of witchcrafts, that selleth nations through her whoredoms, and families through her witchcrafts.
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|都因那美貌的妓女，行邪術的主母，多有淫行，藉淫行出賣列國，用邪術出賣多族。
3:5|ASV|Behold, I am against thee, saith Jehovah of hosts, and I will uncover thy skirts upon thy face; and I will show the nations thy nakedness, and the kingdoms thy shame.
3:5|Darby|behold, I am against thee, saith Jehovah of hosts; and I  will uncover thy skirts upon thy face, and I will shew the  nations thy nakedness, and the kingdoms thy shame.
3:5|KJV|Behold, I am against thee, saith the LORD of hosts; and I will discover thy skirts upon thy face, and I will shew the nations thy nakedness, and the kingdoms thy shame.
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬軍之耶和華說，我與你為敵；我必揭起你的衣襟，蒙在你臉上，使列邦看見你的赤體，使列國看見你的羞恥。
3:6|ASV|And I will cast abominable filth upon thee, and make thee vile, and will set thee as a gazing-stock.
3:6|Darby|And I will cast abominable filth upon thee, and make thee  vile, and will set thee as a gazing stock.
3:6|KJV|And I will cast abominable filth upon thee, and make thee vile, and will set thee as a gazingstock.
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必將可憎污穢之物拋在你身上，使你顯為愚昧，為眾目所觀。
3:7|ASV|And it shall come to pass, that all they that look upon thee shall flee from thee, and say, Nineveh is laid waste: who will bemoan her? whence shall I seek comforters for thee?
3:7|Darby|And it shall come to pass, [that] all they that see thee  shall flee from thee, and shall say, Nineveh is laid waste! Who  will bemoan her? whence shall I seek comforters for thee?
3:7|KJV|And it shall come to pass, that all they that look upon thee shall flee from thee, and say, Nineveh is laid waste: who will bemoan her? whence shall I seek comforters for thee?
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡看見你的，都必逃跑離開你，說，尼尼微成了荒場。有誰為她悲傷呢？我何處尋得安慰你的人呢？
3:8|ASV|Art thou better than No-amon, that was situate among the rivers, that had the waters round about her; whose rampart was the sea, and her wall was of the sea?
3:8|Darby|Art thou better than No-Amon, that was situate among the  rivers, [that had] the waters round about her, whose rampart  was the sea, [and] of the sea was her wall?
3:8|KJV|Art thou better than populous No, that was situate among the rivers, that had the waters round about it, whose rampart was the sea, and her wall was from the sea?
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你豈比挪亞們強麼？挪亞們坐落在眾河渠之間，周圍有水；海作她的屏障，水作她的城牆。
3:9|ASV|Ethiopia and Egypt were her strength, and it was infinite; Put and Lubim were thy helpers.
3:9|Darby|Ethiopia was her strength, and Egypt, and it was infinite;  Phut and the Libyans were her helpers.
3:9|KJV|Ethiopia and Egypt were her strength, and it was infinite; Put and Lubim were thy helpers.
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|古實和埃及是她的力量，無窮無盡；弗人和路比族是她的幫手。
3:10|ASV|Yet was she carried away, she went into captivity; her young children also were dashed in pieces at the head of all the streets; and they cast lots for her honorable men, and all her great men were bound in chains.
3:10|Darby|She too was carried away, she went into captivity: her  infants also were dashed in pieces, at the top of all the  streets; and they cast lots for her honourable men, and all her  great men were bound with chains.
3:10|KJV|Yet was she carried away, she went into captivity: her young children also were dashed in pieces at the top of all the streets: and they cast lots for her honourable men, and all her great men were bound in chains.
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但她還是被遷徙，被擄去；她的嬰孩在各街頭也被摔死；人為她的尊貴人拈鬮；她所有的尊大者都被鍊子鎖著。
3:11|ASV|Thou also shalt be drunken; thou shalt be hid; thou also shalt seek a stronghold because of the enemy.
3:11|Darby|Thou also shalt be drunken: thou shalt be hid; thou also  shalt seek a refuge from the enemy.
3:11|KJV|Thou also shalt be drunken: thou shalt be hid, thou also shalt seek strength because of the enemy.
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你也必喝醉，必被隱藏；並因仇敵的緣故尋求保障。
3:12|ASV|All thy fortresses shall be like fig-trees with the first-ripe figs: if they be shaken, they fall into the mouth of the eater.
3:12|Darby|All thy strongholds are [like] fig-trees with the  first-ripe figs: if they be shaken, they even fall into the  mouth of the eater.
3:12|KJV|All thy strong holds shall be like fig trees with the firstripe figs: if they be shaken, they shall even fall into the mouth of the eater.
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你一切保障必像無花果樹上初熟的無花果；若一搖撼，就落在想喫之人的口中。
3:13|ASV|Behold, thy people in the midst of thee are women; the gates of thy land are set wide open unto thine enemies: the fire hath devoured thy bars.
3:13|Darby|Behold, thy people in the midst of thee are [as] women: the  gates of thy land are set wide open unto thine enemies; the  fire devoureth thy bars.
3:13|KJV|Behold, thy people in the midst of thee are women: the gates of thy land shall be set wide open unto thine enemies: the fire shall devour thy bars.
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|看哪，在你中間的人民，如同婦女；你國土的關口，向仇敵敞開；你的門閂，被火焚燒。
3:14|ASV|Draw thee water for the siege; strengthen thy fortresses; go into the clay, and tread the mortar; make strong the brickkiln.
3:14|Darby|Draw thee water for the siege, strengthen thy fortresses;  go into the clay, and tread the mortar, make strong the  brick-kiln.
3:14|KJV|Draw thee waters for the siege, fortify thy strong holds: go into clay, and tread the morter, make strong the brickkiln.
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要為自己打水，豫備受困！鞏固你的保障！踹土和泥！豫備磚窯！
3:15|ASV|There shall the fire devour thee; the sword shall cut thee off; it shall devour thee like the canker-worm: make thyself many as the canker-worm; make thyself many as the locust.
3:15|Darby|There shall the fire devour thee; the sword shall cut thee  off; it shall devour thee like the cankerworm. Make thyself  many as the cankerworm, make thyself many as the locust.
3:15|KJV|There shall the fire devour thee; the sword shall cut thee off, it shall eat thee up like the cankerworm: make thyself many as the cankerworm, make thyself many as the locusts.
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在那堣鶗窒N滅你；刀必除滅你，吞喫你如同蝗蟲。任你加增人數如蝗蟲，加增人數多如蝗蟲罷。
3:16|ASV|Thou hast multiplied thy merchants above the stars of heaven: the canker-worm ravageth, and fleeth away.
3:16|Darby|Thou hast multiplied thy merchants more than the stars of  the heavens; the cankerworm spreadeth himself out and flieth  away.
3:16|KJV|Thou hast multiplied thy merchants above the stars of heaven: the cankerworm spoileth, and fleeth away.
3:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你增添商賈，多過天上的星；蝗蟲喫盡就飛去。
3:17|ASV|Thy princes are as the locusts, and thy marshals as the swarms of grasshoppers, which encamp in the hedges in the cold day, but when the sun ariseth they flee away, and their place is not known where they are.
3:17|Darby|Thy chosen men are as the locusts, and thy captains as  swarms of grasshoppers, which camp in the hedges in the cold  day: when the sun ariseth they flee away, and their place is  not known where they are.
3:17|KJV|Thy crowned are as the locusts, and thy captains as the great grasshoppers, which camp in the hedges in the cold day, but when the sun ariseth they flee away, and their place is not known where they are.
3:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你的首領多如蝗蟲，你的軍長彷彿成群的蝗蟲，天涼的時候，齊落在籬笆上，日頭一出便都飛去，不知道落在何處。
3:18|ASV|Thy shepherds slumber, O king of Assyria; thy nobles are at rest; thy people are scattered upon the mountains, and there is none to gather them.
3:18|Darby|Thy shepherds slumber, O king of Assyria; thy nobles lie  still; thy people are scattered upon the mountains, and no man  gathereth them.
3:18|KJV|Thy shepherds slumber, O king of Assyria: thy nobles shall dwell in the dust: thy people is scattered upon the mountains, and no man gathereth them.
3:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞述王阿，你的牧人打盹，你的貴冑安歇；你的人民散在山間，無人招聚。
3:19<version name="ASV">There is no assuaging of thy hurt: thy wound is grievous: all that hear the report of thee clap their hands over thee; for upon whom hath not thy wickedness passed continually? </p><p /><br /></version>
3:19<version name="Darby">There is no healing of thy breach; thy wound is grievous;  all that hear the report of thee clap the hands over thee; for  upon whom hath not thy wickedness passed continually? </p><p /><br /></version>
3:19<version name="KJV">There is no healing of thy bruise; thy wound is grievous: all that hear the bruit of thee shall clap the hands over thee: for upon whom hath not thy wickedness passed continually?</p><p /><br /></version>
3:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你的損傷無法醫治，你的創傷極其嚴重。凡聽見你消息的，必都向你拍掌；因為你所行的惡，誰沒有時常遭遇呢？
