1:1|ASV|The words of Nehemiah the son of Hacaliah. Now it came to pass in the month Chislev, in the twentieth year, as I was in Shushan the palace,
1:1|Darby|The words of Nehemiah the son of Hachaliah. And it came to  pass in the month Chislev, in the twentieth year, as I was in  Shushan the fortress,
1:1|KJV|The words of Nehemiah the son of Hachaliah. And it came to pass in the month Chisleu, in the twentieth year, as I was in Shushan the palace,
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈迦利亞的兒子尼希米的言語如下：
1:2|ASV|that Hanani, one of my brethren, came, he and certain men out of Judah; and I asked them concerning the Jews that had escaped, that were left of the captivity, and concerning Jerusalem.
1:2|Darby|that Hanani, one of my brethren, came, he and [certain] men  of Judah. And I asked them concerning the Jews that had  escaped, who were left of the captivity, and concerning  Jerusalem.
1:2|KJV|That Hanani, one of my brethren, came, he and certain men of Judah; and I asked them concerning the Jews that had escaped, which were left of the captivity, and concerning Jerusalem.
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時，有我一個弟兄哈拿尼，同著幾個人從猶大來。我問他們那些被擄歸回、剩下逃脫的猶大人和耶路撒冷的光景。
1:3|ASV|And they said unto me, The remnant that are left of the captivity there in the province are in great affliction and reproach: the wall of Jerusalem also is broken down, and the gates thereof are burned with fire.
1:3|Darby|And they said to me, Those who remain, that are left of the  captivity there in the province, are in great affliction and  reproach; and the wall of Jerusalem is in ruins, and its gates  are burned with fire.
1:3|KJV|And they said unto me, The remnant that are left of the captivity there in the province are in great affliction and reproach: the wall of Jerusalem also is broken down, and the gates thereof are burned with fire.
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們對我說，那些被擄歸回剩下的餘民在猶大省遭大難，受凌辱；並且耶路撒冷的城牆被拆毀，城門被火焚燒。
1:4|ASV|And it came to pass, when I heard these words, that I sat down and wept, and mourned certain days; and I fasted and prayed before the God of heaven,
1:4|Darby|And it came to pass, when I heard these words, that I sat  and wept, and mourned for days, and fasted, and prayed before  the God of the heavens,
1:4|KJV|And it came to pass, when I heard these words, that I sat down and wept, and mourned certain days, and fasted, and prayed before the God of heaven,
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我聽見這些話，就坐下哭泣，悲哀幾日，在天上的神面前禁食禱告，
1:5|ASV|and said, I beseech thee, O Jehovah, the God of heaven, the great and terrible God, that keepeth covenant and lovingkindness with them that love him and keep his commandments:
1:5|Darby|and said, I beseech thee, Jehovah, God of the heavens, the  great and terrible ???’???’?????????God, that keepeth covenant and mercy for  them that love him and keep his commandments.
1:5|KJV|And said, I beseech thee, O LORD God of heaven, the great and terrible God, that keepeth covenant and mercy for them that love him and observe his commandments:
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|說，耶和華天上的神，大而可畏的神阿，你向愛你、守你誡命的人守約並施慈愛；
1:6|ASV|Let thine ear now be attentive, and thine eyes open, that thou mayest hearken unto the prayer of thy servant, which I pray before thee at this time, day and night, for the children of Israel thy servants while I confess the sins of the children of Israel, which we have sinned against thee. Yea, I and my father's house have sinned:
1:6|Darby|Let thine ear now be attentive, and thine eyes open, to hear  the prayer of thy servant, which I pray before thee at this  time, day and night, for the children of Israel thy servants,  confessing the sins of the children of Israel, which we have  sinned against thee: both I and my father's house have sinned.
1:6|KJV|Let thine ear now be attentive, and thine eyes open, that thou mayest hear the prayer of thy servant, which I pray before thee now, day and night, for the children of Israel thy servants, and confess the sins of the children of Israel, which we have sinned against thee: both I and my father's house have sinned.
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願你側耳睜眼，垂聽你僕人的禱告，就是我現今晝夜在你面前為你眾僕人以色列人所禱告的，承認我們以色列人向你所犯的罪。我與我父家都有罪了；
1:7|ASV|we have dealt very corruptly against thee, and have not kept the commandments, nor the statutes, nor the ordinances, which thou commandedst thy servant Moses.
1:7|Darby|We have acted very perversely against thee, and have not  kept the commandments, nor the statutes, nor the ordinances  that thou commandedst thy servant Moses.
1:7|KJV|We have dealt very corruptly against thee, and have not kept the commandments, nor the statutes, nor the judgments, which thou commandedst thy servant Moses.
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們向你所行的甚是敗壞，沒有遵守你吩咐你僕人摩西的誡命、律例和典章。
1:8|ASV|Remember, I beseech thee, the word that thou commandedst thy servant Moses, saying, If ye trespass, I will scatter you abroad among the peoples:
1:8|Darby|Remember, I beseech thee, the word that thou commandedst thy  servant Moses, saying, If ye act unfaithfully, I will scatter  you among the peoples;
1:8|KJV|Remember, I beseech thee, the word that thou commandedst thy servant Moses, saying, If ye transgress, I will scatter you abroad among the nations:
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|求你記念所吩咐你僕人摩西的話，說，你們若不忠信，我就把你們分散在諸民中；
1:9|ASV|but if ye return unto me, and keep my commandments and do them, though your outcasts were in the uttermost part of the heavens, yet will I gather them from thence, and will bring them unto the place that I have chosen, to cause my name to dwell there.
1:9|Darby|but if ye return to me, and keep my commandments and do  them, though there were of you cast out unto the uttermost part  of the heavens, yet will I gather them from thence, and will  bring them unto the place that I have chosen to set my name  there.
1:9|KJV|But if ye turn unto me, and keep my commandments, and do them; though there were of you cast out unto the uttermost part of the heaven, yet will I gather them from thence, and will bring them unto the place that I have chosen to set my name there.
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但你們若歸向我，謹守遵行我的誡命，你們被趕散的人，就是在天涯，我也必從那堭N他們招聚回來，帶到我所選擇給我名居住的地方。
1:10|ASV|Now these are thy servants and thy people, whom thou hast redeemed by thy great power, and by thy strong hand.
1:10|Darby|And they are thy servants and thy people, whom thou hast  redeemed by thy great power and by thy strong hand.
1:10|KJV|Now these are thy servants and thy people, whom thou hast redeemed by thy great power, and by thy strong hand.
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些都是你的僕人、你的百姓，就是你用你的大能，和你大力的手所救贖的。
1:11<version name="ASV">O Lord, I beseech thee, let now thine ear be attentive to the prayer of thy servant, and to the prayer of thy servants, who delight to fear thy name; and prosper, I pray thee, thy servant this day, and grant him mercy in the sight of this man. Now I was cupbearer to the king. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:11<version name="Darby">O Lord, I beseech thee, let now thine ear be attentive to  the prayer of thy servant, and to the prayer of thy servants  who delight to fear thy name; and prosper, I pray thee, thy  servant this day, and grant him mercy in the sight of this man.  Now I was the king's cupbearer. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:11<version name="KJV">O LORD, I beseech thee, let now thine ear be attentive to the prayer of thy servant, and to the prayer of thy servants, who desire to fear thy name: and prosper, I pray thee, thy servant this day, and grant him mercy in the sight of this man. For I was the king's cupbearer.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主阿，求你側耳聽你僕人的禱告，和喜愛敬畏你名眾僕人的禱告，使你僕人今日亨通，使他在王面前蒙憐恤。我是作王司酒的。
2:1|ASV|And it came to pass in the month Nisan, in the twentieth year of Artaxerxes the king, when wine was before him, that I took up the wine, and gave it unto the king. Now I had not been beforetime sad in his presence.
2:1|Darby|And it came to pass in the month Nisan, in the twentieth  year of Artaxerxes the king, [that] wine was before him, and I  took up the wine and gave it to the king. Now, I had never been  sad in his presence.
2:1|KJV|And it came to pass in the month Nisan, in the twentieth year of Artaxerxes the king, that wine was before him: and I took up the wine, and gave it unto the king. Now I had not been beforetime sad in his presence.
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞達薛西王二十年尼散月，有酒擺在王面前，我拿起酒來奉給王。我素來在他面前沒有愁容。
2:2|ASV|And the king said unto me, Why is thy countenance sad, seeing thou art not sick? this is nothing else but sorrow of heart. Then I was very sore afraid.
2:2|Darby|And the king said to me, Why is thy face sad, seeing thou  art not sick? this is nothing else but sadness of heart. And I  was very sore afraid.
2:2|KJV|Wherefore the king said unto me, Why is thy countenance sad, seeing thou art not sick? this is nothing else but sorrow of heart. Then I was very sore afraid,
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王對我說，你既沒有病，為甚麼面帶愁容呢？這不是別的，必是你心中愁煩。於是我甚懼怕。
2:3|ASV|And I said unto the king, Let the king live for ever: why should not my countenance be sad, when the city, the place of my fathers' sepulchres, lieth waste, and the gates thereof are consumed with fire?
2:3|Darby|And I said to the king, Let the king live for ever! Why  should not my countenance be sad, when the city, the place of  my fathers' sepulchres, lies waste, and its gates are consumed  with fire?
2:3|KJV|And said unto the king, Let the king live for ever: why should not my countenance be sad, when the city, the place of my fathers' sepulchres, lieth waste, and the gates thereof are consumed with fire?
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我對王說，願王萬歲！我列祖墳墓所在的那城荒涼，城門被火焚燒，我豈能面無愁容呢？
2:4|ASV|Then the king said unto me, For what dost thou make request? So I prayed to the God of heaven.
2:4|Darby|And the king said to me, For what dost thou make request? So  I prayed to the God of the heavens.
2:4|KJV|Then the king said unto me, For what dost thou make request? So I prayed to the God of heaven.
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王問我說，你要求甚麼？於是我禱告天上的神。
2:5|ASV|And I said unto the king, If it please the king, and if thy servant have found favor in thy sight, that thou wouldest send me unto Judah, unto the city of my fathers' sepulchres, that I may build it.
2:5|Darby|And I said to the king, If it please the king, and if thy  servant have found favour in thy sight, that thou wouldest send  me to Judah, to the city of my fathers' sepulchres, that I may  build it.
2:5|KJV|And I said unto the king, If it please the king, and if thy servant have found favour in thy sight, that thou wouldest send me unto Judah, unto the city of my fathers' sepulchres, that I may build it.
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我對王說，王若以為美，僕人若在王面前蒙恩惠，求王差遣我往猶大，到我列祖墳墓所在的城去，我好重新建造那城。
2:6|ASV|And the king said unto me (the queen also sitting by him,) For how long shall thy journey be? and when wilt thou return? So it pleased the king to send me; and I set him a time.
2:6|Darby|And the king said to me -- the queen also sitting by him, --  For how long shall thy journey be, and when wilt thou return?  And it pleased the king to send me; and I set him a time.
2:6|KJV|And the king said unto me, (the queen also sitting by him,) For how long shall thy journey be? and when wilt thou return? So it pleased the king to send me; and I set him a time.
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時王后坐在王的旁邊。王問我說，你去需時多久？幾時回來？王喜歡差遣我去，我也把日期告訴了王。
2:7|ASV|Moreover I said unto the king, If it please the king, let letters be given me to the governors beyond the River, that they may let me pass through till I come unto Judah;
2:7|Darby|And I said to the king, If it please the king, let letters  be given me to the governors beyond the river, that they may  set me forward till I come into Judah;
2:7|KJV|Moreover I said unto the king, If it please the king, let letters be given me to the governors beyond the river, that they may convey me over till I come into Judah;
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我又對王說，王若以為美，請賜我詔書，通知大河以西的諸省長准我經過，直到我抵達猶大；
2:8|ASV|and a letter unto Asaph the keeper of the king's forest, that he may give me timber to make beams for the gates of the castle which appertaineth to the house, and for the wall of the city, and for the house that I shall enter into. And the king granted me, according to the good hand of my God upon me.
2:8|Darby|and a letter to Asaph the keeper of the king's forest, that  he may give me timber to make beams for the gates of the palace  which [appertains] to the house, and for the wall of the city,  and for the house that I shall enter into. And the king granted  me, according to the good hand of my God upon me.
2:8|KJV|And a letter unto Asaph the keeper of the king's forest, that he may give me timber to make beams for the gates of the palace which appertained to the house, and for the wall of the city, and for the house that I shall enter into. And the king granted me, according to the good hand of my God upon me.
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又賜詔書，通知看守王園林的亞薩，使他給我木料，作屬殿營樓之門的橫梁，並供城牆和我要住的房屋使用。因我神美善的手幫助我，王就把我所求的賜給我。
2:9|ASV|Then I came to the governors beyond the River, and gave them the king's letters. Now the king had sent with me captains of the army and horsemen.
2:9|Darby|And I came to the governors beyond the river, and gave them  the king's letters. Now the king had sent captains of a force  and horsemen with me.
2:9|KJV|Then I came to the governors beyond the river, and gave them the king's letters. Now the king had sent captains of the army and horsemen with me.
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王派了軍長和馬兵護送我。我到了河西的諸省長那堙A將王的詔書交給他們。
2:10|ASV|And when Sanballat the Horonite, and Tobiah the servant, the Ammonite, heard of it, it grieved them exceedingly, for that there was come a man to seek the welfare of the children of Israel.
2:10|Darby|And when Sanballat the Horonite, and Tobijah the servant,  the Ammonite, heard [of it], it grieved them exceedingly that  there had come a man to seek the welfare of the children of  Israel.
2:10|KJV|When Sanballat the Horonite, and Tobiah the servant, the Ammonite, heard of it, it grieved them exceedingly that there was come a man to seek the welfare of the children of Israel.
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|和倫人參巴拉，並作臣僕的亞捫人多比雅，聽見有人來為以色列人求好處，就甚惱怒。
2:11|ASV|So I came to Jerusalem, and was there three days.
2:11|Darby|And I came to Jerusalem, and was there three days.
2:11|KJV|So I came to Jerusalem, and was there three days.
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我到了耶路撒冷，在那埵矰F三日。
2:12|ASV|And I arose in the night, I and some few men with me; neither told I any man what my God put into my heart to do for Jerusalem; neither was there any beast with me, save the beast that I rode upon.
2:12|Darby|And I arose in the night, I and some few men with me -- but  I told no man what my God had put in my heart to do for  Jerusalem -- and there was no beast with me, except the beast  that I rode upon.
2:12|KJV|And I arose in the night, I and some few men with me; neither told I any man what my God had put in my heart to do at Jerusalem: neither was there any beast with me, save the beast that I rode upon.
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我夜間起來，有幾個人也一同起來；但神使我心堸_意要為耶路撒冷作甚麼事，我並沒有告訴人。除了我騎的牲口以外，也沒有別的牲口在我那堙C
2:13|ASV|And I went out by night by the valley gate, even toward the jackal's well, and to the dung gate, and viewed the walls of Jerusalem, which were broken down, and the gates thereof were consumed with fire.
2:13|Darby|And I went out by night by the valley-gate, even toward the  jackal-fountain, and to the dung-gate; and I viewed the walls  of Jerusalem, which were in ruins, and its gates were consumed  with fire.
2:13|KJV|And I went out by night by the gate of the valley, even before the dragon well, and to the dung port, and viewed the walls of Jerusalem, which were broken down, and the gates thereof were consumed with fire.
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當夜我出了谷門，往野狗泉去，到了糞門，察看耶路撒冷的城牆，見城牆被拆毀，城門被火焚燒。
2:14|ASV|Then I went on to the fountain gate and to the king's pool: but there was no place for the beast that was under me to pass.
2:14|Darby|And I went on to the fountain-gate, and to the king's pool;  and there was no place for the beast under me to pass.
2:14|KJV|Then I went on to the gate of the fountain, and to the king's pool: but there was no place for the beast that was under me to pass.
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我又往前，到了泉門和王池，但所騎的牲口沒有地方過去。
2:15|ASV|Then went I up in the night by the brook, and viewed the wall; and I turned back, and entered by the valley gate, and so returned.
2:15|Darby|And I went up in the night through the valley, and viewed  the wall, and turned back, and entered by the valley-gate and  returned.
2:15|KJV|Then went I up in the night by the brook, and viewed the wall, and turned back, and entered by the gate of the valley, and so returned.
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是我在夜間沿溪而上，察看城牆，又轉身進入谷門，就回來了。
2:16|ASV|And the rulers knew not whither I went, or what I did; neither had I as yet told it to the Jews, nor to the priests, nor to the nobles, nor to the rulers, nor to the rest that did the work.
2:16|Darby|And the rulers did not know whither I went or what I did,  for I had not as yet told it to the Jews, nor to the priests,  nor to the nobles, nor to the rulers, nor to the rest that did  the work.
2:16|KJV|And the rulers knew not whither I went, or what I did; neither had I as yet told it to the Jews, nor to the priests, nor to the nobles, nor to the rulers, nor to the rest that did the work.
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我去過那堙A作了甚麼事，官長都不知道；我還沒有告訴猶大人、祭司、貴冑、官長、和其餘作工的人。
2:17|ASV|Then said I unto them, Ye see the evil case that we are in, how Jerusalem lieth waste, and the gates thereof are burned with fire: come, and let us build up the wall of Jerusalem, that we be no more a reproach.
2:17|Darby|And I said to them, Ye see the distress that we are in,  that Jerusalem lies waste, and its gates are burned with fire.  Come, and let us build up the wall of Jerusalem, that we be no  more a reproach.
2:17|KJV|Then said I unto them, Ye see the distress that we are in, how Jerusalem lieth waste, and the gates thereof are burned with fire: come, and let us build up the wall of Jerusalem, that we be no more a reproach.
2:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以後，我對他們說，我們所遭的禍患，耶路撒冷怎樣荒涼，城門被火焚燒，你們都看見了。來罷，我們重建耶路撒冷的城牆，免得再受凌辱。
2:18|ASV|And I told them of the hand of my God which was good upon me, as also of the king's words that he had spoken unto me. And they said, Let us rise up and build. So they strengthened their hands for the good work.
2:18|Darby|And I told them of the hand of my God which had been good  upon me; as also of the king's words which he had said unto me.  And they said, Let us rise up and build. And they strengthened  their hands for the good [work].
2:18|KJV|Then I told them of the hand of my God which was good upon me; as also the king's words that he had spoken unto me. And they said, Let us rise up and build. So they strengthened their hands for this good work.
2:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我告訴他們，我神美善的手怎樣幫助我，也把王對我所說的話告訴他們。他們就說，我們起來建造罷；於是他們奮勇作這善工。
2:19|ASV|But when Sanballat the Horonite, and Tobiah the servant, the Ammonite, and Geshem the Arabian, heard it, they laughed us to scorn, and despised us, and said, What is this thing that ye do? will ye rebel against the king?
2:19|Darby|And Sanballat the Horonite, and Tobijah the servant, the  Ammonite, and Geshem the Arabian, heard it; and they mocked us  and despised us, and said, What is this thing which ye do? will  ye rebel against the king?
2:19|KJV|But when Sanballat the Horonite, and Tobiah the servant, the Ammonite, and Geshem the Arabian, heard it, they laughed us to scorn, and despised us, and said, What is this thing that ye do? will ye rebel against the king?
2:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但和倫人參巴拉、作臣僕的亞捫人多比雅、和亞拉伯人基善聽見，就嗤笑我們，藐視我們，說，你們作的是甚麼事？你們要背叛王麼？
2:20<version name="ASV">Then answered I them, and said unto them, The God of heaven, he will prosper us; therefore we his servants will arise and build: but ye have no portion, nor right, nor memorial, in Jerusalem. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:20<version name="Darby">And I answered them, and said to them, The God of the  heavens, he will prosper us, and we his servants will arise and  build; but ye have no portion, nor right, nor memorial in  Jerusalem. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:20<version name="KJV">Then answered I them, and said unto them, The God of heaven, he will prosper us; therefore we his servants will arise and build: but ye have no portion, nor right, nor memorial, in Jerusalem.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我回答他們說，天上的神必親自使我們亨通；所以我們作祂僕人的，要起來建造。你們卻在耶路撒冷無分、無權、無記念。
3:1|ASV|Then Eliashib the high priest rose up with his brethren the priests, and they builded the sheep gate; they sanctified it, and set up the doors of it; even unto the tower of Hammeah they sanctified it, unto the tower of Hananel.
3:1|Darby|And Eliashib the high priest rose up with his brethren the  priests, and they built the sheep-gate. They hallowed it, and  set up its doors; and they hallowed it even to the tower of  Meah, to the tower of Hananeel.
3:1|KJV|Then Eliashib the high priest rose up with his brethren the priests, and they builded the sheep gate; they sanctified it, and set up the doors of it; even unto the tower of Meah they sanctified it, unto the tower of Hananeel.
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時，大祭司以利亞實和他的弟兄眾祭司起來建造羊門，將這門分別為聖，安立門扇；又築城牆到哈米亞樓，將這樓分別為聖，又築城牆到哈楠業樓。
3:2|ASV|And next unto him builded the men of Jericho. And next to them builded Zaccur the son of Imri.
3:2|Darby|And next to them built the men of Jericho. And next to them  built Zaccur the son of Imri.
3:2|KJV|And next unto him builded the men of Jericho. And next to them builded Zaccur the son of Imri.
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其旁是耶利哥人建造。其旁是音利的兒子撒刻建造。
3:3|ASV|And the fish gate did the sons of Hassenaah build; they laid the beams thereof, and set up the doors thereof, the bolts thereof, and the bars thereof.
3:3|Darby|And the fish-gate did the sons of Senaah build: they laid  its beams, and set up its doors, its locks and its bars.
3:3|KJV|But the fish gate did the sons of Hassenaah build, who also laid the beams thereof, and set up the doors thereof, the locks thereof, and the bars thereof.
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈西拿的子孫建造魚門：架設橫梁，安門扇、門插和門閂。
3:4|ASV|And next unto them repaired Meremoth the son of Uriah, the son of Hakkoz. And next unto them repaired Meshullam the son of Berechiah, the son of Meshezabel. And next unto them repaired Zadok the son of Baana.
3:4|Darby|And next to them repaired Meremoth the son of Urijah, the  son of Koz. And next to them repaired Meshullam the son of  Berechiah, the son of Meshezabeel. And next to them repaired  Zadok the son of Baana.
3:4|KJV|And next unto them repaired Meremoth the son of Urijah, the son of Koz. And next unto them repaired Meshullam the son of Berechiah, the son of Meshezabeel. And next unto them repaired Zadok the son of Baana.
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其旁是哈哥斯的孫子，烏利亞的兒子米利末修造。其旁是米示薩別的孫子，比利迦的兒子米書蘭修造。其旁是巴拿的兒子撒督修造。
3:5|ASV|And next unto them the Tekoites repaired; but their nobles put not their necks to the work of their lord.
3:5|Darby|And next to them the Tekoites repaired; but their nobles put  not their necks to the work of their Lord.
3:5|KJV|And next unto them the Tekoites repaired; but their nobles put not their necks to the work of their LORD.
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其旁是提哥亞人修造；但是他們的貴冑不肯負軛服事他們的主。
3:6|ASV|And the old gate repaired Joiada the son of Paseah and Meshullam the son of Besodeiah; they laid the beams thereof, and set up the doors thereof, and the bolts thereof, and the bars thereof.
3:6|Darby|And the gate of the old [wall] repaired Jehoiada the son of  Paseah, and Meshullam the son of Besodiah; they laid its beams,  and set up its doors, and its locks, and its bars.
3:6|KJV|Moreover the old gate repaired Jehoiada the son of Paseah, and Meshullam the son of Besodeiah; they laid the beams thereof, and set up the doors thereof, and the locks thereof, and the bars thereof.
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|巴西亞的兒子耶何耶大與比所玳的兒子米書蘭修造古門：架設橫梁，安門扇、門插和門閂。
3:7|ASV|And next unto them repaired Melatiah the Gibeonite, and Jadon the Meronothite, the men of Gibeon, and of Mizpah, that appertained to the throne of the governor beyond the River.
3:7|Darby|And next to them repaired Melatiah the Gibeonite, and Jadon  the Meronothite, the men of Gibeon and of Mizpah, to the seat  of the governor on this side the river.
3:7|KJV|And next unto them repaired Melatiah the Gibeonite, and Jadon the Meronothite, the men of Gibeon, and of Mizpah, unto the throne of the governor on this side the river.
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其旁是基遍人米拉提、米倫人雅頓，與基遍人和米斯巴人一同修造，直到河西總督府。
3:8|ASV|Next unto him repaired Uzziel the son of Harhaiah, goldsmiths. And next unto him repaired Hananiah one of the perfumers, and they fortified Jerusalem even unto the broad wall.
3:8|Darby|Next to them repaired Uzziel the son of Harhaiah, of the  goldsmiths; and next to him repaired Hananiah of the perfumers,  and they left Jerusalem [in its state] as far as the broad  wall.
3:8|KJV|Next unto him repaired Uzziel the son of Harhaiah, of the goldsmiths. Next unto him also repaired Hananiah the son of one of the apothecaries, and they fortified Jerusalem unto the broad wall.
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其旁是金匠哈海雅的兒子烏薛修造。其旁是調製香品者哈拿尼雅修造。這些人加固耶路撒冷的城牆，直到寬牆。
3:9|ASV|And next unto them repaired Rephaiah the son of Hur, the ruler of half the district of Jerusalem.
3:9|Darby|And next to them repaired Rephaiah the son of Hur, the ruler  of the half part of Jerusalem.
3:9|KJV|And next unto them repaired Rephaiah the son of Hur, the ruler of the half part of Jerusalem.
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其旁是管理耶路撒冷一半地區，戶珥的兒子利法雅修造。
3:10|ASV|And next unto them repaired Jedaiah the son of Harumaph, over against his house. And next unto him repaired Hattush the son of Hashabneiah.
3:10|Darby|And next to them repaired Jedaiah the son of Harumaph, even  over against his house. And next to him repaired Hattush the  son of Hashabniah.
3:10|KJV|And next unto them repaired Jedaiah the son of Harumaph, even over against his house. And next unto him repaired Hattush the son of Hashabniah.
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其旁是哈路抹的兒子耶大雅對著自己的房屋修造。其旁是哈沙尼的兒子哈突修造。
3:11|ASV|Malchijah the son of Harim, and Hasshub the son of Pahath-moab, repaired another portion, and the tower of the furnaces.
3:11|Darby|Malchijah the son of Harim and Hasshub the son of  Pahath-Moab repaired a second piece, and the tower of the  furnaces.
3:11|KJV|Malchijah the son of Harim, and Hashub the son of Pahathmoab, repaired the other piece, and the tower of the furnaces.
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈琳的兒子瑪基雅和巴哈摩押的兒子哈述修造另一段，包括爐樓。
3:12|ASV|And next unto him repaired Shallum the son of Hallohesh, the ruler of half the district of Jerusalem, he and his daughters.
3:12|Darby|And next to them repaired Shallum the son of Hallohesh, the  ruler of the half part of Jerusalem, he and his daughters.
3:12|KJV|And next unto him repaired Shallum the son of Halohesh, the ruler of the half part of Jerusalem, he and his daughters.
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其旁是管理耶路撒冷另一半地區，哈羅黑的兒子沙龍和他的女兒們修造。
3:13|ASV|The valley gate repaired Hanun, and the inhabitants of Zanoah; they built it, and set up the doors thereof, the bolts thereof, and the bars thereof, and a thousand cubits of the wall unto the dung gate.
3:13|Darby|The valley-gate repaired Hanun, and the inhabitants of  Zanoah; they built it, and set up its doors, its locks and its  bars, and a thousand cubits of the wall as far as the  dung-gate.
3:13|KJV|The valley gate repaired Hanun, and the inhabitants of Zanoah; they built it, and set up the doors thereof, the locks thereof, and the bars thereof, and a thousand cubits on the wall unto the dung gate.
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈嫩和撒挪亞的居民修造谷門：重建那門，安門扇、門插和門閂，又建築城牆一千肘，直到糞門。
3:14|ASV|And the dung gate repaired Malchijah the son of Rechab, the ruler of the district of Beth-haccherem; he built it, and set up the doors thereof, the bolts thereof, and the bars thereof.
3:14|Darby|And the dung-gate repaired Malchijah the son of Rechab, the  chief of the district of Beth-haccerem; he built it, and set up  its doors, its locks and its bars.
3:14|KJV|But the dung gate repaired Malchiah the son of Rechab, the ruler of part of Bethhaccerem; he built it, and set up the doors thereof, the locks thereof, and the bars thereof.
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|管理伯哈基琳區，利甲的兒子瑪基雅修造糞門：重建那門，安門扇、門插和門閂。
3:15|ASV|And the fountain gate repaired Shallun the son of Colhozeh, the ruler of the district of Mizpah; he built it, and covered it, and set up the doors thereof, the bolts thereof, and the bars thereof, and the wall of the pool of Shelah by the king's garden, even unto the stairs that go down from the city of David.
3:15|Darby|And the fountain-gate repaired Shallun the son of Colhozeh,  the chief of the district of Mizpah; he built it, and covered  it, and set up its doors, its locks and its bars, and the wall  of the pool of Shelah by the king's garden, and to the stairs  that go down from the city of David.
3:15|KJV|But the gate of the fountain repaired Shallun the son of Colhozeh, the ruler of part of Mizpah; he built it, and covered it, and set up the doors thereof, the locks thereof, and the bars thereof, and the wall of the pool of Siloah by the king's garden, and unto the stairs that go down from the city of David.
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|管理米斯巴區，各荷西的兒子沙崙修造泉門：重建那門，蓋門頂，安門扇、門插和門閂，又修造靠近王園西羅亞池的牆垣，直到那從大衛城下來的臺階。
3:16|ASV|After him repaired Nehemiah the son of Azbuk, the ruler of half the district of Beth-zur, unto the place over against the sepulchres of David, and unto the pool that was made, and unto the house of the mighty men.
3:16|Darby|After him repaired Nehemiah the son of Azbuk, the chief of  the half district of Beth-zur, even over against the sepulchres  of David, and to the pool that was made, and to the house of  the mighty [men].
3:16|KJV|After him repaired Nehemiah the son of Azbuk, the ruler of the half part of Bethzur, unto the place over against the sepulchres of David, and to the pool that was made, and unto the house of the mighty.
3:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其後是管理伯夙一半地區，押卜的兒子尼希米修造，從大衛墳地的對面，直到挖造的池子，並勇士的房屋。
3:17|ASV|After him repaired the Levites, Rehum the son of Bani. Next unto him repaired Hashabiah, the ruler of half the district of Keilah, for his district.
3:17|Darby|After him repaired the Levites, Rehum the son of Bani. Next  to him repaired Hashabiah, the chief of the half district of  Keilah, for his district.
3:17|KJV|After him repaired the Levites, Rehum the son of Bani. Next unto him repaired Hashabiah, the ruler of the half part of Keilah, in his part.
3:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其後是利未人在巴尼的兒子利宏手下修造。其旁是管理基伊拉一半地區的哈沙比雅，為他本區修造。
3:18|ASV|After him repaired their brethren, Bavvai the son of Henadad, the ruler of half the district of Keilah.
3:18|Darby|After him repaired their brethren, Bavvai the son of  Henadad, the chief of the half district of Keilah.
3:18|KJV|After him repaired their brethren, Bavai the son of Henadad, the ruler of the half part of Keilah.
3:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其後是利未人的弟兄，在管理基伊拉另一半地區，希拿達的兒子巴瓦伊手下修造。
3:19|ASV|And next to him repaired Ezer the son of Jeshua, the ruler of Mizpah, another portion, over against the ascent to the armory at the turning of the wall.
3:19|Darby|And next to him repaired Ezer the son of Jeshua, the ruler  of Mizpah, a second piece over against the going up to the  armoury at the angle.
3:19|KJV|And next to him repaired Ezer the son of Jeshua, the ruler of Mizpah, another piece over against the going up to the armoury at the turning of the wall.
3:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其旁是管理米斯巴、耶書亞的兒子以謝修造另一段，對著軍械庫的上坡、城牆轉彎之處。
3:20|ASV|After him Baruch the son of Zabbai earnestly repaired another portion, from the turning of the wall unto the door of the house of Eliashib the high priest.
3:20|Darby|After him Baruch the son of Zabbai earnestly repaired  another piece, from the angle to the entry of the house of  Eliashib the high priest.
3:20|KJV|After him Baruch the son of Zabbai earnestly repaired the other piece, from the turning of the wall unto the door of the house of Eliashib the high priest.
3:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其後是薩拜的兒子巴錄，竭力修造另一段，從城牆轉彎，直到大祭司以利亞實住宅的門口。
3:21|ASV|After him repaired Meremoth the son of Uriah the son of Hakkoz another portion, from the door of the house of Eliashib even to the end of the house of Eliashib.
3:21|Darby|After him repaired Meremoth the son of Urijah, the son of  Koz, another piece, from the door of the house of Eliashib as  far as the end of the house of Eliashib.
3:21|KJV|After him repaired Meremoth the son of Urijah the son of Koz another piece, from the door of the house of Eliashib even to the end of the house of Eliashib.
3:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其後是哈哥斯的孫子，烏利亞的兒子米利末修造另一段，從以利亞實住宅的門口，直到以利亞實住宅的盡頭。
3:22|ASV|And after him repaired the priests, the men of the Plain.
3:22|Darby|And after him repaired the priests, the men of the plain  [of Jordan].
3:22|KJV|And after him repaired the priests, the men of the plain.
3:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其後是住平原的祭司修造。
3:23|ASV|After them repaired Benjamin and Hasshub over against their house. After them repaired Azariah the son of Maaseiah the son of Ananiah beside his own house.
3:23|Darby|After them repaired Benjamin and Hasshub over against their  house. After them repaired Azariah the son of Maaseiah, the son  of Ananiah, by his house.
3:23|KJV|After him repaired Benjamin and Hashub over against their house. After him repaired Azariah the son of Maaseiah the son of Ananiah by his house.
3:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其後是便雅憫與哈述對著自己的房屋修造。其後是亞難尼的孫子，瑪西雅的兒子亞撒利雅，在自己房屋的旁邊修造。
3:24|ASV|After him repaired Binnui the son of Henadad another portion, from the house of Azariah unto the turning of the wall, and unto the corner.
3:24|Darby|After him repaired Binnui the son of Henadad another piece,  from the house of Azariah to the angle, as far as the corner.
3:24|KJV|After him repaired Binnui the son of Henadad another piece, from the house of Azariah unto the turning of the wall, even unto the corner.
3:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其後是希拿達的兒子賓內修造另一段，從亞撒利雅的房屋直到城牆轉彎，又到城角。
3:25|ASV|Palal the son of Uzai repaired over against the turning of the wall, and the tower that standeth out from the upper house of the king, which is by the court of the guard. After him Pedaiah the son of Parosh repaired.
3:25|Darby|Palal the son of Uzai, over against the angle, and the high  tower that lies out from the king's house, which was by the  court of the prison. After him, Pedaiah the son of Parosh.
3:25|KJV|Palal the son of Uzai, over against the turning of the wall, and the tower which lieth out from the king's high house, that was by the court of the prison. After him Pedaiah the son of Parosh.
3:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|烏賽的兒子巴拉對著城牆的轉彎修造，又修造王上宮凸出來的城樓，靠近護衛兵院的那一段。其後是巴錄的兒子毘大雅修造。
3:26|ASV|(Now the Nethinim dwelt in Ophel, unto the place over against the water gate toward the east, and the tower that standeth out.)
3:26|Darby|(Now the Nethinim dwelt in Ophel, even over against the  water-gate toward the east, and the tower which lies out.)
3:26|KJV|Moreover the Nethinims dwelt in Ophel, unto the place over against the water gate toward the east, and the tower that lieth out.
3:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|（殿役住在俄斐勒，直到朝東水門的對面和凸出來的城樓。）
3:27|ASV|After him the Tekoites repaired another portion, over against the great tower that standeth out, and unto the wall of Ophel.
3:27|Darby|After him the Tekoites repaired a second piece, over  against the great tower which lies out, as far as the wall of  Ophel.
3:27|KJV|After them the Tekoites repaired another piece, over against the great tower that lieth out, even unto the wall of Ophel.
3:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其後是提哥亞人修造另一段，對著那凸出來的大樓，直到俄斐勒的牆。
3:28|ASV|Above the horse gate repaired the priests, every one over against his own house.
3:28|Darby|From above the horse-gate repaired the priests, every one  over against his house.
3:28|KJV|From above the horse gate repaired the priests, every one over against his house.
3:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|從馬門往上，眾祭司各對著自己的房屋修造。
3:29|ASV|After them repaired Zadok the son of Immer over against his own house. And after him repaired Shemaiah the son of Shecaniah, the keeper of the east gate.
3:29|Darby|After them repaired Zadok the son of Immer over against his  house. And after him repaired also Shemaiah the son of  Shechaniah, the keeper of the east gate.
3:29|KJV|After them repaired Zadok the son of Immer over against his house. After him repaired also Shemaiah the son of Shechaniah, the keeper of the east gate.
3:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其後是音麥的兒子撒督對著自己的房屋修造。其後是守東門、示迦尼的兒子示瑪雅修造。
3:30|ASV|After him repaired Hananiah the son of Shelemiah, and Hanun the sixth son of Zalaph, another portion. After him repaired Meshullam the son of Berechiah over against his chamber.
3:30|Darby|After him repaired Hananiah the son of Shelemiah, and Hanun  the sixth son of Zalaph, a second piece. After them repaired  Meshullam the son of Berechiah over against his chamber.
3:30|KJV|After him repaired Hananiah the son of Shelemiah, and Hanun the sixth son of Zalaph, another piece. After him repaired Meshullam the son of Berechiah over against his chamber.
3:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其後是示利米雅的兒子哈拿尼雅，和薩拉的第六子哈嫩，修造另一段。其後是比利迦的兒子米書蘭，對著自己的住所修造。
3:31|ASV|After him repaired Malchijah one of the goldsmiths unto the house of the Nethinim, and of the merchants, over against the gate of Hammiphkad, and to the ascent of the corner.
3:31|Darby|After him repaired Malchijah of the goldsmiths to the place  of the Nethinim and of the dealers, over against the gate  Miphkad, and to the ascent of the corner.
3:31|KJV|After him repaired Malchiah the goldsmith's son unto the place of the Nethinims, and of the merchants, over against the gate Miphkad, and to the going up of the corner.
3:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其後是金匠瑪基雅修造到殿役和商人的房屋，對著點閱門，直到城的角樓。
3:32<version name="ASV">And between the ascent of the corner and the sheep gate repaired the goldsmiths and the merchants. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:32<version name="Darby">And between the ascent of the corner and the sheep-gate  repaired the goldsmiths and the dealers. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:32<version name="KJV">And between the going up of the corner unto the sheep gate repaired the goldsmiths and the merchants.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|金匠與商人在城的角樓和羊門中間修造。
4:1|ASV|But it came to pass that, when Sanballat heard that we were building the wall, he was wroth, and took great indignation, and mocked the Jews.
4:1|Darby|And it came to pass that when Sanballat heard that we built  the wall, he was angry and very indignant, and mocked the Jews.
4:1|KJV|But it came to pass, that when Sanballat heard that we builded the wall, he was wroth, and took great indignation, and mocked the Jews.
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|參巴拉聽見我們建造城牆就發怒，大大惱恨，嗤笑猶大人，
4:2|ASV|And he spake before his brethren and the army of Samaria, and said, What are these feeble Jews doing? will they fortify themselves? will they sacrifice? will they make an end in a day? will they revive the stones out of the heaps of rubbish, seeing they are burned?
4:2|Darby|And he spoke before his brethren and the army of Samaria,  and said, What do these feeble Jews? shall they be permitted to  go on? Will they offer sacrifices? Will they finish in a day?  Will they revive the stones out of the heaps of rubbish, when  they are burned?
4:2|KJV|And he spake before his brethren and the army of Samaria, and said, What do these feeble Jews? will they fortify themselves? will they sacrifice? will they make an end in a day? will they revive the stones out of the heaps of the rubbish which are burned?
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|對他弟兄和撒瑪利亞的軍兵說，這些軟弱的猶大人作甚麼呢？他們要為自己修築城牆麼？要獻祭麼？要一日完成麼？要從土堆堮野X火燒的石頭再立牆麼？
4:3|ASV|Now Tobiah the Ammonite was by him, and he said, Even that which they are building, if a fox go up, he shall break down their stone wall.
4:3|Darby|And Tobijah the Ammonite was by him, and he said, Even that  which they build, if a fox went up, it would break down their  stone wall. --
4:3|KJV|Now Tobiah the Ammonite was by him, and he said, Even that which they build, if a fox go up, he shall even break down their stone wall.
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞捫人多比雅站在旁邊，說，他們所建造的石牆，就是狐狸上去也必踩出洞來。
4:4|ASV|Hear, O our God; for we are despised: and turn back their reproach upon their own head, and give them up for a spoil in a land of captivity;
4:4|Darby|Hear, our God, for we are despised, and turn their reproach  upon their own head, and give them for a prey in a land of  captivity!
4:4|KJV|Hear, O our God; for we are despised: and turn their reproach upon their own head, and give them for a prey in the land of captivity:
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們的神阿，求你垂聽，因為我們被藐視；求你使他們的凌辱歸在他們頭上，使他們在被擄到之地成為掠物。
4:5|ASV|and cover not their iniquity, and let not their sin be blotted out from before thee; for they have provoked thee to anger before the builders.
4:5|Darby|And cover not their iniquity, and let not their sin be  blotted out from before thee; for they have provoked the  builders.
4:5|KJV|And cover not their iniquity, and let not their sin be blotted out from before thee: for they have provoked thee to anger before the builders.
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不要遮掩他們的罪孽，不要使他們的罪從你面前塗抹，因為他們在建造的人面前惹動你的怒氣。
4:6|ASV|So we built the wall; and all the wall was joined together unto half  the height thereof: for the people had a mind to work.
4:6|Darby|But we built the wall; and all the wall was joined together  to the half thereof; for the people had a mind to work.
4:6|KJV|So built we the wall; and all the wall was joined together unto the half thereof: for the people had a mind to work.
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我們建造城牆，城牆就都連接起來，高至一半，因為百姓用心作工。
4:7|ASV|But it came to pass that, when Sanballat, and Tobiah, and the Arabians, and the Ammonites, and the Ashdodites, heard that the repairing of the walls of Jerusalem went forward, and that the breaches began to be stopped, then they were very wroth;
4:7|Darby|And it came to pass, when Sanballat, and Tobijah, and the  Arabians, and the Ammonites, and the Ashdodites heard that the  walls of Jerusalem were being repaired, that the breaches began  to be stopped, then they were very wroth,
4:7|KJV|But it came to pass, that when Sanballat, and Tobiah, and the Arabians, and the Ammonites, and the Ashdodites, heard that the walls of Jerusalem were made up, and that the breaches began to be stopped, then they were very wroth,
4:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|參巴拉、多比雅、亞拉伯人、亞捫人、亞實突人，聽見耶路撒冷城牆修復的工作有進展，破裂的地方開始堵住，就甚發怒。
4:8|ASV|and they conspired all of them together to come and fight against Jerusalem, and to cause confusion therein.
4:8|Darby|and conspired all of them together to come to fight against  Jerusalem, and to hinder it.
4:8|KJV|And conspired all of them together to come and to fight against Jerusalem, and to hinder it.
4:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們同謀要來攻擊耶路撒冷，使城內擾亂。
4:9|ASV|But we made our prayer unto our God, and set a watch against them day and night, because of them.
4:9|Darby|Then we prayed to our God, and set a watch against them day  and night, because of them.
4:9|KJV|Nevertheless we made our prayer unto our God, and set a watch against them day and night, because of them.
4:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而，我們禱告我們的神，又因他們的緣故，設立看守的人，晝夜防備。
4:10|ASV|And Judah said, The strength of the bearers of burdens is decayed, and there is much rubbish; so that we are not able to build the wall.
4:10|Darby|And Judah said, The strength of the bearers of burdens  faileth, and there is much rubbish; so that we are not able to  build at the wall.
4:10|KJV|And Judah said, The strength of the bearers of burdens is decayed, and there is much rubbish; so that we are not able to build the wall.
4:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|猶大人說，灰土尚多，扛抬的人力氣已經衰敗，所以我們不能建造城牆。
4:11|ASV|And our adversaries said, They shall not know, neither see, till we come into the midst of them, and slay them, and cause the work to cease.
4:11|Darby|And our adversaries said, They shall not know, neither see,  till we come into the midst of them and kill them, and put an  end to the work.
4:11|KJV|And our adversaries said, They shall not know, neither see, till we come in the midst among them, and slay them, and cause the work to cease.
4:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們的敵人且說，趁他們還不知道，還看不見，我們進入他們中間殺他們，使工作止住。
4:12|ASV|And it came to pass that, when the Jews that dwelt by them came, they said unto us ten times from all places, Ye must return unto us.
4:12|Darby|And it came to pass that when the Jews that dwelt by them  came and told us so ten times, from all the places whence they  returned to us,
4:12|KJV|And it came to pass, that when the Jews which dwelt by them came, they said unto us ten times, From all places whence ye shall return unto us they will be upon you.
4:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那靠近敵人居住的猶大人，十次來對我們說，他們必從你們所到的各處上來攻擊我們。
4:13|ASV|Therefore set I in the lowest parts of the space behind the wall, in the open places, I set there the people after their families with their swords, their spears, and their bows.
4:13|Darby|I set in the lower places behind the wall in exposed  places, I even set the people, according to their families,  with their swords, their spears and their bows.
4:13|KJV|Therefore set I in the lower places behind the wall, and on the higher places, I even set the people after their families with their swords, their spears, and their bows.
4:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我使百姓各按家族，拿刀、拿槍、拿弓，站在城牆後邊低窪的空曠處。
4:14|ASV|And I looked, and rose up, and said unto the nobles, and to the rulers, and to the rest of the people, Be not ye afraid of them: remember the Lord, who is great and terrible, and fight for your brethren, your sons, and your daughters, your wives, and your houses.
4:14|Darby|And I looked, and rose up, and said to the nobles, and to  the rulers, and to the rest of the people, Be not afraid of  them: remember the Lord who is great and terrible, and fight  for your brethren, your sons and your daughters, your wives and  your houses.
4:14|KJV|And I looked, and rose up, and said unto the nobles, and to the rulers, and to the rest of the people, Be not ye afraid of them: remember the LORD, which is great and terrible, and fight for your brethren, your sons, and your daughters, your wives, and your houses.
4:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我察看了，就起來對貴冑、官長、和其餘的百姓說，不要怕他們；當記念那大而可畏的主，要為你們的弟兄、兒女、妻子、家產爭戰。
4:15|ASV|And it came to pass, when our enemies heard that it was known unto us, and God had brought their counsel to nought, that we returned all of us to the wall, every one unto his work.
4:15|Darby|And it came to pass that when our enemies heard that it was  known to us, and that God had defeated their counsel, we  returned all of us to the wall, every one to his work.
4:15|KJV|And it came to pass, when our enemies heard that it was known unto us, and God had brought their counsel to nought, that we returned all of us to the wall, every one unto his work.
4:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|仇敵聽見我們知道他們的計謀，又見神破壞他們的計畫，就不來了；我們都回到城牆那堙A各作各的工。
4:16|ASV|And it came to pass from that time forth, that half of my servants wrought in the work, and half of them held the spears, the shields, and the bows, and the coats of mail; and the rulers were behind all the house of Judah.
4:16|Darby|And from that time forth the half of my servants wrought in  the work, and the other half of them held the spears, and the  shields, and the bows, and the corslets; and the captains were  behind all the house of Judah.
4:16|KJV|And it came to pass from that time forth, that the half of my servants wrought in the work, and the other half of them held both the spears, the shields, and the bows, and the habergeons; and the rulers were behind all the house of Judah.
4:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|從那日起，我的僕人一半作工，一半拿槍、拿盾牌、拿弓、穿鎧甲；官長都站在猶大家眾人的後邊。
4:17|ASV|They all builded the wall and they that bare burdens laded themselves; every one with one of his hands wrought in the work, and with the other held his weapon;
4:17|Darby|They that built on the wall, and they that bore burdens,  with those that loaded, wrought in the work with one hand, and  with the other they held a weapon.
4:17|KJV|They which builded on the wall, and they that bare burdens, with those that laded, every one with one of his hands wrought in the work, and with the other hand held a weapon.
4:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|建造城牆的、扛抬重物的，都佩帶兵器，一手作工，一手拿兵器。
4:18|ASV|and the builders, every one had his sword girded by his side, and so builded. And he that sounded the trumpet was by me.
4:18|Darby|And the builders had every one his sword girded by his  side, and built. And he that sounded the trumpet was by me.
4:18|KJV|For the builders, every one had his sword girded by his side, and so builded. And he that sounded the trumpet was by me.
4:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|建造的人都腰間佩刀建造，吹角的人在我旁邊。
4:19|ASV|And I said unto the nobles, and to the rulers and to the rest of the people, The work is great and large, and we are separated upon the wall, one far from another:
4:19|Darby|And I said to the nobles, and to the rulers, and to the  rest of the people, The work is great and extended, and we are  scattered upon the wall, one far from another:
4:19|KJV|And I said unto the nobles, and to the rulers, and to the rest of the people, The work is great and large, and we are separated upon the wall, one far from another.
4:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我對貴冑、官長、和其餘的百姓說，這工程浩大，我們在城牆上彼此相離甚遠；
4:20|ASV|in what place soever ye hear the sound of the trumpet, resort ye thither unto us; our God will fight for us.
4:20|Darby|in what place ye hear the sound of the trumpet, thither  shall ye assemble to us; our God will fight for us.
4:20|KJV|In what place therefore ye hear the sound of the trumpet, resort ye thither unto us: our God shall fight for us.
4:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們聽見角聲在那堙A就要聚集到我們那堨h。我們的神必為我們爭戰。
4:21|ASV|So we wrought in the work: and half of them held the spears from the rising of the morning till the stars appeared.
4:21|Darby|And we laboured in the work; and half of them held the  spears from the rising of the dawn till the stars appeared.
4:21|KJV|So we laboured in the work: and half of them held the spears from the rising of the morning till the stars appeared.
4:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是，我們作工，其中一半拿槍，從天亮直到星宿出現的時候。
4:22|ASV|Likewise at the same time said I unto the people, Let every one with his servant lodge within Jerusalem, that in the night they may be a guard to us, and may labor in the day.
4:22|Darby|Likewise at the same time I said to the people, Let every  one with his servant lodge within Jerusalem, that in the night  they may be a guard to us, and [be for] labour in the day.
4:22|KJV|Likewise at the same time said I unto the people, Let every one with his servant lodge within Jerusalem, that in the night they may be a guard to us, and labour on the day.
4:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時，我又對百姓說，各人和他的僕人當在耶路撒冷城中住宿，好在夜間護衛我們，白晝作工。
4:23<version name="ASV">So neither I, nor my brethren, nor my servants, nor the men of the guard that followed me, none of us put off our clothes, every one went with his weapon to the water. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:23<version name="Darby">And neither I, nor my brethren, nor my servants, nor the  men of the guard that followed me, none of us put off our  garments: every one had his weapon on his right side. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:23<version name="KJV">So neither I, nor my brethren, nor my servants, nor the men of the guard which followed me, none of us put off our clothes, saving that every one put them off for washing.</p><p /><br /></version>
4:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我和我的弟兄、僕人、並跟從我的護衛兵，都不脫衣服，各人右手拿著兵器。
5:1|ASV|Then there arose a great cry of the people and of their wives against their brethren the Jews.
5:1|Darby|And there was a great cry of the people and of their wives  against their brethren the Jews.
5:1|KJV|And there was a great cry of the people and of their wives against their brethren the Jews.
5:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|百姓和他們的妻子大大呼號，埋怨他們的弟兄猶大人。
5:2|ASV|For there were that said, We, our sons and our daughters, are many: let us get grain, that we may eat and live.
5:2|Darby|And there were that said, We, our sons and our daughters,  are many, and we must procure corn that we may eat and live.
5:2|KJV|For there were that said, We, our sons, and our daughters, are many: therefore we take up corn for them, that we may eat, and live.
5:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有的說，我們和兒女人口眾多，要去得糧食喫飽活命；
5:3|ASV|Some also there were that said, We are mortgaging our fields, and our vineyards, and our houses: let us get grain, because of the dearth.
5:3|Darby|And there were that said, We have had to pledge our fields,  and our vineyards, and our houses, that we might procure corn  in the dearth.
5:3|KJV|Some also there were that said, We have mortgaged our lands, vineyards, and houses, that we might buy corn, because of the dearth.
5:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有的說，我們典了田地、葡萄園、房屋，要在饑荒中得糧食；
5:4|ASV|There were also that said, We have borrowed money for the king's tribute upon our fields and our vineyards.
5:4|Darby|And there were that said, We have borrowed money for the  king's tribute upon our fields and vineyards;
5:4|KJV|There were also that said, We have borrowed money for the king's tribute, and that upon our lands and vineyards.
5:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有的說，我們已經用田地、葡萄園作抵押，借了錢給王納稅。
5:5|ASV|Yet now our flesh is as the flesh of our brethren, our children as their children: and, lo, we bring into bondage our sons and our daughters to be servants, and some of our daughters are brought into bondage already: neither is it in our power to help it; for other men have our fields and our vineyards.
5:5|Darby|yet now our flesh is as the flesh of our brethren, our  children as their children; and behold, we must bring into  bondage our sons and our daughters to be servants, and some of  our daughters are brought into bondage [already]; neither is it  in the power of our hand [to redeem them], for other men have  our fields and our vineyards.
5:5|KJV|Yet now our flesh is as the flesh of our brethren, our children as their children: and, lo, we bring into bondage our sons and our daughters to be servants, and some of our daughters are brought unto bondage already: neither is it in our power to redeem them; for other men have our lands and vineyards.
5:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其實我們的肉身與我們弟兄的肉身一樣，我們的兒女與他們的兒女一般；看哪，我們將要使兒女作人的僕婢。我們的女兒已有為婢的；我們無力拯救，因為我們的田地、葡萄園，已經歸了別人。
5:6|ASV|And I was very angry when I heard their cry and these words.
5:6|Darby|And I was very angry when I heard their cry and these words.
5:6|KJV|And I was very angry when I heard their cry and these words.
5:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我聽見他們的呼號和這些話，便甚發怒。
5:7|ASV|Then I consulted with myself, and contended with the nobles and the rulers, and said unto them, Ye exact usury, every one of his brother. And I held a great assembly against them.
5:7|Darby|And I consulted with myself; and I remonstrated with the  nobles and the rulers, and said to them, Ye exact usury, every  one of his brother! And I set a great assembly against them.
5:7|KJV|Then I consulted with myself, and I rebuked the nobles, and the rulers, and said unto them, Ye exact usury, every one of his brother. And I set a great assembly against them.
5:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我心媊w畫了，就斥責貴冑和官長，說，你們各人竟向自己的弟兄索取利息！於是我安排大會攻擊他們。
5:8|ASV|And I said unto them, We after our ability have redeemed our brethren the Jews, that were sold unto the nations; and would ye even sell your brethren, and should they be sold unto us? Then held they their peace, and found never a word.
5:8|Darby|And I said to them, We, according to our ability, have  redeemed our brethren the Jews, who were sold to the nations;  and will ye even sell your brethren? or shall they be sold unto  us? And they were silent and found no answer.
5:8|KJV|And I said unto them, We after our ability have redeemed our brethren the Jews, which were sold unto the heathen; and will ye even sell your brethren? or shall they be sold unto us? Then held they their peace, and found nothing to answer.
5:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我對他們說，我們盡力贖回了我們的弟兄，就是賣與外邦的猶大人；你們還要賣弟兄，使我們贖回來麼？他們靜默不語，無話可答。
5:9|ASV|Also I said, The thing that ye do is not good: ought ye not to walk in the fear of our God, because of the reproach of the nations our enemies?
5:9|Darby|And I said, The thing that ye do is not good. Ought ye not  to walk in the fear of our God, so as not to be the reproach of  the nations our enemies?
5:9|KJV|Also I said, It is not good that ye do: ought ye not to walk in the fear of our God because of the reproach of the heathen our enemies?
5:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我又說，你們所行的不善。為著避免我們仇敵外邦人的毀謗，你們行事不當敬畏我們的神麼？
5:10|ASV|And I likewise, my brethren and my servants, do lend them money and grain. I pray you, let us leave off this usury.
5:10|Darby|I also, my brethren and my servants, we might exact usury  of them, money and corn. I pray you, let us leave off this  usury.
5:10|KJV|I likewise, and my brethren, and my servants, might exact of them money and corn: I pray you, let us leave off this usury.
5:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我和我的弟兄與僕人也將銀錢糧食借給百姓；我們大家都放棄收取利息罷。
5:11|ASV|Restore, I pray you, to them, even this day, their fields, their vineyards, their oliveyards, and their houses, also the hundredth part of the money, and of the grain, the new wine, and the oil, that ye exact of them.
5:11|Darby|Restore, I pray you, to them this very day their fields,  their vineyards, their olive-gardens, and their houses, also  the hundredth [part] of the money, and of the corn, the wine  and the oil, that ye have exacted of them.
5:11|KJV|Restore, I pray you, to them, even this day, their lands, their vineyards, their oliveyards, and their houses, also the hundredth part of the money, and of the corn, the wine, and the oil, that ye exact of them.
5:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|如今我勸你們將他們的田地、葡萄園、橄欖園、房屋，並向他們所取的銀錢、糧食、新酒和新油，百分之一的利息，都歸還他們。
5:12|ASV|Then said they, We will restore them, and will require nothing of them; so will we do, even as thou sayest. Then I called the priests, and took an oath of them, that they would do according to this promise.
5:12|Darby|And they said, We will restore [them], and will require  nothing of them; so will we do, as thou hast said. And I called  the priests, and took an oath of them, that they should do  according to this promise.
5:12|KJV|Then said they, We will restore them, and will require nothing of them; so will we do as thou sayest. Then I called the priests, and took an oath of them, that they should do according to this promise.
5:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|眾人說，我們必歸還，不向他們索要，必照你所說的去行。我就召了祭司來，叫眾人起誓，必照著所應許的去行。
5:13|ASV|Also I shook out my lap, and said, So God shake out every man from his house, and from his labor, that performeth not this promise; even thus be he shaken out, and emptied. And all the assembly said, Amen, and praised Jehovah. And the people did according to this promise.
5:13|Darby|Also I shook my lap, and said, So God shake out every man  from his house and from his earnings, that performeth not this  promise: even thus be he shaken out and emptied! And all the  congregation said, Amen! And they praised Jehovah. And the  people did according to this promise.
5:13|KJV|Also I shook my lap, and said, So God shake out every man from his house, and from his labour, that performeth not this promise, even thus be he shaken out, and emptied. And all the congregation said, Amen, and praised the LORD. And the people did according to this promise.
5:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我也抖著胸前的衣襟，說，凡不成就這應許的，願神照樣抖他離開家產和他勞碌得來的，直到抖空了。會眾都說，阿們；又讚美耶和華。百姓就照著所應許的去行。
5:14|ASV|Moreover from the time that I was appointed to be their governor in the land of Judah, from the twentieth year even unto the two and thirtieth year of Artaxerxes the king, that is, twelve years, I and my brethren have not eaten the bread of the governor.
5:14|Darby|Moreover from the time that I was appointed to be their  governor in the land of Judah, from the twentieth year even to  the thirty-second year of Artaxerxes the king, twelve years, I  and my brethren have not eaten the bread of the governor.
5:14|KJV|Moreover from the time that I was appointed to be their governor in the land of Judah, from the twentieth year even unto the two and thirtieth year of Artaxerxes the king, that is, twelve years, I and my brethren have not eaten the bread of the governor.
5:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|自從王派我作猶大地的省長，就是從亞達薛西王二十年，直到三十二年，共十二年之久，我與我弟兄都沒有喫省長的俸祿。
5:15|ASV|But the former governors that were before me were chargeable unto the people, and took of them bread and wine, besides forty shekels of silver; yea, even their servants bare rule over the people: but so did not I, because of the fear of God.
5:15|Darby|But the former governors that were before me had been  chargeable to the people, and had taken of them bread and wine,  besides forty shekels of silver: even their servants bore rule  over the people. But I did not so, because of the fear of God.
5:15|KJV|But the former governors that had been before me were chargeable unto the people, and had taken of them bread and wine, beside forty shekels of silver; yea, even their servants bare rule over the people: but so did not I, because of the fear of God.
5:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在我以前的省長加重百姓的擔子，除了徵收銀子四十舍客勒以外，又索要糧食和酒，就是他們的僕人也轄制百姓；但我因敬畏神，不這樣行。
5:16|ASV|Yea, also I continued in the work of this wall, neither bought we any land: and all my servants were gathered thither unto the work.
5:16|Darby|Yea, also I applied myself to this work of the wall, and we  bought no fields; and all my servants were gathered thither for  the work.
5:16|KJV|Yea, also I continued in the work of this wall, neither bought we any land: and all my servants were gathered thither unto the work.
5:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且我堅定持續作城牆的工，並沒有置買田地；我的僕人也都聚集在那塈@工。
5:17|ASV|Moreover there were at my table, of the Jews and the rulers, a hundred and fifty men, besides those that came unto us from among the nations that were round about us.
5:17|Darby|And there were at my table a hundred and fifty of the Jews  and the rulers, besides those that came to us from among the  nations that were about us.
5:17|KJV|Moreover there were at my table an hundred and fifty of the Jews and rulers, beside those that came unto us from among the heathen that are about us.
5:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|除了從四圍外邦中到我們這堥茠漱H以外，有猶大平民和官長一百五十人，在我席上喫飯。
5:18|ASV|Now that which was prepared for one day was one ox and six choice sheep; also fowls were prepared for me, and once in ten days store of all sorts of wine: yet for all this I demanded not the bread of the governor, because the bondage was heavy upon this people.
5:18|Darby|And that which was prepared daily was one ox [and] six  choice sheep; also fowls were prepared for me, and once in ten  days all sorts of wine in abundance. Yet for all this I  demanded not the bread of the governor; for the service was  heavy upon this people.
5:18|KJV|Now that which was prepared for me daily was one ox and six choice sheep; also fowls were prepared for me, and once in ten days store of all sorts of wine: yet for all this required not I the bread of the governor, because the bondage was heavy upon this people.
5:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|每日豫備的有一隻公牛，六隻肥羊，又為我豫備一些飛禽；每十日一次，多豫備各樣的酒。雖然如此，我並不要省長的俸祿，因為百姓服役甚重。
5:19<version name="ASV">Remember unto me, O my God, for good, all that I have done for this people. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:19<version name="Darby">Remember for me, my God, for good, all that I have done for  this people. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:19<version name="KJV">Think upon me, my God, for good, according to all that I have done for this people.</p><p /><br /></version>
5:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的神阿，求你記念我為這百姓所行的一切事，以善待我。
6:1|ASV|Now it came to pass, when it was reported to Sanballat and Tobiah, and to Geshem the Arabian, and unto the rest of our enemies, that I had builded the wall, and that there was no breach left therein; (though even unto that time I had not set up the doors in the gates;)
6:1|Darby|And it came to pass when Sanballat, and Tobijah, and Geshem  the Arabian, and the rest of our enemies, heard that I had  built the wall, and that there was no breach left in it (though  at that time I had not set up the doors in the gates),
6:1|KJV|Now it came to pass when Sanballat, and Tobiah, and Geshem the Arabian, and the rest of our enemies, heard that I had builded the wall, and that there was no breach left therein; (though at that time I had not set up the doors upon the gates;)
6:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|參巴拉、多比雅、亞拉伯人基善、和我們其餘的仇敵，聽見我已經建造了城牆，其中沒有破裂之處，（不過到那時我還沒有在城門上安門扇，）
6:2|ASV|that Sanballat and Geshem sent unto me, saying, Come, let us meet together in one of the villages in the plain of Ono. But they thought to do me mischief.
6:2|Darby|that Sanballat and Geshem sent to me, saying, Come, let us  meet together in the villages in the plain of Ono. But they  thought to do me mischief.
6:2|KJV|That Sanballat and Geshem sent unto me, saying, Come, let us meet together in some one of the villages in the plain of Ono. But they thought to do me mischief.
6:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|參巴拉和基善就打發人來見我，說，請你來，我們在阿挪平原的一個村莊相會。他們卻圖謀害我。
6:3|ASV|And I sent messengers unto them, saying, I am doing a great work, so that I cannot come down: why should the work cease, whilst I leave it, and come down to you?
6:3|Darby|And I sent messengers to them, saying, I am doing a great  work, and I cannot come down. Why should the work cease, whilst  I leave it and come down to you?
6:3|KJV|And I sent messengers unto them, saying, I am doing a great work, so that I cannot come down: why should the work cease, whilst I leave it, and come down to you?
6:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是我差遣人去見他們，說，我現在辦理大工，不能下去。我為何放開工作，下去見你們，使工作停頓呢？
6:4|ASV|And they sent unto me four times after this sort; and I answered them after the same manner.
6:4|Darby|And they sent to me four times after this sort; and I  answered them in the same manner.
6:4|KJV|Yet they sent unto me four times after this sort; and I answered them after the same manner.
6:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們四次這樣打發人來見我，我都如此回答。
6:5|ASV|Then sent Sanballat his servant unto me in like manner the fifth time with an open letter in his hand,
6:5|Darby|Then sent Sanballat his servant to me in this manner the  fifth time, with an open letter in his hand,
6:5|KJV|Then sent Sanballat his servant unto me in like manner the fifth time with an open letter in his hand;
6:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|參巴拉第五次這樣打發僕人來見我，手堮陬菪憤坁澈H，
6:6|ASV|wherein was written, It is reported among the nations, and Gashmu saith it, that thou and the Jews think to rebel; for which cause thou art building the wall: and thou wouldest be their king, according to these words.
6:6|Darby|in which was written: It is reported among the nations, and  Gashmu says [it, that] thou and the Jews think to rebel, for  which cause thou buildest the wall, and according to these  words thou wilt become their king.
6:6|KJV|Wherein was written, It is reported among the heathen, and Gashmu saith it, that thou and the Jews think to rebel: for which cause thou buildest the wall, that thou mayest be their king, according to these words.
6:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|信上寫著說，外邦人中有風聲，基善也說，你和猶大人謀反，因此你建造城牆。照他們這些話，你要作他們的王。
6:7|ASV|And thou hast also appointed prophets to preach of thee at Jerusalem, saying, There is a king in Judah: and now shall it be reported to the king according to these words. Come now therefore, and let us take counsel together.
6:7|Darby|And thou hast also appointed prophets to proclaim concerning  thee at Jerusalem saying, There is a king in Judah! And now it  will be reported to the king according to these words. Come now  therefore, and let us take counsel together.
6:7|KJV|And thou hast also appointed prophets to preach of thee at Jerusalem, saying, There is a king in Judah: and now shall it be reported to the king according to these words. Come now therefore, and let us take counsel together.
6:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你又設立申言者在耶路撒冷指著你宣告說，在猶大有王了！現在這些話必傳與王知；所以請你來，與我們彼此商議。
6:8|ASV|Then I sent unto him, saying, There are no such things done as thou sayest, but thou feignest them out of thine own heart.
6:8|Darby|And I sent to him, saying, There are no such things done as  thou sayest, but thou feignest them out of thine own heart.
6:8|KJV|Then I sent unto him, saying, There are no such things done as thou sayest, but thou feignest them out of thine own heart.
6:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我就差遣人去見他，說，你所說的這些事，一概沒有，是你自己心堮熙y的。
6:9|ASV|For they all would have made us afraid, saying, Their hands shall be weakened from the work, that it be not done. But now, O God, strengthen thou my hands.
6:9|Darby|For they all would have made us afraid, saying, Their hands  shall be slackened from the work, that it be not carried out.  -- Now therefore strengthen my hands!
6:9|KJV|For they all made us afraid, saying, Their hands shall be weakened from the work, that it be not done. Now therefore, O God, strengthen my hands.
6:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們都要使我們懼怕，意思說，他們的手必軟弱不能作工，以致工作不能成就。現在，神阿，求你堅固我的手。
6:10|ASV|And I went unto the house of Shemaiah the son of Delaiah the son of Mehetabel, who was shut up; and he said, Let us meet together in the house of God, within the temple, and let us shut the doors of the temple: for they will come to slay thee; yea, in the night will they come to slay thee.
6:10|Darby|And I came to the house of Shemaiah the son of Delaiah, the  son of Mehetabeel, who had shut himself up. And he said, Let us  meet together in the house of God, within the temple, and let  us shut the doors of the temple; for they are coming to kill  thee; even in the night are they coming to kill thee.
6:10|KJV|Afterward I came unto the house of Shemaiah the son of Delaiah the son of Mehetabeel, who was shut up; and he said, Let us meet together in the house of God, within the temple, and let us shut the doors of the temple: for they will come to slay thee; yea, in the night will they come to slay thee.
6:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我到了米希大別的孫子，第來雅的兒子示瑪雅家；那時，他閉門不出。他說，我們不如在神的殿，在殿堂中會面，將殿堂的門關鎖；因為他們要來殺你，就是在夜堥荓你。
6:11|ASV|And I said, Should such a man as I flee? and who is there, that, being such as I, would go into the temple to save his life? I will not go in.
6:11|Darby|And I said, Should such a man as I flee? and who is there,  that, being as I am, could go into the temple, and live? I will  not go in.
6:11|KJV|And I said, Should such a man as I flee? and who is there, that, being as I am, would go into the temple to save his life? I will not go in.
6:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我說，像我這樣的人豈要逃跑呢？像我這樣的人豈能進入殿堳O全生命呢？我不進去！
6:12|ASV|And I discerned, and, lo, God had not sent him; but he pronounced this prophecy against me: and Tobiah and Sanballat had hired him.
6:12|Darby|And I perceived, and behold, God had not sent him; for he  pronounced this prophecy against me; and Tobijah and Sanballat  had hired him.
6:12|KJV|And, lo, I perceived that God had not sent him; but that he pronounced this prophecy against me: for Tobiah and Sanballat had hired him.
6:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我看出神並沒有差遣他，是他自己這樣申言攻擊我，是多比雅和參巴拉賄買了他。
6:13|ASV|For this cause was he hired, that I should be afraid, and do so, and sin, and that they might have matter for an evil report, that they might reproach me.
6:13|Darby|Therefore was he hired, that I should be afraid, and do so,  and sin, and that they might have wherewith to spread an evil  report, that they might reproach me.
6:13|KJV|Therefore was he hired, that I should be afraid, and do so, and sin, and that they might have matter for an evil report, that they might reproach me.
6:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|賄買他的緣故，是要叫我懼怕，依從他這樣行，以致犯罪，他們就有理由傳揚惡言毀謗我。
6:14|ASV|Remember, O my God, Tobiah and Sanballat according to these their works, and also the prophetess Noadiah, and the rest of the prophets, that would have put me in fear.
6:14|Darby|My God, remember Tobijah and Sanballat according to these  their works, and also the prophetess Noadiah, and the rest of  the prophets who would have put me in fear.
6:14|KJV|My God, think thou upon Tobiah and Sanballat according to these their works, and on the prophetess Noadiah, and the rest of the prophets, that would have put me in fear.
6:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的神阿，求你記得多比雅和參巴拉，照著他們所作的這些事報應他們，也要記得女申言者挪亞底和其餘的申言者，他們想要叫我懼怕。
6:15|ASV|So the wall was finished in the twenty and fifth day of the month Elul, in fifty and two days.
6:15|Darby|So the wall was finished on the twenty-fifth of Elul, in  fifty-two days.
6:15|KJV|So the wall was finished in the twenty and fifth day of the month Elul, in fifty and two days.
6:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以祿月二十五日，城牆修完了，共修了五十二天。
6:16|ASV|And it came to pass, when all our enemies heard  thereof, that all the nations that were about us feared, and were much cast down in their own eyes; for they perceived that this work was wrought of our God.
6:16|Darby|And it came to pass that when all our enemies heard [of  it], all the nations that were about us were afraid and were  much cast down in their own eyes, and they perceived that this  work was wrought by our God.
6:16|KJV|And it came to pass, that when all our enemies heard thereof, and all the heathen that were about us saw these things, they were much cast down in their own eyes: for they perceived that this work was wrought of our God.
6:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們一切的仇敵聽見了，四圍的外邦人都懼怕，愁眉不展；因為知道這工作完成是出於我們的神。
6:17|ASV|Moreover in those days the nobles of Judah sent many letters unto Tobiah, and the letters of Tobiah came unto them.
6:17|Darby|Moreover in those days the nobles of Judah sent many  letters to Tobijah, and those of Tobijah came to them.
6:17|KJV|Moreover in those days the nobles of Judah sent many letters unto Tobiah, and the letters of Tobiah came unto them.
6:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|再者，在那些日子，猶大的貴冑屢次寄信與多比雅，多比雅也來信與他們。
6:18|ASV|For there were many in Judah sworn unto him, because he was the son-in-law of Shecaniah the son of Arah; and his son Jehohanan had taken the daughter of Meshullam the son of Berechiah to wife.
6:18|Darby|For there were many in Judah sworn to him; for he was a  son-in-law of Shechaniah the son of Arah; and his son Johanan  had taken the daughter of Meshullam the son of Berechiah.
6:18|KJV|For there were many in Judah sworn unto him, because he was the son in law of Shechaniah the son of Arah; and his son Johanan had taken the daughter of Meshullam the son of Berechiah.
6:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在猶大有許多人與多比雅結盟，因他是亞拉兒子示迦尼的女婿，並且他的兒子約哈難娶了比利迦兒子米書蘭的女兒為妻。
6:19<version name="ASV">Also they spake of his good deeds before me, and reported my words to him. And Tobiah sent letters to put me in fear. </p><p /><br /></version>
6:19<version name="Darby">Also they spoke of his good deeds before me, and reported  my words to him. [And] Tobijah sent letters to put me in fear. </p><p /><br /></version>
6:19<version name="KJV">Also they reported his good deeds before me, and uttered my words to him. And Tobiah sent letters to put me in fear.</p><p /><br /></version>
6:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們常在我面前說多比雅的善行，也將我的話傳與他。多比雅又寄一些信來，要叫我懼怕。
7:1|ASV|Now it came to pass, when the wall was built, and I had set up the doors, and the porters and the singers and the Levites were appointed,
7:1|Darby|And it came to pass when the wall was built, and I had set  up the doors, that the doorkeepers and the singers and the  Levites were appointed.
7:1|KJV|Now it came to pass, when the wall was built, and I had set up the doors, and the porters and the singers and the Levites were appointed,
7:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|城牆建成，我安了門扇，守門的、歌唱的、和利未人都已派定。
7:2|ASV|that I gave my brother Hanani, and Hananiah the governor of the castle, charge over Jerusalem; for he was a faithful man, and feared God above many.
7:2|Darby|And I gave my brother Hanani, and Hananiah the ruler of the  citadel, charge over Jerusalem; for he was a faithful man and  feared God above many.
7:2|KJV|That I gave my brother Hanani, and Hananiah the ruler of the palace, charge over Jerusalem: for he was a faithful man, and feared God above many.
7:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我就吩咐我的弟兄哈拿尼，和營樓長哈拿尼雅管理耶路撒冷，因為哈拿尼雅是個忠信的人，又敬畏神過於眾人。
7:3|ASV|And I said unto them, Let not the gates of Jerusalem be opened until the sun be hot; and while they stand on guard, let them shut the doors, and bar ye them: and appoint watches of the inhabitants of Jerusalem, every one in his watch, and every one to be over against his house.
7:3|Darby|And I said to them that the gates of Jerusalem should not be  opened until the sun was hot, and that they should shut the  doors and bar them while they stood by; and that there should  be appointed watches of the inhabitants of Jerusalem, every one  in his watch, and every one over against his house.
7:3|KJV|And I said unto them, Let not the gates of Jerusalem be opened until the sun be hot; and while they stand by, let them shut the doors, and bar them: and appoint watches of the inhabitants of Jerusalem, every one in his watch, and every one to be over against his house.
7:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我對他們說，等到日頭暖和，纔可開耶路撒冷的城門；人尚站著看守的時候，就要把門關好，你要上閂；也當派耶路撒冷的居民，各按班次看守自己房屋對面之處。
7:4|ASV|Now the city was wide and large; but the people were few therein, and the houses were not builded.
7:4|Darby|Now the city was large and great; but the people in it were  few, and no houses were built.
7:4|KJV|Now the city was large and great: but the people were few therein, and the houses were not builded.
7:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|城廣大，其中的民卻稀少，房屋還沒有建造。
7:5|ASV|And my God put into my heart to gather together the nobles, and the rulers, and the people, that they might be reckoned by genealogy. And I found the book of the genealogy of them that came up at the first, and I found written therein:
7:5|Darby|And my God put into my heart to gather together the nobles,  and the rulers, and the people, for registration by genealogy.  And I found a genealogical register of those that had come up  at the first, and I found written in it:
7:5|KJV|And my God put into mine heart to gather together the nobles, and the rulers, and the people, that they might be reckoned by genealogy. And I found a register of the genealogy of them which came up at the first, and found written therein,
7:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的神使我心堸_意，招聚貴冑、官長和百姓，要照家譜登記。我找著第一次上來之人的家譜，其上寫著：
7:6|ASV|These are the children of the province, that went up out of the captivity of those that had been carried away, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away, and that returned unto Jerusalem and to Judah, every one unto his city;
7:6|Darby|These are the children of the province that went up out of  the captivity of those that had been carried away, whom  Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away, and who  came again to Jerusalem and to Judah, every one to his city;
7:6|KJV|These are the children of the province, that went up out of the captivity, of those that had been carried away, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away, and came again to Jerusalem and to Judah, every one unto his city;
7:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|巴比倫王尼布甲尼撒從前所遷徙之猶大省的人，現在他們的子孫從被擄到之地上到耶路撒冷和猶大，各歸本城，這些人記在下面。
7:7|ASV|who came with Zerubbabel, Jeshua, Nehemiah, Azariah, Raamiah, Nahamani, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispereth, Bigvai, Nehum, Baanah. The number of the men of the people of Israel:
7:7|Darby|those who came with Zerubbabel, Jeshua, Nehemiah, Azariah,  Raamiah, Nahamani, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispereth, Bigvai, Nehum,  Baanah. The number of the men of the people of Israel:
7:7|KJV|Who came with Zerubbabel, Jeshua, Nehemiah, Azariah, Raamiah, Nahamani, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispereth, Bigvai, Nehum, Baanah. The number, I say, of the men of the people of Israel was this;
7:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們是同著所羅巴伯、耶書亞、尼希米、亞撒利雅、拉米、拿哈瑪尼、末底改、必珊、米斯毘列、比革瓦伊、尼宏、巴拿回來的。以色列民中男子的數目記在下面：
7:8|ASV|The children of Parosh, two thousand a hundred and seventy and two.
7:8|Darby|The children of Parosh, two thousand one hundred and  seventy-two.
7:8|KJV|The children of Parosh, two thousand an hundred seventy and two.
7:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|巴錄的子孫二千一百七十二名；
7:9|ASV|The children of Shephatiah, three hundred seventy and two.
7:9|Darby|The children of Shephatiah, three hundred and seventy-two.
7:9|KJV|The children of Shephatiah, three hundred seventy and two.
7:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|示法提雅的子孫三百七十二名；
7:10|ASV|The children of Arah, six hundred fifty and two.
7:10|Darby|The children of Arah, six hundred and fifty-two.
7:10|KJV|The children of Arah, six hundred fifty and two.
7:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞拉的子孫六百五十二名；
7:11|ASV|The children of Pahath-moab, of the children of Jeshua and Joab, two thousand and eight hundred and eighteen.
7:11|Darby|The children of Pahath-Moab, of the children of Jeshua and  Joab, two thousand eight hundred and eighteen.
7:11|KJV|The children of Pahathmoab, of the children of Jeshua and Joab, two thousand and eight hundred and eighteen.
7:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|巴哈摩押的子孫，屬耶書亞和約押子孫的，二千八百一十八名；
7:12|ASV|The children of Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four.
7:12|Darby|The children of Elam, a thousand two hundred and  fifty-four.
7:12|KJV|The children of Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four.
7:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以攔的子孫一千二百五十四名；
7:13|ASV|The children of Zattu, eight hundred forty and five.
7:13|Darby|The children of Zattu, eight hundred and forty-five.
7:13|KJV|The children of Zattu, eight hundred forty and five.
7:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|薩土的子孫八百四十五名；
7:14|ASV|The children of Zaccai, seven hundred and threescore.
7:14|Darby|The children of Zaccai, seven hundred and sixty.
7:14|KJV|The children of Zaccai, seven hundred and threescore.
7:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|薩改的子孫七百六十名；
7:15|ASV|The children of Binnui, six hundred forty and eight.
7:15|Darby|The children of Binnui, six hundred and forty-eight.
7:15|KJV|The children of Binnui, six hundred forty and eight.
7:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|賓內的子孫六百四十八名；
7:16|ASV|The children of Bebai, six hundred twenty and eight.
7:16|Darby|The children of Bebai, six hundred and twenty-eight.
7:16|KJV|The children of Bebai, six hundred twenty and eight.
7:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|比拜的子孫六百二十八名；
7:17|ASV|The children of Azgad, two thousand three hundred twenty and two.
7:17|Darby|The children of Azgad, two thousand three hundred and  twenty-two.
7:17|KJV|The children of Azgad, two thousand three hundred twenty and two.
7:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|押甲的子孫二千三百二十二名；
7:18|ASV|The children of Adonikam, six hundred threescore and seven.
7:18|Darby|The children of Adonikam, six hundred and sixty-seven.
7:18|KJV|The children of Adonikam, six hundred threescore and seven.
7:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞多尼干的子孫六百六十七名；
7:19|ASV|The children of Bigvai, two thousand threescore and seven.
7:19|Darby|The children of Bigvai, two thousand and sixty-seven.
7:19|KJV|The children of Bigvai, two thousand threescore and seven.
7:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|比革瓦伊的子孫二千零六十七名；
7:20|ASV|The children of Adin, six hundred fifty and five.
7:20|Darby|The children of Adin, six hundred and fifty-five.
7:20|KJV|The children of Adin, six hundred fifty and five.
7:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞丁的子孫六百五十五名；
7:21|ASV|The children of Ater, of Hezekiah, ninety and eight.
7:21|Darby|The children of Ater of [the family of] Hezekiah,  ninety-eight.
7:21|KJV|The children of Ater of Hezekiah, ninety and eight.
7:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞特的子孫，屬希西家子孫的，九十八名；
7:22|ASV|The children of Hashum, three hundred twenty and eight.
7:22|Darby|The children of Hashum, three hundred and twenty-eight.
7:22|KJV|The children of Hashum, three hundred twenty and eight.
7:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈順的子孫三百二十八名；
7:23|ASV|The children of Bezai, three hundred twenty and four.
7:23|Darby|The children of Bezai, three hundred and twenty-four.
7:23|KJV|The children of Bezai, three hundred twenty and four.
7:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|比賽的子孫三百二十四名；
7:24|ASV|The children of Hariph, a hundred and twelve.
7:24|Darby|The children of Hariph, a hundred and twelve.
7:24|KJV|The children of Hariph, an hundred and twelve.
7:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈拉的子孫一百一十二名；
7:25|ASV|The children of Gibeon, ninety and five.
7:25|Darby|The children of Gibeon, ninety-five.
7:25|KJV|The children of Gibeon, ninety and five.
7:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|基遍人九十五名；
7:26|ASV|The men of Bethlehem and Netophah, a hundred fourscore and eight.
7:26|Darby|The men of Bethlehem and Netophah, a hundred and  eighty-eight.
7:26|KJV|The men of Bethlehem and Netophah, an hundred fourscore and eight.
7:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|伯利恆人和尼陀法人共一百八十八名；
7:27|ASV|The men of Anathoth, a hundred twenty and eight.
7:27|Darby|The men of Anathoth, a hundred and twenty-eight.
7:27|KJV|The men of Anathoth, an hundred twenty and eight.
7:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞拿突人一百二十八名；
7:28|ASV|The men of Beth-azmaveth, forty and two.
7:28|Darby|The men of Beth-azmaveth, forty-two.
7:28|KJV|The men of Bethazmaveth, forty and two.
7:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|伯亞斯瑪弗人四十二名；
7:29|ASV|The men of Kiriath-jearim, Chephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred forty and three.
7:29|Darby|The men of Kirjath-jearim, Chephirah, and Beeroth, seven  hundred and forty-three.
7:29|KJV|The men of Kirjathjearim, Chephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred forty and three.
7:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|基列耶琳人、基非拉人、比錄人共七百四十三名；
7:30|ASV|The men of Ramah and Geba, six hundred twenty and one.
7:30|Darby|The men of Ramah and Geba, six hundred and twenty-one.
7:30|KJV|The men of Ramah and Gaba, six hundred twenty and one.
7:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|拉瑪人和迦巴人共六百二十一名；
7:31|ASV|The men of Michmas, a hundred and twenty and two.
7:31|Darby|The men of Michmas, a hundred and twenty-two.
7:31|KJV|The men of Michmas, an hundred and twenty and two.
7:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|默瑪人一百二十二名；
7:32|ASV|The men of Beth-el and Ai, a hundred twenty and three.
7:32|Darby|The men of Bethel and Ai, a hundred and twenty-three.
7:32|KJV|The men of Bethel and Ai, an hundred twenty and three.
7:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|伯特利人和艾人共一百二十三名；
7:33|ASV|The men of the other Nebo, fifty and two.
7:33|Darby|The men of the other Nebo, fifty-two.
7:33|KJV|The men of the other Nebo, fifty and two.
7:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|另一個尼波的人五十二名；
7:34|ASV|The children of the other Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four.
7:34|Darby|The children of the other Elam, a thousand two hundred and  fifty-four.
7:34|KJV|The children of the other Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four.
7:34|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|另一個以攔的子孫一千二百五十四名；
7:35|ASV|The children of Harim, three hundred and twenty.
7:35|Darby|The children of Harim, three hundred and twenty.
7:35|KJV|The children of Harim, three hundred and twenty.
7:35|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈琳的子孫三百二十名；
7:36|ASV|The children of Jericho, three hundred forty and five.
7:36|Darby|The children of Jericho, three hundred and forty-five.
7:36|KJV|The children of Jericho, three hundred forty and five.
7:36|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶利哥人三百四十五名；
7:37|ASV|The children of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred twenty and one.
7:37|Darby|The children of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred and  twenty-one.
7:37|KJV|The children of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred twenty and one.
7:37|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|羅德人、哈第人、阿挪人共七百二十一名；
7:38|ASV|The children of Senaah, three thousand nine hundred and thirty.
7:38|Darby|The children of Senaah, three thousand nine hundred and  thirty.
7:38|KJV|The children of Senaah, three thousand nine hundred and thirty.
7:38|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|西拿人三千九百三十名。
7:39|ASV|The priests: The children of Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred seventy and three.
7:39|Darby|The priests: the children of Jedaiah, of the house of  Jeshua, nine hundred and seventy-three.
7:39|KJV|The priests: the children of Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred seventy and three.
7:39|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祭司的數目記在下面：耶書亞家耶大雅的子孫九百七十三名；
7:40|ASV|The children of Immer, a thousand fifty and two.
7:40|Darby|The children of Immer, a thousand and fifty-two.
7:40|KJV|The children of Immer, a thousand fifty and two.
7:40|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|音麥的子孫一千零五十二名；
7:41|ASV|The children of Pashhur, a thousand two hundred forty and seven.
7:41|Darby|The children of Pashhur, a thousand two hundred and  forty-seven.
7:41|KJV|The children of Pashur, a thousand two hundred forty and seven.
7:41|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|巴施戶珥的子孫一千二百四十七名；
7:42|ASV|The children of Harim, a thousand and seventeen.
7:42|Darby|The children of Harim, a thousand and seventeen.
7:42|KJV|The children of Harim, a thousand and seventeen.
7:42|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈琳的子孫一千零一十七名。
7:43|ASV|The Levites: the children of Jeshua, of Kadmiel, of the children of Hodevah, seventy and four.
7:43|Darby|The Levites: the children of Jeshua [and] of Kadmiel, of  the children of Hodvah, seventy-four.
7:43|KJV|The Levites: the children of Jeshua, of Kadmiel, and of the children of Hodevah, seventy and four.
7:43|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|利未人有耶書亞和甲篾的子孫，屬何達威雅子孫的，共七十四名。
7:44|ASV|The singers: the children of Asaph, a hundred forty and eight.
7:44|Darby|The singers: the children of Asaph, a hundred and  forty-eight.
7:44|KJV|The singers: the children of Asaph, an hundred forty and eight.
7:44|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|歌唱的有亞薩的子孫一百四十八名。
7:45|ASV|The porters: the children of Shallum, the children of Ater, the children of Talmon, the children of Akkub, the children of Hatita, the children of Shobai, a hundred thirty and eight.
7:45|Darby|The doorkeepers: the children of Shallum, the children of  Ater, the children of Talmon, the children of Akkub, the  children of Hatita, the children of Shobai, a hundred and  thirty-eight.
7:45|KJV|The porters: the children of Shallum, the children of Ater, the children of Talmon, the children of Akkub, the children of Hatita, the children of Shobai, an hundred thirty and eight.
7:45|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|守門的有沙龍的子孫、亞特的子孫、達們的子孫、亞谷的子孫、哈底大的子孫、朔拜的子孫，共一百三十八名。
7:46|ASV|The Nethinim: the children of Ziha, the children of Hasupha, the children of Tabbaoth,
7:46|Darby|The Nethinim: the children of Ziha, the children of  Hasupha, the children of Tabbaoth,
7:46|KJV|The Nethinims: the children of Ziha, the children of Hashupha, the children of Tabbaoth,
7:46|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|殿役有西哈的子孫、哈蘇巴的子孫、答巴俄的子孫、
7:47|ASV|the children of Keros, the children of Sia, the children of Padon,
7:47|Darby|the children of Keros, the children of Sia, the children of  Padon,
7:47|KJV|The children of Keros, the children of Sia, the children of Padon,
7:47|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|基綠的子孫、西亞的子孫、巴頓的子孫、
7:48|ASV|the children of Lebana, the children of Hagaba, the children of Salmai,
7:48|Darby|the children of Lebana, the children of Hagaba, the  children of Salmai,
7:48|KJV|The children of Lebana, the children of Hagaba, the children of Shalmai,
7:48|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|利巴拿的子孫、哈迦巴的子孫、薩買的子孫、
7:49|ASV|the children of Hanan, the children of Giddel, the children of Gahar,
7:49|Darby|the children of Hanan, the children of Giddel, the children  of Gahar,
7:49|KJV|The children of Hanan, the children of Giddel, the children of Gahar,
7:49|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈難的子孫、吉德的子孫、迦哈的子孫、
7:50|ASV|the children of Reaiah, the children of Rezin, the children of Nekoda,
7:50|Darby|the children of Reaiah, the children of Rezin, the children  of Nekoda,
7:50|KJV|The children of Reaiah, the children of Rezin, the children of Nekoda,
7:50|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|利亞雅的子孫、利汛的子孫、尼哥大的子孫、
7:51|ASV|the children of Gazzam, the children of Uzza, the children of Paseah.
7:51|Darby|the children of Gazzam, the children of Uzza, the children  of Phaseah,
7:51|KJV|The children of Gazzam, the children of Uzza, the children of Phaseah,
7:51|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|迦散的子孫、烏撒的子孫、巴西亞的子孫、
7:52|ASV|The children of Besai, the children of Meunim, the children of Nephushesim,
7:52|Darby|the children of Besai, the children of Meunim, the children  of Nephishesim,
7:52|KJV|The children of Besai, the children of Meunim, the children of Nephishesim,
7:52|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|比賽的子孫、米烏寧的子孫、尼普心的子孫、
7:53|ASV|the children of Bakbuk, the children of Hakupha, the children of Harhur,
7:53|Darby|the children of Bakbuk, the children of Hakupha, the  children of Harhur,
7:53|KJV|The children of Bakbuk, the children of Hakupha, the children of Harhur,
7:53|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|巴卜的子孫、哈古巴的子孫、哈忽的子孫、
7:54|ASV|the children of Bazlith, the children of Mehida, the children of Harsha,
7:54|Darby|the children of Bazlith, the children of Mehida, the  children of Harsha,
7:54|KJV|The children of Bazlith, the children of Mehida, the children of Harsha,
7:54|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|巴洗律的子孫、米希大的子孫、哈沙的子孫、
7:55|ASV|the children of Barkos, the children of Sisera, the children of Temah,
7:55|Darby|the children of Barkos, the children of Sisera, the  children of Thamah,
7:55|KJV|The children of Barkos, the children of Sisera, the children of Tamah,
7:55|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|巴柯的子孫、西西拉的子孫、答瑪的子孫、
7:56|ASV|the children of Neziah, the children of Hatipha.
7:56|Darby|the children of Neziah, the children of Hatipha.
7:56|KJV|The children of Neziah, the children of Hatipha.
7:56|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|尼細亞的子孫、哈提法的子孫。
7:57|ASV|The children of Solomon's servants: the children of Sotai, the children of Sophereth, the children of Perida,
7:57|Darby|The children of Solomon's servants: the children of Sotai,  the children of Sophereth, the children of Perida,
7:57|KJV|The children of Solomon's servants: the children of Sotai, the children of Sophereth, the children of Perida,
7:57|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所羅門僕人的子孫有瑣太的子孫、瑣斐列的子孫、比路大的子孫、
7:58|ASV|the children of Jaala, the children of Darkon, the children of Giddel,
7:58|Darby|the children of Jaala, the children of Darkon, the children  of Giddel,
7:58|KJV|The children of Jaala, the children of Darkon, the children of Giddel,
7:58|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|雅拉的子孫、達昆的子孫、吉德的子孫、
7:59|ASV|the children of Shephatiah, the children of Hattil, the children of Pochereth-hazzebaim, the children of Amon.
7:59|Darby|the children of Shephatiah, the children of Hattil, the  children of Pochereth-Hazzebaim, the children of Amon.
7:59|KJV|The children of Shephatiah, the children of Hattil, the children of Pochereth of Zebaim, the children of Amon.
7:59|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|示法提雅的子孫、哈替的子孫、玻黑列哈斯巴音的子孫、亞們的子孫。
7:60|ASV|All the Nethinim, and the children of Solomon's servants, were three hundred ninety and two.
7:60|Darby|All the Nethinim, and the children of Solomon's servants,  three hundred and ninety-two.
7:60|KJV|All the Nethinims, and the children of Solomon's servants, were three hundred ninety and two.
7:60|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|殿役和所羅門僕人的子孫共三百九十二名。
7:61|ASV|And these were they that went up from Tel-melah, Tel-harsha, Cherub, Addon, and Immer; but they could not show their fathers' houses, nor their seed, whether they were of Israel:
7:61|Darby|And these are they that went up from Tel-melah, Tel-harsha,  Cherub-Addon and Immer; but they could not shew their father's  house, nor their seed, whether they were of Israel.
7:61|KJV|And these were they which went up also from Telmelah, Telharesha, Cherub, Addon, and Immer: but they could not shew their father's house, nor their seed, whether they were of Israel.
7:61|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|從特米拉、特哈薩、基綠、亞頓、音麥上來，卻不能指明他們的宗族和世系是不是以色列人的，記在下面：
7:62|ASV|The children of Delaiah, the children of Tobiah, the children of Nekoda, six hundred forty and two.
7:62|Darby|The children of Delaiah, the children of Tobijah, the  children of Nekoda, six hundred and forty-two.
7:62|KJV|The children of Delaiah, the children of Tobiah, the children of Nekoda, six hundred forty and two.
7:62|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|第來雅的子孫、多比雅的子孫、尼哥大的子孫，共六百四十二名。
7:63|ASV|And of the priests: the children of Hobaiah, the children of Hakkoz, the children of Barzillai, who took a wife of the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite, and was called after their name.
7:63|Darby|And of the priests: the children of Hobaiah, the children  of Koz, the children of Barzillai, who took a wife of the  daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite and was called after their  name.
7:63|KJV|And of the priests: the children of Habaiah, the children of Koz, the children of Barzillai, which took one of the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite to wife, and was called after their name.
7:63|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祭司中有哈巴雅的子孫、哈哥斯的子孫、和巴西萊的子孫；巴西萊因娶了基列人巴西萊的女兒為妻，所以按其名叫巴西萊。
7:64|ASV|These sought their register among those that were reckoned by genealogy, but it was not found: therefore were they deemed polluted and put from the priesthood.
7:64|Darby|These sought their genealogical register, but it was not  found; therefore were they, as polluted, removed from the  priesthood.
7:64|KJV|These sought their register among those that were reckoned by genealogy, but it was not found: therefore were they, as polluted, put from the priesthood.
7:64|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些人在家譜的記載中尋查自己的記錄，卻尋不著，因此算為不潔，不准供祭司的職任。
7:65|ASV|And the governor said unto them, that they should not eat of the most holy things, till there stood up a priest with Urim and Thummim.
7:65|Darby|And the Tirshatha said to them that they should not eat of  the most holy things, till there stood up the priest with Urim  and Thummim.
7:65|KJV|And the Tirshatha said unto them, that they should not eat of the most holy things, till there stood up a priest with Urim and Thummim.
7:65|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|省長對他們說，不可喫至聖的物，直到有用烏陵和土明決疑的祭司興起來。
7:66|ASV|The whole assembly together was forty and two thousand three hundred and threescore,
7:66|Darby|The whole congregation together was forty-two thousand  three hundred and sixty,
7:66|KJV|The whole congregation together was forty and two thousand three hundred and threescore,
7:66|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|全會眾共有四萬二千三百六十名。
7:67|ASV|besides their men-servants and their maid-servants, of whom there were seven thousand three hundred thirty and seven: and they had two hundred forty and five singing men and singing women.
7:67|Darby|besides their servants and their maids, of whom there were  seven thousand three hundred and thirty-seven; and they had two  hundred and forty-five singing-men and singing-women.
7:67|KJV|Beside their manservants and their maidservants, of whom there were seven thousand three hundred thirty and seven: and they had two hundred forty and five singing men and singing women.
7:67|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|此外，還有他們的僕婢七千三百三十七名，又有歌唱的男女二百四十五名。
7:68|ASV|Their horses were seven hundred thirty and six; their mules, two hundred forty and five;
7:68|Darby|Their horses were seven hundred and thirty-six; their  mules, two hundred and forty-five;
7:68|KJV|Their horses, seven hundred thirty and six: their mules, two hundred forty and five:
7:68|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們有馬七百三十六匹，騾二百四十五匹，
7:69|ASV|their camels, four hundred thirty and five; their asses, six thousand seven hundred and twenty.
7:69|Darby|the camels, four hundred and thirty-five; the asses, six  thousand seven hundred and twenty.
7:69|KJV|Their camels, four hundred thirty and five: six thousand seven hundred and twenty asses.
7:69|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|駱駝四百三十五隻，驢六千七百二十匹。
7:70|ASV|And some from among the heads of fathers' houses gave unto the work. The governor gave to the treasury a thousand darics of gold, fifty basins, five hundred and thirty priests' garments.
7:70|Darby|And some of the chief fathers gave to the work. The  Tirshatha gave to the treasure a thousand darics of gold, fifty  basons, five hundred and thirty priests' coats.
7:70|KJV|And some of the chief of the fathers gave unto the work. The Tirshatha gave to the treasure a thousand drams of gold, fifty basons, five hundred and thirty priests' garments.
7:70|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有些宗族的首領為工程捐助。省長捐入庫中的有金子一千達利克，碗五十個，祭司的禮服五百三十件。
7:71|ASV|And some of the heads of fathers' houses gave into the treasury of the work twenty thousand darics of gold, and two thousand and two hundred pounds of silver.
7:71|Darby|And [some] of the chief fathers gave to the treasure of the  work twenty thousand darics of gold, and two thousand two  hundred pounds of silver.
7:71|KJV|And some of the chief of the fathers gave to the treasure of the work twenty thousand drams of gold, and two thousand and two hundred pound of silver.
7:71|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|宗族的首領捐入工程庫的有金子二萬達利克，銀子二千二百彌拿。
7:72|ASV|And that which the rest of the people gave was twenty thousand darics of gold, and two thousand pounds of silver, and threescore and seven priests' garments.
7:72|Darby|And that which the rest of the people gave was twenty  thousand darics of gold, and two thousand pounds of silver, and  sixty-seven priests' coats.
7:72|KJV|And that which the rest of the people gave was twenty thousand drams of gold, and two thousand pound of silver, and threescore and seven priests' garments.
7:72|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其餘百姓所捐的有金子二萬達利克，銀子二千彌拿，祭司的禮服六十七件。
7:73<version name="ASV">So the priests, and the Levites, and the porters, and the singers, and some of the people, and the Nethinim, and all Israel, dwelt in their cities. And when the seventh month was come, the children of Israel were in their cities. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:73<version name="Darby">And the priests, and the Levites, and the doorkeepers, and  the singers, and [some] of the people, and the Nethinim, and  all Israel, dwelt in their cities. And when the seventh month  came, and the children of Israel were in their cities, </p><p /><br /></version>
7:73<version name="KJV">So the priests, and the Levites, and the porters, and the singers, and some of the people, and the Nethinims, and all Israel, dwelt in their cities; and when the seventh month came, the children of Israel were in their cities.</p><p /><br /></version>
7:73|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是祭司、利未人、守門的、歌唱的、民中的一些人、殿役、並以色列眾人，都住在自己的城堙C七月到了，以色列人住在自己的城堙C
8:1|ASV|And all the people gathered themselves together as one man into the broad place that was before the water gate; and they spake unto Ezra the scribe to bring the book of the law of Moses, which Jehovah had commanded to Israel.
8:1|Darby|all the people gathered together as one man to the open  place that was before the water-gate; and they spoke to Ezra  the scribe to bring the book of the law of Moses, which Jehovah  had commanded Israel.
8:1|KJV|And all the people gathered themselves together as one man into the street that was before the water gate; and they spake unto Ezra the scribe to bring the book of the law of Moses, which the LORD had commanded to Israel.
8:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|眾民如同一人，聚集在水門前的寬闊處，請經學家以斯拉將摩西的律法書帶來，這律法是耶和華吩咐以色列人遵守的。
8:2|ASV|And Ezra the priest brought the law before the assembly, both men and women, and all that could hear with understanding, upon the first day of the seventh month.
8:2|Darby|And Ezra the priest brought the law before the congregation,  both of men and women, and all that could hear with  understanding, on the first day of the seventh month.
8:2|KJV|And Ezra the priest brought the law before the congregation both of men and women, and all that could hear with understanding, upon the first day of the seventh month.
8:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|七月初一日，祭司以斯拉將律法書帶到男女會眾、並一切聽了能明白的人面前。
8:3|ASV|And he read therein before the broad place that was before the water gate from early morning until midday, in the presence of the men and the women, and of those that could understand; and the ears of all the people were attentive unto the book of the law.
8:3|Darby|And he read in it before the open place that was before the  water-gate from the morning until midday, in presence of the  men and the women, and those that could understand. And the  ears of all the people were [attentive] to the book of the law.
8:3|KJV|And he read therein before the street that was before the water gate from the morning until midday, before the men and the women, and those that could understand; and the ears of all the people were attentive unto the book of the law.
8:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他在水門前的寬闊處，從清早到晌午，在眾男女，並一切聽了能明白的人面前念這律法書。眾民側耳而聽。
8:4|ASV|And Ezra the scribe stood upon a pulpit of wood, which they had made for the purpose; and beside him stood Mattithiah, and Shema, and Anaiah, and Uriah, and Hilkiah, and Maaseiah, on his right hand; and on his left hand, Pedaiah, and Mishael, and Malchijah, and Hashum, and Hashbaddanah, Zechariah, and Meshullam.
8:4|Darby|And Ezra the scribe stood upon a high stage of wood, which  they had made for the purpose. And beside him stood Mattithiah,  and Shema, and Anaiah, and Urijah, and Hilkijah, and Maaseiah  on his right hand; and on his left hand, Pedaiah, and Mishael,  and Malchijah, and Hashum, and Hashbaddana, Zechariah,  Meshullam.
8:4|KJV|And Ezra the scribe stood upon a pulpit of wood, which they had made for the purpose; and beside him stood Mattithiah, and Shema, and Anaiah, and Urijah, and Hilkiah, and Maaseiah, on his right hand; and on his left hand, Pedaiah, and Mishael, and Malchiah, and Hashum, and Hashbadana, Zechariah, and Meshullam.
8:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|經學家以斯拉站在為這事特製的木臺上；瑪他提雅、示瑪、亞奈雅、烏利亞、希勒家、和瑪西雅站在他的右邊；毘大雅、米沙利、瑪基雅、哈順、哈拔大拿、撒迦利亞、和米書蘭站在他的左邊。
8:5|ASV|And Ezra opened the book in the sight of all the people; (for he was above all the people;) and when he opened it, all the people stood up:
8:5|Darby|And Ezra opened the book in the sight of all the people, for  he was above all the people; and when he opened it, all the  people stood up.
8:5|KJV|And Ezra opened the book in the sight of all the people; (for he was above all the people;) and when he opened it, all the people stood up:
8:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以斯拉站在眾民以上，在眾民眼前展開這書；他一展開，眾民就都站起來。
8:6|ASV|and Ezra blessed Jehovah, the great God. And all the people answered, Amen, Amen, with the lifting up of their hands: and they bowed their heads, and worshipped Jehovah with their faces to the ground.
8:6|Darby|And Ezra blessed Jehovah, the great God; and all the people  answered, Amen, Amen! with lifting up of their hands; and they  bowed their heads, and worshipped Jehovah with their faces to  the ground.
8:6|KJV|And Ezra blessed the LORD, the great God. And all the people answered, Amen, Amen, with lifting up their hands: and they bowed their heads, and worshipped the LORD with their faces to the ground.
8:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以斯拉頌讚耶和華至大的神；眾民都舉手應聲說，阿們，阿們；就低頭，面伏於地，敬拜耶和華。
8:7|ASV|Also Jeshua, and Bani, and Sherebiah, Jamin, Akkub, Shabbethai, Hodiah, Maaseiah, Kelita, Azariah, Jozabad, Hanan, Pelaiah, and the Levites, caused the people to understand the law: and the people stood in their place.
8:7|Darby|And Jeshua, and Bani, and Sherebiah, Jamin, Akkub,  Shabbethai, Hodijah, Maaseiah, Kelita, Azariah, Jozabad, Hanan,  Pelaiah, and the Levites, caused the people to understand the  law; and the people [stood] in their place.
8:7|KJV|Also Jeshua, and Bani, and Sherebiah, Jamin, Akkub, Shabbethai, Hodijah, Maaseiah, Kelita, Azariah, Jozabad, Hanan, Pelaiah, and the Levites, caused the people to understand the law: and the people stood in their place.
8:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶書亞、巴尼、示利比、雅憫、亞谷、沙比太、荷第雅、瑪西雅、基利他、亞撒利雅、約撒拔、哈難、毘萊雅、和利未人，幫助百姓明白律法；百姓都站在自己的地方。
8:8|ASV|And they read in the book, in the law of God, distinctly; and they gave the sense, so that they understood the reading.
8:8|Darby|And they read in the law of God distinctly out of the book,  and gave the sense, and caused [them] to understand the  reading.
8:8|KJV|So they read in the book in the law of God distinctly, and gave the sense, and caused them to understand the reading.
8:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們念神的律法書，繙譯並講明意思，使百姓明白所念的。
8:9|ASV|And Nehemiah, who was the governor, and Ezra the priest the scribe, and the Levites that taught the people, said unto all the people, This day is holy unto Jehovah your God; mourn not, nor weep. For all the people wept, when they heard the words of the law.
8:9|Darby|And Nehemiah, that is, the Tirshatha, and Ezra the priest  the scribe, and the Levites that explained to the people, said  to all the people, This day is holy to Jehovah your God: mourn  not, nor weep. For all the people wept when they heard the  words of the law.
8:9|KJV|And Nehemiah, which is the Tirshatha, and Ezra the priest the scribe, and the Levites that taught the people, said unto all the people, This day is holy unto the LORD your God; mourn not, nor weep. For all the people wept, when they heard the words of the law.
8:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|省長尼希米和作祭司的經學家以斯拉，並幫助百姓明白的利未人，對眾民說，今日是耶和華你們神的聖日，不要悲哀哭泣。這是因為眾民聽見律法書上的話都哭了。
8:10|ASV|Then he said unto them, Go your way, eat the fat, and drink the sweet, and send portions unto him for whom nothing is prepared; for this day is holy unto our Lord: neither be ye grieved; for the joy of Jehovah is your strength.
8:10|Darby|And he said to them, Go your way, eat the fat, and drink  the sweet, and send portions to them for whom nothing is  prepared; for the day is holy to our Lord; and be not grieved,  for the joy of Jehovah is your strength.
8:10|KJV|Then he said unto them, Go your way, eat the fat, and drink the sweet, and send portions unto them for whom nothing is prepared: for this day is holy unto our LORD: neither be ye sorry; for the joy of the LORD is your strength.
8:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他又對他們說，你們去喫肥美的，喝甘甜的，有不能豫備的就分給他，因為今日是我們主的聖日。你們不要憂愁，因耶和華的喜樂是你們的力量。
8:11|ASV|So the Levites stilled all the people, saying, Hold your peace, for the day is holy; neither be ye grieved.
8:11|Darby|And the Levites quieted all the people, saying, Be still!  for the day is holy; neither be grieved.
8:11|KJV|So the Levites stilled all the people, saying, Hold your peace, for the day is holy; neither be ye grieved.
8:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是利未人使眾民靜默，說，不要作聲，因今日是聖日；也不要憂愁。
8:12|ASV|And all the people went their way to eat, and to drink, and to send portions, and to make great mirth, because they had understood the words that were declared unto them.
8:12|Darby|And all the people went their way, to eat and to drink, and  to send portions, and to make great rejoicing. For they had  understood the words that were declared to them.
8:12|KJV|And all the people went their way to eat, and to drink, and to send portions, and to make great mirth, because they had understood the words that were declared unto them.
8:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|眾民都去喫喝，也分給人，大大快樂，因為他們明白所指示他們的話。
8:13|ASV|And on the second day were gathered together the heads of fathers' houses of all the people, the priests, and the Levites, unto Ezra the scribe, even to give attention to the words of the law.
8:13|Darby|And on the second day were gathered together the chief  fathers of all the people, the priests, and the Levites, to  Ezra the scribe, even to gain wisdom as to the words of the  law.
8:13|KJV|And on the second day were gathered together the chief of the fathers of all the people, the priests, and the Levites, unto Ezra the scribe, even to understand the words of the law.
8:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|次日，眾民宗族的首領、祭司、和利未人，都聚集到經學家以斯拉那堙A要深入領略律法書上的話。
8:14|ASV|And they found written in the law, how that Jehovah had commanded by Moses, that the children of Israel should dwell in booths in the feast of the seventh month;
8:14|Darby|And they found written in the law which Jehovah had  commanded through Moses, that the children of Israel should  dwell in booths in the feast of the seventh month,
8:14|KJV|And they found written in the law which the LORD had commanded by Moses, that the children of Israel should dwell in booths in the feast of the seventh month:
8:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們見律法上寫著，耶和華藉摩西吩咐以色列人要在七月節住棚，
8:15|ASV|and that they should publish and proclaim in all their cities, and in Jerusalem, saying, Go forth unto the mount, and fetch olive branches, and branches of wild olive, and myrtle branches, and palm branches, and branches of thick trees, to make booths, as it is written.
8:15|Darby|and that they should publish and proclaim through all their  cities, and at Jerusalem, saying, Go forth to the mount, and  fetch olive-branches, and wild olive-branches, and  myrtle-branches, and palm-branches, and branches of thick  trees, to make booths, as it is written.
8:15|KJV|And that they should publish and proclaim in all their cities, and in Jerusalem, saying, Go forth unto the mount, and fetch olive branches, and pine branches, and myrtle branches, and palm branches, and branches of thick trees, to make booths, as it is written.
8:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並要在各城和耶路撒冷宣揚傳佈說，你們當上山去，將橄欖樹、野橄欖樹、番石榴樹、棕樹、和各樣茂密樹的枝葉取來，照著所寫的搭棚。
8:16|ASV|So the people went forth, and brought them, and made themselves booths, every one upon the roof of his house, and in their courts, and in the courts of the house of God, and in the broad place of the water gate, and in the broad place of the gate of Ephraim.
8:16|Darby|And the people went forth and brought [them], and made  themselves booths, everyone upon the roof of his house, and in  their courts, and in the courts of the house of God, and in the  open space of the water-gate, and in the open space of the gate  of Ephraim.
8:16|KJV|So the people went forth, and brought them, and made themselves booths, every one upon the roof of his house, and in their courts, and in the courts of the house of God, and in the street of the water gate, and in the street of the gate of Ephraim.
8:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是百姓出去，取了樹枝來，各人在自己的房頂上，或院內，或神殿的院內，或水門的寬闊處，或以法蓮門的寬闊處搭棚。
8:17|ASV|And all the assembly of them that were come again out of the captivity made booths, and dwelt in the booths; for since the days of Jeshua the son of Nun unto that day had not the children of Israel done so. And there was very great gladness.
8:17|Darby|And all the congregation of them that had come back from  the captivity made booths, and dwelt in the booths. For since  the days of Jeshua the son of Nun until that day had not the  children of Israel done so. And there was very great gladness.
8:17|KJV|And all the congregation of them that were come again out of the captivity made booths, and sat under the booths: for since the days of Jeshua the son of Nun unto that day had not the children of Israel done so. And there was very great gladness.
8:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|被擄歸回的全會眾就搭棚，住在棚堙C從嫩的兒子約書亞的日子，直到那日，以色列人沒有這樣行過；於是眾人大大喜樂。
8:18<version name="ASV">Also day by day, from the first day unto the last day, he read in the book of the law of God. And they kept the feast seven days; and on the eighth day was a solemn assembly, according unto the ordinance. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:18<version name="Darby">Also day by day, from the first day to the last day, he  read in the book of the law of God. And they observed the feast  seven days; and on the eighth day was a solemn assembly,  according to the ordinance. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:18<version name="KJV">Also day by day, from the first day unto the last day, he read in the book of the law of God. And they kept the feast seven days; and on the eighth day was a solemn assembly, according unto the manner.</p><p /><br /></version>
8:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|從頭一天直到末一天，以斯拉每日念神的律法書。眾人守節七日，第八日照例有嚴肅會。
9:1|ASV|Now in the twenty and fourth day of this month the children of Israel were assembled with fasting, and with sackcloth, and earth upon them.
9:1|Darby|And on the twenty-fourth day of this month the children of  Israel were assembled with fasting, and with sackclothes, and  earth upon them.
9:1|KJV|Now in the twenty and fourth day of this month the children of Israel were assembled with fasting, and with sackclothes, and earth upon them.
9:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這月二十四日，以色列人聚集禁食，身穿麻衣，頭蒙塵土。
9:2|ASV|And the seed of Israel separated themselves from all foreigners, and stood and confessed their sins, and the iniquities of their fathers.
9:2|Darby|And the seed of Israel separated themselves from all  foreigners, and stood and confessed their sins, and the  iniquities of their fathers.
9:2|KJV|And the seed of Israel separated themselves from all strangers, and stood and confessed their sins, and the iniquities of their fathers.
9:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列的後裔就與一切外邦人離絕，站著承認自己的罪和列祖的罪孽。
9:3|ASV|And they stood up in their place, and read in the book of the law of Jehovah their God a fourth part of the day; and another fourth part they confessed, and worshipped Jehovah their God.
9:3|Darby|And they stood up in their place, and read in the book of  the law of Jehovah their God a fourth part of the day; and a  fourth part they confessed, and worshipped Jehovah their God.
9:3|KJV|And they stood up in their place, and read in the book of the law of the LORD their God one fourth part of the day; and another fourth part they confessed, and worshipped the LORD their God.
9:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那日四分之一的時間，他們站在自己的地方念耶和華他們神的律法書；又四分之一的時間，他們認罪並敬拜耶和華他們的神。
9:4|ASV|Then stood up upon the stairs of the Levites, Jeshua, and Bani, Kadmiel, Shebaniah, Bunni, Sherebiah, Bani, and Chenani, and cried with a loud voice unto Jehovah their God.
9:4|Darby|Then stood up upon the platform of the Levites, Jeshua, and  Bani, Kadmiel, Shebaniah, Bunni, Sherebiah, Bani, Chenani, and  cried with a loud voice to Jehovah their God.
9:4|KJV|Then stood up upon the stairs, of the Levites, Jeshua, and Bani, Kadmiel, Shebaniah, Bunni, Sherebiah, Bani, and Chenani, and cried with a loud voice unto the LORD their God.
9:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶書亞、巴尼、甲篾、示巴尼、布尼、示利比、巴尼、基拿尼，站在利未人的臺上，大聲哀求耶和華他們的神。
9:5|ASV|Then the Levites, Jeshua, and Kadmiel, Bani, Hashabneiah, Sherebiah, Hodiah, Shebaniah, and Pethahiah, said, Stand up and bless Jehovah your God from everlasting to everlasting; and blessed be thy glorious name, which is exalted above all blessing and praise.
9:5|Darby|And the Levites, Jeshua, and Kadmiel, Bani, Hashabniah,  Sherebiah, Hodijah, Shebaniah, Pethahiah, said, Stand up, bless  Jehovah your God from eternity to eternity. And let [men] bless  the name of thy glory, which is exalted above all blessing and  praise.
9:5|KJV|Then the Levites, Jeshua, and Kadmiel, Bani, Hashabniah, Sherebiah, Hodijah, Shebaniah, and Pethahiah, said, Stand up and bless the LORD your God for ever and ever: and blessed be thy glorious name, which is exalted above all blessing and praise.
9:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|利未人耶書亞、甲篾、巴尼、哈沙尼、示利比、荷第雅、示巴尼、毘他希雅說，你們要站起來，頌讚耶和華，祂從亙古到永遠是你們的神：耶和華阿，你榮耀的名是當受頌讚的，當被高舉超越一切頌讚和讚美。
9:6|ASV|Thou art Jehovah, even thou alone; thou hast made heaven, the heaven of heavens, with all their host, the earth and all things that are thereon, the seas and all that is in them, and thou preservest them all; and the host of heaven worshippeth thee.
9:6|Darby|Thou art the Same, thou alone, Jehovah, who hast made the  heaven of heavens, and all their host, the earth and all that  is therein, the seas and all that is therein. And thou  quickenest them all; and the host of heaven worshippeth thee.
9:6|KJV|Thou, even thou, art LORD alone; thou hast made heaven, the heaven of heavens, with all their host, the earth, and all things that are therein, the seas, and all that is therein, and thou preservest them all; and the host of heaven worshippeth thee.
9:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你，惟獨你是耶和華；你造了天和天上的天，並天上的萬象，地和地上的萬物，海和海中所有的；這一切都是你所保存的；天軍也都敬拜你。
9:7|ASV|Thou art Jehovah the God, who didst choose Abram, and broughtest him forth out of Ur of the Chaldees, and gavest him the name of Abraham,
9:7|Darby|Thou art the Same, Jehovah Elohim, who didst choose Abram  and broughtest him forth out of Ur of the Chaldees, and gavest  him the name of Abraham;
9:7|KJV|Thou art the LORD the God, who didst choose Abram, and broughtest him forth out of Ur of the Chaldees, and gavest him the name of Abraham;
9:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你是耶和華神，曾揀選亞伯蘭，領他出迦勒底的吾珥，給他起名叫亞伯拉罕。
9:8|ASV|and foundest his heart faithful before thee, and madest a covenant with him to give the land of the Canaanite, the Hittite, the Amorite, and the Perizzite, and the Jebusite, and the Girgashite, to give it unto his seed, and hast performed thy words; for thou art righteous.
9:8|Darby|and foundest his heart faithful before thee, and madest the  covenant with him to give the land of the Canaanites, the  Hittites, the Amorites, and the Perizzites, and the Jebusites,  and the Girgashites, -- to give it to his seed; and thou hast  performed thy words, for thou art righteous.
9:8|KJV|And foundest his heart faithful before thee, and madest a covenant with him to give the land of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Amorites, and the Perizzites, and the Jebusites, and the Girgashites, to give it, I say, to his seed, and hast performed thy words; for thou art righteous:
9:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你見他在你面前心堜儕H，就與他立約，要把迦南人、赫人、亞摩利人、比利洗人、耶布斯人、革迦撒人之地賜給他，賜給他的後裔。你應驗了你的應許，因為你是公義的。
9:9|ASV|And thou sawest the affliction of our fathers in Egypt, and heardest their cry by the Red Sea,
9:9|Darby|And thou sawest the affliction of our fathers in Egypt, and  heardest their cry by the Red Sea;
9:9|KJV|And didst see the affliction of our fathers in Egypt, and heardest their cry by the Red sea;
9:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你看見我們列祖在埃及所受的困苦，垂聽他們在紅海邊的哀求，
9:10|ASV|and showedst signs and wonders upon Pharaoh, and on all his servants, and on all the people of his land; for thou knewest that they dealt proudly against them, and didst get thee a name, as it is this day.
9:10|Darby|and didst shew signs and wonders upon Pharaoh, and upon all  his servants, and upon all the people of his land; for thou  knewest that they dealt proudly against them, and thou didst  make thee a name, as it is this day.
9:10|KJV|And shewedst signs and wonders upon Pharaoh, and on all his servants, and on all the people of his land: for thou knewest that they dealt proudly against them. So didst thou get thee a name, as it is this day.
9:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就施行神蹟和奇事在法老和他一切臣僕，並他那地的眾民身上；因為你知道他們向我們列祖行事狂傲；你也使自己得了名聲，正如今日一樣。
9:11|ASV|And thou didst divide the sea before them, so that they went through the midst of the sea on the dry land; and their pursuers thou didst cast into the depths, as a stone into the mighty waters.
9:11|Darby|And thou didst divide the sea before them, and they went  through the midst of the sea on dry [ground]; and their  pursuers thou threwest into the depths, as a stone into the  mighty waters.
9:11|KJV|And thou didst divide the sea before them, so that they went through the midst of the sea on the dry land; and their persecutors thou threwest into the deeps, as a stone into the mighty waters.
9:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你又在我們列祖面前把海分開，使他們在海中乾地上走過；卻將追趕他們的人拋在深海，如石頭拋在大水中。
9:12|ASV|Moreover in a pillar of cloud thou leddest them by day; and in a pillar of fire by night, to give them light in the way wherein they should go.
9:12|Darby|And thou leddest them in the day by a pillar of cloud, and  in the night by a pillar of fire, to give them light in the way  wherein they should go.
9:12|KJV|Moreover thou leddest them in the day by a cloudy pillar; and in the night by a pillar of fire, to give them light in the way wherein they should go.
9:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你日間在雲柱中引導他們，夜間在火柱中照亮他們當行的路。
9:13|ASV|Thou camest down also upon mount Sinai, and spakest with them from heaven, and gavest them right ordinances and true laws, good statutes and commandments,
9:13|Darby|And thou camest down on mount Sinai, and didst speak with  them from the heavens, and gavest them right judgments and true  laws, good statutes and commandments.
9:13|KJV|Thou camest down also upon mount Sinai, and spakest with them from heaven, and gavest them right judgments, and true laws, good statutes and commandments:
9:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你也降臨在西乃山，從天上與他們說話，賜給他們公正的典章、真實的律法、美好的律例和誡命，
9:14|ASV|and madest known unto them thy holy sabbath, and commandedst them commandments, and statutes, and a law, by Moses thy servant,
9:14|Darby|And thou madest known unto them thy holy sabbath, and  prescribedst for them commandments and statutes and a law,  through Moses thy servant.
9:14|KJV|And madest known unto them thy holy sabbath, and commandedst them precepts, statutes, and laws, by the hand of Moses thy servant:
9:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又使他們知道你的聖安息日，並藉你僕人摩西吩咐他們遵行誡命、律例和律法。
9:15|ASV|and gavest them bread from heaven for their hunger, and broughtest forth water for them out of the rock for their thirst, and commandedst them that they should go in to possess the land which thou hadst sworn to give them.
9:15|Darby|And thou gavest them bread from the heavens for their  hunger, and broughtest forth water for them out of the rock for  their thirst, and didst say to them that they should go in to  possess the land which thou hadst sworn to give them.
9:15|KJV|And gavest them bread from heaven for their hunger, and broughtest forth water for them out of the rock for their thirst, and promisedst them that they should go in to possess the land which thou hadst sworn to give them.
9:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你從天上賜下糧食充他們的飢，從磐石使水流出解他們的渴；又叫他們進去得你起誓賜給他們的地。
9:16|ASV|But they and our fathers dealt proudly and hardened their neck, and hearkened not to thy commandments,
9:16|Darby|But they, our fathers, dealt proudly, and hardened their  neck, and hearkened not to thy commandments,
9:16|KJV|But they and our fathers dealt proudly, and hardened their necks, and hearkened not to thy commandments,
9:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但他們，就是我們的列祖，行事狂傲，硬著頸項不聽從你的誡命；
9:17|ASV|and refused to obey, neither were mindful of thy wonders that thou didst among them, but hardened their neck, and in their rebellion appointed a captain to return to their bondage. But thou art a God ready to pardon, gracious and merciful, slow to anger, and abundant in lovingkindness, and forsookest them not.
9:17|Darby|and refused to obey, neither were they mindful of thy  wonders which thou hadst done among them; but hardened their  neck, and in their rebellion made a captain to return to their  bondage. But thou art a +God ready to forgive, gracious and  merciful, slow to anger and of great loving-kindness, and thou  forsookest them not.
9:17|KJV|And refused to obey, neither were mindful of thy wonders that thou didst among them; but hardened their necks, and in their rebellion appointed a captain to return to their bondage: but thou art a God ready to pardon, gracious and merciful, slow to anger, and of great kindness, and forsookest them not.
9:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不肯聽從，也不記念你在他們中間所行的奇事，竟硬著頸項，自立首領，要回埃及去受奴役。但你是樂意饒恕人的神，有恩典，有憐恤，不輕易發怒，有豐盛的慈愛，所以你沒有丟棄他們。
9:18|ASV|Yea, when they had made them a molten calf, and said, This is thy God that brought thee up out of Egypt, and had wrought great provocations;
9:18|Darby|Yea, when they had made them a molten calf, and said, This  is thy god that brought thee up out of Egypt! and they had  wrought great provocation,
9:18|KJV|Yea, when they had made them a molten calf, and said, This is thy God that brought thee up out of Egypt, and had wrought great provocations;
9:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|甚至當他們為自己鑄一隻牛犢，說，這是你的神，就是那領你從埃及上來的，因而大大褻慢了你；
9:19|ASV|yet thou in thy manifold mercies forsookest them not in the wilderness: the pillar of cloud departed not from over them by day, to lead them in the way; neither the pillar of fire by night, to show them light, and the way wherein they should go.
9:19|Darby|yet thou in thy manifold mercies forsookest them not in the  wilderness. The pillar of the cloud departed not from over them  by day, to lead them on the way; neither the pillar of fire by  night, to shew them light, and the way wherein they should go.
9:19|KJV|Yet thou in thy manifold mercies forsookest them not in the wilderness: the pillar of the cloud departed not from them by day, to lead them in the way; neither the pillar of fire by night, to shew them light, and the way wherein they should go.
9:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你還是大施憐恤，沒有把他們丟棄在曠野。日間雲柱沒有離開他們，仍引導他們行路；夜間火柱也沒有離開他們，仍照亮他們當行的路。
9:20|ASV|Thou gavest also thy good Spirit to instruct them, and withheldest not thy manna from their mouth, and gavest them water for their thirst.
9:20|Darby|Thou gavest also thy good Spirit to instruct them, and  withheldest not thy manna from their mouth, and gavest them  water for their thirst.
9:20|KJV|Thou gavest also thy good spirit to instruct them, and withheldest not thy manna from their mouth, and gavest them water for their thirst.
9:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你也賜下你良善的靈指教他們；沒有扣住嗎哪不給他們餬口，並賜水給他們解渴。
9:21|ASV|Yea, forty years didst thou sustain them in the wilderness, and they lacked nothing; their clothes waxed not old, and their feet swelled not.
9:21|Darby|Yea, forty years didst thou sustain them in the wilderness;  they lacked nothing; their clothes grew not old, and their feet  swelled not.
9:21|KJV|Yea, forty years didst thou sustain them in the wilderness, so that they lacked nothing; their clothes waxed not old, and their feet swelled not.
9:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你在曠野四十年供養他們，他們就一無所缺；他們的衣服沒有穿破，腳也沒有走腫。
9:22|ASV|Moreover thou gavest them kingdoms and peoples, which thou didst allot after their portions: so they possessed the land of Sihon, even the land of the king of Heshbon, and the land of Og king of Bashan.
9:22|Darby|And thou gavest them kingdoms and peoples, and didst divide  them by countries; and they possessed the land of Sihon, as  well the land of the king of Heshbon, as the land of Og king of  Bashan.
9:22|KJV|Moreover thou gavest them kingdoms and nations, and didst divide them into corners: so they possessed the land of Sihon, and the land of the king of Heshbon, and the land of Og king of Bashan.
9:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你將列國和諸民賜給他們，將這些分給他們作疆界；他們就得了西宏之地、希實本王之地、和巴珊王噩之地。
9:23|ASV|Their children also multipliedst thou as the stars of heaven, and broughtest them into the land concerning which thou didst say to their fathers, that they should go in to possess it.
9:23|Darby|And their children thou didst multiply as the stars of  heaven, and thou broughtest them into the land concerning which  thou didst say to their fathers that they should go in to  possess it.
9:23|KJV|Their children also multipliedst thou as the stars of heaven, and broughtest them into the land, concerning which thou hadst promised to their fathers, that they should go in to possess it.
9:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你也使他們的子孫繁增，如同天上的星那樣多，帶他們到你所應許他們列祖進入得為業之地。
9:24|ASV|So the children went in and possessed the land, and thou subduedst before them the inhabitants of the land, the Canaanites, and gavest them into their hands, with their kings, and the peoples of the land, that they might do with them as they would.
9:24|Darby|And the children went in and possessed the land; and thou  subduedst before them the inhabitants of the land, the  Canaanites, and gavest them into their hands, both their kings  and the peoples of the land, that they might do with them as  they would.
9:24|KJV|So the children went in and possessed the land, and thou subduedst before them the inhabitants of the land, the Canaanites, and gavest them into their hands, with their kings, and the people of the land, that they might do with them as they would.
9:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們的子孫進去得了那地；你在他們面前制伏那地的居民，就是迦南人；將迦南人和其君王，並那地的諸民，都交在他們手堙A讓他們任意對待。
9:25|ASV|And they took fortified cities, and a fat land, and possessed houses full of all good things, cisterns hewn out, vineyards, and oliveyards, and fruit-trees in abundance: so they did eat, and were filled, and became fat, and delighted themselves in thy great goodness.
9:25|Darby|And they took strong cities, and a fat land, and possessed  houses full of all good things, wells digged, vineyards and  olive-gardens, and fruit trees in abundance. And they did eat  and were filled, and became fat, and delighted themselves in  thy great goodness.
9:25|KJV|And they took strong cities, and a fat land, and possessed houses full of all goods, wells digged, vineyards, and oliveyards, and fruit trees in abundance: so they did eat, and were filled, and became fat, and delighted themselves in thy great goodness.
9:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們攻取了堅固的城邑、肥美的地土，得著了充滿各樣美物的房屋、鑿成的水井、葡萄園、橄欖園、並許多果樹為業；他們就喫而得飽，身體肥胖，因你大大的善待，得以安逸享樂。
9:26|ASV|Nevertheless they were disobedient, and rebelled against thee, and cast thy law behind their back, and slew thy prophets that testified against them to turn them again unto thee, and they wrought great provocations.
9:26|Darby|But they were disobedient, and rebelled against thee, and  cast thy law behind their backs, and slew thy prophets who  testified against them to turn them to thee, and they wrought  great provocations.
9:26|KJV|Nevertheless they were disobedient, and rebelled against thee, and cast thy law behind their backs, and slew thy prophets which testified against them to turn them to thee, and they wrought great provocations.
9:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而，他們竟不順從，背叛了你，將你的律法丟在背後，殺害那些向他們作見證，要使他們歸向你的眾申言者，大大褻慢了你。
9:27|ASV|Therefore thou deliveredst them into the hand of their adversaries, who distressed them: and in the time of their trouble, when they cried unto thee, thou heardest from heaven; and according to thy manifold mercies thou gavest them saviours who saved them out of the hand of their adversaries.
9:27|Darby|And thou gavest them into the hand of their oppressors, and  they oppressed them; and in the time of their distress, when  they cried unto thee, thou heardest them from the heavens, and  according to thy manifold mercies thou gavest them saviours,  who saved them out of the hand of their oppressors.
9:27|KJV|Therefore thou deliveredst them into the hand of their enemies, who vexed them: and in the time of their trouble, when they cried unto thee, thou heardest them from heaven; and according to thy manifold mercies thou gavest them saviours, who saved them out of the hand of their enemies.
9:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以你將他們交在敵人的手中，困迫他們；他們遭困迫的時候哀求你，你就從天上垂聽，照你的大憐恤賜給他們拯救者，救他們脫離敵人的手。
9:28|ASV|But after they had rest, they did evil again before thee; therefore leftest thou them in the hand of their enemies, so that they had the dominion over them: yet when they returned, and cried unto thee, thou heardest from heaven; and many times didst thou deliver them according to thy mercies,
9:28|Darby|But when they had rest, they did evil again before thee;  and thou didst leave them in the hand of their enemies, and  they had dominion over them; and again they cried unto thee,  and thou heardest [them] from the heavens, and many times didst  thou deliver them, according to thy mercies.
9:28|KJV|But after they had rest, they did evil again before thee: therefore leftest thou them in the land of their enemies, so that they had the dominion over them: yet when they returned, and cried unto thee, thou heardest them from heaven; and many times didst thou deliver them according to thy mercies;
9:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但他們得安息之後，又在你面前行惡；你就丟棄他們在仇敵的手中，使仇敵轄制他們。然而他們轉回哀求你，你仍從天上垂聽，屢次照你的憐恤拯救他們。
9:29|ASV|and testifiedst against them, that thou mightest bring them again unto thy law. Yet they dealt proudly, and hearkened not unto thy commandments, but sinned against thine ordinances, (which if a man do, he shall live in them,) and withdrew the shoulder, and hardened their neck, and would not hear.
9:29|Darby|And thou testifiedst against them, that thou mightest bring  them again unto thy law; but they dealt proudly, and hearkened  not unto thy commandments, but sinned against thine ordinances  (which if a man do, he shall live in them); and they withdrew  the shoulder, and hardened their neck, and would not hear.
9:29|KJV|And testifiedst against them, that thou mightest bring them again unto thy law: yet they dealt proudly, and hearkened not unto thy commandments, but sinned against thy judgments, (which if a man do, he shall live in them;) and withdrew the shoulder, and hardened their neck, and would not hear.
9:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你警戒他們，要使他們歸服你的律法；他們卻行事狂傲，不聽從你的誡命，干犯你的典章，（人若行這些，必因這些活著，）扭轉肩頭，硬著頸項，不肯聽從。
9:30|ASV|Yet many years didst thou bear with them, and testifiedst against them by thy Spirit through thy prophets: yet would they not give ear: therefore gavest thou them into the hand of the peoples of the lands.
9:30|Darby|And many years didst thou forbear with them, and  testifiedst against them by thy Spirit through thy prophets;  but they would not give ear: and thou gavest them into the hand  of the peoples of the lands.
9:30|KJV|Yet many years didst thou forbear them, and testifiedst against them by thy spirit in thy prophets: yet would they not give ear: therefore gavest thou them into the hand of the people of the lands.
9:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你多年寬容他們，又用你的靈藉你的眾申言者警戒他們，他們仍不聽從；所以你將他們交在各地之民的手中。
9:31|ASV|Nevertheless in thy manifold mercies thou didst not make a full end of them, nor forsake them; for thou art a gracious and merciful God.
9:31|Darby|Nevertheless for thy manifold mercies' sake, thou didst not  make a full end of them nor forsake them; for thou art a  gracious and merciful ???’???’?????????God.
9:31|KJV|Nevertheless for thy great mercies' sake thou didst not utterly consume them, nor forsake them; for thou art a gracious and merciful God.
9:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而因你豐盛的憐恤，你沒有把他們滅盡；你沒有丟棄他們，因為你是有恩典、有憐恤的神。
9:32|ASV|Now therefore, our God, the great, the mighty, and the terrible God, who keepest covenant and lovingkindness, let not all the travail seem little before thee, that hath come upon us, on our kings, on our princes, and on our priests, and on our prophets, and on our fathers, and on all thy people, since the time of the kings of Assyria unto this day.
9:32|Darby|And now, our God, the great, the mighty, and the terrible  ???’???’?????????God, who keepest covenant and loving-kindness, let not all the  trouble seem little before thee, that hath come upon us, on our  kings, on our princes, and on our priests, and on our prophets,  and on our fathers, and on all thy people, since the days of  the kings of Assyria unto this day.
9:32|KJV|Now therefore, our God, the great, the mighty, and the terrible God, who keepest covenant and mercy, let not all the trouble seem little before thee, that hath come upon us, on our kings, on our princes, and on our priests, and on our prophets, and on our fathers, and on all thy people, since the time of the kings of Assyria unto this day.
9:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們的神阿，你是偉大、有能、可畏、守約並施慈愛的神；我們的君王、首領、祭司、申言者、列祖，和你的眾民，從亞述列王的日子直到今日所遭遇的一切苦難，現在求你不要看為小。
9:33|ASV|Howbeit thou art just in all that is come upon us; for thou hast dealt truly, but we have done wickedly;
9:33|Darby|But thou art just in all that is come upon us; for thou  hast acted according to truth, and we have done wickedly.
9:33|KJV|Howbeit thou art just in all that is brought upon us; for thou hast done right, but we have done wickedly:
9:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在一切臨到我們的事上，你卻是公義的；因你所行的是信實，我們所作的是邪惡。
9:34|ASV|neither have our kings, our princes, our priests, nor our fathers, kept thy law, nor hearkened unto thy commandments and thy testimonies wherewith thou didst testify against them.
9:34|Darby|And our kings, our princes, our priests, and our fathers,  have not performed thy law, nor hearkened unto thy commandments  and thy testimonies, wherewith thou didst testify against them.
9:34|KJV|Neither have our kings, our princes, our priests, nor our fathers, kept thy law, nor hearkened unto thy commandments and thy testimonies, wherewith thou didst testify against them.
9:34|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們的君王、首領、祭司、列祖都不遵行你的律法，不聽從你的誡命和你警戒他們的話。
9:35|ASV|For they have not served thee in their kingdom, and in thy great goodness that thou gavest them, and in the large and fat land which thou gavest before them, neither turned they from their wicked works.
9:35|Darby|And they have not served thee in their kingdom, and in thy  great goodness that thou gavest them, and in the large and fat  land that thou didst set before them, neither turned they from  their wicked works.
9:35|KJV|For they have not served thee in their kingdom, and in thy great goodness that thou gavest them, and in the large and fat land which thou gavest before them, neither turned they from their wicked works.
9:35|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們在本國，在你所賜至大的美善中，在你所擺在他們面前這廣大肥美的地上，不事奉你，也不轉離他們的惡行。
9:36|ASV|Behold, we are servants this day, and as for the land that thou gavest unto our fathers to eat the fruit thereof and the good thereof, behold, we are servants in it.
9:36|Darby|Behold, we are servants this day, and the land that thou  gavest unto our fathers to eat the fruit thereof and the good  thereof, behold, we are bondmen in it.
9:36|KJV|Behold, we are servants this day, and for the land that thou gavest unto our fathers to eat the fruit thereof and the good thereof, behold, we are servants in it:
9:36|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|看哪，我們今天作了奴僕；至於你所賜給我們列祖，讓他們喫其上的果實和美物之地，我們竟在其上作了奴僕。
9:37|ASV|And it yieldeth much increase unto the kings whom thou hast set over us because of our sins: also they have power over our bodies, and over our cattle, at their pleasure, and we are in great distress.
9:37|Darby|And it yieldeth much increase unto the kings whom thou hast  set over us because of our sins: and they have dominion over  our bodies, and over our cattle, at their pleasure; and we are  in great distress.
9:37|KJV|And it yieldeth much increase unto the kings whom thou hast set over us because of our sins: also they have dominion over our bodies, and over our cattle, at their pleasure, and we are in great distress.
9:37|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這地的許多出產歸了列王，就是你因我們的罪所派轄制我們的；他們任意轄制我們的身體和牲畜，我們遭了大難。
9:38<version name="ASV">And yet for all this we make a sure covenant, and write it; and our princes, our Levites, and our priests, seal unto it. </p><p /><br /></version>
9:38<version name="Darby">And because of all this we make a sure covenant, and write  it; and our princes, our Levites, [and] our priests are at the  sealing. </p><p /><br /></version>
9:38<version name="KJV">And because of all this we make a sure covenant, and write it; and our princes, Levites, and priests, seal unto it.</p><p /><br /></version>
9:38|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因這一切的事，我們立確實的約，寫在冊上；我們的首領、利未人和祭司，都在其上蓋了印。
10:1|ASV|Now those that sealed were: Nehemiah the governor, the son of Hacaliah, and Zedekiah,
10:1|Darby|And at the head of those that sealed were Nehemiah the  Tirshatha, the son of Hachaliah, and Zedekiah.
10:1|KJV|Now those that sealed were, Nehemiah, the Tirshatha, the son of Hachaliah, and Zidkijah,
10:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在約書上蓋印的記在下面：哈迦利亞的兒子，省長尼希米，和西底家；
10:2|ASV|Seraiah, Azariah, Jeremiah,
10:2|Darby|-- Seraiah, Azariah, Jeremiah,
10:2|KJV|Seraiah, Azariah, Jeremiah,
10:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又有西萊雅、亞撒利雅、耶利米、
10:3|ASV|Pashhur, Amariah, Malchijah,
10:3|Darby|Pashhur, Amariah, Malchijah,
10:3|KJV|Pashur, Amariah, Malchijah,
10:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|巴施戶珥、亞瑪利雅、瑪基雅、
10:4|ASV|Hattush, Shebaniah, Malluch,
10:4|Darby|Hattush, Shebaniah, Malluch,
10:4|KJV|Hattush, Shebaniah, Malluch,
10:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈突、示巴尼、瑪鹿、
10:5|ASV|Harim, Meremoth, Obadiah,
10:5|Darby|Harim, Meremoth, Obadiah,
10:5|KJV|Harim, Meremoth, Obadiah,
10:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈琳、米利末、俄巴底亞、
10:6|ASV|Daniel, Ginnethon, Baruch,
10:6|Darby|Daniel, Ginnethon, Baruch,
10:6|KJV|Daniel, Ginnethon, Baruch,
10:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但以理、近頓、巴錄、
10:7|ASV|Meshullam, Abijah, Mijamin,
10:7|Darby|Meshullam, Abijah, Mijamin,
10:7|KJV|Meshullam, Abijah, Mijamin,
10:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|米書蘭、亞比雅、米雅民、
10:8|ASV|Maaziah, Bilgai, Shemaiah; these were the priests.
10:8|Darby|Maaziah, Bilgai, Shemaiah: these were the priests.
10:8|KJV|Maaziah, Bilgai, Shemaiah: these were the priests.
10:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|瑪西亞、璧該、示瑪雅，這些是祭司；
10:9|ASV|And the Levites: namely, Jeshua the son of Azaniah, Binnui of the sons of Henadad, Kadmiel;
10:9|Darby|-- And the Levites: Jeshua the son of Azaniah; Binnui, of  the sons of Henadad; Kadmiel,
10:9|KJV|And the Levites: both Jeshua the son of Azaniah, Binnui of the sons of Henadad, Kadmiel;
10:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又有利未人，就是亞散尼的兒子耶書亞、希拿達的子孫賓內、甲篾；
10:10|ASV|and their brethren, Shebaniah, Hodiah, Kelita, Pelaiah, Hanan,
10:10|Darby|and their brethren, Shebaniah, Hodijah, Kelita, Pelaiah,  Hanan,
10:10|KJV|And their brethren, Shebaniah, Hodijah, Kelita, Pelaiah, Hanan,
10:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|還有他們的弟兄示巴尼、荷第雅、基利他、毘萊雅、哈難、
10:11|ASV|Mica, Rehob, Hashabiah,
10:11|Darby|Mica, Rehob, Hashabiah,
10:11|KJV|Micha, Rehob, Hashabiah,
10:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|米迦、利合、哈沙比雅、
10:12|ASV|Zaccur, Sherebiah, Shebaniah,
10:12|Darby|Zaccur, Sherebiah, Shebaniah,
10:12|KJV|Zaccur, Sherebiah, Shebaniah,
10:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|撒刻、示利比、示巴尼、
10:13|ASV|Hodiah, Bani, Beninu.
10:13|Darby|Hodijah, Bani, Beninu.
10:13|KJV|Hodijah, Bani, Beninu.
10:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|荷第雅、巴尼、比尼努；
10:14|ASV|The chiefs of the people: Parosh, Pahath-moab, Elam, Zattu, Bani,
10:14|Darby|-- The chief of the people: Parosh, Pahath-Moab, Elam,  Zatthu, Bani,
10:14|KJV|The chief of the people; Parosh, Pahathmoab, Elam, Zatthu, Bani,
10:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又有民的首領，就是巴錄、巴哈摩押、以攔、薩土、巴尼、
10:15|ASV|Bunni, Azgad, Bebai,
10:15|Darby|Bunni, Azgad, Bebai,
10:15|KJV|Bunni, Azgad, Bebai,
10:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|布尼、押甲、比拜、
10:16|ASV|Adonijah, Bigvai, Adin,
10:16|Darby|Adonijah, Bigvai, Adin,
10:16|KJV|Adonijah, Bigvai, Adin,
10:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞多尼雅、比革瓦伊、亞丁、
10:17|ASV|Ater, Hezekiah, Azzur,
10:17|Darby|Ater, Hezekiah, Azzur,
10:17|KJV|Ater, Hizkijah, Azzur,
10:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞特、希西家、押朔、
10:18|ASV|Hodiah, Hashum, Bezai,
10:18|Darby|Hodijah, Hashum, Bezai,
10:18|KJV|Hodijah, Hashum, Bezai,
10:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|荷第雅、哈順、比賽、
10:19|ASV|Hariph, Anathoth, Nobai,
10:19|Darby|Hariph, Anathoth, Nebai,
10:19|KJV|Hariph, Anathoth, Nebai,
10:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈拉、亞拿突、尼拜、
10:20|ASV|Magpiash, Meshullam, Hezir,
10:20|Darby|Magpiash, Meshullam, Hezir,
10:20|KJV|Magpiash, Meshullam, Hezir,
10:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|抹比押、米書蘭、希悉、
10:21|ASV|Meshezabel, Zadok, Jaddua,
10:21|Darby|Meshezabeel, Zadok, Jaddua,
10:21|KJV|Meshezabeel, Zadok, Jaddua,
10:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|米示薩別、撒督、押杜亞、
10:22|ASV|Pelatiah, Hanan, Anaiah,
10:22|Darby|Pelatiah, Hanan, Anaiah,
10:22|KJV|Pelatiah, Hanan, Anaiah,
10:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|毘拉提、哈難、亞奈雅、
10:23|ASV|Hoshea, Hananiah, Hasshub,
10:23|Darby|Hoshea, Hananiah, Hashub,
10:23|KJV|Hoshea, Hananiah, Hashub,
10:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|何細亞、哈拿尼雅、哈述、
10:24|ASV|Hallohesh, Pilha, Shobek,
10:24|Darby|Hallohesh, Pilha, Shobek,
10:24|KJV|Hallohesh, Pileha, Shobek,
10:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈羅黑、毘利哈、朔百、
10:25|ASV|Rehum, Hashabnah, Maaseiah,
10:25|Darby|Rehum, Hashabnah, Maaseiah,
10:25|KJV|Rehum, Hashabnah, Maaseiah,
10:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|利宏、哈沙拿、瑪西雅、
10:26|ASV|and Ahiah, Hanan, Anan,
10:26|Darby|and Ahijah, Hanan, Anan,
10:26|KJV|And Ahijah, Hanan, Anan,
10:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞希雅、哈難、亞難、
10:27|ASV|Malluch, Harim, Baanah.
10:27|Darby|Malluch, Harim, Baanah.
10:27|KJV|Malluch, Harim, Baanah.
10:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|瑪鹿、哈琳、巴拿。
10:28|ASV|And the rest of the people, the priests, the Levites, the porters, the singers, the Nethinim, and all they that had separated themselves from the peoples of the lands unto the law of God, their wives, their sons, and their daughters, every one that had knowledge, and understanding;
10:28|Darby|And the rest of the people, the priests, the Levites, the  doorkeepers, the singers, the Nethinim, and all they that had  separated themselves from the peoples of the lands to the law  of God, their wives, their sons and their daughters, every one  having knowledge [and] having understanding,
10:28|KJV|And the rest of the people, the priests, the Levites, the porters, the singers, the Nethinims, and all they that had separated themselves from the people of the lands unto the law of God, their wives, their sons, and their daughters, every one having knowledge, and having understanding;
10:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其餘的民、祭司、利未人、守門的、歌唱的、殿役、和一切從各地的民分別出來歸服神律法的，並他們的妻子、兒女，凡有知識能明白的，
10:29|ASV|They clave to their brethren, their nobles, and entered into a curse, and into an oath, to walk in God's law, which was given by Moses the servant of God, and to observe and do all the commandments of Jehovah our Lord, and his ordinances and his statutes;
10:29|Darby|joined with their brethren, their nobles, and entered into  a curse and into an oath, to walk in the law of God, which had  been given by Moses the servant of God, and to keep and do all  the commandments of Jehovah our Lord, and his ordinances and  his statutes;
10:29|KJV|They clave to their brethren, their nobles, and entered into a curse, and into an oath, to walk in God's law, which was given by Moses the servant of God, and to observe and do all the commandments of the LORD our Lord, and his judgments and his statutes;
10:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|都隨從他們貴冑的弟兄，發咒起誓，必遵行神藉祂僕人摩西所賜的律法，謹守遵行耶和華我們主的一切誡命、典章和律例；
10:30|ASV|and that we would not give our daughters unto the peoples of the land, nor take their daughters for our sons;
10:30|Darby|and that we would not give our daughters to the peoples of  the land, nor take their daughters for our sons:
10:30|KJV|And that we would not give our daughters unto the people of the land, not take their daughters for our sons:
10:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且必不將我們的女兒嫁給這地的民，也不為我們的兒子娶他們的女兒。
10:31|ASV|and if the peoples of the land bring wares or any grain on the sabbath day to sell, that we would not buy of them on the sabbath, or on a holy day; and that we would forego the seventh year, and the exaction of every debt.
10:31|Darby|and that if the peoples of the land brought wares or any  grain on the sabbath day to sell, we would not take it of them  on the sabbath, or on [any] holy day; and that we would leave  [the land uncultivated] the seventh year, and the exaction of  every debt.
10:31|KJV|And if the people of the land bring ware or any victuals on the sabbath day to sell, that we would not buy it of them on the sabbath, or on the holy day: and that we would leave the seventh year, and the exaction of every debt.
10:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這地的民若在安息日，或甚麼聖日，帶了貨物或糧食來賣給我們，我們必不買。每逢第七年，我們必不耕種，並且豁免一切債務。
10:32|ASV|Also we made ordinances for us, to charge ourselves yearly with the third part of a shekel for the service of the house of our God;
10:32|Darby|And we made ordinances for us, to charge ourselves yearly  with the third part of a shekel for the service of the house of  our God,
10:32|KJV|Also we made ordinances for us, to charge ourselves yearly with the third part of a shekel for the service of the house of our God;
10:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們又為自己立下定例，每年各人捐銀一舍客勒的三分之一，為我們神殿的使用，
10:33|ASV|for the showbread, and for the continual meal-offering, and for the continual burnt-offering, for the sabbaths, for the new moons, for the set feasts, and for the holy things, and for the sin-offerings to make atonement for Israel, and for all the work of the house of our God.
10:33|Darby|for the bread to be set in rows, and for the continual  oblation, and for the continual burnt-offering, [for that] of  the sabbaths [and] of the new moons, for the set feasts and for  the holy [things], and for the sin-offerings to make an  atonement for Israel, and [for] all the work of the house of  our God.
10:33|KJV|For the shewbread, and for the continual meat offering, and for the continual burnt offering, of the sabbaths, of the new moons, for the set feasts, and for the holy things, and for the sin offerings to make an atonement for Israel, and for all the work of the house of our God.
10:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就是為陳設餅、常獻的素祭、和常獻的燔祭，安息日、月朔、節期所獻的，與聖物，並為以色列人遮罪的贖罪祭，以及我們神殿堣@切工作的費用。
10:34|ASV|And we cast lots, the priests, the Levites, and the people, for the wood-offering, to bring it into the house of our God, according to our fathers' houses, at times appointed, year by year, to burn upon the altar of Jehovah our God, as it is written in the law;
10:34|Darby|And we cast the lots among the priests, the Levites, and  the people, for the wood-offering, to bring [it] into the house  of our God, according to our fathers' houses, at times  appointed year by year, to burn upon the altar of Jehovah our  God, as it is written in the law;
10:34|KJV|And we cast the lots among the priests, the Levites, and the people, for the wood offering, to bring it into the house of our God, after the houses of our fathers, at times appointed year by year, to burn upon the altar of the LORD our God, as it is written in the law:
10:34|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們祭司、利未人、和百姓都為奉獻木柴掣籤，以便年年按著宗族，定期將木柴奉到我們神的殿堙A照著律法上所寫的，燒在耶和華我們神的壇上；
10:35|ASV|and to bring the first-fruits of our ground, and the first-fruits of all fruit of all manner of trees, year by year, unto the house of Jehovah;
10:35|Darby|and to bring the first-fruits of our land, and the  first-fruits of all fruit of all trees, year by year to the  house of Jehovah,
10:35|KJV|And to bring the firstfruits of our ground, and the firstfruits of all fruit of all trees, year by year, unto the house of the LORD:
10:35|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以及年年將我們地上的初熟之物和各樣樹上一切果子中初熟的，都奉到耶和華的殿堙F
10:36|ASV|also the first-born of our sons, and of our cattle, as it is written in the law, and the firstlings of our herds and of our flocks, to bring to the house of our God, unto the priests that minister in the house of our God;
10:36|Darby|and the firstborn of our sons and of our cattle, as it is  written in the law; and to bring the firstlings of our herds  and of our flocks to the house of our God, to the priests that  minister in the house of our God;
10:36|KJV|Also the firstborn of our sons, and of our cattle, as it is written in the law, and the firstlings of our herds and of our flocks, to bring to the house of our God, unto the priests that minister in the house of our God:
10:36|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又照律法上所寫的，將我們頭胎的兒子和牲口奉上；將頭生的牛羊，都奉到我們神的殿，交給我們神殿堥捔儐熔膝q；
10:37|ASV|and that we should bring the first-fruits of our dough, and our heave-offerings, and the fruit of all manner of trees, the new wine and the oil, unto the priests, to the chambers of the house of our God; and the tithes of our ground unto the Levites; for they, the Levites, take the tithes in all the cities of our tillage.
10:37|Darby|and that we should bring the first-fruits of our coarse  meal and our heave-offerings, and the fruit of all manner of  trees, new wine and oil, to the priests, into the chambers of  the house of our God, and the tithes of our ground to the  Levites, that they, the Levites, should take the tithes in all  the cities of our tillage.
10:37|KJV|And that we should bring the firstfruits of our dough, and our offerings, and the fruit of all manner of trees, of wine and of oil, unto the priests, to the chambers of the house of our God; and the tithes of our ground unto the Levites, that the same Levites might have the tithes in all the cities of our tillage.
10:37|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並將初熟麥子所磨的麵和舉祭、各樣樹上初熟的果子、新酒與新油奉給祭司，收在我們神殿的庫房堙A且把我們地上所產的十分之一奉給利未人，因利未人在我們一切有耕作的鄉鎮中當取十分之一。
10:38|ASV|And the priest the son of Aaron shall be with the Levites, when the Levites take tithes: and the Levites shall bring up the tithe of the tithes unto the house of our God, to the chambers, into the treasure-house.
10:38|Darby|And the priest the son of Aaron shall be with the Levites,  when the Levites take tithes; and the Levites shall bring up  the tithe of the tithes to the house of our God, into the  chambers of the treasure-house.
10:38|KJV|And the priest the son of Aaron shall be with the Levites, when the Levites take tithes: and the Levites shall bring up the tithe of the tithes unto the house of our God, to the chambers, into the treasure house.
10:38|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|利未人取十分之一的時候，亞倫的子孫作祭司的，當有一個與利未人在一起；利未人也當從十分之一中取十分之一，奉到我們神的殿，收在庫房中。
10:39<version name="ASV">For the children of Israel and the children of Levi shall bring the heave-offering of the grain, of the new wine, and of the oil, unto the chambers, where are the vessels of the sanctuary, and the priests that minister, and the porters, and the singers: and we will not forsake the house of our God. </p><p /><br /></version>
10:39<version name="Darby">For the children of Israel and the children of Levi shall  bring the heave-offering of the corn, of the new wine and the  oil, into the chambers, where are the vessels of the sanctuary,  and the priests that minister, and the doorkeepers and the  singers. And we will not forsake the house of our God. </p><p /><br /></version>
10:39<version name="KJV">For the children of Israel and the children of Levi shall bring the offering of the corn, of the new wine, and the oil, unto the chambers, where are the vessels of the sanctuary, and the priests that minister, and the porters, and the singers: and we will not forsake the house of our God.</p><p /><br /></version>
10:39|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列人和利未人要將五穀、新酒與新油為舉祭，奉到庫房堙A就是聖所的器皿、供職的祭司、守門的、和歌唱的所在之處；我們必不離棄我們神的殿。
11:1|ASV|And the princes of the people dwelt in Jerusalem: the rest of the people also cast lots, to bring one of ten to dwell in Jerusalem the holy city, and nine parts in the other cities.
11:1|Darby|And the princes of the people dwelt in Jerusalem; and the  rest of the people cast lots, to bring one of ten to dwell in  Jerusalem, the holy city, and nine parts in the cities.
11:1|KJV|And the rulers of the people dwelt at Jerusalem: the rest of the people also cast lots, to bring one of ten to dwell in Jerusalem the holy city, and nine parts to dwell in other cities.
11:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|百姓的首領住在耶路撒冷；其餘的百姓掣籤，每十人中使一人來住在聖城耶路撒冷，那九人住在別的城邑。
11:2|ASV|And the people blessed all the men that willingly offered themselves to dwell in Jerusalem.
11:2|Darby|And the people blessed all the men that willingly offered  themselves to dwell in Jerusalem.
11:2|KJV|And the people blessed all the men, that willingly offered themselves to dwell at Jerusalem.
11:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡樂意獻上自己去住在耶路撒冷的，百姓都為他們祝福。
11:3|ASV|Now these are the chiefs of the province that dwelt in Jerusalem: but in the cities of Judah dwelt every one in his possession in their cities, to wit, Israel, the priests, and the Levites, and the Nethinim, and the children of Solomon's servants.
11:3|Darby|And these are the chiefs of the province that dwelt in  Jerusalem; but in the cities of Judah dwelt every one in his  possession in their cities, Israel, the priests, and the  Levites, and the Nethinim, and the children of Solomon's  servants.
11:3|KJV|Now these are the chief of the province that dwelt in Jerusalem: but in the cities of Judah dwelt every one in his possession in their cities, to wit, Israel, the priests, and the Levites, and the Nethinims, and the children of Solomon's servants.
11:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列人、祭司、利未人、殿役、和所羅門僕人的子孫，都住在猶大諸城邑，在自己城內各人的地業中。本省的首領住在耶路撒冷的記在下面：
11:4|ASV|And in Jerusalem dwelt certain of the children of Judah, and of the children of Benjamin. Of the children of Judah: Athaiah the son of Uzziah, the son of Zechariah, the son of Amariah, the son of Shephatiah, the son of Mahalalel, of the children of Perez;
11:4|Darby|And in Jerusalem dwelt some of the children of Judah and of  the children of Benjamin. Of the children of Judah: Athaiah the  son of Uzziah, the son of Zechariah, the son of Amariah, the  son of Shephatiah, the son of Mahalaleel, of the children of  Pherez;
11:4|KJV|And at Jerusalem dwelt certain of the children of Judah, and of the children of Benjamin. Of the children of Judah; Athaiah the son of Uzziah, the son of Zechariah, the son of Amariah, the son of Shephatiah, the son of Mahalaleel, of the children of Perez;
11:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有些猶大人和便雅憫人住在耶路撒冷。猶大人中有法勒斯的子孫，烏西雅的兒子亞他雅，烏西雅是撒迦利雅的兒子，撒迦利雅是亞瑪利雅的兒子，亞瑪利雅是示法提雅的兒子，示法提雅是瑪勒列的兒子；
11:5|ASV|and Maaseiah the son of Baruch, the son of Colhozeh, the son of Hazaiah, the son of Adaiah, the son of Joiarib, the son of Zechariah, the son of the Shilonite.
11:5|Darby|and Maaseiah the son of Baruch, the son of Col-hozeh, the  son of Hazaiah, the son of Adaiah, the son of Joiarib, the son  of Zechariah, the son of Shiloni.
11:5|KJV|And Maaseiah the son of Baruch, the son of Colhozeh, the son of Hazaiah, the son of Adaiah, the son of Joiarib, the son of Zechariah, the son of Shiloni.
11:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又有巴錄的兒子瑪西雅，巴錄是谷何西的兒子，谷何西是哈賽雅的兒子，哈賽雅是亞大雅的兒子，亞大雅是約雅立的兒子，約雅立是撒迦利雅的兒子，撒迦利雅是示羅尼的兒子。
11:6|ASV|All the sons of Perez that dwelt in Jerusalem were four hundred threescore and eight valiant men.
11:6|Darby|All the children of Pherez that dwelt in Jerusalem were  four hundred and sixty-eight valiant men.
11:6|KJV|All the sons of Perez that dwelt at Jerusalem were four hundred threescore and eight valiant men.
11:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|住在耶路撒冷，法勒斯的子孫共四百六十八名，都是勇士。
11:7|ASV|And these are the sons of Benjamin: Sallu the son of Meshullam, the son of Joed, the son of Pedaiah, the son of Kolaiah, the son of Maaseiah, the son of Ithiel, the son of Jeshaiah.
11:7|Darby|And these are the children of Benjamin: Sallu the son of  Meshullam, the son of Joed, the son of Pedaiah, the son of  Kolaiah, the son of Maaseiah, the son of Ithiel, the son of  Isaiah;
11:7|KJV|And these are the sons of Benjamin; Sallu the son of Meshullam, the son of Joed, the son of Pedaiah, the son of Kolaiah, the son of Maaseiah, the son of Ithiel, the son of Jesaiah.
11:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|便雅憫人中有米書蘭的兒子撒路，米書蘭是約葉的兒子，約葉是毘大雅的兒子，毘大雅是哥賴雅的兒子，哥賴雅是瑪西雅的兒子，瑪西雅是以鐵的兒子，以鐵是耶篩亞的兒子；
11:8|ASV|And after him Gabbai, Sallai, nine hundred twenty and eight.
11:8|Darby|and after him, Gabbai, Sallai, nine hundred and  twenty-eight:
11:8|KJV|And after him Gabbai, Sallai, nine hundred twenty and eight.
11:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在他以後有迦拜和撒來；便雅憫人共九百二十八名。
11:9|ASV|And Joel the son of Zichri was their overseer; and Judah the son of Hassenuah was second over the city.
11:9|Darby|and Joel the son of Zicri was their overseer, and Judah the  son of Senuah was second over the city.
11:9|KJV|And Joel the son of Zichri was their overseer: and Judah the son of Senuah was second over the city.
11:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|細基利的兒子約珥是他們的監督；哈西努亞的兒子猶大是那城的副監督。
11:10|ASV|Of the priests: Jedaiah the son of Joiarib, Jachin,
11:10|Darby|Of the priests: Jedaiah [the son of] Joiarib, Jachin,
11:10|KJV|Of the priests: Jedaiah the son of Joiarib, Jachin.
11:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祭司中有約雅立的兒子耶大雅，又有雅斤，
11:11|ASV|Seraiah the son of Hilkiah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, the ruler of the house of God,
11:11|Darby|Seraiah the son of Hilkijah, the son of Meshullam, the son  of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, the ruler of  the house of God.
11:11|KJV|Seraiah the son of Hilkiah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, was the ruler of the house of God.
11:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|還有管理神殿的西萊雅，西萊雅是希勒家的兒子，希勒家是米書蘭的兒子，米書蘭是撒督的兒子，撒督是米拉約的兒子，米拉約是亞希突的兒子；
11:12|ASV|and their brethren that did the work of the house, eight hundred twenty and two; and Adaiah the son of Jeroham, the son of Pelaliah, the son of Amzi, the son of Zechariah, the son of Pashhur, the son of Malchijah,
11:12|Darby|And their brethren that did the work of the house, eight  hundred and twenty-two; and Adaiah the son of Jeroham, the son  of Pelaliah, the son of Amzi, the son of Zechariah, the son of  Pashhur, the son of Malchijah;
11:12|KJV|And their brethren that did the work of the house were eight hundred twenty and two: and Adaiah the son of Jeroham, the son of Pelaliah, the son of Amzi, the son of Zechariah, the son of Pashur, the son of Malchiah.
11:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|還有他們的弟兄在殿堥捔儐滿A共八百二十二名；又有耶羅罕的兒子亞大雅，耶羅罕是毘拉利的兒子，毘拉利是暗洗的兒子，暗洗是撒迦利亞的兒子，撒迦利亞是巴施戶珥的兒子，巴施戶珥是瑪基雅的兒子；
11:13|ASV|and his brethren, chiefs of fathers' houses, two hundred forty and two; and Amashsai the son of Azarel, the son of Ahzai, the son of Meshillemoth, the son of Immer,
11:13|Darby|and his brethren, chief fathers, two hundred and  forty-two; and Amassai the son of Azareel, the son of Ahzai,  the son of Meshillemoth, the son of Immer;
11:13|KJV|And his brethren, chief of the fathers, two hundred forty and two: and Amashai the son of Azareel, the son of Ahasai, the son of Meshillemoth, the son of Immer,
11:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|還有他的弟兄作宗族首領的，共二百四十二名；又有亞薩列的兒子亞瑪帥，亞薩列是亞哈賽的兒子，亞哈賽是米實利末的兒子，米實利末是音麥的兒子；
11:14|ASV|and their brethren, mighty men of valor, a hundred twenty and eight; and their overseer was Zabdiel, the son of Haggedolim.
11:14|Darby|and their brethren, mighty men of valour, a hundred and  twenty-eight: and their overseer was Zabdiel the son of  Gedolim.
11:14|KJV|And their brethren, mighty men of valour, an hundred twenty and eight: and their overseer was Zabdiel, the son of one of the great men.
11:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|還有他們的弟兄，大能的勇士，共一百二十八名；哈基多琳的兒子撒巴第業是他們的監督。
11:15|ASV|And of the Levites: Shemaiah the son of Hasshub, the son of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Bunni;
11:15|Darby|And of the Levites: Shemaiah the son of Hasshub, the son  of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Bunni;
11:15|KJV|Also of the Levites: Shemaiah the son of Hashub, the son of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Bunni;
11:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|利未人中有哈述的兒子示瑪雅，哈述是押利甘的兒子，押利甘是哈沙比雅的兒子，哈沙比雅是布尼的兒子；
11:16|ASV|and Shabbethai and Jozabad, of the chiefs of the Levites, who had the oversight of the outward business of the house of God;
11:16|Darby|and Shabbethai and Jozabad, of the chiefs of the Levites,  [who were] over the outward work of the house of God;
11:16|KJV|And Shabbethai and Jozabad, of the chief of the Levites, had the oversight of the outward business of the house of God.
11:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又有利未人的首領沙比太和約撒拔，管理神殿外部的事。
11:17|ASV|and Mattaniah the son of Mica, the son of Zabdi, the son of Asaph, who was the chief to begin the thanksgiving in prayer, and Bakbukiah, the second among his brethren; and Abda the son of Shammua, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun.
11:17|Darby|and Mattaniah the son of Mica, the son of Zabdi, the son  of Asaph, [who was] the principal to begin the thanksgiving in  prayer; and Bakbukiah, the second among his brethren; and Abda  the son of Shammua, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun:
11:17|KJV|And Mattaniah the son of Micha, the son of Zabdi, the son of Asaph, was the principal to begin the thanksgiving in prayer: and Bakbukiah the second among his brethren, and Abda the son of Shammua, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun.
11:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|禱告的時候，領頭稱謝的是米迦的兒子瑪他尼，米迦是撒底的兒子，撒底是亞薩的兒子；又有瑪他尼弟兄中的八布迦為副；還有沙母亞的兒子押大，沙母亞是加拉的兒子，加拉是耶杜頓的兒子。
11:18|ASV|All the Levites in the holy city were two hundred fourscore and four.
11:18|Darby|all the Levites in the holy city were two hundred and  eighty-four.
11:18|KJV|All the Levites in the holy city were two hundred fourscore and four.
11:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在聖城的利未人共二百八十四名。
11:19|ASV|Moreover the porters, Akkub, Talmon, and their brethren, that kept watch at the gates, were a hundred seventy and two.
11:19|Darby|And the doorkeepers, Akkub, Talmon, and their brethren,  that kept watch at the gates, were a hundred and seventy-two.
11:19|KJV|Moreover the porters, Akkub, Talmon, and their brethren that kept the gates, were an hundred seventy and two.
11:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|守門的是亞谷、達們、和他們的弟兄，他們看守各門，共一百七十二名。
11:20|ASV|And the residue of Israel, of the priests, the Levites, were in all the cities of Judah, every one in his inheritance.
11:20|Darby|And the residue of Israel, the priests, [and] the Levites,  were in all the cities of Judah, every one in his inheritance.
11:20|KJV|And the residue of Israel, of the priests, and the Levites, were in all the cities of Judah, every one in his inheritance.
11:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其餘的以色列人、祭司、利未人，都住在猶大的一切城邑，各在自己的地業中。
11:21|ASV|But the Nethinim dwelt in Ophel: and Ziha and Gishpa were over the Nethinim.
11:21|Darby|And the Nethinim dwelt in Ophel; and Ziha and Gispa were  over the Nethinim.
11:21|KJV|But the Nethinims dwelt in Ophel: and Ziha and Gispa were over the Nethinims.
11:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|殿役卻住在俄斐勒；西哈和基斯帕管理殿役。
11:22|ASV|The overseer also of the Levites at Jerusalem was Uzzi the son of Bani, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Mica, of the sons of Asaph, the singers, over the business of the house of God.
11:22|Darby|And the overseer of the Levites at Jerusalem was Uzzi the  son of Bani, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Mattaniah, the  son of Mica, of the sons of Asaph, the singers, for the work of  the house of God.
11:22|KJV|The overseer also of the Levites at Jerusalem was Uzzi the son of Bani, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Micha. Of the sons of Asaph, the singers were over the business of the house of God.
11:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在耶路撒冷，利未人的監督，照料神殿事務的是歌唱者亞薩的子孫，巴尼的兒子烏西，巴尼是哈沙比雅的兒子，哈沙比雅是瑪他尼的兒子，瑪他尼是米迦的兒子。
11:23|ASV|For there was a commandment from the king concerning them, and a settled provision for the singers, as every day required.
11:23|Darby|For it was the king's commandment concerning them, and  there was a settled portion for the singers, due for each day.
11:23|KJV|For it was the king's commandment concerning them, that a certain portion should be for the singers, due for every day.
11:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王為歌唱的出令，為每日之需供給他們一定的糧。
11:24|ASV|And Pethahiah the son of Meshezabel, of the children of Zerah the son of Judah, was at the king's hand in all matters concerning the people.
11:24|Darby|And Pethahiah the son of Meshezabeel, of the children of  Zerah the son of Judah, was at the king's hand in all matters  concerning the people.
11:24|KJV|And Pethahiah the son of Meshezabeel, of the children of Zerah the son of Judah, was at the king's hand in all matters concerning the people.
11:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|猶大兒子謝拉的子孫，米示薩別的兒子毘他希雅是王的助手，辦理一切關於百姓的事。
11:25|ASV|And as for the villages, with their fields, some of the children of Judah dwelt in Kiriath-arba and the towns thereof, and in Dibon and the towns thereof, and in Jekabzeel and the villages thereof,
11:25|Darby|And as to the hamlets in their fields, [some] of the  children of Judah dwelt in Kirjath-Arba and its dependent  villages, and in Dibon and its dependent villages, and in  Jekabzeel and its dependent villages,
11:25|KJV|And for the villages, with their fields, some of the children of Judah dwelt at Kirjatharba, and in the villages thereof, and at Dibon, and in the villages thereof, and at Jekabzeel, and in the villages thereof,
11:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於村莊連同屬村莊的田地，有猶大人住在基列亞巴和屬基列亞巴的鄉村、底本和屬底本的鄉村、葉甲薛和屬葉甲薛的村莊、
11:26|ASV|and in Jeshua, and in Moladah, and Beth-pelet,
11:26|Darby|and in Jeshua, and in Moladah, and in Beth-phelet,
11:26|KJV|And at Jeshua, and at Moladah, and at Bethphelet,
11:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶書亞、摩拉大、伯帕列、
11:27|ASV|and in Hazar-shual, and in Beer-sheba and the towns thereof,
11:27|Darby|and in Hazar-Shual, and in Beer-sheba and its dependent  villages,
11:27|KJV|And at Hazarshual, and at Beersheba, and in the villages thereof,
11:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈薩書亞、別是巴和屬別是巴的鄉村、
11:28|ASV|and in Ziklag, and in Meconah and in the towns thereof,
11:28|Darby|and in Ziklag, and in Meconah and its dependent villages;
11:28|KJV|And at Ziklag, and at Mekonah, and in the villages thereof,
11:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|洗革拉、米哥拿和屬米哥拿的鄉村、
11:29|ASV|and in En-rimmon, and in Zorah, and in Jarmuth,
11:29|Darby|and in En-Rimmon, and in Zorah, and in Jarmuth,
11:29|KJV|And at Enrimmon, and at Zareah, and at Jarmuth,
11:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|音臨門、瑣拉、耶末、
11:30|ASV|Zanoah, Adullam, and their villages, Lachish and the fields thereof, Azekah and the towns thereof. So they encamped from Beer-sheba unto the valley of Hinnom.
11:30|Darby|Zanoah, Adullam, and their hamlets, in Lachish and its  fields, in Azekah and its dependent villages: and they encamped  from Beer-sheba unto the valley of Hinnom.
11:30|KJV|Zanoah, Adullam, and in their villages, at Lachish, and the fields thereof, at Azekah, and in the villages thereof. And they dwelt from Beersheba unto the valley of Hinnom.
11:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|撒挪亞、亞杜蘭和屬這兩處的村莊、拉吉和屬拉吉的田地、亞西加和屬亞西加的鄉村。他們安營的地方是從別是巴直到欣嫩谷。
11:31|ASV|The children of Benjamin also dwelt from Geba onward, at Michmash and Aija, and at Beth-el and the towns thereof,
11:31|Darby|And the children of Benjamin from Geba [dwelt] in Michmash  and Aija and Bethel, and their dependent villages,
11:31|KJV|The children also of Benjamin from Geba dwelt at Michmash, and Aija, and Bethel, and in their villages.
11:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|便雅憫人從迦巴起，住在密抹、亞雅、伯特利和屬伯特利的鄉村、
11:32|ASV|at Anathoth, Nob, Ananiah,
11:32|Darby|in Anathoth, Nob, Ananiah,
11:32|KJV|And at Anathoth, Nob, Ananiah,
11:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞拿突、挪伯、亞難雅、
11:33|ASV|Hazor, Ramah, Gittaim,
11:33|Darby|Hazor, Ramah, Gittaim,
11:33|KJV|Hazor, Ramah, Gittaim,
11:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|夏瑣、拉瑪、基他音、
11:34|ASV|Hadid, Zeboim, Neballat,
11:34|Darby|Hadid, Zeboim, Neballat,
11:34|KJV|Hadid, Zeboim, Neballat,
11:34|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈疊、洗編、尼八拉、
11:35|ASV|Lod, and Ono, the valley of craftsmen.
11:35|Darby|Lod, and Ono, the valley of craftsmen.
11:35|KJV|Lod, and Ono, the valley of craftsmen.
11:35|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|羅德、阿挪、匠人之谷。
11:36<version name="ASV">And of the Levites, certain courses in Judah were joined to Benjamin. </p><p /><br /></version>
11:36<version name="Darby">And of the Levites there were divisions of Judah  [dwelling] in Benjamin. </p><p /><br /></version>
11:36<version name="KJV">And of the Levites were divisions in Judah, and in Benjamin.</p><p /><br /></version>
11:36|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有幾班在猶大地的利未人，是歸於便雅憫的。
12:1|ASV|Now these are the priests and the Levites that went up with Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua: Seraiah, Jeremiah, Ezra,
12:1|Darby|And these are the priests and the Levites that went up with  Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua: Seraiah, Jeremiah,  Ezra,
12:1|KJV|Now these are the priests and the Levites that went up with Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua: Seraiah, Jeremiah, Ezra,
12:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|同著撒拉鐵的兒子所羅巴伯和耶書亞上來的祭司與利未人，記在下面：祭司是西萊雅、耶利米、以斯拉、
12:2|ASV|Amariah, Malluch, Hattush,
12:2|Darby|Amariah, Malluch, Hattush,
12:2|KJV|Amariah, Malluch, Hattush,
12:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞瑪利雅、瑪鹿、哈突、
12:3|ASV|Shecaniah, Rehum, Meremoth,
12:3|Darby|Shechaniah, Rehum, Meremoth,
12:3|KJV|Shechaniah, Rehum, Meremoth,
12:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|示迦尼、利宏、米利末、
12:4|ASV|Iddo, Ginnethoi, Abijah,
12:4|Darby|Iddo, Ginnethoi, Abijah,
12:4|KJV|Iddo, Ginnetho, Abijah,
12:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|易多、近頓、亞比雅、
12:5|ASV|Mijamin, Maadiah, Bilgah,
12:5|Darby|Mijamin, Maadiah, Bilgah,
12:5|KJV|Miamin, Maadiah, Bilgah,
12:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|米雅民、瑪底雅、璧迦、
12:6|ASV|Shemaiah, and Joiarib, Jedaiah.
12:6|Darby|Shemaiah, and Joiarib, Jedaiah,
12:6|KJV|Shemaiah, and Joiarib, Jedaiah,
12:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|示瑪雅、約雅立、耶大雅、
12:7|ASV|Sallu, Amok, Hilkiah, Jedaiah. These were the chiefs of the priests and of their brethren in the days of Jeshua.
12:7|Darby|Sallu, Amok, Hilkijah, Jedaiah. These were the chief of the  priests and of their brethren in the days of Jeshua.
12:7|KJV|Sallu, Amok, Hilkiah, Jedaiah. These were the chief of the priests and of their brethren in the days of Jeshua.
12:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|撒路、亞木、希勒家、耶大雅。這些人在耶書亞的日子，作祭司和他們弟兄的首領。
12:8|ASV|Moreover the Levites: Jeshua, Binnui, Kadmiel, Sherebiah, Judah, and Mattaniah, who was over the thanksgiving, he and his brethren.
12:8|Darby|And the Levites: Jeshua, Binnui, Kadmiel, Sherebiah, Judah,  Mattaniah, [who was] over the thanksgiving, he and his  brethren;
12:8|KJV|Moreover the Levites: Jeshua, Binnui, Kadmiel, Sherebiah, Judah, and Mattaniah, which was over the thanksgiving, he and his brethren.
12:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|利未人是耶書亞、賓內、甲篾、示利比、猶大、瑪他尼，這瑪他尼和他的弟兄管理稱謝的事。
12:9|ASV|Also Bakbukiah and Unno, their brethren, were over against them according to their offices.
12:9|Darby|and Bakbukiah and Unni, their brethren, were over against  them as watches.
12:9|KJV|Also Bakbukiah and Unni, their brethren, were over against them in the watches.
12:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們的弟兄八布迦和烏尼照事奉的班次，與他們相對站立。
12:10|ASV|And Jeshua begat Joiakim, and Joiakim begat Eliashib, and Eliashib begat Joiada,
12:10|Darby|And Jeshua begot Joiakim, and Joiakim begot Eliashib, and  Eliashib begot Joiada,
12:10|KJV|And Jeshua begat Joiakim, Joiakim also begat Eliashib, and Eliashib begat Joiada,
12:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶書亞生約雅金，約雅金生以利亞實，以利亞實生耶何耶大，
12:11|ASV|and Joiada begat Jonathan, and Jonathan begat Jaddua.
12:11|Darby|and Joiada begot Jonathan, and Jonathan begot Jaddua.
12:11|KJV|And Joiada begat Jonathan, and Jonathan begat Jaddua.
12:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶何耶大生約拿單，約拿單生押杜亞。
12:12|ASV|And in the days of Joiakim were priests, heads of fathers'  houses: of Seraiah, Meraiah; of Jeremiah, Hananiah;
12:12|Darby|And in the days of Joiakim were priests, chief fathers: of  Seraiah, Meraiah; of Jeremiah, Hananiah;
12:12|KJV|And in the days of Joiakim were priests, the chief of the fathers: of Seraiah, Meraiah; of Jeremiah, Hananiah;
12:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在約雅金的日子，祭司作宗族首領的是西萊雅族的米拉雅、耶利米族的哈拿尼雅、
12:13|ASV|of Ezra, Meshullam; of Amariah, Jehohanan;
12:13|Darby|of Ezra, Meshullam; of Amariah, Jehohanan;
12:13|KJV|Of Ezra, Meshullam; of Amariah, Jehohanan;
12:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以斯拉族的米書蘭、亞瑪利雅族的約哈難、
12:14|ASV|of Malluchi, Jonathan; of Shebaniah, Joseph;
12:14|Darby|of Melicu, Jonathan; of Shebaniah, Joseph;
12:14|KJV|Of Melicu, Jonathan; of Shebaniah, Joseph;
12:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|米利古族的約拿單、示巴尼族的約瑟、
12:15|ASV|of Harim, Adna; of Meraioth, Helkai;
12:15|Darby|of Harim, Adna; of Meraioth, Helkai;
12:15|KJV|Of Harim, Adna; of Meraioth, Helkai;
12:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哈琳族的押拿、米拉約族的希勒愷、
12:16|ASV|of Iddo, Zechariah; of Ginnethon, Meshullam;
12:16|Darby|of Iddo, Zechariah; of Ginnethon, Meshullam;
12:16|KJV|Of Iddo, Zechariah; of Ginnethon, Meshullam;
12:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|易多族的撒迦利亞、近頓族的米書蘭、
12:17|ASV|of Abijah, Zichri; of Miniamin, of Moadiah, Piltai;
12:17|Darby|of Abijah, Zichri; of Miniamin [and] Moadiah, Piltai;
12:17|KJV|Of Abijah, Zichri; of Miniamin, of Moadiah, Piltai:
12:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞比雅族的細基利、米拿民族的某一位、摩亞底族的毘勒太、
12:18|ASV|of Bilgah, Shammua; of Shemaiah, Jehonathan;
12:18|Darby|of Bilgah, Shammua; of Shemaiah, Jehonathan;
12:18|KJV|Of Bilgah, Shammua; of Shemaiah, Jehonathan;
12:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|璧迦族的沙母亞、示瑪雅族的約拿單、
12:19|ASV|and of Joiarib, Mattenai; of Jedaiah, Uzzi;
12:19|Darby|and of Joiarib, Mattenai; of Jedaiah, Uzzi;
12:19|KJV|And of Joiarib, Mattenai; of Jedaiah, Uzzi;
12:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|約雅立族的瑪特乃、耶大雅族的烏西、
12:20|ASV|of Sallai, Kallai; of Amok, Eber;
12:20|Darby|of Sallai, Kallai; of Amok, Eber;
12:20|KJV|Of Sallai, Kallai; of Amok, Eber;
12:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|撒來族的加萊、亞木族的希伯、
12:21|ASV|of Hilkiah, Hashabiah; of Jedaiah, Nethanel.
12:21|Darby|of Hilkijah, Hashabiah; of Jedaiah, Nethaneel.
12:21|KJV|Of Hilkiah, Hashabiah; of Jedaiah, Nethaneel.
12:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|希勒家族的哈沙比雅、耶大雅族的拿坦業。
12:22|ASV|As for the Levites, in the days of Eliashib, Joiada, and Johanan, and Jaddua, there were recorded the heads of fathers'  houses; also the priests, in the reign of Darius the Persian.
12:22|Darby|of the Levites, the chief fathers were recorded in the  days of Eliashib, Joiada, and Johanan, and Jaddua, and the  priests, until the reign of Darius the Persian.
12:22|KJV|The Levites in the days of Eliashib, Joiada, and Johanan, and Jaddua, were recorded chief of the fathers: also the priests, to the reign of Darius the Persian.
12:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於利未人，當以利亞實、耶何耶大、約哈難、押杜亞的日子，他們宗族的首領記在冊上。大利烏作波斯王的時候，作祭司的也記在冊上。
12:23|ASV|The sons of Levi, heads of fathers' houses, were written in the book of the chronicles, even until the days of Johanan the son of Eliashib.
12:23|Darby|The children of Levi, the chief fathers, were recorded in  the book of the chronicles, even until the days of Johanan the  son of Eliashib.
12:23|KJV|The sons of Levi, the chief of the fathers, were written in the book of the chronicles, even until the days of Johanan the son of Eliashib.
12:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|利未人作宗族首領的記在年代志上，直到以利亞實的兒子約哈難的日子。
12:24|ASV|And the chiefs of the Levites: Hashabiah, Sherebiah, and Jeshua the son of Kadmiel, with their brethren over against them, to praise and give thanks, according to the commandment of David the man of God, watch next to watch.
12:24|Darby|And the chief Levites: Hashabiah, Sherebiah, and Jeshua  the son of Kadmiel, with their brethren over against them, to  praise [and] to give thanks, according to the commandment of  David the man of God, ward over against ward.
12:24|KJV|And the chief of the Levites: Hashabiah, Sherebiah, and Jeshua the son of Kadmiel, with their brethren over against them, to praise and to give thanks, according to the commandment of David the man of God, ward over against ward.
12:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|利未人的首領是哈沙比雅、示利比、甲篾的兒子耶書亞，有他們的弟兄與他們相對站立，照著神人大衛的命令，一班一班的讚美稱謝。
12:25|ASV|Mattaniah, and Bakbukiah, Obadiah, Meshullam, Talmon, Akkub, were porters keeping the watch at the store-houses of the gates.
12:25|Darby|Mattaniah and Bakbukiah, Obadiah, Meshullam, Talmon,  Akkub, were doorkeepers keeping the ward at the storehouses of  the gates.
12:25|KJV|Mattaniah, and Bakbukiah, Obadiah, Meshullam, Talmon, Akkub, were porters keeping the ward at the thresholds of the gates.
12:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|瑪他尼、八布迦、俄巴底亞、米書蘭、達們、亞谷是守門的，在城門的庫房那堿搹u。
12:26|ASV|These were in the days of Joiakim the son of Jeshua, the son of Jozadak, and in the days of Nehemiah the governor, and of Ezra the priest the scribe.
12:26|Darby|These were in the days of Joiakim the son of Jeshua the  son of Jozadak, and in the days of Nehemiah the governor, and  of Ezra the priest, the scribe.
12:26|KJV|These were in the days of Joiakim the son of Jeshua, the son of Jozadak, and in the days of Nehemiah the governor, and of Ezra the priest, the scribe.
12:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些都是在約撒達的孫子，耶書亞的兒子約雅金的日子，並在省長尼希米和作祭司的經學家以斯拉的日子，有職任的。
12:27|ASV|And at the dedication of the wall of Jerusalem they sought the Levites out of all their places, to bring them to Jerusalem, to keep the dedication with gladness, both with thanksgivings, and with singing, with cymbals, psalteries, and with harps.
12:27|Darby|And at the dedication of the wall of Jerusalem they sought  the Levites out of all their places, to bring them to  Jerusalem, to hold the dedication with gladness, both with  thanksgivings, and with singing, [with] cymbals, lutes and  harps.
12:27|KJV|And at the dedication of the wall of Jerusalem they sought the Levites out of all their places, to bring them to Jerusalem, to keep the dedication with gladness, both with thanksgivings, and with singing, with cymbals, psalteries, and with harps.
12:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|為耶路撒冷城牆行奉獻之禮的時候，眾民把利未人從他們所在的各處找出來，把他們帶到耶路撒冷，好稱謝、歌唱、敲鈸、鼓瑟、彈琴，歡歡喜喜的行奉獻之禮。
12:28|ASV|And the sons of the singers gathered themselves together, both out of the plain round about Jerusalem, and from the villages of the Netophathites;
12:28|Darby|And the children of the singers were assembled, both from  the plain [of Jordan] round about Jerusalem, and from the  villages of the Netophathites,
12:28|KJV|And the sons of the singers gathered themselves together, both out of the plain country round about Jerusalem, and from the villages of Netophathi;
12:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|歌唱者的子孫，從耶路撒冷周圍的平原和尼陀法人的村莊，
12:29|ASV|also from Beth-gilgal, and out of the fields of Geba and Azmaveth: for the singers had builded them villages round about Jerusalem.
12:29|Darby|also from Beth-Gilgal, and out of the fields of Geba and  Azmaveth; for the singers had built themselves hamlets round  about Jerusalem.
12:29|KJV|Also from the house of Gilgal, and out of the fields of Geba and Azmaveth: for the singers had builded them villages round about Jerusalem.
12:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並從伯吉甲，又從迦巴和押瑪弗的鄉間聚集，因為歌唱的人在耶路撒冷四圍為自己建造了村莊。
12:30|ASV|And the priests and the Levites purified themselves; and they purified the people, and the gates, and the wall.
12:30|Darby|And the priests and the Levites purified themselves; and  they purified the people, and the gates and the wall.
12:30|KJV|And the priests and the Levites purified themselves, and purified the people, and the gates, and the wall.
12:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祭司和利未人就潔淨自己，也潔淨百姓、城門和城牆。
12:31|ASV|Then I brought up the princes of Judah upon the wall, and appointed two great companies that gave thanks and went in procession; whereof one went on the right hand upon the wall toward the dung gate:
12:31|Darby|And I brought up the princes of Judah upon the wall, and  appointed two great choirs and processions, on the right hand  upon the wall towards the dung-gate.
12:31|KJV|Then I brought up the princes of Judah upon the wall, and appointed two great companies of them that gave thanks, whereof one went on the right hand upon the wall toward the dung gate:
12:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然後我帶猶大的首領上城牆，分派兩大隊稱謝的人，列隊而行。第一隊在城牆上往右邊向糞門行走；
12:32|ASV|and after them went Hoshaiah, and half of the princes of Judah,
12:32|Darby|And after them went Hoshaiah, and half of the princes of  Judah,
12:32|KJV|And after them went Hoshaiah, and half of the princes of Judah,
12:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在他們後頭走的有何沙雅與猶大首領的一半，
12:33|ASV|and Azariah, Ezra, and Meshullam,
12:33|Darby|and Azariah, Ezra, and Meshullam,
12:33|KJV|And Azariah, Ezra, and Meshullam,
12:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又有亞撒利雅、以斯拉、米書蘭、
12:34|ASV|Judah, and Benjamin, and Shemaiah, and Jeremiah,
12:34|Darby|Judah and Benjamin, and Shemaiah, and Jeremiah,
12:34|KJV|Judah, and Benjamin, and Shemaiah, and Jeremiah,
12:34|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|猶大、便雅憫、示瑪雅、耶利米。
12:35|ASV|and certain of the priests' sons with trumpets: Zechariah the son of Jonathan, the son of Shemaiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Micaiah, the son of Zaccur, the son of Asaph;
12:35|Darby|and [certain] of the priests' sons with trumpets:  Zechariah the son of Jonathan, the son of Shemaiah, the son of  Mattaniah, the son of Micaiah, the son of Zaccur, the son of  Asaph;
12:35|KJV|And certain of the priests' sons with trumpets; namely, Zechariah the son of Jonathan, the son of Shemaiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Michaiah, the son of Zaccur, the son of Asaph:
12:35|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|還有些吹號之祭司的子孫，約拿單的兒子撒迦利亞，約拿單是示瑪雅的兒子，示瑪雅是瑪他尼的兒子，瑪他尼是米該亞的兒子，米該亞是撒刻的兒子，撒刻是亞薩的兒子；
12:36|ASV|and his brethren, Shemaiah, and Azarel, Milalai, Gilalai, Maai, Nethanel, and Judah, Hanani, with the musical instruments of David the man of God; and Ezra the scribe was before them.
12:36|Darby|and his brethren, Shemaiah, and Azareel, Milalai, Gilalai,  Maai, Nethaneel, and Judah, Hanani, with the musical  instruments of David the man of God; and Ezra the scribe before  them.
12:36|KJV|And his brethren, Shemaiah, and Azarael, Milalai, Gilalai, Maai, Nethaneel, and Judah, Hanani, with the musical instruments of David the man of God, and Ezra the scribe before them.
12:36|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又有撒迦利亞的弟兄示瑪雅、亞撒利、米拉萊、基拉萊、瑪艾、拿坦業、猶大、哈拿尼，都拿著神人大衛的樂器；經學家以斯拉走在他們前面。
12:37|ASV|And by the fountain gate, and straight before them, they went up by the stairs of the city of David, at the ascent of the wall, above the house of David, even unto the water gate eastward.
12:37|Darby|And at the fountain-gate, and over against them, they went  up by the stairs of the city of David, at the ascent of the  wall, above the house of David, even to the water-gate  eastward.
12:37|KJV|And at the fountain gate, which was over against them, they went up by the stairs of the city of David, at the going up of the wall, above the house of David, even unto the water gate eastward.
12:37|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|到了泉門，他們直往前行，從大衛城的臺階隨城牆的地勢而上，在大衛的宮以上，走到朝東的水門。
12:38|ASV|And the other company of them that gave thanks went to meet them, and I after them, with the half of the people, upon the wall, above the tower of the furnaces, even unto the broad wall,
12:38|Darby|And the second choir went in the opposite direction upon  the wall, and I after them, and the half of the people, from  beyond the tower of the furnaces even to the broad wall;
12:38|KJV|And the other company of them that gave thanks went over against them, and I after them, and the half of the people upon the wall, from beyond the tower of the furnaces even unto the broad wall;
12:38|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|第二隊稱謝的人與那一隊相迎而行，我和民的一半跟隨他們，在城牆上過了爐樓，直到寬牆；
12:39|ASV|and above the gate of Ephraim, and by the old gate, and by the fish gate, and the tower of Hananel, and the tower of Hammeah, even unto the sheep gate: and they stood still in the gate of the guard.
12:39|Darby|and from above the gate of Ephraim, and above the gate of  the old [wall], and above the fish-gate, and the tower of  Hananeel, and the tower of Meah, even to the sheep-gate; and  they stood still in the prison-gate.
12:39|KJV|And from above the gate of Ephraim, and above the old gate, and above the fish gate, and the tower of Hananeel, and the tower of Meah, even unto the sheep gate: and they stood still in the prison gate.
12:39|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又過了以法蓮門、古門、魚門、哈楠業樓、哈米亞樓，直到羊門，就在護衛門站住。
12:40|ASV|So stood the two companies of them that gave thanks in the house of God, and I, and the half of the rulers with me;
12:40|Darby|And both choirs stood in the house of God, and I, and the  half of the rulers with me;
12:40|KJV|So stood the two companies of them that gave thanks in the house of God, and I, and the half of the rulers with me:
12:40|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是這兩隊稱謝的人，連我和官長的一半，站在神的殿堙C
12:41|ASV|and the priests, Eliakim, Maaseiah, Miniamin, Micaiah, Elioenai, Zechariah, and Hananiah, with trumpets;
12:41|Darby|and the priests, Eliakim, Maaseiah, Miniamin, Micaiah,  Elioenai, Zechariah, Hananiah, with trumpets;
12:41|KJV|And the priests; Eliakim, Maaseiah, Miniamin, Michaiah, Elioenai, Zechariah, and Hananiah, with trumpets;
12:41|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|還有祭司以利亞金、瑪西雅、米拿民、米該雅、以利約乃、撒迦利亞、哈楠尼亞吹號；
12:42|ASV|and Maaseiah, and Shemaiah, and Eleazar, and Uzzi, and Jehohanan, and Malchijah, and Elam, and Ezer. And the singers sang loud, with Jezrahiah their overseer.
12:42|Darby|and Maaseiah, and Shemaiah, and Eleazar, and Uzzi, and  Jehohanan, and Malchijah, and Elam, and Ezer. And the singers  sang loud; and Jizrahiah was their overseer.
12:42|KJV|And Maaseiah, and Shemaiah, and Eleazar, and Uzzi, and Jehohanan, and Malchijah, and Elam, and Ezer. And the singers sang loud, with Jezrahiah their overseer.
12:42|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又有瑪西雅、示瑪雅、以利亞撒、烏西、約哈難、瑪基雅、以攔和以謝奏樂。歌唱的就大聲歌唱，伊斯拉希雅監督他們。
12:43|ASV|And they offered great sacrifices that day, and rejoiced; for God had made them rejoice with great joy; and the women also and the children rejoiced: so that the joy of Jerusalem was heard even afar off.
12:43|Darby|And that day they offered great sacrifices, and rejoiced:  for God had made them rejoice with great joy; and also the  women and the children rejoiced. And the joy of Jerusalem was  heard even afar off.
12:43|KJV|Also that day they offered great sacrifices, and rejoiced: for God had made them rejoice with great joy: the wives also and the children rejoiced: so that the joy of Jerusalem was heard even afar off.
12:43|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那日，眾人獻大祭而歡樂，因為神使他們大大歡樂；連婦女帶孩童也都歡樂。耶路撒冷的歡聲，遠處都可聽見。
12:44|ASV|And on that day were men appointed over the chambers for the treasures, for the heave-offerings, for the first-fruits, and for the tithes, to gather into them, according to the fields of the cities, the portions appointed by the law for the priests and Levites: for Judah rejoiced for the priests and for the Levites that waited.
12:44|Darby|And at that time men were appointed over the chambers of  the treasures for the heave-offerings, for the first-fruits,  and for the tithes, to gather into them, out of the fields of  the cities, the portions assigned by the law for the priests  and the Levites; for Judah rejoiced over the priests, and over  the Levites that waited.
12:44|KJV|And at that time were some appointed over the chambers for the treasures, for the offerings, for the firstfruits, and for the tithes, to gather into them out of the fields of the cities the portions of the law for the priests and Levites: for Judah rejoiced for the priests and for the Levites that waited.
12:44|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當日，派人管理庫房，將舉祭、初熟之物、和所取的十分之一，就是按各城田地，照律法所定歸給祭司和利未人的分，都收在媕Y；猶大人因祭司和利未人供職，就歡樂了。
12:45|ASV|And they kept the charge of their God, and the charge of the purification, and so did the singers and the porters, according to the commandment of David, and of Solomon his son.
12:45|Darby|And, with the singers and the doorkeepers, they kept the  ward of their God, and the ward of the purification, according  to the commandment of David [and] of Solomon his son.
12:45|KJV|And both the singers and the porters kept the ward of their God, and the ward of the purification, according to the commandment of David, and of Solomon his son.
12:45|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祭司和利未人遵守神所吩咐的，並守潔淨的禮。歌唱的和守門的，照著大衛和他兒子所羅門的命令，也如此行。
12:46|ASV|For in the days of David and Asaph of old there was a chief of the singers, and songs of praise and thanksgiving unto God.
12:46|Darby|For of old, in the days of David and Asaph, there were the  chiefs of the singers, and songs of praise and thanksgivings to  God.
12:46|KJV|For in the days of David and Asaph of old there were chief of the singers, and songs of praise and thanksgiving unto God.
12:46|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|古時，在大衛和亞薩的日子，有歌詠長，並有讚美稱謝神的詩歌。
12:47<version name="ASV">And all Israel in the days of Zerubbabel, and in the days of Nehemiah, gave the portions of the singers and the porters, as every day required: and they set apart that which was for the Levites; and the Levites set apart that which was for the sons of Aaron. </p><p /><br /></version>
12:47<version name="Darby">And all Israel, in the days of Zerubbabel and in the days  of Nehemiah, gave the portions of the singers and the  doorkeepers, every day what was needed, and they consecrated  things for the Levites; and the Levites consecrated for the  children of Aaron. </p><p /><br /></version>
12:47<version name="KJV">And all Israel in the days of Zerubbabel, and in the days of Nehemiah, gave the portions of the singers and the porters, every day his portion: and they sanctified holy things unto the Levites; and the Levites sanctified them unto the children of Aaron.</p><p /><br /></version>
12:47|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在所羅巴伯和尼希米的日子，以色列眾人將歌唱的、守門的，每日所當得的分供給他們；又把當得的分別為聖給利未人，利未人又把當得的分別為聖給亞倫的子孫。
13:1|ASV|On that day they read in the book of Moses in the audience of the people; and therein was found written, that an Ammonite and a Moabite should not enter into the assembly of God for ever,
13:1|Darby|On that day they read in the book of Moses in the audience  of the people; and there was found written in it that the  Ammonite and the Moabite should not come into the congregation  of God for ever;
13:1|KJV|On that day they read in the book of Moses in the audience of the people; and therein was found written, that the Ammonite and the Moabite should not come into the congregation of God for ever;
13:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當日，人念摩西的律法書給百姓聽，遇見書上寫著說，亞捫人或摩押人永不可入神的會，
13:2|ASV|because they met not the children of Israel with bread and with water, but hired Balaam against them, to curse them: howbeit our God turned the curse into a blessing.
13:2|Darby|because they had not met the children of Israel with bread  and with water, and had hired Balaam against them, to curse  them; but our God turned the curse into blessing.
13:2|KJV|Because they met not the children of Israel with bread and with water, but hired Balaam against them, that he should curse them: howbeit our God turned the curse into a blessing.
13:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為他們沒有拿食物和水來迎接以色列人，反而雇了巴蘭咒詛他們，但我們的神使那咒詛變為祝福。
13:3|ASV|And it came to pass, when they had heard the law, that they separated from Israel all the mixed multitude.
13:3|Darby|And it came to pass, when they heard the law, that they  separated from Israel all the mixed multitude.
13:3|KJV|Now it came to pass, when they had heard the law, that they separated from Israel all the mixed multitude.
13:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|眾民聽見這律法，就使一切閒雜人與以色列人分開。
13:4|ASV|Now before this, Eliashib the priest, who was appointed over the chambers of the house of our God, being allied unto Tobiah,
13:4|Darby|And before this, Eliashib the priest, who had the oversight  of the chambers of the house of our God, a kinsman of Tobijah,
13:4|KJV|And before this, Eliashib the priest, having the oversight of the chamber of the house of our God, was allied unto Tobiah:
13:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這事以前，蒙派管理我們神殿中屋子的祭司以利亞實，因與多比雅結親，
13:5|ASV|had prepared for him a great chamber, where aforetime they laid the meal-offerings, the frankincense, and the vessels, and the tithes of the grain, the new wine, and the oil, which were given by commandment to the Levites, and the singers, and the porters; and the heave-offerings for the priests.
13:5|Darby|had prepared for him a great chamber, where formerly they  laid the oblations, the frankincense, and the vessels, and the  tithes of the corn, the new wine and the oil, which was  commanded for the Levites and the singers and the doorkeepers,  and the heave-offerings of the priests.
13:5|KJV|And he had prepared for him a great chamber, where aforetime they laid the meat offerings, the frankincense, and the vessels, and the tithes of the corn, the new wine, and the oil, which was commanded to be given to the Levites, and the singers, and the porters; and the offerings of the priests.
13:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|為他豫備了一間大屋子，那是從前存放素祭、乳香、器皿，以及照命令供給利未人、歌唱的、守門的，五穀、新酒、和新油的十分之一，並歸祭司之舉祭的地方。
13:6|ASV|But in all this  time I was not at Jerusalem; for in the two and thirtieth year of Artaxerxes king of Babylon I went unto the king: and after certain days asked I leave of the king,
13:6|Darby|And during all that [time] I was not at Jerusalem; for in  the two-and-thirtieth year of Artaxerxes king of Babylon I came  to the king; and after some time I obtained leave of the king.
13:6|KJV|But in all this time was not I at Jerusalem: for in the two and thirtieth year of Artaxerxes king of Babylon came I unto the king, and after certain days obtained I leave of the king:
13:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這一切發生時我不在耶路撒冷，因為巴比倫王亞達薛西三十二年，我到王那堨h；過了一段日子，我向王告假。
13:7|ASV|and I came to Jerusalem, and understood the evil that Eliashib had done for Tobiah, in preparing him a chamber in the courts of the house of God.
13:7|Darby|And I came to Jerusalem, and observed the evil that  Eliashib had done for Tobijah, in preparing him a chamber in  the courts of the house of God.
13:7|KJV|And I came to Jerusalem, and understood of the evil that Eliashib did for Tobiah, in preparing him a chamber in the courts of the house of God.
13:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我來到耶路撒冷，就知道以利亞實為多比雅在神殿的院內豫備屋子的這件惡事。
13:8|ASV|And it grieved me sore: therefore I cast forth all the household stuff of Tobiah out of the chamber.
13:8|Darby|And it grieved me much, and I cast forth all the household  stuff of Tobijah out of the chamber.
13:8|KJV|And it grieved me sore: therefore I cast forth all the household stuff to Tobiah out of the chamber.
13:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我甚惱怒，就把多比雅的一切用器都從屋子堜艄X去，
13:9|ASV|Then I commanded, and they cleansed the chambers: and thither brought I again the vessels of the house of God, with the meal-offerings and the frankincense.
13:9|Darby|And I commanded, and they purified the chambers; and  thither brought I again the vessels of the house of God, the  oblation and the frankincense.
13:9|KJV|Then I commanded, and they cleansed the chambers: and thither brought I again the vessels of the house of God, with the meat offering and the frankincense.
13:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又吩咐人潔淨那些屋子，然後將神殿的器皿、素祭、和乳香搬回去。
13:10|ASV|And I perceived that the portions of the Levites had not been given them; so that the Levites and the singers, that did the work, were fled every one to his field.
13:10|Darby|And I perceived that the portions of the Levites had not  been given, and that the Levites and the singers that did the  work had fled every one to his field.
13:10|KJV|And I perceived that the portions of the Levites had not been given them: for the Levites and the singers, that did the work, were fled every one to his field.
13:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我見利未人所當得的分無人供給他們，甚至供職的利未人與歌唱的，俱各奔回自己的田地去了。
13:11|ASV|Then contended I with the rulers, and said, Why is the house of God forsaken? And I gathered them together, and set them in their place.
13:11|Darby|Then I contended with the rulers, and said, Why is the  house of God forsaken? And I gathered them together and set  them in their place.
13:11|KJV|Then contended I with the rulers, and said, Why is the house of God forsaken? And I gathered them together, and set them in their place.
13:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我就斥責官長說，為何離棄神的殿呢？我便招聚利未人，使他們重站原來的崗位。
13:12|ASV|Then brought all Judah the tithe of the grain and the new wine and the oil unto the treasuries.
13:12|Darby|And all Judah brought the tithe of the corn and the new  wine and the oil into the storehouses.
13:12|KJV|Then brought all Judah the tithe of the corn and the new wine and the oil unto the treasuries.
13:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|猶大眾人就把五穀、新酒、和新油的十分之一，送入倉庫。
13:13|ASV|And I made treasurers over the treasuries, Shelemiah the priest, and Zadok the scribe, and of the Levites, Pedaiah: and next to them was Hanan the son of Zaccur, the son of Mattaniah; for they were counted faithful, and their business was to distribute unto their brethren.
13:13|Darby|And I made storekeepers over the storehouses: Shelemiah  the priest, and Zadok the scribe, and of the Levites, Pedaiah;  and subordinate to them, Hanan the son of Zaccur, the son of  Mattaniah; for they were esteemed faithful, and their office  was to distribute to their brethren.
13:13|KJV|And I made treasurers over the treasuries, Shelemiah the priest, and Zadok the scribe, and of the Levites, Pedaiah: and next to them was Hanan the son of Zaccur, the son of Mattaniah: for they were counted faithful, and their office was to distribute unto their brethren.
13:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我派祭司示利米雅、經學家撒督、和利未人毘大雅，作庫官管理倉庫；副官是瑪他尼的孫子，撒刻的兒子哈難。這些人都算是忠信的，他們的職分是將所供給的分給他們的弟兄。
13:14|ASV|Remember me, O my God, concerning this, and wipe not out my good deeds that I have done for the house of my God, and for the observances thereof.
13:14|Darby|Remember me, O my God, concerning this, and wipe not out  my good deeds which I have done for the house of my God, and  for the charges thereof!
13:14|KJV|Remember me, O my God, concerning this, and wipe not out my good deeds that I have done for the house of my God, and for the offices thereof.
13:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的神阿，求你因這事記念我，不要塗抹我為我神的殿與其中的職任所行的善。
13:15|ASV|In those days saw I in Judah some men treading wine-presses on the sabbath, and bringing in sheaves, and lading asses therewith; as also wine, grapes, and figs, and all manner of burdens, which they brought into Jerusalem on the sabbath day: and I testified against them in the day wherein they sold victuals.
13:15|Darby|In those days I saw in Judah some treading winepresses on  the sabbath, and bringing in sheaves, and lading them on asses;  as also wine, grapes and figs, and all manner of burdens; and  they brought them into Jerusalem on the sabbath day; and I  protested in the day on which they sold the victuals.
13:15|KJV|In those days saw I in Judah some treading wine presses on the sabbath, and bringing in sheaves, and lading asses; as also wine, grapes, and figs, and all manner of burdens, which they brought into Jerusalem on the sabbath day: and I testified against them in the day wherein they sold victuals.
13:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那些日子，我在猶大見有人在安息日踹酒醡，搬運禾捆馱在驢上，又把酒、葡萄、無花果、和各樣的擔子，在安息日運進耶路撒冷；我就在他們賣食物的那日警戒他們。
13:16|ASV|There dwelt men of Tyre also therein, who brought in fish, and all manner of wares, and sold on the sabbath unto the children of Judah, and in Jerusalem.
13:16|Darby|Men of Tyre also dwelt therein, who brought fish and all  manner of ware, and sold it on the sabbath to the children of  Judah, and in Jerusalem.
13:16|KJV|There dwelt men of Tyre also therein, which brought fish, and all manner of ware, and sold on the sabbath unto the children of Judah, and in Jerusalem.
13:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又有住在耶路撒冷的推羅人，把魚和各樣貨物運進來，在安息日，在耶路撒冷賣給猶大人。
13:17|ASV|Then I contended with the nobles of Judah, and said unto them, What evil thing is this that ye do, and profane the sabbath day?
13:17|Darby|And I contended with the nobles of Judah, and said to  them, What evil thing is this which ye do, profaning the  sabbath day?
13:17|KJV|Then I contended with the nobles of Judah, and said unto them, What evil thing is this that ye do, and profane the sabbath day?
13:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我就斥責猶大的貴冑，對他們說，你們怎麼行這惡事瀆犯安息日呢？
13:18|ASV|Did not your fathers thus, and did not our God bring all this evil upon us, and upon this city? yet ye bring more wrath upon Israel by profaning the sabbath.
13:18|Darby|Did not your fathers thus, and did not our God bring all  this evil upon us and upon this city? And ye will bring more  wrath against Israel by profaning the sabbath.
13:18|KJV|Did not your fathers thus, and did not our God bring all this evil upon us, and upon this city? yet ye bring more wrath upon Israel by profaning the sabbath.
13:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|從前你們列祖豈不是這樣行，以致我們的神使這一切災禍臨到我們和這城麼？現在你們還瀆犯安息日，使神的忿怒越發臨到以色列。
13:19|ASV|And it came to pass that, when the gates of Jerusalem began to be dark before the sabbath, I commanded that the doors should be shut, and commanded that they should not be opened till after the sabbath: and some of my servants set I over the gates, that there should no burden be brought in on the sabbath day.
13:19|Darby|And it came to pass, that when it began to be dark in the  gates of Jerusalem before the sabbath, I commanded that the  gates should be shut; and I commanded that they should not be  opened till after the sabbath. And I set [some] of my servants  at the gates, so that no burden should be brought in on the  sabbath day.
13:19|KJV|And it came to pass, that when the gates of Jerusalem began to be dark before the sabbath, I commanded that the gates should be shut, and charged that they should not be opened till after the sabbath: and some of my servants set I at the gates, that there should no burden be brought in on the sabbath day.
13:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在安息日以前，耶路撒冷城門日落有黑影的時候，我就吩咐人將門關鎖，並且吩咐人不准開放，直到安息日過了；我又派我幾個僕人在城門站崗，免得有人在安息日擔甚麼擔子進來。
13:20|ASV|So the merchants and sellers of all kind of wares lodged without Jerusalem once or twice.
13:20|Darby|And the dealers and sellers of all kind of ware passed the  night without Jerusalem once or twice.
13:20|KJV|So the merchants and sellers of all kind of ware lodged without Jerusalem once or twice.
13:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是商人和販賣各樣貨物的，有一兩次在耶路撒冷城外過夜。
13:21|ASV|Then I testified against them, and said unto them, Why lodge ye about the wall? if ye do so again, I will lay hands on you. From that time forth came they no more on the sabbath.
13:21|Darby|And I testified against them, and said to them, Why do ye  pass the night before the wall? if ye do so again, I will lay  hands on you. From that time forth they came not on the  sabbath.
13:21|KJV|Then I testified against them, and said unto them, Why lodge ye about the wall? if ye do so again, I will lay hands on you. From that time forth came they no more on the sabbath.
13:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我就警戒他們，說，你們為何在城牆前面過夜？若再這樣，我必下手拿辦你們。從此以後，他們在安息日就不來了。
13:22|ASV|And I commanded the Levites that they should purify themselves, and that they should come and keep the gates, to sanctify the sabbath day. Remember unto me, O my God, this also, and spare me according to the greatness of thy lovingkindness.
13:22|Darby|And I commanded the Levites that they should purify  themselves, and that they should come and keep the gates, to  hallow the sabbath day. Remember this also for me, my God, and  spare me according to thy great loving-kindness!
13:22|KJV|And I commanded the Levites that they should cleanse themselves, and that they should come and keep the gates, to sanctify the sabbath day. Remember me, O my God, concerning this also, and spare me according to the greatness of thy mercy.
13:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我吩咐利未人當潔淨自己，並來守城門，使安息日分別為聖。我的神阿，求你也因這事記念我，照你的大慈愛憐惜我。
13:23|ASV|In those days also saw I the Jews that had married women of Ashdod, of Ammon, and of Moab:
13:23|Darby|In those days also I saw Jews that had married wives of  Ashdod, of Ammon, [and] of Moab.
13:23|KJV|In those days also saw I Jews that had married wives of Ashdod, of Ammon, and of Moab:
13:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那些日子，我也見猶大人娶了亞實突、亞捫、摩押的女子為妻。
13:24|ASV|and their children spake half in the speech of Ashdod, and could not speak in the Jews' language, but according to the language of each people.
13:24|Darby|And their children spoke half in the language of Ashdod,  and could not speak in the Jews' language, but according to the  language of each people.
13:24|KJV|And their children spake half in the speech of Ashdod, and could not speak in the Jews' language, but according to the language of each people.
13:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們的兒女說話，一半是亞實突的話，不會說猶大的話，所說的是照著各民的方言。
13:25|ASV|And I contended with them, and cursed them, and smote certain of them, and plucked off their hair, and made them swear by God, saying, Ye shall not give your daughters unto their sons, nor take their daughters for your sons, or for yourselves.
13:25|Darby|And I contended with them, and cursed them, and smote  certain of them and plucked off their hair, and adjured them by  God [saying], Ye shall not give your daughters to their sons,  nor take their daughters for your sons or for yourselves.
13:25|KJV|And I contended with them, and cursed them, and smote certain of them, and plucked off their hair, and made them swear by God, saying, Ye shall not give your daughters unto their sons, nor take their daughters unto your sons, or for yourselves.
13:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我就斥責他們，咒詛他們，打了他們幾個人，拔下他們的頭髮，叫他們指著神起誓，我說，你們不可將自己的女兒嫁給他們的兒子，也不可為自己的兒子和自己娶他們的女兒。
13:26|ASV|Did not Solomon king of Israel sin by these things? yet among many nations was there no king like him, and he was beloved of his God, and God made him king over all Israel: nevertheless even him did foreign women cause to sin.
13:26|Darby|Did not Solomon king of Israel sin by these things? Yet  among the many nations was there no king like him, who was  beloved of his God, and God made him king over all Israel; but  even him did foreign wives cause to sin.
13:26|KJV|Did not Solomon king of Israel sin by these things? yet among many nations was there no king like him, who was beloved of his God, and God made him king over all Israel: nevertheless even him did outlandish women cause to sin.
13:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我又說，以色列王所羅門不是在這些事上犯罪麼？在多國中並沒有一王像他，且蒙他神所愛，神使他作全以色列的王；然而連他也被外邦女子引誘犯罪。
13:27|ASV|Shall we then hearken unto you to do all this great evil, to trespass against our God in marrying foreign women?
13:27|Darby|And should we hearken to you to do all this great evil, to  act unfaithfully to our God by marrying foreign wives?
13:27|KJV|Shall we then hearken unto you to do all this great evil, to transgress against our God in marrying strange wives?
13:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|難道我們要聽從你們，行這一切大惡，娶外邦女子為妻，行事不忠信得罪我們的神麼？
13:28|ASV|And one of the sons of Joiada, the son of Eliashib the high priest, was son-in-law to Sanballat the Horonite: therefore I chased him from me.
13:28|Darby|And [one] of the sons of Joiada, the son of Eliashib the  high priest, was son-in-law to Sanballat the Horonite; and I  chased him from me.
13:28|KJV|And one of the sons of Joiada, the son of Eliashib the high priest, was son in law to Sanballat the Horonite: therefore I chased him from me.
13:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|大祭司以利亞實的孫子，耶何耶大的一個兒子，是和倫人參巴拉的女婿，我就從我這塈漭L趕出去。
13:29|ASV|Remember them, O my God, because they have defiled the priesthood, and the covenant of the priesthood, and of the Levites.
13:29|Darby|Remember them, my God, for they are polluters of the  priesthood, and of the covenant of the priesthood and of the  Levites!
13:29|KJV|Remember them, O my God, because they have defiled the priesthood, and the covenant of the priesthood, and of the Levites.
13:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的神阿，求你記念他們的罪；因為他們玷污了祭司的職任，並玷污了有關祭司職任及利未人的約。
13:30|ASV|Thus cleansed I them from all foreigners, and appointed charges for the priests and for the Levites, every one in his work;
13:30|Darby|And I purified them from all foreigners, and appointed the  charges of the priests and the Levites, every one in his  service;
13:30|KJV|Thus cleansed I them from all strangers, and appointed the wards of the priests and the Levites, every one in his business;
13:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我潔淨他們，使他們離絕一切外邦的事物。
13:31<version name="ASV">and for the wood-offering, at times appointed, and for the first-fruits. Remember me, O my God, for good. </p><p /><br /></version>
13:31<version name="Darby">and for the wood-offering, at times appointed, and for the  first-fruits. Remember me, O my God, for good! </p><p /><br /></version>
13:31<version name="KJV">And for the wood offering, at times appointed, and for the firstfruits. Remember me, O my God, for good.</p><p /><br /></version>
13:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我又派百姓按定期獻木柴和初熟之物。我的神阿，求你記念我，以善待我。
