1:1|ASV|Paul and Timothy, servants of Christ Jesus, to all the saints in Christ Jesus that are at Philippi, with the bishops and deacons:
1:1|Darby|Paul and Timotheus, bondmen of Jesus Christ, to all the  saints in Christ Jesus who are in Philippi, with [the]  overseers and ministers;
1:1|KJV|Paul and Timotheus, the servants of Jesus Christ, to all the saints in Christ Jesus which are at Philippi, with the bishops and deacons:
1:1|WYC|Paul and Timothy, servants of Jesus Christ, to all the holy men in Christ Jesus, that be at Philippi, with bishops and deacons,
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|基督耶穌的奴僕，保羅和提摩太，寫信給所有在腓立比，在基督耶穌裡的聖徒，同諸位監督和諸位執事：
1:2|ASV|Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.
1:2|Darby|grace to you, and peace from God our Father and [the] Lord  Jesus Christ.
1:2|KJV|Grace be unto you, and peace, from God our Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ.
1:2|WYC|grace and peace to you of God our Father [grace to you and peace of God our Father], and of the Lord Jesus Christ.
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願恩典與平安，從神我們的父，並主耶穌基督歸與你們。
1:3|ASV|I thank my God upon all my remembrance of you,
1:3|Darby|I thank my God for my whole remembrance of you,
1:3|KJV|I thank my God upon every remembrance of you,
1:3|WYC|I do thankings to my God in all mind of you
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我每逢想念你們，就感謝我的神；
1:4|ASV|always in every supplication of mine on behalf of you all making my supplication with joy,
1:4|Darby|constantly in my every supplication, making the supplication  for you all with joy,
1:4|KJV|Always in every prayer of mine for you all making request with joy,
1:4|WYC|evermore in all my prayers for all you with joy, and make beseeching
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|每逢為你們眾人祈求的時候，總是歡歡喜喜的祈求，
1:5|ASV|for your fellowship in furtherance of the gospel from the first day until now;
1:5|Darby|because of your fellowship with the gospel, from the first  day until now;
1:5|KJV|For your fellowship in the gospel from the first day until now;
1:5|WYC|on your communing in the gospel of Christ, from the first day till now [from the first day unto now];
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|為了你們從頭一天直到如今，在推廣福音上所有的交通；
1:6|ASV|being confident of this very thing, that he who began a good work in you will perfect it until the day of Jesus Christ:
1:6|Darby|having confidence of this very thing, that he who has begun  in you a good work will complete it unto Jesus Christ's day:
1:6|KJV|Being confident of this very thing, that he which hath begun a good work in you will perform it until the day of Jesus Christ:
1:6<version name="WYC">trusting this same thing, that he that began in you a good work, shall perform <i>it</i> till into the day of Jesus Christ.</version>
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我深信那在你們裡面開始了善工的，必完成這工，直到基督耶穌的日子。
1:7|ASV|even as it is right for me to be thus minded on behalf of you all, because I have you in my heart, inasmuch as, both in my bonds and in the defence and confirmation of the gospel, ye all are partakers with me of grace.
1:7|Darby|as it is righteous for me to think this as to you all,  because ye have *me* in your hearts, and that both in my bonds  and in the defence and confirmation of the glad tidings ye are  all participators in my grace.
1:7|KJV|Even as it is meet for me to think this of you all, because I have you in my heart; inasmuch as both in my bonds, and in the defence and confirmation of the gospel, ye all are partakers of my grace.
1:7|WYC|As it is just to me to feel this thing for all you [for you all], for that I have you in heart, and in my bonds, and in defending and confirming of the gospel, that all ye be fellows of my joy.
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我為你們眾人有這樣的想法，原是應當的，因為你們有我在你們心裡，無論我在捆鎖之中，或在辯護、證實福音的時候，你們眾人都與我同享恩典。
1:8|ASV|For God is my witness, how I long after you all in the tender mercies of Christ Jesus.
1:8|Darby|For God is my witness how I long after you all in [the]  bowels of Christ Jesus.
1:8|KJV|For God is my record, how greatly I long after you all in the bowels of Jesus Christ.
1:8|WYC|For God is a witness to me, how I covet all you [how I covet you all] in the bowels of Jesus Christ.
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神可為我作見證，我在基督耶穌的心腸裡，怎樣切切的想念你們眾人。
1:9|ASV|And this I pray, that your love may abound yet more and more in knowledge and all discernment;
1:9|Darby|And this I pray, that your love may abound yet more and more  in full knowledge and all intelligence,
1:9|KJV|And this I pray, that your love may abound yet more and more in knowledge and in all judgment;
1:9<version name="WYC">And this thing I pray, that your charity be plenteous more and more in knowing [that your charity be plenteous more and more in science, <i>or knowing</i>], and in all wit;</version>
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我所禱告的，就是要你們的愛，在充足的知識並一切的辨識上，多而又多的洋溢，
1:10|ASV|so that ye may approve the things that are excellent; that ye may be sincere and void of offence unto the day of Christ;
1:10|Darby|that ye may judge of and approve the things that are more  excellent, in order that ye may be pure and without offence for  Christ's day,
1:10|KJV|That ye may approve things that are excellent; that ye may be sincere and without offence till the day of Christ.
1:10|WYC|that ye approve the better things [that ye prove the better things], that ye be clean and without offence in the day of Christ;
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|使你們能鑑賞那更美、不同的事，好叫你們純誠無過，直到基督的日子，
1:11|ASV|being filled with the fruits of righteousness, which are through Jesus Christ, unto the glory and praise of God.
1:11|Darby|being complete as regards the fruit of righteousness, which  [is] by Jesus Christ, to God's glory and praise.
1:11|KJV|Being filled with the fruits of righteousness, which are by Jesus Christ, unto the glory and praise of God.
1:11|WYC|filled [full-filled] with the fruit of rightwiseness by Jesus Christ, into the glory and praising of God.
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|結滿了那藉著耶穌基督而有的義果，使榮耀稱讚歸與神。
1:12|ASV|Now I would have you know, brethren, that the things  which happened unto me have fallen out rather unto the progress of the gospel;
1:12|Darby|But I would have you know, brethren, that the circumstances  in which I am have turned out rather to the furtherance of the  glad tidings,
1:12|KJV|But I would ye should understand, brethren, that the things which happened unto me have fallen out rather unto the furtherance of the gospel;
1:12|WYC|For, brethren, I will that ye know, that the things that be about me have come more to the profit of the gospel,
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，我願意你們知道，我所遭遇的事，更是為著福音的進展，
1:13|ASV|so that my bonds became manifest in Christ throughout the whole praetorian guard, and to all the rest;
1:13|Darby|so that my bonds have become manifest [as being] in Christ  in all the praetorium and to all others;
1:13|KJV|So that my bonds in Christ are manifest in all the palace, and in all other places;
1:13|WYC|so that my bonds were made known in Christ, in each moot hall, and in all other places;
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以致我的捆鎖，在御營全軍，和所有其餘的人中，已經顯明是為基督的緣故。
1:14|ASV|and that most of the brethren in the Lord, being confident through my bonds, are more abundantly bold to speak the word of God without fear.
1:14|Darby|and that the most of the brethren, trusting in [the] Lord  through my bonds, dare more abundantly to speak the word of God  fearlessly.
1:14|KJV|And many of the brethren in the Lord, waxing confident by my bonds, are much more bold to speak the word without fear.
1:14|WYC|that more of [the] brethren trusting in the Lord more plenteously for my bonds, durst without dread speak the word of God. [that more of the brethren in the Lord trusting in my bonds, more plenteously durst without dread speak the word of God.]
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且大多數的弟兄們，因我的捆鎖，在主裡篤信不疑，越發放膽講說神的話，無所懼怕。
1:15|ASV|Some indeed preach Christ even of envy and strife; and some also of good will:
1:15|Darby|Some indeed also for envy and strife, but some also for  good will, preach the Christ.
1:15|KJV|Some indeed preach Christ even of envy and strife; and some also of good will:
1:15|WYC|But some for envy and strife, some for good will, preach Christ;
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有的人傳基督，是因著嫉妒爭競，也有的是因著好意：
1:16|ASV|the one do it of love, knowing that I am set for the defence of the gospel;
1:16|Darby|These indeed out of love, knowing that I am set for the  defence of the glad tidings;
1:16|KJV|The one preach Christ of contention, not sincerely, supposing to add affliction to my bonds:
1:16|WYC|and some of charity, witting that I am put in the defence of the gospel.
1:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這一等是出於愛，知道我是為辯護福音設立的，
1:17|ASV|but the other proclaim Christ of faction, not sincerely, thinking to raise up affliction for me in my bonds.
1:17|Darby|but those out of contention, announce the Christ, not  purely, supposing to arouse tribulation for my bonds.
1:17|KJV|But the other of love, knowing that I am set for the defence of the gospel.
1:17<version name="WYC">But some of strife [Forsooth some of contention, <i>or strife</i>,] show Christ not cleanly, guessing them(selves) to raise tribulation to my bonds.</version>
1:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那一等宣傳基督，卻是出於私圖好爭，並不純潔，想要加重我捆鎖的苦楚。
1:18|ASV|What then? only that in every way, whether in pretence or in truth, Christ is proclaimed; and therein I rejoice, yea, and will rejoice.
1:18|Darby|What is it then? at any rate, in every way, whether in  pretext or in truth, Christ is announced; and in this I  rejoice, yea, also I will rejoice;
1:18|KJV|What then? notwithstanding, every way, whether in pretence, or in truth, Christ is preached; and I therein do rejoice, yea, and will rejoice.
1:18|WYC|But what? while on all manner, either by occasion, either by truth, Christ is showed [What soothly? the while on all manner, either by contention, either by truth, Christ is showed]; and in this thing I have joy, but also I shall have joy.
1:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這有何妨呢？或假意，或真誠，無論怎樣，基督究竟被宣傳開了，為此我就歡喜，並且還要歡喜；
1:19|ASV|For I know that this shall turn out to my salvation, through your supplication and the supply of the Spirit of Jesus Christ,
1:19|Darby|for I know that this shall turn out for me to salvation,  through your supplication and [the] supply of the Spirit of  Jesus Christ;
1:19|KJV|For I know that this shall turn to my salvation through your prayer, and the supply of the Spirit of Jesus Christ,
1:19|WYC|And I know, that this thing shall come to me into health by your prayer, and the under-ministering of the Spirit of Jesus Christ,
1:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我知道，這事藉著你們的祈求，和耶穌基督之靈全備的供應，終必叫我得救。
1:20|ASV|according to my earnest expectation and hope, that in nothing shall I be put to shame, but that with all boldness, as always, so now also Christ shall be magnified in my body, whether by life, or by death.
1:20|Darby|according to my earnest expectation and hope, that in  nothing I shall be ashamed, but in all boldness, as always, now  also Christ shall be magnified in my body whether by life or by  death.
1:20|KJV|According to my earnest expectation and my hope, that in nothing I shall be ashamed, but that with all boldness, as always, so now also Christ shall be magnified in my body, whether it be by life, or by death.
1:20|WYC|by mine abiding and hope [after mine abiding and hope].  For in nothing I shall be ashamed, but in all trust as evermore and now, Christ shall be magnified in my body, either by life, either by death.
1:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這是照著我所專切期待並盼望的，就是沒有一事會叫我羞愧，只要凡事放膽，無論是生，是死，總叫基督在我身體上，現今也照常顯大，
1:21|ASV|For to me to live is Christ, and to die is gain.
1:21|Darby|For for me to live [is] Christ, and to die gain;
1:21|KJV|For to me to live is Christ, and to die is gain.
1:21|WYC|For [to] me to live is Christ, and to die is winning.
1:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為在我，活著就是基督，死了就有益處。
1:22|ASV|But if to live in the flesh, --if this shall bring fruit from my work, then what I shall choose I know not.
1:22|Darby|but if to live in flesh [is my lot], this is for me worth  the while: and what I shall choose I cannot tell.
1:22|KJV|But if I live in the flesh, this is the fruit of my labour: yet what I shall choose I wot not.
1:22|WYC|That if to live in flesh, [this] is fruit of work to me, lo! what I shall choose, I know not. [That if to live in flesh, this is fruit of work to me, and what I shall choose, I know not.]
1:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但我在肉身活著，若使我的工作有果子，我就不知道該挑選甚麼。
1:23|ASV|But I am in a strait betwixt the two, having the desire to depart and be with Christ; for it is very far better:
1:23|Darby|But I am pressed by both, having the desire for departure  and being with Christ, [for] [it is] very much better,
1:23|KJV|For I am in a strait betwixt two, having a desire to depart, and to be with Christ; which is far better:
1:23<version name="WYC">But I am constrained of two things, I have desire to be departed [Forsooth I am constrained of two things, having desire to be dissolved, <i>or departed the soul from the body</i>], and to be with Christ,<i> it is</i> much more better;</version>
1:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我正困迫於兩難之間，情願離世與基督同在，因為那是好得無比的；
1:24|ASV|yet to abide in the flesh is more needful for your sake.
1:24|Darby|but remaining in the flesh [is] more necessary for your  sakes;
1:24|KJV|Nevertheless to abide in the flesh is more needful for you.
1:24|WYC|but to dwell in flesh, is needful for you.
1:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而留在肉身，為你們更是需要的。
1:25|ASV|And having this confidence, I know that I shall abide, yea, and abide with you all, for your progress and joy in the faith;
1:25|Darby|and having confidence of this, I know that I shall remain  and abide along with you all, for your progress and joy in  faith;
1:25|KJV|And having this confidence, I know that I shall abide and continue with you all for your furtherance and joy of faith;
1:25|WYC|And I trusting this thing, know that I shall dwell, and perfectly dwell to all you, to your profit and joy of faith,
1:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我既然這樣深信，就知道仍要留下，繼續與你們眾人同住，使你們得到信仰上的進步和喜樂，
1:26|ASV|that your glorying may abound in Christ Jesus in me through my presence with you again.
1:26|Darby|that your boasting may abound in Christ Jesus through me by  my presence again with you.
1:26|KJV|That your rejoicing may be more abundant in Jesus Christ for me by my coming to you again.
1:26|WYC|that your thanking abound in Christ Jesus in me, by my coming again to you.
1:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|好叫你們的誇耀，在基督耶穌裡，因我再到你們那裡去，就在我身上得以洋溢。
1:27|ASV|Only let your manner of life be worthy of the gospel of Christ: that, whether I come and see you and be absent, I may hear of your state, that ye stand fast in one spirit, with one soul striving for the faith of the gospel;
1:27|Darby|Only conduct yourselves worthily of the glad tidings of the  Christ, in order that whether coming and seeing you, or absent,  I may hear of what concerns you, that ye stand firm in one  spirit, with one soul, labouring together in the same conflict  with the faith of the glad tidings;
1:27|KJV|Only let your conversation be as it becometh the gospel of Christ: that whether I come and see you, or else be absent, I may hear of your affairs, that ye stand fast in one spirit, with one mind striving together for the faith of the gospel;
1:27|WYC|Only live ye worthily to the gospel of Christ, that whether when I come and see you, either absent I hear of you [or absent I shall hear of you], that ye stand in one spirit of one will, travailing together to the faith of the gospel.
1:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只要你們行事為人配得過基督的福音，叫我或來見你們，或不在你們那裡，可以聽見關於你們的事，就是你們在一個靈裡站立得住，同魂與福音的信仰一齊努力；
1:28|ASV|and in nothing affrighted by the adversaries: which is for them an evident token of perdition, but of your salvation, and that from God;
1:28|Darby|and not frightened in anything by the opposers, which is to  them a demonstration of destruction, but of your salvation, and  that from God;
1:28|KJV|And in nothing terrified by your adversaries: which is to them an evident token of perdition, but to you of salvation, and that of God.
1:28<version name="WYC">And in nothing be ye afeared of adversaries, which is to them cause of perdition, but to you <i>a</i> <i>cause</i> of health.  And this thing <i>is</i> of God.</version>
1:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡事不為敵人所驚嚇：這是證明他們滅亡，你們得救，而且這樣的證明乃是從神而來的；
1:29|ASV|because to you it hath been granted in the behalf of Christ, not only to believe on him, but also to suffer in his behalf:
1:29|Darby|because to you has been given, as regards Christ, not only  the believing on him but the suffering for him also,
1:29|KJV|For unto you it is given in the behalf of Christ, not only to believe on him, but also to suffer for his sake;
1:29|WYC|For it is given to you for Christ, that not only ye believe in him, but also that ye suffer for him;
1:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為你們是為了基督的緣故蒙恩，不但得以信入祂，也得以為祂受苦，
1:30<version name="ASV">having the same conflict which ye saw in me, and now hear to be in me. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:30<version name="Darby">having the same conflict which ye have seen in me, and now  hear of in me. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:30<version name="KJV">Having the same conflict which ye saw in me, and now hear to be in me.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:30|WYC|having the same strife, which ye saw in me, and now ye have heard of me.
1:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|經歷你們在我身上從前所看見，現在所聽見同樣的爭戰。
2:1|ASV|If there is therefore any exhortation in Christ, if any consolation of love, if any fellowship of the Spirit, if any tender mercies and compassions,
2:1|Darby|If then [there be] any comfort in Christ, if any consolation  of love, if any fellowship of [the] Spirit, if any bowels and  compassions,
2:1|KJV|If there be therefore any consolation in Christ, if any comfort of love, if any fellowship of the Spirit, if any bowels and mercies,
2:1<version name="WYC">Therefore if any comfort <i>is</i> in Christ, if any solace of charity, if any fellowship of Spirit, if any inwardness of mercy doing [if any entrails of mercy doing],</version>
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以在基督裡若有甚麼鼓勵，若有甚麼愛的安慰，若有甚麼靈的交通，若有甚麼慈心、憐恤，
2:2|ASV|make full my joy, that ye be of the same mind, having the same love, being of one accord, of one mind;
2:2|Darby|fulfil my joy, that ye may think the same thing, having the  same love, joined in soul, thinking one thing;
2:2|KJV|Fulfil ye my joy, that ye be likeminded, having the same love, being of one accord, of one mind.
2:2|WYC|fill ye my joy, that ye understand the same thing, and have the same charity, of one will, and feel the same thing; [fulfill ye my joy, that ye understand the same thing, having the same charity, of one will, feeling the same thing;]
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們就要使我的喜樂滿足，就是要思念相同的事，有相同的愛，魂裡聯結，思念同一件事，
2:3|ASV|doing nothing through faction or through vainglory, but in lowliness of mind each counting other better than himself;
2:3|Darby|[let] nothing [be] in the spirit of strife or vain glory,  but, in lowliness of mind, each esteeming the other as more  excellent than themselves;
2:3|KJV|Let nothing be done through strife or vainglory; but in lowliness of mind let each esteem other better than themselves.
2:3<version name="WYC">nothing by strife, neither by vain glory, but in meekness, deeming each other to be higher than himself; <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22412a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡事都不私圖好爭，也不貪圖虛榮，只要心思卑微，各人看別人比自己強；
2:4|ASV|not looking each of you to his own things, but each of you also to the things of others.
2:4|Darby|regarding not each his own [qualities], but each those of  others also.
2:4|KJV|Look not every man on his own things, but every man also on the things of others.
2:4|WYC|not beholding each by himself what things be his own, but those things that be of other men. [not each by themselves beholding what things be their own, but those things that be of others.]
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|各人不單看重自己的長處，也看重別人的。
2:5|ASV|Have this mind in you, which was also in Christ Jesus:
2:5|Darby|For let this mind be in you which [was] also in Christ  Jesus;
2:5|KJV|Let this mind be in you, which was also in Christ Jesus:
2:5<version name="WYC">And feel ye this thing in you, which <i>was</i> also in Christ Jesus;</version>
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們裡面要思念基督耶穌裡面所思念的：
2:6|ASV|who, existing in the form of God, counted not the being on an equality with God a thing to be grasped,
2:6|Darby|who, subsisting in the form of God, did not esteem it an  object of rapine to be on an equality with God;
2:6|KJV|Who, being in the form of God, thought it not robbery to be equal with God:
2:6|WYC|which when he was in the form of God, deemed not raven, that himself were even to God; [which when he was in the form of God, deemed not raven, himself to be even to God;]
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂本有神的形狀，不以自己與神同等為強奪之珍，緊持不放，
2:7|ASV|but emptied himself, taking the form of a servant, being made in the likeness of men;
2:7|Darby|but emptied himself, taking a bondman's form, taking his  place in [the] likeness of men;
2:7|KJV|But made himself of no reputation, and took upon him the form of a servant, and was made in the likeness of men:
2:7|WYC|but he lowed himself [but he meeked himself], taking the form of a servant, and was made into the likeness of men,
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|反而倒空自己，取了奴僕的形狀，成為人的樣式；
2:8|ASV|and being found in fashion as a man, he humbled himself, becoming obedient even unto death, yea, the death of the cross.
2:8|Darby|and having been found in figure as a man, humbled himself,  becoming obedient even unto death, and [that the] death of  [the] cross.
2:8|KJV|And being found in fashion as a man, he humbled himself, and became obedient unto death, even the death of the cross.
2:8<version name="WYC">and in habit was found as a man.  He meeked himself, and was made obedient to the death <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22417b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup>, yea, to the death of the cross.</version>
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|既顯為人的樣子，就降卑自己，順從至死，且死在十字架上。
2:9|ASV|Wherefore also God highly exalted him, and gave unto him the name which is above every name;
2:9|Darby|Wherefore also God highly exalted him, and granted him a  name, that which is above every name,
2:9|KJV|Wherefore God also hath highly exalted him, and given him a name which is above every name:
2:9|WYC|For which thing God enhanced him, and gave to him a name that is above all name; [For which thing and God enhanced him, and gave to him a name that is above all names;]
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以神將祂升為至高，又賜給祂那超乎萬名之上的名，
2:10|ASV|that in the name of Jesus every knee should bow, of things in heaven and things on earth and things under the earth,
2:10|Darby|that at the name of Jesus every knee should bow, of  heavenly and earthly and infernal [beings],
2:10|KJV|That at the name of Jesus every knee should bow, of things in heaven, and things in earth, and things under the earth;
2:10|WYC|that in the name of Jesus each knee be bowed, of heavenly things, [and] of earthly things, and of hell's;
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|叫天上的、地上的和地底下的，在耶穌的名裡，萬膝都要跪拜，
2:11|ASV|and that every tongue should confess that Jesus Christ is Lord, to the glory of God the Father.
2:11|Darby|and every tongue confess that Jesus Christ [is] Lord to God  [the] Father's glory.
2:11|KJV|And that every tongue should confess that Jesus Christ is Lord, to the glory of God the Father.
2:11|WYC|and each tongue acknowledge, that the Lord Jesus Christ is in the glory of God the Father.
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|萬口都要公開承認耶穌基督為主，使榮耀歸與父神。
2:12|ASV|So then, my beloved, even as ye have always obeyed, not as in my presence only, but now much more in my absence, work out your own salvation with fear and trembling;
2:12|Darby|So that, my beloved, even as ye have always obeyed, not as  in my presence only, but now much rather in my absence, work  out your own salvation with fear and trembling,
2:12|KJV|Wherefore, my beloved, as ye have always obeyed, not as in my presence only, but now much more in my absence, work out your own salvation with fear and trembling.
2:12<version name="WYC">Therefore, my most dear-worthy <i>brethren </i>[my most dear-worthy], as evermore ye have obeyed, not in my presence only, but much more now in mine absence, work ye with dread and trembling your health.</version>
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我親愛的，你們既是常順從的，不但我與你們同在的時候，就是我如今不在的時候，更是順從的，就當恐懼戰兢，作成你們自己的救恩，
2:13|ASV|for it is God who worketh in you both to will and to work, for his good pleasure.
2:13|Darby|for it is God who works in you both the willing and the  working according to [his] good pleasure.
2:13|KJV|For it is God which worketh in you both to will and to do of his good pleasure.
2:13|WYC|For it is God that worketh in you, both to will [both to desire], and to perform, for good will.
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為乃是神為著祂的美意，在你們裡面運行，使你們立志並行事。
2:14|ASV|Do all things without murmurings and questionings:
2:14|Darby|Do all things without murmurings and reasonings,
2:14|KJV|Do all things without murmurings and disputings:
2:14|WYC|And do ye all things without grumblings and doubtings; [Forsooth do ye all things without grutchings and doubtings;]
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡所行的，都不要發怨言，起爭論，
2:15|ASV|that ye may become blameless and harmless, children of God without blemish in the midst of a crooked and perverse generation, among whom ye are seen as lights in the world,
2:15|Darby|that ye may be harmless and simple, irreproachable children  of God in the midst of a crooked and perverted generation;  among whom ye appear as lights in [the] world,
2:15|KJV|That ye may be blameless and harmless, the sons of God, without rebuke, in the midst of a crooked and perverse nation, among whom ye shine as lights in the world;
2:15|WYC|that ye be without plaint, and simple as the sons of God, without reproof, in the middle of a depraved nation [in the middle of a shrewd nation] and a wayward; among which ye shine as givers of light in the world [among whom ye shine as givers of light in the world;].
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|使你們無可指摘、純潔無雜，在彎曲悖謬的世代中，作神無瑕疵的兒女；你們在其中好像發光之體顯在世界裡，
2:16|ASV|holding forth the word of life; that I may have whereof to glory in the day of Christ, that I did not run in vain neither labor in vain.
2:16|Darby|holding forth [the] word of life, so as to be a boast for  me in Christ's day, that I have not run in vain nor laboured in  vain.
2:16|KJV|Holding forth the word of life; that I may rejoice in the day of Christ, that I have not run in vain, neither laboured in vain.
2:16|WYC|And hold ye together the word of life to my glory in the day of Christ; for I have not run in vain, neither I have travailed in vain. [holding together the word of life to my glory in the day of Christ; for I have not run in vain, neither in vain travailed.]
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|將生命的話表明出來，叫我在基督的日子，好誇我沒有空跑，也沒有徒勞。
2:17|ASV|Yea, and if I am offered upon the sacrifice and service of your faith, I joy, and rejoice with you all:
2:17|Darby|But if also I am poured out as a libation on the sacrifice  and ministration of your faith, I rejoice, and rejoice in  common with you all.
2:17|KJV|Yea, and if I be offered upon the sacrifice and service of your faith, I joy, and rejoice with you all.
2:17<version name="WYC">But though I be offered, <i>or slain</i>, on the sacrifice and service of your faith, I have joy, and I thank you all. [But and if I be offered, <i>or slain</i>, upon the sacrifice and service of your faith, I have joy, and together thank you all.]</version>
2:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而，即使我成為奠祭，澆奠在你們信心的祭物和供奉上，也是喜樂，並且與你們眾人一同喜樂。
2:18|ASV|and in the same manner do ye also joy, and rejoice with me.
2:18|Darby|In like manner do *ye* also rejoice, and rejoice with me.
2:18|KJV|For the same cause also do ye joy, and rejoice with me.
2:18|WYC|And for the same thing have ye joy, and thank ye me. [The same thing forsooth and ye have joy, and together thank me.]
2:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們也要同樣喜樂，並且與我一同喜樂。
2:19|ASV|But I hope in the Lord Jesus to send Timothy shortly unto you, that I also may be of good comfort, when I know your state.
2:19|Darby|But I hope in [the] Lord Jesus to send Timotheus to you  shortly, that *I* also may be refreshed, knowing how ye get on.
2:19|KJV|But I trust in the Lord Jesus to send Timotheus shortly unto you, that I also may be of good comfort, when I know your state.
2:19|WYC|And I hope in the Lord Jesus, that I shall send Timothy soon to you [Forsooth I hope in the Lord Jesus, me to send Timothy soon to you], that I be of good comfort, when those things be known that be about you.
2:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在主耶穌裡，盼望快打發提摩太到你們那裡去，叫我知道關於你們的事，也可魂中快慰。
2:20|ASV|For I have no man likeminded, who will care truly for your state.
2:20|Darby|For I have no one like-minded who will care with genuine  feeling how ye get on.
2:20|KJV|For I have no man likeminded, who will naturally care for your state.
2:20|WYC|For I have no man so of one will, that is busy for you with clean affection.
2:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因我沒有人與我同魂，真正關心你們的事，
2:21|ASV|For they all seek their own, not the things of Jesus Christ.
2:21|Darby|For all seek their own things, not the things of Jesus  Christ.
2:21|KJV|For all seek their own, not the things which are Jesus Christ's.
2:21|WYC|For all men seek those things that be their own, not those that be of Christ Jesus.
2:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為眾人都尋求自己的事，並不尋求基督耶穌的事。
2:22|ASV|But ye know the proof of him, that, as a child serveth a father, so he served with me in furtherance of the gospel.
2:22|Darby|But ye know the proof of him, that, as a child a father, he  has served with me in the work of the glad tidings.
2:22|KJV|But ye know the proof of him, that, as a son with the father, he hath served with me in the gospel.
2:22<version name="WYC">But know ye the assay of him [Forsooth know ye the experiment, <i>or assay</i>, of him], for as a son to the father he hath served with me in the gospel.</version>
2:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但你們知道提摩太蒙稱許的明證，他為著福音與我一同事奉，像兒子待父親一樣。
2:23|ASV|Him therefore I hope to send forthwith, so soon as I shall see how it will go with me:
2:23|Darby|Him therefore I hope to send immediately, as soon as I  shall see how it goes with me:
2:23|KJV|Him therefore I hope to send presently, so soon as I shall see how it will go with me.
2:23|WYC|Therefore I hope that I shall send him to you, at once as I see what things be about me. [Forsooth I hope me to send him to you, anon as I shall see what things be about me.]
2:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我一旦看出我的事要怎樣了結，就盼望立刻打發他去；
2:24|ASV|but I trust in the Lord that I myself also shall come shortly.
2:24|Darby|but I trust in [the] Lord that I myself also shall soon  come;
2:24|KJV|But I trust in the Lord that I also myself shall come shortly.
2:24|WYC|And I trust in the Lord, that also myself shall come to you soon.
2:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但我在主裡深信，我自己也必快去。
2:25|ASV|But I counted it necessary to send to you Epaphroditus, my brother and fellow-worker and fellow-soldier, and your messenger and minister to my need;
2:25|Darby|but I have thought it necessary to send to you  Epaphroditus, my brother and fellow-workman and fellow-soldier,  but your messenger and minister to my need,
2:25|KJV|Yet I supposed it necessary to send to you Epaphroditus, my brother, and companion in labour, and fellowsoldier, but your messenger, and he that ministered to my wants.
2:25|WYC|And I guessed it needful to send to you Epaphroditus, my brother and even-worker, and mine even-knight, but your apostle, and the minister of my need.
2:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而，我認為必須打發以巴弗提到你們那裡去，他是我的弟兄、同工、並一同當兵的，也是你們的使徒，和供應我需用的供奉者。
2:26|ASV|since he longed after you all, and was sore troubled, because ye had heard that he was sick:
2:26|Darby|since he had a longing desire after you all, and was  distressed because ye had heard that he was sick;
2:26|KJV|For he longed after you all, and was full of heaviness, because that ye had heard that he had been sick.
2:26|WYC|For he desired you all, and he was sorrowful, therefore that ye heard that he was sick.
2:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他很想念你們眾人，並且極其難過，因你們聽見他病了，
2:27|ASV|for indeed he was sick nigh unto death: but God had mercy on him; and not on him only, but on me also, that I might not have sorrow upon sorrow.
2:27|Darby|for he was also sick close to death, but God had mercy on  him, and not indeed on him alone, but also on me, that I might  not have sorrow upon sorrow.
2:27|KJV|For indeed he was sick nigh unto death: but God had mercy on him; and not on him only, but on me also, lest I should have sorrow upon sorrow.
2:27|WYC|For he was sick [till] to the death, but God had mercy on him; and not only on him, but also on me, lest I had heaviness on heaviness [lest I had heaviness upon heaviness].
2:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他實在是病了，幾乎要死；然而神憐憫他，不但憐憫他，也憐憫我，免得我憂上加憂。
2:28|ASV|I have sent him therefore the more diligently, that, when ye see him again, ye may rejoice, and that I may be the less sorrowful.
2:28|Darby|I have sent him therefore the more diligently, that seeing  him ye might again rejoice, and that *I* might be the less  sorrowful.
2:28|KJV|I sent him therefore the more carefully, that, when ye see him again, ye may rejoice, and that I may be the less sorrowful.
2:28|WYC|Therefore more hastily I sent him, that when ye have seen him, ye have joy again, and I be without heaviness.
2:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我越發急切打發他去，叫你們再見到他，就可以喜樂，我也可以少些憂愁。
2:29|ASV|Receive him therefore in the Lord with all joy; and hold such in honor:
2:29|Darby|Receive him therefore in [the] Lord with all joy, and hold  such in honour;
2:29|KJV|Receive him therefore in the Lord with all gladness; and hold such in reputation:
2:29<version name="WYC">Therefore receive ye him with all joy in the Lord, and have ye such with <i>all</i> honour.</version>
2:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此你們要在主裡歡歡喜喜的接待他，並且要尊重這樣的人，
2:30<version name="ASV">because for the work of Christ he came nigh unto death, hazarding his life to supply that which was lacking in your service toward me. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:30<version name="Darby">because for the sake of the work he drew near even to  death, venturing his life that he might fill up what lacked in  your ministration toward me. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:30<version name="KJV">Because for the work of Christ he was nigh unto death, not regarding his life, to supply your lack of service toward me.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:30|WYC|For the work of Christ he went to death, giving his life, that he should fulfill that that failed of you with my service. [For why for the work of Christ unto the death he went, giving his life, that he should fulfill that that failed to you with my service.]
2:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因他為基督的工作，冒著性命的危險，幾乎至死，要補足你們在供奉我的事上所有的短缺。
3:1|ASV|Finally, my brethren, rejoice in the Lord. To write the same things to you, to me indeed is not irksome, but for you it is safe.
3:1|Darby|For the rest, my brethren, rejoice in [the] Lord: to write  the same things to you, to me [is] not irksome, and for you  safe.
3:1|KJV|Finally, my brethren, rejoice in the Lord. To write the same things to you, to me indeed is not grievous, but for you it is safe.
3:1<version name="WYC">Henceforward, my brethren, have ye joy in the Lord.  To write to you the same things, to me <i>it is</i> not slow, and to you <i>it is</i> necessary.</version>
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|還有，我的弟兄們，你們要在主裡喜樂。把同樣的話寫給你們，於我並不為難，於你們卻是妥當。
3:2|ASV|Beware of the dogs, beware of the evil workers, beware of the concision:
3:2|Darby|See to dogs, see to evil workmen, see to the concision.
3:2|KJV|Beware of dogs, beware of evil workers, beware of the concision.
3:2|WYC|See ye hounds, see ye evil workmen, see ye division [see ye concision].
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要提防犬類，提防作惡的，提防妄自行割的。
3:3|ASV|for we are the circumcision, who worship by the Spirit of God, and glory in Christ Jesus, and have no confidence in the flesh:
3:3|Darby|For *we* are the circumcision, who worship by [the] Spirit  of God, and boast in Christ Jesus, and do not trust in flesh.
3:3|KJV|For we are the circumcision, which worship God in the spirit, and rejoice in Christ Jesus, and have no confidence in the flesh.
3:3|WYC|For we be circumcision, which by spirit serve to God, and glory in Christ Jesus, and have not trust in the flesh,
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|真受割禮的，乃是我們這憑神的靈事奉，在基督耶穌裡誇口，不信靠肉體的。
3:4|ASV|though I myself might have confidence even in the flesh: if any other man thinketh to have confidence in the flesh, I yet more:
3:4|Darby|Though *I* have [my] trust even in flesh; if any other think  to trust in flesh, *I* rather:
3:4|KJV|Though I might also have confidence in the flesh. If any other man thinketh that he hath whereof he might trust in the flesh, I more:
3:4|WYC|though I have trust, yea, in the flesh.  If any other man is seen to trust in the flesh, I more,
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其實我也可以信靠肉體；若別人自以為可以信靠肉體，我更可以：
3:5|ASV|circumcised the eighth day, of the stock of Israel, of the tribe of Benjamin, a Hebrew of Hebrews; as touching the law, a Pharisee;
3:5|Darby|as to circumcision, [I received it] the eighth day; of [the]  race of Israel, of [the] tribe of Benjamin, Hebrew of Hebrews;  as to [the] law, a Pharisee;
3:5|KJV|Circumcised the eighth day, of the stock of Israel, of the tribe of Benjamin, an Hebrew of the Hebrews; as touching the law, a Pharisee;
3:5<version name="WYC">that <i>was</i> circumcised in the eighth day, of the kin of Israel [circumcised in the eighth day, of the kindred of Israel], of the lineage of Benjamin, an Hebrew of Hebrews, by the law a Pharisee [after the law a Pharisee],</version>
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|論割禮，我是第八天受的，我是出於以色列族便雅憫支派，是希伯來人所生的希伯來人；按律法說，是法利賽人；
3:6|ASV|as touching zeal, persecuting the church; as touching the righteousness which is in the law, found blameless.
3:6|Darby|as to zeal, persecuting the assembly; as to righteousness  which [is] in [the] law, found blameless;
3:6|KJV|Concerning zeal, persecuting the church; touching the righteousness which is in the law, blameless.
3:6|WYC|by love pursuing the church of God, by rightwiseness that is in the law living without plaint. [after love pursuing the church of God, after rightwiseness that is in the law living without plaint.]
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|按熱心說，是逼迫召會的；按律法上的義說，是無可指摘的。
3:7|ASV|Howbeit what things were gain to me, these have I counted loss for Christ.
3:7|Darby|but what things were gain to me these I counted, on account  of Christ, loss.
3:7|KJV|But what things were gain to me, those I counted loss for Christ.
3:7|WYC|But which things were to me winnings, I have deemed these impairings for Christ.
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只是從前我以為對我是贏得的，這些，我因基督都已經看作虧損。
3:8|ASV|Yea verily, and I count all things to be loss for the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord: for whom I suffered the loss of all things, and do count them but refuse, that I may gain Christ,
3:8|Darby|But surely I count also all things to be loss on account of  the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord, on  account of whom I have suffered the loss of all, and count them  to be filth, that I may gain Christ;
3:8|KJV|Yea doubtless, and I count all things but loss for the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord: for whom I have suffered the loss of all things, and do count them but dung, that I may win Christ,
3:8|WYC|Nevertheless I guess all things to be impairment for the clear science of Jesus Christ my Lord.  For whom I made all things impairment, and I deem as drit [and I deem as turds], that I win Christ,
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不但如此，我也將萬事看作虧損，因我以認識我主基督耶穌為至寶；我因祂已經虧損萬事，看作糞土，為要贏得基督，
3:9|ASV|and be found in him, not having a righteousness of mine own, even that which is of the law, but that which is through faith in Christ, the righteousness which is from God by faith:
3:9|Darby|and that I may be found in him, not having my righteousness,  which [would be] on the principle of law, but that which is by  faith of Christ, the righteousness which [is] of God through  faith,
3:9|KJV|And be found in him, not having mine own righteousness, which is of the law, but that which is through the faith of Christ, the righteousness which is of God by faith:
3:9|WYC|and that I be found in him, not having my rightwiseness that is of the law, but that that is of the faith of Christ Jesus [but that that is of the faith of Christ], that is of God the rightwiseness in faith,
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且給人看出我是在祂裡面，不是有自己那本於律法的義，乃是有那藉著信基督而有的義，就是那基於信、本於神的義，
3:10|ASV|that I may know him, and the power of his resurrection, and the fellowship of his sufferings, becoming conformed unto his death;
3:10|Darby|to know him, and the power of his resurrection, and the  fellowship of his sufferings, being conformed to his death,
3:10|KJV|That I may know him, and the power of his resurrection, and the fellowship of his sufferings, being made conformable unto his death;
3:10<version name="WYC">to know him, and the virtue of his rising again, and the fellowship of his passion, and to be made like to his death, [to know him, and the virtue of his rising again, and the fellowship of his passion, I configured, <i>or made like</i>, to his death,]</version>
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|使我認識基督、並祂復活的大能、以及同祂受苦的交通，模成祂的死，
3:11|ASV|if by any means I may attain unto the resurrection from the dead.
3:11|Darby|if any way I arrive at the resurrection from among [the]  dead.
3:11|KJV|If by any means I might attain unto the resurrection of the dead.
3:11<version name="WYC">if on any manner I come to the resurrection that is from death. [if on any manner I shall come to the resurrection that is of dead <i>men</i>.]</version>
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|或者我可以達到那從死人中傑出的復活。
3:12|ASV|Not that I have already obtained, or am already made perfect: but I press on, if so be that I may lay hold on that for which also I was laid hold on by Christ Jesus.
3:12|Darby|Not that I have already obtained [the prize], or am already  perfected; but I pursue, if also I may get possession [of it],  seeing that also I have been taken possession of by Christ  [Jesus].
3:12|KJV|Not as though I had already attained, either were already perfect: but I follow after, if that I may apprehend that for which also I am apprehended of Christ Jesus.
3:12|WYC|Not that now I have taken, or now am perfect; but I follow, if in any manner I catch, in which thing also I am caught of Christ Jesus. [Not that now I have taken, or now am perfect; forsooth I follow, if on any manner I shall comprehend, in which thing also I am comprehended of Christ Jesus.]
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這不是說，我已經得著了，或已經完全了，我乃是竭力追求，或者可以取得基督耶穌所以取得我的。
3:13|ASV|Brethren, I count not myself yet to have laid hold: but one thing I do, forgetting the things which are behind, and stretching forward to the things which are before,
3:13|Darby|Brethren, *I* do not count to have got possession myself;  but one thing -- forgetting the things behind, and stretching  out to the things before,
3:13|KJV|Brethren, I count not myself to have apprehended: but this one thing I do, forgetting those things which are behind, and reaching forth unto those things which are before,
3:13|WYC|Brethren, I deem me not that I have caught; but one thing, I forget those things that be behind, and stretching forth myself to those things that be before, [Brethren, I deem me not to have comprehended; one thing, forsooth, I forgetting soothly those things that be behind, stretching myself forsooth to those things that be the former,]
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，我不是以為自己已經取得了，我只有一件事，就是忘記背後，努力面前的，
3:14|ASV|I press on toward the goal unto the prize of the high calling of God in Christ Jesus.
3:14|Darby|I pursue, [looking] towards [the] goal, for the prize of  the calling on high of God in Christ Jesus.
3:14|KJV|I press toward the mark for the prize of the high calling of God in Christ Jesus.
3:14|WYC|and pursue to the ordained meed of the high calling of God in Christ Jesus. [to the ordained thing, pursue to the prize of the high calling of God in Christ Jesus.]
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|向著標竿竭力追求，要得神在基督耶穌裡，召我向上去得的獎賞。
3:15|ASV|Let us therefore, as many as are perfect, be thus minded: and if in anything ye are otherwise minded, this also shall God reveal unto you:
3:15|Darby|As many therefore as [are] perfect, let us be thus minded;  and if ye are any otherwise minded, this also God shall reveal  to you.
3:15|KJV|Let us therefore, as many as be perfect, be thus minded: and if in any thing ye be otherwise minded, God shall reveal even this unto you.
3:15|WYC|Therefore whoever we be perfect, feel we this thing.  And if ye understand in other manner any thing, this thing God shall show to you.
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我們凡是長成的人，都要思念這事；你們若思念任何別的事，神也必將這事啟示你們。
3:16|ASV|only, whereunto we have attained, by that same rule let us walk.
3:16|Darby|But whereto we have attained, [let us] walk in the same  steps.
3:16|KJV|Nevertheless, whereto we have already attained, let us walk by the same rule, let us mind the same thing.
3:16|WYC|Nevertheless to what thing we have come, that we understand the same thing, and that we perfectly dwell in the same rule.
3:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而，我們無論到了甚麼地步，都當按著那同一規則而行。
3:17|ASV|Brethren, be ye imitators together of me, and mark them that so walk even as ye have us for an ensample.
3:17|Darby|Be imitators [all] together of me, brethren, and fix your  eyes on those walking thus as you have us for a model;
3:17|KJV|Brethren, be followers together of me, and mark them which walk so as ye have us for an ensample.
3:17|WYC|Brethren, be ye my followers, and watch ye them that walk so [and wait ye (on) them that walk so], as ye have our form.
3:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，你們要一同效法我，你們怎樣以我們為榜樣，也當留意那些這樣行的人。
3:18|ASV|For many walk, of whom I told you often, and now tell you even weeping, that they are the enemies of the cross of Christ:
3:18|Darby|(for many walk of whom I have told you often, and now tell  you even weeping, that they [are] the enemies of the cross of  Christ:
3:18|KJV|(For many walk, of whom I have told you often, and now tell you even weeping, that they are the enemies of the cross of Christ:
3:18<version name="WYC">For many walk, which I have said oft to you, but now I weeping say, the enemies of Christ's cross, [Forsooth many walk, whom I have said oft to you, forsooth now and I weeping say, <i>them</i>, the enemies of Christ's cross,]</version>
3:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為有許多人，就是那些我屢次告訴你們，現在又流淚告訴你們的，他們的行事為人，是基督十字架的仇敵，
3:19|ASV|whose end is perdition, whose god is the belly, and whose glory is in their shame, who mind earthly things.
3:19|Darby|whose end [is] destruction, whose god [is] the belly, and  [their] glory in their shame, who mind earthly things:)
3:19|KJV|Whose end is destruction, whose God is their belly, and whose glory is in their shame, who mind earthly things.)
3:19<version name="WYC">whose end <i>is</i> death, whose god is the womb, and the glory in [the] confusion of them, that savour earthly things [that savour, <i>or understand</i>, earthly things].</version>
3:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們的結局就是滅亡，他們的神就是自己的肚腹，他們以自己的羞辱為榮耀，是思念地上之事的人。
3:20|ASV|For our citizenship is in heaven; whence also we wait for a Saviour, the Lord Jesus Christ:
3:20|Darby|for *our* commonwealth has its existence in [the] heavens,  from which also we await the Lord Jesus Christ [as] Saviour,
3:20|KJV|For our conversation is in heaven; from whence also we look for the Saviour, the Lord Jesus Christ:
3:20|WYC|But our living is in heavens [Forsooth our living is in heaven]; from whence also we abide the Saviour our Lord Jesus Christ,
3:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們的國籍乃是在諸天之上，我們也熱切等待救主，就是主耶穌基督，從那裡降臨；
3:21<version name="ASV">who shall fashion anew the body of our humiliation, that it may be conformed to the body of his glory, according to the working whereby he is able even to subject all things unto himself. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:21<version name="Darby">who shall transform our body of humiliation into conformity  to his body of glory, according to the working of [the] power  which he has even to subdue all things to himself. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:21<version name="KJV">Who shall change our vile body, that it may be fashioned like unto his glorious body, according to the working whereby he is able even to subdue all things unto himself.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:21<version name="WYC">which shall reform the body of our meekness, <i>that is</i> made like to the body of his clearness, by the working by which he may also make all things subject to him. [which shall reform the body of our meekness, configured, <i>or made like</i>, to the body of his clearness, after the working by which he may also make all things subject to him.]</version>
3:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂要按著祂那甚至能叫萬有歸服自己的動力，將我們這卑賤的身體改變形狀，使之同形於祂榮耀的身體。
4:1|ASV|Wherefore, my brethren beloved and longed for, my joy and crown, so stand fast in the Lord, my beloved.
4:1|Darby|So that, my brethren, beloved and longed for, my joy and  crown, thus stand fast in [the] Lord, beloved.
4:1|KJV|Therefore, my brethren dearly beloved and longed for, my joy and crown, so stand fast in the Lord, my dearly beloved.
4:1<version name="WYC">Therefore, my brethren most dear-worthy and most desired, my joy and my crown, so stand ye in the Lord, most dear <i>brethren</i>.</version>
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，我所親愛所切慕的弟兄們，我的喜樂和冠冕─親愛的，你們要這樣在主裡站立得住。
4:2|ASV|I exhort Euodia, and I exhort Syntyche, to be of the same mind in the Lord.
4:2|Darby|I exhort Euodia, and exhort Syntyche, to be of the same mind  in [the] Lord;
4:2|KJV|I beseech Euodias, and beseech Syntyche, that they be of the same mind in the Lord.
4:2|WYC|I pray Euodias, and beseech Syntyche, to understand the same thing in the Lord.
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我勸友歐底亞，也勸循都基，要在主裡思念相同的事。
4:3|ASV|Yea, I beseech thee also, true yokefellow, help these women, for they labored with me in the gospel, with Clement also, and the rest of my fellow-workers, whose names are in the book of life.
4:3|Darby|yea, I ask thee also, true yokefellow, assist them, who have  contended along with me in the glad tidings, with Clement also,  and my other fellow-labourers, whose names [are] in [the] book  of life.
4:3|KJV|And I intreat thee also, true yokefellow, help those women which laboured with me in the gospel, with Clement also, and with other my fellowlabourers, whose names are in the book of life.
4:3<version name="WYC">Also I pray and thee, german fellow [Also and I pray thee, german even-fellow], help thou those <i>women</i> that travailed with me in the gospel, with Clement and other mine helpers, whose names be in the book of life.</version>
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|是的，我也求你這真實同負一軛的，幫助她們；她們在福音上曾與我和革利免、並我其餘的同工一同努力，他們的名字都在生命冊上。
4:4|ASV|Rejoice in the Lord always: again I will say, Rejoice.
4:4|Darby|Rejoice in [the] Lord always: again I will say, Rejoice.
4:4|KJV|Rejoice in the Lord always: and again I say, Rejoice.
4:4|WYC|Joy ye in the Lord evermore; again I say, joy ye.
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要在主裡常常喜樂，我再說，你們要喜樂。
4:5|ASV|Let your forbearance be known unto all men. The Lord is at hand.
4:5|Darby|Let your gentleness be known of all men. The Lord [is] near.
4:5|KJV|Let your moderation be known unto all men. The Lord is at hand.
4:5<version name="WYC">Be your patience known to all men [Be your temperance, <i>or patience</i>, known to all men]; the Lord is nigh.</version>
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當叫眾人知道你們的謙讓宜人。主是近的。
4:6|ASV|In nothing be anxious; but in everything by prayer and supplication with thanksgiving let your requests be made known unto God.
4:6|Darby|Be careful about nothing; but in everything, by prayer and  supplication with thanksgiving, let your requests be made known  to God;
4:6|KJV|Be careful for nothing; but in every thing by prayer and supplication with thanksgiving let your requests be made known unto God.
4:6|WYC|Be ye nothing busy [Be nothing busy], but in all prayer and beseeching, with doing of thankings, be your askings known at God.
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|應當一無罣慮，只要凡事藉著禱告、祈求，帶著感謝，將你們所要的告訴神；
4:7|ASV|And the peace of God, which passeth all understanding, shall guard your hearts and your thoughts in Christ Jesus.
4:7|Darby|and the peace of God, which surpasses every understanding,  shall guard your hearts and your thoughts by Christ Jesus.
4:7|KJV|And the peace of God, which passeth all understanding, shall keep your hearts and minds through Christ Jesus.
4:7|WYC|And the peace of God, that passeth all wit, keep your hearts and understandings in Christ Jesus.
4:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神那超越人所能理解的平安，必在基督耶穌裡，保衛你們的心懷意念。
4:8|ASV|Finally, brethren, whatsoever things are true, whatsoever things are honorable, whatsoever things are just, whatsoever things are pure, whatsoever things are lovely, whatsoever things are of good report; if there be any virtue, and if there be any praise, think on these things.
4:8|Darby|For the rest, brethren, whatsoever things [are] true,  whatsoever things [are] noble, whatsoever things [are] just,  whatsoever things [are] pure, whatsoever things [are] amiable,  whatsoever things [are] of good report; if [there be] any  virtue and if any praise, think on these things.
4:8|KJV|Finally, brethren, whatsoever things are true, whatsoever things are honest, whatsoever things are just, whatsoever things are pure, whatsoever things are lovely, whatsoever things are of good report; if there be any virtue, and if there be any praise, think on these things.
4:8<version name="WYC">From henceforth, brethren, whatever things be sooth, whatever things chaste, whatever things just, whatever things holy, whatever things able to be loved <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22468a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>, whatever things of good fame, if any virtue, if any praising of discipline, think ye (on) these things,</version>
4:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|末了的話，弟兄們，凡是真實的，凡是莊重的，凡是公義的，凡是純潔的，凡是可愛的，凡是有美名的；若有甚麼德行，若有甚麼稱讚，這些事你們都要思念。
4:9|ASV|The things which ye both learned and received and heard and saw in me, these things do: and the God of peace shall be with you.
4:9|Darby|What ye have both learned, and received, and heard, and seen  in me, these things do; and the God of peace shall be with you.
4:9|KJV|Those things, which ye have both learned, and received, and heard, and seen in me, do: and the God of peace shall be with you.
4:9|WYC|that also ye have learned, and taken, and heard, and seen in me.  Do ye these things, and God of peace shall be with you.
4:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們在我身上所學習的、所領受的、所聽見的、所看見的，這些事你們都要去行，平安的神就必與你們同在。
4:10|ASV|But I rejoice in the Lord greatly, that now at length ye have revived your thought for me; wherein ye did indeed take thought, but ye lacked opportunity.
4:10|Darby|But I rejoiced in [the] Lord greatly, that now however at  length ye have revived your thinking of me, though surely ye  did also think [of me], but lacked opportunity.
4:10|KJV|But I rejoiced in the Lord greatly, that now at the last your care of me hath flourished again; wherein ye were also careful, but ye lacked opportunity.
4:10|WYC|But I joyed greatly in the Lord, that sometime afterward ye flowered again to feel for me [for sometime afterward ye again flourished for to feel for me], as also ye feeled.  But ye were occupied,
4:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在主裡大大的喜樂，因為你們對我的思念，如今終於重新發生；你們向來就思念我，只是未得機會。
4:11|ASV|Not that I speak in respect of want: for I have learned, in whatsoever state I am, therein to be content.
4:11|Darby|Not that I speak as regards privation, for as to me *I*  have learnt in those circumstances in which I am, to be  satisfied in myself.
4:11|KJV|Not that I speak in respect of want: for I have learned, in whatsoever state I am, therewith to be content.
4:11|WYC|I say not as for need, for I have learned to be sufficient in which things I am. [I say not as for need, for I have learned, in which things I am, sufficient to be.]
4:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我並不是因缺乏說這話，因為我已經學會了，無論在甚麼景況，都可以知足。
4:12|ASV|I know how to be abased, and I know also how to abound: in everything and in all things have I learned the secret both to be filled and to be hungry, both to abound and to be in want.
4:12|Darby|I know both how to be abased and I know how to abound. In  everything and in all things I am initiated both to be full and  to be hungry, both to abound and to suffer privation.
4:12|KJV|I know both how to be abased, and I know how to abound: every where and in all things I am instructed both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to suffer need.
4:12<version name="WYC">And I know also how to be lowed, I know also how to have plenty.  Every where and in all things I am taught to be filled, and to hunger, and to abound, and to suffer need. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22472b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
4:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我知道怎樣處卑賤，也知道怎樣處富餘；或飽足、或飢餓、或富餘、或缺乏，在各事上，並在一切事上，我都學得祕訣。
4:13|ASV|I can do all things in him that strengtheneth me.
4:13|Darby|I have strength for all things in him that gives me power.
4:13|KJV|I can do all things through Christ which strengtheneth me.
4:13|WYC|I may all things in him that comforteth me.
4:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在那加我能力者的裡面，凡事都能作。
4:14|ASV|Howbeit ye did well that ye had fellowship with my affliction.
4:14|Darby|But ye have done well in taking part in my affliction.
4:14|KJV|Notwithstanding ye have well done, that ye did communicate with my affliction.
4:14|WYC|Nevertheless ye have done well, communing to my tribulation.
4:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而，你們有分於我的患難，乃是美事。
4:15|ASV|And ye yourselves also know, ye Philippians, that in the beginning of the gospel, when I departed from Macedonia, no church had fellowship with me in the matter of giving and receiving but ye only;
4:15|Darby|And know also *ye*, O Philippians, that in [the] beginning  of the gospel, when I came out of Macedonia, no assembly  communicated [anything] to me in [the] way of giving and  receiving save *ye* alone;
4:15|KJV|Now ye Philippians know also, that in the beginning of the gospel, when I departed from Macedonia, no church communicated with me as concerning giving and receiving, but ye only.
4:15|WYC|For ye, Philippians, know also, that in the beginning of the gospel, when I went forth from Macedonia, no church communed with me in reason of thing given and taken, but ye alone.
4:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|腓立比人哪，你們也知道我初傳福音，離開馬其頓的時候，在授受的賬上，除了你們以外，並沒有一個召會與我有交通；
4:16|ASV|for even in Thessalonica ye sent once and again unto my need.
4:16|Darby|for also in Thessalonica once and even twice ye sent to me  for my need.
4:16|KJV|For even in Thessalonica ye sent once and again unto my necessity.
4:16|WYC|Which sent to Thessalonica once and twice also into use to me. [For and to Thessalonica ye sent once and twice into use to me.]
4:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就是我在帖撒羅尼迦，你們也一次兩次的，打發人供給我的需用。
4:17|ASV|Not that I seek for the gift; but I seek for the fruit that increaseth to your account.
4:17|Darby|Not that I seek gift, but I seek fruit abounding to your  account.
4:17|KJV|Not because I desire a gift: but I desire fruit that may abound to your account.
4:17<version name="WYC">Not for I seek gift, but I require fruit abounding in your reason. [Not for I seek gift, but I require, <i>or seek again</i>, fruit abounding in your reason.]</version>
4:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我並不尋求甚麼餽送，只尋求你們的果子增多，歸入你們的賬上。
4:18|ASV|But I have all things, and abound: I am filled, having received from Epaphroditus the things that came from you, and odor of a sweet smell, a sacrifice acceptable, well-pleasing to God.
4:18|Darby|But I have all things in full supply and abound; I am full,  having received of Epaphroditus the things [sent] from you, an  odour of sweet savour, an acceptable sacrifice, agreeable to  God.
4:18|KJV|But I have all, and abound: I am full, having received of Epaphroditus the things which were sent from you, an odour of a sweet smell, a sacrifice acceptable, wellpleasing to God.
4:18<version name="WYC">For I have all things, and abound; I am filled <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22478c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup> with those things taken of Epaphroditus, which ye sent into the odour of sweetness, a suitable sacrifice [a covenable host, <i>or sacrifice</i>], pleasing to God.</version>
4:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但我一切都收到了，並且有餘，我已經充足，因我從以巴弗提受了你們的餽送，如同馨香之氣，可收納的祭物，是神所喜悅的。
4:19|ASV|And my God shall supply every need of yours according to his riches in glory in Christ Jesus.
4:19|Darby|But my God shall abundantly supply all your need according  to his riches in glory in Christ Jesus.
4:19|KJV|But my God shall supply all your need according to his riches in glory by Christ Jesus.
4:19|WYC|And my God fill all your desire, by his riches in glory in Christ Jesus. [Forsooth my God full-fill all your desire, after his riches in glory in Christ Jesus.]
4:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的神必在榮耀中，照著祂的豐富，在基督耶穌裡，使你們一切所需用的都充足。
4:20|ASV|Now unto our God and Father be the glory for ever and ever. Amen.
4:20|Darby|But to our God and Father [be] glory to the ages of ages.  Amen.
4:20|KJV|Now unto God and our Father be glory for ever and ever. Amen.
4:20|WYC|But to God and our Father be glory into worlds of worlds.  Amen.
4:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願榮耀歸與我們的神與父，直到永永遠遠。阿們。
4:21|ASV|Salute every saint in Christ Jesus. The brethren that are with me salute you.
4:21|Darby|Salute every saint in Christ Jesus. The brethren who [are]  with me salute you.
4:21|KJV|Salute every saint in Christ Jesus. The brethren which are with me greet you.
4:21<version name="WYC">Greet ye well every holy <i>man</i> in Christ Jesus.  Those brethren that be with me, greet you well.</version>
4:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|請問在基督耶穌裡的各位聖徒安，與我同在的弟兄們都問你們安，
4:22|ASV|All the saints salute you, especially they that are of Caesar's household.
4:22|Darby|All the saints salute you, and specially those of the  household of Caesar.
4:22|KJV|All the saints salute you, chiefly they that are of Caesar's household.
4:22|WYC|All holy men greet you well, most soothly they that be of the emperor's house [most soothly those that be of Caesar's house].
4:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|眾聖徒，尤其是該撒家裡的人，都問你們安。
4:23<version name="ASV">The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:23<version name="Darby">The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ [be] with your spirit.  Amen. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:23<version name="KJV">The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen.</p><p /><br /></version>
4:23|WYC|The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit.  Amen.
4:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願主耶穌基督的恩與你們的靈同在。
