1:1|ASV|Paul, a prisoner of Christ Jesus, and Timothy our brother, to Philemon our beloved and fellow-worker,
1:1|Darby|Paul, prisoner of Christ Jesus, and Timotheus the brother,  to Philemon the beloved and our fellow-workman,
1:1|KJV|Paul, a prisoner of Jesus Christ, and Timothy our brother, unto Philemon our dearly beloved, and fellowlabourer,
1:1<version name="WYC">Paul, the bound of Christ Jesus [the bound of Jesus Christ], and Timothy, brother, to Philemon, beloved, and our helper [and our<i> even-worker</i>],</version>
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|基督耶穌的囚犯保羅，和弟兄提摩太，寫信給所愛的並我們的同工腓利門，
1:2|ASV|and to Apphia our sister, and to Archippus our fellow-soldier, and to the church in thy house:
1:2|Darby|and to the sister Apphia and to Archippus our  fellow-soldier, and to the assembly which [is] in thine house.
1:2|KJV|And to our beloved Apphia, and Archippus our fellowsoldier, and to the church in thy house:
1:2|WYC|and to Apphia, most dear sister, and to Archippus, our even-knight, and to the church that is in thine house,
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|和姊妹亞腓亞，並與我們一同當兵的亞基布，以及在你家中的召會：
1:3|ASV|Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.
1:3|Darby|Grace to you and peace from God our Father, and [the] Lord  Jesus Christ.
1:3|KJV|Grace to you, and peace, from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.
1:3<version name="WYC">grace <i>be</i> to you [grace to you], and peace of God our Father, and of the Lord Jesus Christ.</version>
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願恩典與平安，從神我們的父，並主耶穌基督歸與你們。
1:4|ASV|I thank my God always, making mention of thee in my prayers,
1:4|Darby|I thank my God, always making mention of thee at my prayers,
1:4|KJV|I thank my God, making mention of thee always in my prayers,
1:4|WYC|I do thankings to my God, evermore making mind of thee in my prayers,
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我禱告的時候題到你，常常感謝我的神，
1:5|ASV|hearing of thy love, and of the faith which thou hast toward the Lord Jesus, and toward all the saints;
1:5|Darby|hearing of thy love and the faith which thou hast towards  the Lord Jesus, and towards all the saints,
1:5|KJV|Hearing of thy love and faith, which thou hast toward the Lord Jesus, and toward all saints;
1:5|WYC|hearing thy charity and faith, that thou hast in the Lord Jesus, and to all holy men,
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因聽見你對主耶穌，並對眾聖徒的愛與信；
1:6|ASV|that the fellowship of thy faith may become effectual, in the knowledge of every good thing which is in you, unto Christ.
1:6|Darby|in such sort that thy participation in the faith should  become operative in the acknowledgment of every good thing  which is in us towards Christ [Jesus].
1:6|KJV|That the communication of thy faith may become effectual by the acknowledging of every good thing which is in you in Christ Jesus.
1:6|WYC|that the communing of thy faith be made open, in knowing of all good thing in Christ Jesus.
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願你信的交通顯出功效，使人充分認識你們裡面為著基督的各樣善事。
1:7|ASV|For I had much joy and comfort in thy love, because the hearts of the saints have been refreshed through thee, brother.
1:7|Darby|For we have great thankfulness and encouragement through thy  love, because the bowels of the saints are refreshed by thee,  brother.
1:7|KJV|For we have great joy and consolation in thy love, because the bowels of the saints are refreshed by thee, brother.
1:7<version name="WYC">And I had great joy and comfort in thy charity, for the entrails of holy men rested by thee, brother. [Forsooth I had great joy and comfort in thy charity, for the entrails of holy men rested, <i>or</i> <i>were refreshed</i>, by thee, brother.]</version>
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為弟兄阿，我因你的愛，大大喜樂，滿受鼓勵，因為眾聖徒的心腸藉著你得了舒暢。
1:8|ASV|Wherefore, though I have all boldness in Christ to enjoin thee that which is befitting,
1:8|Darby|Wherefore having much boldness in Christ to enjoin thee what  is fitting,
1:8|KJV|Wherefore, though I might be much bold in Christ to enjoin thee that which is convenient,
1:8|WYC|For which thing I having much trust in Christ Jesus, to command to thee that that pertaineth to profit;
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|為此，我雖然在基督裡能大有膽量吩咐你合宜的事，
1:9|ASV|yet for love's sake I rather beseech, being such a one as Paul the aged, and now a prisoner also of Christ Jesus:
1:9|Darby|for love's sake I rather exhort, being such a one as Paul  the aged, and now also prisoner of Jesus Christ.
1:9|KJV|Yet for love's sake I rather beseech thee, being such an one as Paul the aged, and now also a prisoner of Jesus Christ.
1:9<version name="WYC">but I beseech more for charity, since thou art such as the old Paul, and now the bound of Jesus Christ. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22965a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而像我這有年紀的保羅，現在又是基督耶穌的囚犯，寧可因著愛懇求你，
1:10|ASV|I beseech thee for my child, whom I have begotten in my bonds, Onesimus,
1:10|Darby|I exhort thee for *my* child, whom I have begotten in [my]  bonds, Onesimus,
1:10|KJV|I beseech thee for my son Onesimus, whom I have begotten in my bonds:
1:10|WYC|I beseech thee for my son Onesimus, whom I in bonds begat,
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就是為我在捆鎖中所生的孩子歐尼西母懇求你；
1:11|ASV|who once was unprofitable to thee, but now is profitable to thee and to me:
1:11|Darby|once unserviceable to thee, but now serviceable to thee and  to me:
1:11|KJV|Which in time past was to thee unprofitable, but now profitable to thee and to me:
1:11|WYC|which sometime was unprofitable to thee [which sometime was to thee unprofitable], but now profitable, both to thee and to me;
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他從前對你沒有益處，但如今對你我都有益處。
1:12|ASV|whom I have sent back to thee in his own person, that is, my very heart:
1:12|Darby|whom I have sent back to thee: [but do *thou* receive] him,  that is, *my* bowels:
1:12|KJV|Whom I have sent again: thou therefore receive him, that is, mine own bowels:
1:12|WYC|whom I sent again to thee.  And receive thou him as mine entrails;
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我現在打發他回你那裡去，他乃是我心上的人。
1:13|ASV|whom I would fain have kept with me, that in thy behalf he might minister unto me in the bonds of the gospel:
1:13|Darby|whom *I* was desirous of keeping with myself, that for thee  he might minister to me in the bonds of the glad tidings;
1:13|KJV|Whom I would have retained with me, that in thy stead he might have ministered unto me in the bonds of the gospel:
1:13|WYC|whom I would withhold with me, that he should serve for thee to me in bonds of the gospel;
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我本有意將他留在身邊，使他在我為福音所受的捆鎖中，替你服事我。
1:14|ASV|but without thy mind I would do nothing; that thy goodness should not be as of necessity, but of free will.
1:14|Darby|but I have wished to do nothing without thy mind, that thy  good might not be as of necessity but of willingness:
1:14|KJV|But without thy mind would I do nothing; that thy benefit should not be as it were of necessity, but willingly.
1:14|WYC|but without thy counsel I would not do any thing, that thy good should not be as of need, but willful.
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但未得知你的意見，我就不願作甚麼，好叫你的善行不像是出於勉強，乃是出於甘心。
1:15|ASV|For perhaps he was therefore parted from thee for a season, that thou shouldest have him for ever;
1:15|Darby|for perhaps for this reason he has been separated [from  thee] for a time, that thou mightest possess him fully for  ever;
1:15|KJV|For perhaps he therefore departed for a season, that thou shouldest receive him for ever;
1:15|WYC|For peradventure therefore he departed from thee for a time, that thou shouldest receive him without end [that thou shouldest receive him into without end];
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為他暫時離開你，或者是叫你可以永遠完全得著他，
1:16|ASV|no longer as a servant, but more than a servant, a brother beloved, specially to me, but how much rather to thee, both in the flesh and in the Lord.
1:16|Darby|not any longer as a bondman, but above a bondman, a beloved  brother, specially to me, and how much rather to thee, both in  [the] flesh and in [the] Lord?
1:16|KJV|Not now as a servant, but above a servant, a brother beloved, specially to me, but how much more unto thee, both in the flesh, and in the Lord?
1:16|WYC|now not as a servant, but for a servant [but more than a servant] a most dear brother, most to me; and how much more to thee, both in [the] flesh and in the Lord?
1:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不再是奴僕，乃是高過奴僕，是親愛的弟兄，對我固然是如此，對你，不拘在肉身上，或在主裡，豈不都更是這樣。
1:17|ASV|If then thou countest me a partner, receive him as myself.
1:17|Darby|If therefore thou holdest me to be a partner [with thee],  receive him as me;
1:17|KJV|If thou count me therefore a partner, receive him as myself.
1:17|WYC|Therefore if thou hast me a fellow, receive him as me;
1:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，你若以我為同夥，就接納他，如同接納我一樣。
1:18|ASV|But if he hath wronged the at all, or oweth thee aught, put that to mine account;
1:18|Darby|but if he have wronged thee anything or owe anything [to  thee], put this to my account.
1:18|KJV|If he hath wronged thee, or oweth thee ought, put that on mine account;
1:18|WYC|for if he hath any thing harmed thee, either oweth, areckon thou this thing to me. [forsooth if he hath any thing harmed thee, or oweth, reckon thou this thing to me.]
1:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他若虧負你，或欠你甚麼，這都歸在我的賬上；
1:19|ASV|I Paul write it with mine own hand, I will repay it: that I say not unto thee that thou owest to me even thine own self besides.
1:19|Darby|*I* Paul have written [it] with mine own hand; *I* will  repay [it]: that I say not to thee that thou owest even thine  own self also to me.
1:19|KJV|I Paul have written it with mine own hand, I will repay it: albeit I do not say to thee how thou owest unto me even thine own self besides.
1:19|WYC|I Paul wrote with mine hand, I shall yield; that I say not to thee, that also thou owest to me thyself.
1:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必償還，這是我保羅親筆寫的。我並不用對你說，連你自己也是虧欠於我。
1:20|ASV|Yea, brother, let me have joy of thee in the Lord: refresh my heart in Christ.
1:20|Darby|Yea, brother, *I* would have profit of *thee* in [the]  Lord: refresh my bowels in Christ.
1:20|KJV|Yea, brother, let me have joy of thee in the Lord: refresh my bowels in the Lord.
1:20|WYC|So, brother, I shall use thee in the Lord; fill thou mine entrails in Christ [full-fill mine entrails in Christ].
1:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄阿，是的，願我在主裡從你得著益處，願你使我的心腸在基督裡得舒暢。
1:21|ASV|Having confidence in thine obedience I write unto thee, knowing that thou wilt do even beyond what I say.
1:21|Darby|Being confident of thine obedience, I have written to thee,  knowing that thou wilt do even more than I say.
1:21|KJV|Having confidence in thy obedience I wrote unto thee, knowing that thou wilt also do more than I say.
1:21|WYC|I trusting of thine obedience wrote to thee, witting that thou shalt do over that that I say.
1:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我寫信給你，深信你必順從，知道你所要行的，甚至必過於我所說的。
1:22|ASV|But withal prepare me also a lodging: for I hope that through your prayers I shall be granted unto you.
1:22|Darby|But withal prepare me also a lodging; for I hope that I  shall be granted to you through your prayers.
1:22|KJV|But withal prepare me also a lodging: for I trust that through your prayers I shall be given unto you.
1:22|WYC|Also make thou ready to me an house to dwell in; for I hope that by your prayers I shall be given to you.
1:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|同時，你還要給我豫備住所，因為我盼望藉著你們的禱告，我可當作恩典賜給你們。
1:23|ASV|Epaphras, my fellow-prisoner in Christ Jesus, saluteth thee;
1:23|Darby|Epaphras salutes thee, my fellow-prisoner in Christ Jesus;
1:23|KJV|There salute thee Epaphras, my fellowprisoner in Christ Jesus;
1:23|WYC|Epaphras, prisoner with me in Christ Jesus [mine even-captive in Christ Jesus], greeteth thee well,
1:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在基督耶穌裡與我一同坐監的以巴弗問你安。
1:24|ASV|and so do Mark, Aristarchus, Demas, Luke, my fellow-workers.
1:24|Darby|Mark, Aristarchus, Demas, Luke, my fellow-workmen.
1:24|KJV|Marcus, Aristarchus, Demas, Lucas, my fellowlabourers.
1:24|WYC|and Marcus, Aristarchus, Demas, Lucas, mine helpers.
1:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的同工馬可、亞里達古、底馬、路加，也都問你安。
1:25<version name="ASV">The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:25<version name="Darby">The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ [be] with your spirit. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:25<version name="KJV">The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:25<version name="WYC">The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ <i>be</i> with your spirit.  Amen.</version>
1:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願主耶穌基督的恩與你們的靈同在。
