1:1|ASV|Paul, a servant of Jesus Christ, called to be an apostle, separated unto the gospel of God,
1:1|Darby|Paul, bondman of Jesus Christ, [a] called apostle, separated  to God's glad tidings,
1:1|KJV|Paul, a servant of Jesus Christ, called to be an apostle, separated unto the gospel of God,
1:1|WYC|Paul, the servant of Jesus Christ, called an apostle, separated into the gospel of God [parted into the gospel of God];
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|基督耶穌的奴僕保羅，蒙召的使徒，被分別出來歸於神福音的；
1:2|ASV|which he promised afore through his prophets in the holy scriptures,
1:2|Darby|(which he had before promised by his prophets in holy  writings,)
1:2|KJV|(Which he had promised afore by his prophets in the holy scriptures,)
1:2|WYC|which he had promised before by his prophets in holy scriptures
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這福音是神從前藉著祂的眾申言者，在聖經上所應許的，
1:3|ASV|concerning his Son, who was born of the seed of David according to the flesh,
1:3|Darby|concerning his Son (come of David's seed according to flesh,
1:3|KJV|Concerning his Son Jesus Christ our Lord, which was made of the seed of David according to the flesh;
1:3|WYC|of his Son, which is made to him of the seed of David by the flesh, [of his Son, the which is made of the seed of David after the flesh,]
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|論到祂的兒子，我們的主耶穌基督：按肉體說，是從大衛後裔生的，
1:4|ASV|who was declared to be the Son of God with power, according to the spirit of holiness, by the resurrection from the dead;  even Jesus Christ our Lord,
1:4|Darby|marked out Son of God in power, according to [the] Spirit of  holiness, by resurrection of [the] dead) Jesus Christ our Lord;
1:4|KJV|And declared to be the Son of God with power, according to the spirit of holiness, by the resurrection from the dead:
1:4<version name="WYC">and he was before-ordained the Son of God in virtue, by the Spirit of hallowing of the again-rising of dead men, of Jesus Christ our Lord <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-20952a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|按聖別的靈說，是從死人的復活，以大能標出為神的兒子；
1:5|ASV|through whom we received grace and apostleship, unto obedience of faith among all the nations, for his name's sake;
1:5|Darby|by whom we have received grace and apostleship in behalf of  his name, for obedience of faith among all the nations,
1:5|KJV|By whom we have received grace and apostleship, for obedience to the faith among all nations, for his name:
1:5<version name="WYC">by whom we have received grace and the office of apostle [by whom we have received grace and apostlehood, <i>or state of apostle</i>], to obey to the faith in all folks for his name,</version>
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們藉著祂，領受了恩典和使徒的職分，為祂的名在萬國中使人順從信仰，
1:6|ASV|among whom are ye also called to be Jesus Christ's:
1:6|Darby|among whom are *ye* also [the] called of Jesus Christ:
1:6|KJV|Among whom are ye also the called of Jesus Christ:
1:6|WYC|among which ye be also called of Jesus Christ,
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其中也有你們這蒙召屬耶穌基督的人；
1:7|ASV|To all that are in Rome, beloved of God, called to be saints: Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.
1:7|Darby|to all that are in Rome, beloved of God, called saints:  Grace to you and peace from God our Father and [our] Lord Jesus  Christ.
1:7|KJV|To all that be in Rome, beloved of God, called to be saints: Grace to you and peace from God our Father, and the Lord Jesus Christ.
1:7<version name="WYC">to all that be at Rome, darlings of God, and called holy, grace to you [to all that be at Rome, the loved of God, called holy, grace <i>be</i> to you], and peace of God our Father, and of the Lord Jesus Christ.</version>
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|寫信給一切在羅馬，為神所愛，蒙召的聖徒。願恩典與平安，從神我們的父，並主耶穌基督歸與你們。
1:8|ASV|First, I thank my God through Jesus Christ for you all, that your faith is proclaimed throughout the whole world.
1:8|Darby|First, I thank my God through Jesus Christ for you all, that  your faith is proclaimed in the whole world.
1:8|KJV|First, I thank my God through Jesus Christ for you all, that your faith is spoken of throughout the whole world.
1:8|WYC|First I do thankings to my God, by Jesus Christ, for all you, for your faith is showed in all the world.
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|首先，我藉著耶穌基督，為你們眾人感謝我的神，因你們的信心傳遍了全世界。
1:9|ASV|For God is my witness, whom I serve in my spirit in the gospel of his Son, how unceasingly I make mention of you, always in my prayers
1:9|Darby|For God is my witness, whom I serve in my spirit in the glad  tidings of his Son, how unceasingly I make mention of you,
1:9|KJV|For God is my witness, whom I serve with my spirit in the gospel of his Son, that without ceasing I make mention of you always in my prayers;
1:9|WYC|For God is a witness to me, to whom I serve in my spirit, in the gospel of his Son, that without ceasing I make mind of you ever in my prayers [whom I serve in my spirit, in the gospel of his Son, for without ceasing I make mind of you evermore in my prayers],
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在祂兒子的福音上，在我靈裡所事奉的神，可以見證我怎樣在禱告中，常常不住的題到你們，
1:10|ASV|making request, if by any means now at length I may be prospered by the will of God to come unto you.
1:10|Darby|always beseeching at my prayers, if any way now at least I  may be prospered by the will of God to come to you.
1:10|KJV|Making request, if by any means now at length I might have a prosperous journey by the will of God to come unto you.
1:10|WYC|and beseech [praying], if in any manner sometime I have a speedy way in the will of God to come to you.
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祈求神，或許在祂的旨意中，終能順利的往你們那裡去。
1:11|ASV|For I long to see you, that I may impart unto you some spiritual gift, to the end ye may be established;
1:11|Darby|For I greatly desire to see you, that I may impart to you  some spiritual gift to establish you;
1:11|KJV|For I long to see you, that I may impart unto you some spiritual gift, to the end ye may be established;
1:11<version name="WYC">For I desire to see you, to part somewhat <i>to you</i> of spiritual grace [that I give to you something of spiritual grace], that ye be confirmed,</version>
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我切切的想見你們，要把些屬靈的恩賜分給你們，使你們得以堅固；
1:12|ASV|that is, that I with you may be comforted in you, each of us by the other's faith, both yours and mine.
1:12|Darby|that is, to have mutual comfort among you, each by the  faith [which is] in the other, both yours and mine.
1:12|KJV|That is, that I may be comforted together with you by the mutual faith both of you and me.
1:12|WYC|that is, to be comforted together in you, by [that] faith that is both yours and mine together.
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我在你們中間，因你們與我彼此的信心，就可以同得鼓勵。
1:13|ASV|And I would not have you ignorant, brethren, that oftentimes I purposed to come unto you (and was hindered hitherto), that I might have some fruit in you also, even as in the rest of the Gentiles.
1:13|Darby|But I do not wish you to be ignorant, brethren, that I  often proposed to come to you, (and have been hindered until  the present time,) that I might have some fruit among you too,  even as among the other nations also.
1:13|KJV|Now I would not have you ignorant, brethren, that oftentimes I purposed to come unto you, (but was let hitherto,) that I might have some fruit among you also, even as among other Gentiles.
1:13|WYC|And, brethren, I will not, that ye not know [that ye unknow], that oft I purposed to come to you, and I am letted [and I am forbidden] till this time, that I have some fruit in you, as [and] in other folks.
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，我不願意你們不知道，我屢次定意往你們那裡去，要在你們中間也得些果子，如同在其餘的外邦人中一樣，只是到如今仍有攔阻。
1:14|ASV|I am debtor both to Greeks and to Barbarians, both to the wise and to the foolish.
1:14|Darby|I am a debtor both to Greeks and barbarians, both to wise  and unintelligent:
1:14|KJV|I am debtor both to the Greeks, and to the Barbarians; both to the wise, and to the unwise.
1:14|WYC|To Greeks and to barbarians, to wise men and to unwise men, I am debtor,
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|無論對希利尼人還是對化外人，無論對智慧人還是對愚拙人，我都是欠債的。
1:15|ASV|So, as much as in me is, I am ready to preach the gospel to you also that are in Rome.
1:15|Darby|so, as far as depends on me, am I ready to announce the  glad tidings to you also who [are] in Rome.
1:15|KJV|So, as much as in me is, I am ready to preach the gospel to you that are at Rome also.
1:15|WYC|so that that is in me is ready to preach the gospel also to you that be at Rome.
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以在我，我已經豫備好，要將福音也傳給你們在羅馬的人。
1:16|ASV|For I am not ashamed of the gospel: for it is the power of God unto salvation to every one that believeth; to the Jew first, and also to the Greek.
1:16|Darby|For I am not ashamed of the glad tidings; for it is God's  power to salvation, to every one that believes, both to Jew  first and to Greek:
1:16|KJV|For I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ: for it is the power of God unto salvation to every one that believeth; to the Jew first, and also to the Greek.
1:16|WYC|For I shame not the gospel, for it is the virtue of God into health to each man that believeth, to the Jew first, and to the Greek.
1:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我不以福音為恥；這福音本是神的大能，要救一切信的人，先是猶太人，後是希利尼人。
1:17|ASV|For therein is revealed a righteousness of God from faith unto faith: as it is written, But the righteous shall live by faith.
1:17|Darby|for righteousness of God is revealed therein, on the  principle of faith, to faith: according as it is written, But  the just shall live by faith.
1:17|KJV|For therein is the righteousness of God revealed from faith to faith: as it is written, The just shall live by faith.
1:17|WYC|For the rightwiseness of God is showed in it, of faith into faith, as it is written, For a just man liveth of faith.
1:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神的義在這福音上，本於信顯示與信，如經上所記：“義人必本於信得生並活著。”
1:18|ASV|For the wrath of God is revealed from heaven against all ungodliness and unrighteousness of men, who hinder the truth in unrighteousness;
1:18|Darby|For there is revealed wrath of God from heaven upon all  impiety, and unrighteousness of men holding the truth in  unrighteousness.
1:18|KJV|For the wrath of God is revealed from heaven against all ungodliness and unrighteousness of men, who hold the truth in unrighteousness;
1:18<version name="WYC">For the wrath of God is showed from heaven on all unpiety and wickedness of those men, that withhold the truth of God in unrightwiseness. [Forsooth the wrath of God is showed from heaven upon all unpiety and unrightwiseness of those men, that withhold, <i>or</i> <i>hold aback</i>, the truth of God in unrightwiseness.]</version>
1:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|原來神的忿怒，從天上顯示在那些以不義抑制真理之人一切的不虔不義上。
1:19|ASV|because that which is known of God is manifest in them; for God manifested it unto them.
1:19|Darby|Because what is known of God is manifest among them, for  God has manifested [it] to them,
1:19|KJV|Because that which may be known of God is manifest in them; for God hath shewed it unto them.
1:19<version name="WYC">For that thing of God that is known, is showed to them [For that that is known of God is shown, <i>or</i> <i>made open</i>, to them], for God hath showed to them.</version>
1:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神的事情，人所能知道的，原顯明在人裡面，因為神已經給他們顯明了。
1:20|ASV|For the invisible things of him since the creation of the world are clearly seen, being perceived through the things that are made, even his everlasting power and divinity; that they may be without excuse:
1:20|Darby|-- for from [the] world's creation the invisible things of  him are perceived, being apprehended by the mind through the  things that are made, both his eternal power and divinity, --  so as to render them inexcusable.
1:20|KJV|For the invisible things of him from the creation of the world are clearly seen, being understood by the things that are made, even his eternal power and Godhead; so that they are without excuse:
1:20|WYC|For the invisible things of him, that be understood, be beheld of the creature of the world, by those things that be made, yea, and the everlasting virtue of him and the Godhead, so that they may not be excused. [For the invisible things of him, of the creature of the world, by those things that be made, understood be beholden, and the everlasting virtue of him, and the Godhead, so that they be unexcusable.]
1:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|自從創造世界以來，神那看不見永遠的大能，和神性的特徵，是人所洞見的，乃是藉著受造之物，給人曉得的，叫人無法推諉；
1:21|ASV|because that, knowing God, they glorified him not as God, neither gave thanks; but became vain in their reasonings, and their senseless heart was darkened.
1:21|Darby|Because, knowing God, they glorified [him] not as God,  neither were thankful; but fell into folly in their thoughts,  and their heart without understanding was darkened:
1:21|KJV|Because that, when they knew God, they glorified him not as God, neither were thankful; but became vain in their imaginations, and their foolish heart was darkened.
1:21<version name="WYC">For when they had known God, they glorified <i>him</i> not as God, neither did thankings; but they vanished in their thoughts, and the unwise heart of them was darked [was darked, <i>or</i>  <i>made dark</i>].</version>
1:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為他們雖然知道神，卻不當作神榮耀祂，也不感謝祂，反倒在他們的推想上變為虛妄，他們無知的心就昏暗了。
1:22|ASV|Professing themselves to be wise, they became fools,
1:22|Darby|professing themselves to be wise, they became fools,
1:22|KJV|Professing themselves to be wise, they became fools,
1:22|WYC|For they saying that themselves were wise [Soothly they saying themselves to be wise men], they were made fools.
1:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們自稱是智慧的，反成了愚拙的，
1:23|ASV|and changed the glory of the incorruptible God for the likeness of an image of corruptible man, and of birds, and four-footed beasts, and creeping things.
1:23|Darby|and changed the glory of the incorruptible God into [the]  likeness of an image of corruptible man and of birds and  quadrupeds and reptiles.
1:23|KJV|And changed the glory of the uncorruptible God into an image made like to corruptible man, and to birds, and fourfooted beasts, and creeping things.
1:23|WYC|And they changed the glory of uncorruptible God into the likeness of an image of a deadly man [into the likeness of an image of corruptible man], and of birds, and of four-footed beasts, and of serpents.
1:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|將不能朽壞之神的榮耀，改換為必朽壞的人、飛禽、走獸和爬物之像的樣式。
1:24|ASV|Wherefore God gave them up in the lusts of their hearts unto uncleanness, that their bodies should be dishonored among themselves:
1:24|Darby|Wherefore God gave them up [also] in the lusts of their  hearts to uncleanness, to dishonour their bodies between  themselves:
1:24|KJV|Wherefore God also gave them up to uncleanness through the lusts of their own hearts, to dishonour their own bodies between themselves:
1:24|WYC|For which thing God betook them into the desires of their heart, into uncleanness, that they punish with wrongs their bodies in themselves.
1:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以神任憑他們逞著心裡的情慾，陷入污穢中，以致彼此玷辱自己的身體。
1:25|ASV|for that they exchanged the truth of God for a lie, and worshipped and served the creature rather than the Creator, who is blessed for ever. Amen.
1:25|Darby|who changed the truth of God into falsehood, and honoured  and served the creature more than him who had created [it], who  is blessed for ever. Amen.
1:25|KJV|Who changed the truth of God into a lie, and worshipped and served the creature more than the Creator, who is blessed for ever. Amen.
1:25<version name="WYC">The which [<i>men</i>] changed the truth of God into lying, and praised and served a creature rather than the creator, that is blessed into worlds of worlds [that is blessed into worlds, <i>or</i> <i>without end</i>].  Amen.</version>
1:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們將神的真實換為虛謊，去敬拜事奉受造之物，不敬拜事奉那創造者；祂乃是當受頌讚的，直到永遠。阿們。
1:26|ASV|For this cause God gave them up unto vile passions: for their women changed the natural use into that which is against nature:
1:26|Darby|For this reason God gave them up to vile lusts; for both  their females changed the natural use into that contrary to  nature;
1:26|KJV|For this cause God gave them up unto vile affections: for even their women did change the natural use into that which is against nature:
1:26<version name="WYC">Therefore God betook them into passions of shame [Therefore God betook them into passions of evil fame, <i>or shame</i>].  For the women of them changed the natural use into that use that is against kind.</version>
1:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此，神任憑他們陷入可恥的情慾：他們的女人把順性的用處換為逆性的用處；
1:27|ASV|and likewise also the men, leaving the natural use of the woman, burned in their lust one toward another, men with men working unseemliness, and receiving in themselves that recompense of their error which was due.
1:27|Darby|and in like manner the males also, leaving the natural use  of the female, were inflamed in their lust towards one another;  males with males working shame, and receiving in themselves the  recompense of their error which was fit.
1:27|KJV|And likewise also the men, leaving the natural use of the woman, burned in their lust one toward another; men with men working that which is unseemly, and receiving in themselves that recompence of their error which was meet.
1:27<version name="WYC">Also the men [the males, <i>or men</i>,] forsook the natural use of woman, and burned in their desires together, and men into men wrought filthhood, and received into themselves the meed that behooved of their error [males into males working filthhood, and receiving in themselves the meed, <i>or</i> <i>hire</i>, that behooved of their error].</version>
1:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|男人也是如此，棄了女人順性的用處，慾火中燒，彼此貪戀，男和男行可恥的事，就在自己身上受這妄為當得的報應。
1:28|ASV|And even as they refused to have God in their knowledge, God gave them up unto a reprobate mind, to do those things which are not fitting;
1:28|Darby|And according as they did not think good to have God in  [their] knowledge, God gave them up to a reprobate mind to  practise unseemly things;
1:28|KJV|And even as they did not like to retain God in their knowledge, God gave them over to a reprobate mind, to do those things which are not convenient;
1:28|WYC|And as they proved that they had not God in knowing [And as they proved not to have God in knowing], God betook them into a reprovable wit, that they do those things that be not suitable;
1:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們既然不以認識神為美，神就任憑他們存可棄絕的心思，行那些不合宜的事，
1:29|ASV|being filled with all unrighteousness, wickedness, covetousness, maliciousness; full of envy, murder, strife, deceit, malignity; whisperers,
1:29|Darby|being filled with all unrighteousness, wickedness,  covetousness, malice; full of envy, murder, strife, deceit,  evil dispositions; whisperers,
1:29|KJV|Being filled with all unrighteousness, fornication, wickedness, covetousness, maliciousness; full of envy, murder, debate, deceit, malignity; whisperers,
1:29|WYC|that they be full-filled with all wickedness [full-filled with all wickedness], malice, fornication, covetousness, waywardness, full of envy, manslayings [manslaying], strife, guile, evil will,
1:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|充滿了各樣不義、邪惡、貪婪、惡毒，滿了嫉妒、兇殺、爭競、詭詐、毒恨；
1:30|ASV|backbiters, hateful to God, insolent, haughty, boastful, inventors of evil things, disobedient to parents,
1:30|Darby|back-biters, hateful to God, insolent, proud, boasters,  inventors of evil things, disobedient to parents,
1:30|KJV|Backbiters, haters of God, despiteful, proud, boasters, inventors of evil things, disobedient to parents,
1:30|WYC|privy backbiters, detractors, hateful to God, debaters, proud, and high over measure [hateful to God, wrongful despisers, proud, high over measure], finders of evil things, not obedient to father and mother,
1:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又是讒毀人的，背後說人的，憎恨神的，侮慢人的，狂傲的，自誇的，捏造惡事的，違背父母的，
1:31|ASV|without understanding, covenant-breakers, without natural affection, unmerciful:
1:31|Darby|void of understanding, faithless, without natural  affection, unmerciful;
1:31|KJV|Without understanding, covenantbreakers, without natural affection, implacable, unmerciful:
1:31<version name="WYC">unwise, unmannerly, without love [without affection, <i>or love</i>], without bond of peace, without mercy.</version>
1:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|無知的，背約的，無親情的，無憐憫的。
1:32<version name="ASV">who, knowing the ordinance of God, that they that practise such things are worthy of death, not only do the same, but also consent with them that practise them. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:32<version name="Darby">who knowing the righteous judgment of God, that they who do  such things are worthy of death, not only practise them, but  have fellow delight in those who do [them]. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:32<version name="KJV">Who knowing the judgment of God, that they which commit such things are worthy of death, not only do the same, but have pleasure in them that do them.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:32|WYC|The which when they had known the rightwiseness of God, understood not, that they that do such things be worthy the death, not only they that do those things [not only they that do such things], but also they that consent to the doers.
1:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們雖明知神公義的判決，行這樣事的人是當死的，然而他們不但自己去行，還與那些行這樣事的人同歡，以他們為樂。
2:1|ASV|Wherefore thou art without excuse, O man, whosoever thou art that judgest: for wherein thou judges another, thou condemnest thyself; for thou that judgest dost practise the same things.
2:1|Darby|Therefore thou art inexcusable, O man, every one who  judgest, for in that in which thou judgest another, thou  condemnest thyself; for thou that judgest doest the same  things.
2:1|KJV|Therefore thou art inexcusable, O man, whosoever thou art that judgest: for wherein thou judgest another, thou condemnest thyself; for thou that judgest doest the same things.
2:1|WYC|Therefore thou art unexcusable, each man that deemest, for in what thing thou deemest another, thou condemnest thyself; for thou doest the same things which thou deemest.
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人哪，每一個審判人的！你是無法推諉的，你在甚麼事上審判人，就在甚麼事上定自己的罪；因你這審判人的，也行同樣的事。
2:2|ASV|And we know that the judgment of God is according to truth against them that practise such things.
2:2|Darby|But we know that the judgment of God is according to truth  upon those who do such things.
2:2|KJV|But we are sure that the judgment of God is according to truth against them which commit such things.
2:2|WYC|And we know, that the doom of God is after truth against them, that do such things.
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們知道行這樣事的人，神必按真理審判他。
2:3|ASV|And reckonest thou this, O man, who judgest them that practise such things, and doest the same, that thou shalt escape the judgment of God?
2:3|Darby|And thinkest thou this, O man, who judgest those that do  such things, and practisest them [thyself], that *thou* shalt  escape the judgment of God?
2:3|KJV|And thinkest thou this, O man, that judgest them which do such things, and doest the same, that thou shalt escape the judgment of God?
2:3|WYC|But guessest thou, man, that deemest them that do such things, and thou doest those things [and thou doest them], that thou shalt escape the doom of God?
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人哪，你審判行這樣事的人，自己卻照樣行，你以為能逃脫神的審判麼？
2:4|ASV|Or despisest thou the riches of his goodness and forbearance and longsuffering, not knowing that the goodness of God leadeth thee to repentance?
2:4|Darby|or despisest thou the riches of his goodness, and  forbearance, and long-suffering, not knowing that the goodness  of God leads thee to repentance?
2:4|KJV|Or despisest thou the riches of his goodness and forbearance and longsuffering; not knowing that the goodness of God leadeth thee to repentance?
2:4<version name="WYC">Whether thou despisest the riches of his goodness, and the patience, and the long abiding?  Knowest thou not, that the benignity of God leadeth thee to repenting? [Whether despisest thou the riches of his goodness, and patience, and long abiding?  Unknowest thou, that the benignity, <i>or</i> <i>good will</i>, of God leadeth thee to penance?]</version>
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|還是你藐視祂豐富的恩慈、寬容與恆忍，不曉得神的恩慈是領你悔改？
2:5|ASV|but after thy hardness and impenitent heart treasurest up for thyself wrath in the day of wrath and revelation of the righteous judgment of God;
2:5|Darby|but, according to thy hardness and impenitent heart,  treasurest up to thyself wrath, in [the] day of wrath and  revelation of [the] righteous judgment of God,
2:5|KJV|But after thy hardness and impenitent heart treasurest up unto thyself wrath against the day of wrath and revelation of the righteous judgment of God;
2:5|WYC|But after thine hardness and unrepentant heart, thou treasurest to thee wrath in the day of wrath [Forsooth after thy hardness and unrepentant heart, thou treasurest to thee wrath into the day of wrath] and of showing of the rightful doom of God,
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你竟任著你剛硬不悔改的心，為自己在神動怒並顯示祂公義審判的日子，積蓄忿怒。
2:6|ASV|who will render to every man according to his works:
2:6|Darby|who shall render to each according to his works:
2:6|KJV|Who will render to every man according to his deeds:
2:6|WYC|that shall yield to each man after his works;
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂必照各人的行為報應各人：
2:7|ASV|to them that by patience in well-doing seek for glory and honor and incorruption, eternal life:
2:7|Darby|to them who, in patient continuance of good works, seek for  glory and honour and incorruptibility, life eternal.
2:7|KJV|To them who by patient continuance in well doing seek for glory and honour and immortality, eternal life:
2:7|WYC|soothly to them that be by patience of good work, glory, and honour, and uncorruption, to them that seek everlasting life;
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡恆心行善，尋求榮耀、尊貴和不朽壞的，就以永遠的生命報應他們；
2:8|ASV|but unto them that are factious, and obey not the truth, but obey unrighteousness, shall be wrath and indignation,
2:8|Darby|But to those that are contentious, and are disobedient to  the truth, but obey unrighteousness, [there shall be] wrath and  indignation,
2:8|KJV|But unto them that are contentious, and do not obey the truth, but obey unrighteousness, indignation and wrath,
2:8|WYC|but to them that be of strife, and that assent not to truth, but believe to wickedness, wrath and indignation,
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|惟有私圖好爭，不信從真理，反信從不義的，就以忿怒、惱恨報應他們；
2:9|ASV|tribulation and anguish, upon every soul of man that worketh evil, of the Jew first, and also of the Greek;
2:9|Darby|tribulation and distress, on every soul of man that works  evil, both of Jew first, and of Greek;
2:9|KJV|Tribulation and anguish, upon every soul of man that doeth evil, of the Jew first, and also of the Gentile;
2:9|WYC|tribulation and anguish, into each soul of man that worketh evil, to the Jew first, and to the Greek [of Jew first and of the Greek];
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|將患難、困苦加給一切作惡的人，先是猶太人，後是希利尼人；
2:10|ASV|but glory and honor and peace to every man that worketh good, to the Jew first, and also to the Greek:
2:10|Darby|but glory and honour and peace to every one that works  good, both to Jew first and to Greek:
2:10|KJV|But glory, honour, and peace, to every man that worketh good, to the Jew first, and also to the Gentile:
2:10|WYC|but glory, and honour, and peace, to each man that worketh good thing, to the Jew first, and to the Greek.
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|卻將榮耀、尊貴與平安加給一切行善的人，先是猶太人，後是希利尼人。
2:11|ASV|for there is no respect of persons with God.
2:11|Darby|for there is no acceptance of persons with God.
2:11|KJV|For there is no respect of persons with God.
2:11<version name="WYC">For acception of persons [<i>that is, to put one before another without desert</i>,] is not with God.</version>
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神並不偏待人。
2:12|ASV|For as many as have sinned without law shall also perish without the law: and as many as have sinned under the law shall be judged by the law;
2:12|Darby|For as many as have sinned without law shall perish also  without law; and as many as have sinned under law shall be  judged by law,
2:12|KJV|For as many as have sinned without law shall also perish without law: and as many as have sinned in the law shall be judged by the law;
2:12|WYC|For whoever have sinned without the law, shall perish without the law; and whoever have sinned in the law, they shall be deemed by the law. [For whoever sin without law, shall perish without law; and whoever in the law sin, shall be deemed by the law.]
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡在律法以外犯了罪的，也必在律法以外滅亡；凡在律法以下犯了罪的，必按律法受審判，
2:13|ASV|for not the hearers of the law are just before God, but the doers of the law shall be justified:
2:13|Darby|(for not the hearers of the law [are] just before God, but  the doers of the law shall be justified.
2:13|KJV|(For not the hearers of the law are just before God, but the doers of the law shall be justified.
2:13|WYC|For the hearers of the law be not just with God, but the doers of the law shall be made just.
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|（原來在神面前，不是聽律法的為義，乃是行律法的稱義。
2:14|ASV|(for when Gentiles that have not the law do by nature the things of the law, these, not having the law, are the law unto themselves;
2:14|Darby|For when [those of the] nations, which have no law,  practise by nature the things of the law, these, having no law,  are a law to themselves;
2:14|KJV|For when the Gentiles, which have not the law, do by nature the things contained in the law, these, having not the law, are a law unto themselves:
2:14|WYC|For when heathen men that have not law, do naturally [do by kind] those things that be of the law, they not having such manner [of] law, be law to themselves,
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|沒有律法的外邦人，若順著本性行律法上的事，他們雖然沒有律法，自己就是自己的律法：
2:15|ASV|in that they show the work of the law written in their hearts, their conscience bearing witness therewith, and their thoughts one with another accusing or else excusing them);
2:15|Darby|who shew the work of the law written in their hearts, their  conscience also bearing witness, and their thoughts accusing or  else excusing themselves between themselves;)
2:15|KJV|Which shew the work of the law written in their hearts, their conscience also bearing witness, and their thoughts the mean while accusing or else excusing one another;)
2:15|WYC|that show the work of the law written in their hearts.  For the conscience of them yieldeth to them a witnessing betwixt themselves of thoughts that be accusing or defending, [that show the work of law written in their hearts; the conscience of them yielding to them a witnessing and between themselves of thoughts accusing or also defending,]
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們顯出那寫在他們心裡律法的功用，他們的良心同作見證，並且他們的思想互相控告或者也辯護。）
2:16|ASV|in the day when God shall judge the secrets of men, according to my gospel, by Jesus Christ.
2:16|Darby|in [the] day when God shall judge the secrets of men,  according to my glad tidings, by Jesus Christ.
2:16|KJV|In the day when God shall judge the secrets of men by Jesus Christ according to my gospel.
2:16|WYC|in the day when God shall deem the privy things of men after my gospel, by Jesus Christ.
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就是在神藉耶穌基督，照著我的福音，審判人隱祕事的日子。
2:17|ASV|But if thou bearest the name of a Jew, and restest upon the law, and gloriest in God,
2:17|Darby|But if *thou* art named a Jew, and restest in the law, and  makest thy boast in God,
2:17|KJV|Behold, thou art called a Jew, and restest in the law, and makest thy boast of God,
2:17|WYC|But if thou art named a Jew [Forsooth if thou art named a Jew], and restest in the law, and hast glory in God,
2:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你名為猶太人，又倚靠律法，且指著神誇口，
2:18|ASV|and knowest his will, and approvest the things that are excellent, being instructed out of the law,
2:18|Darby|and knowest the will, and discerningly approvest the things  that are more excellent, being instructed out of the law;
2:18|KJV|And knowest his will, and approvest the things that are more excellent, being instructed out of the law;
2:18|WYC|and hast known his will, and thou learned by the law approvest [provest] the more profitable things,
2:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|既從律法受了教導，就認識神的旨意，也能鑑賞那更美的事，
2:19|ASV|and art confident that thou thyself art a guide of the blind, a light of them that are in darkness,
2:19|Darby|and hast confidence that thou thyself art a leader of the  blind, a light of those who [are] in darkness,
2:19|KJV|And art confident that thou thyself art a guide of the blind, a light of them which are in darkness,
2:19|WYC|and trustest thyself to be a leader of blind men, the light of them that be in darknesses,
2:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又深信自己是給瞎子領路的，是黑暗中之人的光，
2:20|ASV|a corrector of the foolish, a teacher of babes, having in the law the form of knowledge and of the truth;
2:20|Darby|an instructor of the foolish, a teacher of babes, having  the form of knowledge and of truth in the law:
2:20|KJV|An instructor of the foolish, a teacher of babes, which hast the form of knowledge and of the truth in the law.
2:20<version name="WYC">a teacher of unwise men, a master of young children, that hast the form of knowing [having the form of science, <i>or knowing</i>,] and of truth in the law;</version>
2:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|是愚昧人的管教者，是幼稚人的教師，在律法上有知識和真理的規模；
2:21|ASV|thou therefore that teachest another, teachest thou not thyself? thou that preachest a man should not steal, dost thou steal?
2:21|Darby|thou then that teachest another, dost thou not teach  thyself? thou that preachest not to steal, dost thou steal?
2:21|KJV|Thou therefore which teachest another, teachest thou not thyself? thou that preachest a man should not steal, dost thou steal?
2:21|WYC|what then teachest thou another, and teachest not thyself?  Thou that preachest that me shall not steal, stealest? [therefore thou that teachest another, teachest not thyself? Thou that preachest to not steal, stealest?]
2:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，你這教導別人的，不教導自己麼？你這傳講不可偷竊的，自己偷竊麼？
2:22|ASV|thou that sayest a man should not commit adultery, dost thou commit adultery? thou that abhorrest idols, dost thou rob temples?
2:22|Darby|thou that sayest [man should] not commit adultery, dost  thou commit adultery? thou that abhorrest idols, dost thou  commit sacrilege?
2:22|KJV|Thou that sayest a man should not commit adultery, dost thou commit adultery? thou that abhorrest idols, dost thou commit sacrilege?
2:22<version name="WYC">Thou that teachest that me shall not do lechery, doest lechery?  Thou that loathest maumets, doest sacrilege? <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21002a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
2:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你這說不可姦淫的，自己姦淫麼？你這憎惡偶像的，自己搶劫廟宇麼？
2:23|ASV|thou who gloriest in the law, through thy transgression of the law dishonorest thou God?
2:23|Darby|thou who boastest in law, dost thou by transgression of the  law dishonour God?
2:23|KJV|Thou that makest thy boast of the law, through breaking the law dishonourest thou God?
2:23<version name="WYC">Thou that hast glory in the law, unhonourest God by breaking of the law?  [Thou that gloriest in the law, by breaking of the law unworshippest, <i>or despisest</i>, God?]</version>
2:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你指著律法誇口，自己卻犯律法玷辱神麼？
2:24|ASV|For the name of God is blasphemed among the Gentiles because of you, even as it is written.
2:24|Darby|For the name of God is blasphemed on your account among the  nations, according as it is written.
2:24|KJV|For the name of God is blasphemed among the Gentiles through you, as it is written.
2:24|WYC|For the name of God is blasphemed by you among heathen men, as [it] is written. [For the name of God by you is blasphemed among heathen men, as it is written.]
2:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|如經上所記：“神的名在外邦人中，因你們受了褻瀆。”
2:25|ASV|For circumcision indeed profiteth, if thou be a doer of the law: but if thou be a transgressor of the law, thy circumcision is become uncircumcision.
2:25|Darby|For circumcision indeed profits if thou keep [the] law; but  if thou be a law-transgressor, thy circumcision is become  uncircumcision.
2:25|KJV|For circumcision verily profiteth, if thou keep the law: but if thou be a breaker of the law, thy circumcision is made uncircumcision.
2:25|WYC|For circumcision profiteth, if thou keep the law; but if thou be a trespasser against the law [forsooth if thou be a trespasser of the law], thy circumcision is made prepuce.
2:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你若行律法，割禮固然於你有益；但你若是犯律法的，你的割禮就不算割禮。
2:26|ASV|If therefore the uncircumcision keep the ordinances of the law, shall not his uncircumcision be reckoned for circumcision?
2:26|Darby|If therefore the uncircumcision keep the requirements of  the law, shall not his uncircumcision be reckoned for  circumcision,
2:26|KJV|Therefore if the uncircumcision keep the righteousness of the law, shall not his uncircumcision be counted for circumcision?
2:26|WYC|Therefore if prepuce keep the rightwiseness of the law, whether his prepuce shall not be areckoned [shall not be reckoned] into circumcision?
2:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以那未受割禮的，若遵守律法的典章，他雖然未受割禮，豈不算是受割禮的麼？
2:27|ASV|and shall not the uncircumcision which is by nature, if it fulfil the law, judge thee, who with the letter and circumcision art a transgressor of the law?
2:27|Darby|and uncircumcision by nature, fulfilling the law, judge  thee, who, with letter and circumcision, [art] a  law-transgressor?
2:27|KJV|And shall not uncircumcision which is by nature, if it fulfil the law, judge thee, who by the letter and circumcision dost transgress the law?
2:27|WYC|And the prepuce of kind that fulfilleth the law, shall deem thee, that by letter and circumcision art a trespasser against the law. [And the prepuce, which is of the kind, fulfilling the law, shall deem thee, that by letter and circumcision art trespasser of the law.]
2:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|而且那本來未受割禮的，若全守律法，就要審判你這有字句和割禮卻犯律法的人。
2:28|ASV|For he is not a Jew who is one outwardly; neither is that circumcision which is outward in the flesh:
2:28|Darby|For he is not a Jew who [is] one outwardly, neither that  circumcision which is outward in flesh;
2:28|KJV|For he is not a Jew, which is one outwardly; neither is that circumcision, which is outward in the flesh:
2:28|WYC|For he that is in open is not a Jew, neither it is circumcision that is openly in the flesh [neither the circumcision that is in the flesh in open];
2:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為外表上作猶太人的，並不是猶太人；外表上肉體的割禮，也不是割禮。
2:29<version name="ASV">but he is a Jew who is one inwardly; and circumcision is that of the heart, in the spirit not in the letter; whose praise is not of men, but of God. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:29<version name="Darby">but he [is] a Jew [who is so] inwardly; and circumcision,  of the heart, in spirit, not in letter; whose praise [is] not  of men, but of God. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:29<version name="KJV">But he is a Jew, which is one inwardly; and circumcision is that of the heart, in the spirit, and not in the letter; whose praise is not of men, but of God.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:29|WYC|but he that is a Jew in hid, and the circumcision of heart, in spirit, not by the letter [not in letter], whose praising is not of men, but of God.
2:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|惟有在內裡作的，纔是猶太人；割禮也是心裡的，在於靈，不在於字句。這人的稱讚，不是從人來的，乃是從神來的。
3:1|ASV|What advantage then hath the Jew? or what is the profit of circumcision?
3:1|Darby|What then [is] the superiority of the Jew? or what the  profit of circumcision?
3:1|KJV|What advantage then hath the Jew? or what profit is there of circumcision?
3:1|WYC|What then is more to a Jew, or what profit of circumcision?
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，猶太人有甚麼長處？割禮有甚麼益處？
3:2|ASV|Much every way: first of all, that they were intrusted with the oracles of God.
3:2|Darby|Much every way: and first, indeed, that to them were  entrusted the oracles of God.
3:2|KJV|Much every way: chiefly, because that unto them were committed the oracles of God.
3:2|WYC|Much by all wise [Much by all manner]; first, for the speakings of God were betaken to them.
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|各方面都很多。第一，是神的諭言信託了他們。
3:3|ASV|For what if some were without faith? shall their want of faith make of none effect the faithfulness of God?
3:3|Darby|For what? if some have not believed, shall their unbelief  make the faith of God of none effect?
3:3|KJV|For what if some did not believe? shall their unbelief make the faith of God without effect?
3:3|WYC|And what if some of them believed not?  Whether the unbelief of them hath voided the faith of God?
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|即便有不信的，這有何妨？難道他們的不信，就廢掉神的信麼？
3:4|ASV|God forbid: yea, let God be found true, but every man a liar; as it is written, That thou mightest be justified in thy words, And mightest prevail when thou comest into judgment.
3:4|Darby|Far be the thought: but let God be true, and every man  false; according as it is written, So that thou shouldest be  justified in thy words, and shouldest overcome when thou art in  judgment.
3:4|KJV|God forbid: yea, let God be true, but every man a liar; as it is written, That thou mightest be justified in thy sayings, and mightest overcome when thou art judged.
3:4<version name="WYC">God forbid [Far be it].  For God is soothfast [Forsooth God is true, <i>or soothfast</i>], but each man a liar; as it is written, That thou be justified in thy words, and overcome, when thou art deemed.</version>
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|絕對不能！神總是真實的，人都是虛謊的，如經上所記：“好叫你說話的時候，顯為公義；被人審判的時候，可以得勝。”
3:5|ASV|But if our righteousness commendeth the righteousness of God, what shall we say? Is God unrighteous who visiteth with wrath? (I speak after the manner of men.)
3:5|Darby|But if our unrighteousness commend God's righteousness, what  shall we say? Is God unrighteous who inflicts wrath? I speak  according to man.
3:5|KJV|But if our unrighteousness commend the righteousness of God, what shall we say? Is God unrighteous who taketh vengeance? (I speak as a man)
3:5<version name="WYC">But if our wickedness [Forsooth if our wickedness, <i>or unequity</i>,] commend the rightwiseness of God, what shall we say?  Whether God is wicked, that bringeth in wrath?  After man I say.</version>
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我且照著人的常話說，我們的不義若顯出神的義來，我們要說甚麼？神降怒，難道是祂不義麼？
3:6|ASV|God forbid: for then how shall God judge the world?
3:6|Darby|Far be the thought: since how shall God judge the world?
3:6|KJV|God forbid: for then how shall God judge the world?
3:6|WYC|God forbid [Far be it].  Else how shall God deem this world?
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|絕對不是！若是這樣，神怎能審判世界？
3:7|ASV|But if the truth of God through my lie abounded unto his glory, why am I also still judged as a sinner?
3:7|Darby|For if the truth of God, in my lie, has more abounded to his  glory, why yet am *I* also judged as a sinner?
3:7|KJV|For if the truth of God hath more abounded through my lie unto his glory; why yet am I also judged as a sinner?
3:7|WYC|For if the truth of God hath abounded in my lying, into the glory of him, what [and] yet am I deemed as a sinner?
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但神的真實，若因我的虛謊，越發洋溢出祂的榮耀，為甚麼我還受審判像罪人一樣？
3:8|ASV|and why not (as we are slanderously reported, and as some affirm that we say), Let us do evil, that good may come? whose condemnation is just.
3:8|Darby|and not, according as we are injuriously charged, and  according as some affirm that we say, Let us practise evil  things, that good ones may come? whose judgment is just.
3:8|KJV|And not rather, (as we be slanderously reported, and as some affirm that we say,) Let us do evil, that good may come? whose damnation is just.
3:8|WYC|And not as we be blasphemed, and as some say that we say, Do we evil things, that good things come.  Whose damnation is just.
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|為甚麼不說，讓我們作惡以成善？這是我們所受的毀謗，也是有些人硬說我們有這話。這等人受審判是該當的。
3:9|ASV|What then? are we better than they? No, in no wise: for we before laid to the charge both of Jews and Greeks, that they are all under sin;
3:9|Darby|What then? are we better? No, in no wise: for we have before  charged both Jews and Greeks with being all under sin:
3:9|KJV|What then? are we better than they? No, in no wise: for we have before proved both Jews and Gentiles, that they are all under sin;
3:9<version name="WYC">What then?  Surpass we them?  Nay; for we have showed by skill, that all both Jews and Greeks be under sin, <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21018a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這卻怎麼樣？我們比他們強麼？絕對沒有！因我們已經指控，猶太人和希利尼人都在罪之下，
3:10|ASV|as it is written, There is none righteous, no, not one;
3:10|Darby|according as it is written, There is not a righteous [man],  not even one;
3:10|KJV|As it is written, There is none righteous, no, not one:
3:10|WYC|as it is written, For there is no man just [For there is not any man just];
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就如經上所記：“沒有義人，連一個也沒有，
3:11|ASV|There is none that understandeth, There is none that seeketh after God;
3:11|Darby|there is not the [man] that understands, there is not one  that seeks after God.
3:11|KJV|There is none that understandeth, there is none that seeketh after God.
3:11|WYC|there is no man understanding [there is not a man understanding], neither seeking God.
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|沒有明白的，沒有尋求神的；
3:12|ASV|They have all turned aside, they are together become unprofitable; There is none that doeth good, no, not, so much as one:
3:12|Darby|All have gone out of the way, they have together become  unprofitable; there is not one that practises goodness, there  is not so much as one:
3:12|KJV|They are all gone out of the way, they are together become unprofitable; there is none that doeth good, no, not one.
3:12|WYC|All bowed away, together they be made unprofitable; there is none that doeth good thing, there is none till to one [there is not till to one].
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|都是偏離正路，一同變為無用；沒有行善的，連一個也沒有。
3:13|ASV|Their throat is an open sepulchre; With their tongues they have used deceit: The poison of asps is under their lips:
3:13|Darby|their throat is an open sepulchre; with their tongues they  have used deceit; asps' poison [is] under their lips:
3:13|KJV|Their throat is an open sepulchre; with their tongues they have used deceit; the poison of asps is under their lips:
3:13<version name="WYC">The throat of them is an open sepulchre; with their tongues they did guilefully; the venom of snakes <i>is</i> under their lips <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21022b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup>.</version>
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們的喉嚨是敞開的墳墓，他們用舌頭弄詭詐，嘴脣裡有虺蛇的毒氣，
3:14|ASV|Whose mouth is full of cursing and bitterness:
3:14|Darby|whose mouth is full of cursing and bitterness;
3:14|KJV|Whose mouth is full of cursing and bitterness:
3:14|WYC|The mouth of whom is full of cursing and bitterness;
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們滿口是咒罵苦毒；
3:15|ASV|Their feet are swift to shed blood;
3:15|Darby|swift their feet to shed blood;
3:15|KJV|Their feet are swift to shed blood:
3:15<version name="WYC">the feet of them <i>be</i> swift to shed blood.</version>
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|殺人流血，他們的腳飛跑，
3:16|ASV|Destruction and misery are in their ways;
3:16|Darby|ruin and misery [are] in their ways,
3:16|KJV|Destruction and misery are in their ways:
3:16<version name="WYC">Sorrow and cursedness <i>be</i> in the ways of them, <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21025c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup></version>
3:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在他們所經過的路上，遍行毀壞和禍害，
3:17|ASV|And the way of peace have they not known:
3:17|Darby|and way of peace they have not known:
3:17|KJV|And the way of peace have they not known:
3:17|WYC|and they knew not the way of peace;
3:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|平安的路，他們未曾知道；
3:18|ASV|There is no fear of God before their eyes.
3:18|Darby|there is no fear of God before their eyes.
3:18|KJV|There is no fear of God before their eyes.
3:18|WYC|the dread of God is not before their eyes.
3:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們眼中不怕神。”
3:19|ASV|Now we know that what things soever the law saith, it speaketh to them that are under the law; that every mouth may be stopped, and all the world may be brought under the judgment of God:
3:19|Darby|Now we know that whatever the things the law says, it  speaks to those under the law, that every mouth may be stopped,  and all the world be under judgment to God.
3:19|KJV|Now we know that what things soever the law saith, it saith to them who are under the law: that every mouth may be stopped, and all the world may become guilty before God.
3:19|WYC|And we know [Forsooth we know], that whatever things the law speaketh, it speaketh to them that be in the law, that each mouth be stopped, and each world be made subject to God.
3:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們曉得律法上的話，都是對律法以下之人說的，好堵住各人的口，叫普世的人都伏在神的審判之下。
3:20|ASV|because by the works of the law shall no flesh be justified in his sight; for through the law cometh the knowledge of sin.
3:20|Darby|Wherefore by works of law no flesh shall be justified  before him; for by law [is] knowledge of sin.
3:20|KJV|Therefore by the deeds of the law there shall no flesh be justified in his sight: for by the law is the knowledge of sin.
3:20|WYC|For of the works of the law each flesh shall not be justified before him; for by the law there is knowing of sin [for by the law is knowing of sin].
3:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為凡屬肉體的人，都不能本於行律法在神面前得稱義，因為律法本是叫人知罪。
3:21|ASV|But now apart from the law a righteousness of God hath been manifested, being witnessed by the law and the prophets;
3:21|Darby|But now without law righteousness of God is manifested,  borne witness to by the law and the prophets;
3:21|KJV|But now the righteousness of God without the law is manifested, being witnessed by the law and the prophets;
3:21|WYC|But now without the law the rightwiseness of God is showed, that is witnessed of the law and the prophets.
3:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但如今神的義在律法以外已經顯明出來，有律法和申言者為證，
3:22|ASV|even the righteousness of God through faith in Jesus Christ unto all them that believe; for there is no distinction;
3:22|Darby|righteousness of God by faith of Jesus Christ towards all,  and upon all those who believe: for there is no difference;
3:22|KJV|Even the righteousness of God which is by faith of Jesus Christ unto all and upon all them that believe: for there is no difference:
3:22<version name="WYC">And the rightwiseness of God is by the faith of Jesus Christ into all men and on all men that believe in him; for there is no parting. [Soothly the rightwiseness of God is by the faith of Jesus Christ into all and on all that believe into him; forsooth there is no distinction, <i>or parting</i>.]</version>
3:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就是神的義，藉著信耶穌基督，歸與一切信的人，並沒有分別。
3:23|ASV|for all have sinned, and fall short of the glory of God;
3:23|Darby|for all have sinned, and come short of the glory of God;
3:23|KJV|For all have sinned, and come short of the glory of God;
3:23|WYC|For all men sinned, and have need to the glory of God;
3:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為眾人都犯了罪，虧缺了神的榮耀，
3:24|ASV|being justified freely by his grace through the redemption that is in Christ Jesus:
3:24|Darby|being justified freely by his grace through the redemption  which [is] in Christ Jesus;
3:24|KJV|Being justified freely by his grace through the redemption that is in Christ Jesus:
3:24<version name="WYC">and be justified freely by his grace, by the again-buying that is in Christ Jesus [by the redemption, <i>or the again-buying</i>, that is in Jesus Christ].</version>
3:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但因神的恩典，藉著在基督耶穌裡的救贖，就白白的得稱義。
3:25|ASV|whom God set forth to be a propitiation, through faith, in his blood, to show his righteousness because of the passing over of the sins done aforetime, in the forbearance of God;
3:25|Darby|whom God has set forth a mercy-seat, through faith in his  blood, for [the] shewing forth of his righteousness, in respect  of the passing by the sins that had taken place before, through  the forbearance of God;
3:25|KJV|Whom God hath set forth to be a propitiation through faith in his blood, to declare his righteousness for the remission of sins that are past, through the forbearance of God;
3:25|WYC|Whom God ordained forgiver [Whom God purposed an helper], by faith in his blood, to the showing of his rightwiseness, for [the] remission of before-going sins, in the bearing up of God,
3:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神擺出基督耶穌作平息處，是憑著祂的血，藉著人的信，為要在神以寬容越過人先時所犯的罪上，顯示祂的義；
3:26|ASV|for the showing, I say, of his righteousness at this present season: that he might himself be just, and the justifier of him that hath faith in Jesus.
3:26|Darby|for [the] shewing forth of his righteousness in the present  time, so that he should be just, and justify him that is of  [the] faith of Jesus.
3:26|KJV|To declare, I say, at this time his righteousness: that he might be just, and the justifier of him which believeth in Jesus.
3:26|WYC|to the showing of his rightwiseness in this time, that he be just, and justifying him that is of the faith of Jesus Christ.
3:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|為著在今時顯示祂的義，使祂能是義的，也能稱那以信耶穌為本的人為義。
3:27|ASV|Where then is the glorying? It is excluded. By what manner of law? of works? Nay: but by a law of faith.
3:27|Darby|Where then [is] boasting? It has been excluded. By what  law? of works? Nay, but by law of faith;
3:27|KJV|Where is boasting then? It is excluded. By what law? of works? Nay: but by the law of faith.
3:27|WYC|Where then is thy glorying?  It is excluded.  By what law?  Of deeds doing?  Nay, but by the law of faith.
3:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|既是這樣，那裡有可誇的？完全沒有了！藉著甚麼律？藉著行的律麼？不是，乃是藉著信的律。
3:28|ASV|We reckon therefore that a man is justified by faith apart from the works of the law.
3:28|Darby|for we reckon that a man is justified by faith, without  works of law.
3:28|KJV|Therefore we conclude that a man is justified by faith without the deeds of the law.
3:28|WYC|For we deem a man to be justified by faith, without works of the law.
3:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們算定了，人得稱義是藉著信，與行律法無關。
3:29|ASV|Or is God the God of Jews only? is he not the God of Gentiles also? Yea, of Gentiles also:
3:29|Darby|Is [God] the God of Jews only? is he not of [the] nations  also? Yea, of nations also:
3:29|KJV|Is he the God of the Jews only? is he not also of the Gentiles? Yes, of the Gentiles also:
3:29|WYC|Whether of the Jews is God only?  Whether he is not also of heathen men?  Yes, and of heathen men.
3:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|難道神只是猶太人的神麼？不也是外邦人的麼？是的，也是外邦人的；
3:30|ASV|if so be that God is one, and he shall justify the circumcision by faith, and the uncircumcision through faith.
3:30|Darby|since indeed [it is] one God who shall justify [the]  circumcision on the principle of faith, and uncircumcision by  faith.
3:30|KJV|Seeing it is one God, which shall justify the circumcision by faith, and uncircumcision through faith.
3:30|WYC|For there is one God, that justifieth circumcision by faith, and prepuce by faith.
3:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神既是一位，祂就要本於信稱那受割禮的為義，也要藉著信稱那未受割禮的為義。
3:31<version name="ASV">Do we then make the law of none effect through faith? God forbid: nay, we establish the law. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:31<version name="Darby">Do we then make void law by faith? Far be the thought:  [no,] but we establish law. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:31<version name="KJV">Do we then make void the law through faith? God forbid: yea, we establish the law.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:31|WYC|Destroy we therefore the law by faith?  God forbid [Far be it]; but we stablish the law.
3:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我們藉著信使律法失效麼？絕對不是！反而堅固了律法。
4:1|ASV|What then shall we say that Abraham, our forefather, hath found according to the flesh?
4:1|Darby|What shall we say then that Abraham our father according to  flesh has found?
4:1|KJV|What shall we say then that Abraham our father, as pertaining to the flesh, hath found?
4:1|WYC|What then shall we say, that Abraham our father after the flesh found?
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我們可說我們的祖宗亞伯拉罕照著肉體得了甚麼？
4:2|ASV|For if Abraham was justified by works, he hath whereof to glory; but not toward God.
4:2|Darby|For if Abraham has been justified on the principle of works,  he has whereof to boast: but not before God;
4:2|KJV|For if Abraham were justified by works, he hath whereof to glory; but not before God.
4:2|WYC|For if Abraham is justified of works of the law, he hath glory, but not with God.
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|倘若亞伯拉罕是本於行為得稱義，就有可誇的，只是在神面前並無可誇。
4:3|ASV|For what saith the scripture? And Abraham believed God, and it was reckoned unto him for righteousness.
4:3|Darby|for what does the scripture say? And Abraham believed God,  and it was reckoned to him as righteousness.
4:3|KJV|For what saith the scripture? Abraham believed God, and it was counted unto him for righteousness.
4:3|WYC|For what saith the scripture?  Abraham believed to God, and it was areckoned [reckoned] to him to rightwiseness.
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|原來經上說甚麼？說，“亞伯拉罕信神，這就算為他的義。”
4:4|ASV|Now to him that worketh, the reward is not reckoned as of grace, but as of debt.
4:4|Darby|Now to him that works the reward is not reckoned as of  grace, but of debt:
4:4|KJV|Now to him that worketh is the reward not reckoned of grace, but of debt.
4:4<version name="WYC">And to him that worketh meed is not areckoned by grace [is not given to, <i>or</i> <i>reckoned</i>, after grace], but by debt.</version>
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|作工的得工價，不是照著恩典，乃是照著所該得者算的。
4:5|ASV|But to him that worketh not, but believeth on him that justifieth the ungodly, his faith is reckoned for righteousness.
4:5|Darby|but to him who does not work, but believes on him who  justifies the ungodly, his faith is reckoned as righteousness.
4:5|KJV|But to him that worketh not, but believeth on him that justifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted for righteousness.
4:5<version name="WYC">Soothly to him that worketh not, but believeth into him that justifieth a wicked man, his faith is areckoned to rightwiseness <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21045a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>, after the purpose of God's grace.</version>
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|惟有不作工，只信靠那稱不虔者為義之神的，他的信就算為他的義。
4:6|ASV|Even as David also pronounceth blessing upon the man, unto whom God reckoneth righteousness apart from works,
4:6|Darby|Even as David also declares the blessedness of the man to  whom God reckons righteousness without works:
4:6|KJV|Even as David also describeth the blessedness of the man, unto whom God imputeth righteousness without works,
4:6<version name="WYC">As David saith the blessedness of a man, whom God accepteth, he giveth to him rightwiseness without works <i>of the law</i>, [As and David saith the blessedness of a man, to whom God accepteth, rightwiseness without works,]</version>
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|正如大衛也稱那在行為以外，蒙神算為義的人為有福的：
4:7|ASV|saying, Blessed are they whose iniquities are forgiven, And whose sins are covered.
4:7|Darby|Blessed [they] whose lawlessnesses have been forgiven, and  whose sins have been covered:
4:7|KJV|Saying, Blessed are they whose iniquities are forgiven, and whose sins are covered.
4:7<version name="WYC">Blessed <i>be</i> they, whose wickednesses be forgiven, and whose sins be hid [and whose sins be covered, <i>or hid</i>].</version>
4:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|“不法得赦免，罪得遮蓋的人，是有福的。
4:8|ASV|Blessed is the man to whom, the Lord will not reckon sin.
4:8|Darby|blessed [the] man to whom [the] Lord shall not at all reckon  sin.
4:8|KJV|Blessed is the man to whom the Lord will not impute sin.
4:8<version name="WYC">Blessed <i>is</i> that man, to whom God areckoned [reckoned] not sin.</version>
4:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|主絕不算為有罪的人，是有福的。”
4:9|ASV|Is this blessing then pronounced upon the circumcision, or upon the uncircumcision also? for we say, To Abraham his faith was reckoned for righteousness.
4:9|Darby|[Does] this blessedness then [rest] on the circumcision, or  also on the uncircumcision? For we say that faith has been  reckoned to Abraham as righteousness.
4:9|KJV|Cometh this blessedness then upon the circumcision only, or upon the uncircumcision also? for we say that faith was reckoned to Abraham for righteousness.
4:9|WYC|Then whether dwelleth this blessedness only in circumcision, or also in prepuce?  For we say, that the faith was areckoned [reckoned] to Abraham to rightwiseness.
4:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|如此，這稱為有福的福是單加給受割禮的人，還是也加給未受割禮的人？因我們說，亞伯拉罕的信，就算為他的義，
4:10|ASV|How then was it reckoned? when he was in circumcision, or in uncircumcision? Not in circumcision, but in uncircumcision:
4:10|Darby|How then has it been reckoned? when he was in circumcision,  or in uncircumcision? Not in circumcision, but in  uncircumcision.
4:10|KJV|How was it then reckoned? when he was in circumcision, or in uncircumcision? Not in circumcision, but in uncircumcision.
4:10|WYC|How then was it areckoned [reckoned]? in circumcision, or in prepuce?  Not in circumcision, but in prepuce.
4:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|是怎麼算的？是在他受割禮的時候，還是在他未受割禮的時候？不是在受割禮的時候，乃是在未受割禮的時候。
4:11|ASV|and he received the sign of circumcision, a seal of the righteousness of the faith which he had while he was in uncircumcision; that he might be the father of all them that believe, though they be in uncircumcision, that righteousness might be reckoned unto them;
4:11|Darby|And he received [the] sign of circumcision [as] seal of the  righteousness of faith which [he had] being in uncircumcision,  that he might be [the] father of all them that believe being in  uncircumcision, that righteousness might be reckoned to them  also;
4:11|KJV|And he received the sign of circumcision, a seal of the righteousness of the faith which he had yet being uncircumcised: that he might be the father of all them that believe, though they be not circumcised; that righteousness might be imputed unto them also:
4:11<version name="WYC">And he took a sign of circumcision, a token of rightwiseness of the faith [a marking, <i>or tokening</i>, of rightwiseness of faith] which is in prepuce, that he be father of all men believing by prepuce, that it be areckoned [reckoned] also to them to rightwiseness;</version>
4:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且他受了割禮的記號，作他未受割禮時那信之義的印記，叫他作一切未受割禮而信之人的父，使他們也算為義；
4:12|ASV|and the father of circumcision to them who not only are of the circumcision, but who also walk in the steps of that faith of our father Abraham which he had in uncircumcision.
4:12|Darby|and father of circumcision, not only to those who are of  [the] circumcision, but to those also who walk in the steps of  the faith, during uncircumcision, of our father Abraham.
4:12|KJV|And the father of circumcision to them who are not of the circumcision only, but who also walk in the steps of that faith of our father Abraham, which he had being yet uncircumcised.
4:12<version name="WYC">and that he be father of circumcision, not only to them that be of circumcision, but also to them that follow the steps of the faith, which <i>faith </i>is in prepuce of our father Abraham. [and that he be father of circumcision, not only to them that be of circumcision, but and to them that follow the steps of the faith of our father Abraham, that is in prepuce.]</version>
4:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又作受割禮之人的父，就是那些不但受割禮，並且照我們祖宗亞伯拉罕，未受割禮時之信的腳蹤而行的人。
4:13|ASV|For not through the law was the promise to Abraham or to his seed that he should be heir of the world, but through the righteousness of faith.
4:13|Darby|For [it was] not by law that the promise was to Abraham, or  to his seed, that he should be heir of [the] world, but by  righteousness of faith.
4:13|KJV|For the promise, that he should be the heir of the world, was not to Abraham, or to his seed, through the law, but through the righteousness of faith.
4:13|WYC|For not by the law is [the] promise to Abraham, or to his seed, that he should be [the] heir of the world, but by the rightwiseness of faith.
4:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神應許亞伯拉罕，或他的後裔，必得承受世界，不是藉著律法，乃是藉著信的義。
4:14|ASV|For if they that are of the law are heirs, faith is made void, and the promise is made of none effect:
4:14|Darby|For if they which [are] of law be heirs, faith is made  vain, and the promise made of no effect.
4:14|KJV|For if they which are of the law be heirs, faith is made void, and the promise made of none effect:
4:14|WYC|For if they that be of the law, be heirs, faith is destroyed, promise is done away.
4:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若是本於律法的，纔得為後嗣，信就成了虛空，應許也就失效了。
4:15|ASV|for the law worketh wrath; but where there is no law, neither is there transgression.
4:15|Darby|For law works wrath; but where no law is neither [is there]  transgression.
4:15|KJV|Because the law worketh wrath: for where no law is, there is no transgression.
4:15<version name="WYC">For the law worketh wrath; for where is no law, there is no trespass, neither is trespassing. [Forsooth the law worketh wrath; soothly where the law is not, neither is prevarication, <i>or</i> <i>trespassing</i>.]</version>
4:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為律法是惹動忿怒的；那裡沒有律法，那裡就沒有過犯。
4:16|ASV|For this cause it is of faith, that it may be according to grace; to the end that the promise may be sure to all the seed; not to that only which is of the law, but to that also which is of the faith of Abraham, who is the father of us all
4:16|Darby|Therefore [it is] on the principle of faith, that [it might  be] according to grace, in order to the promise being sure to  all the seed, not to that only which [is] of the law, but to  that also which [is] of Abraham's faith, who is father of us  all,
4:16|KJV|Therefore it is of faith, that it might be by grace; to the end the promise might be sure to all the seed; not to that only which is of the law, but to that also which is of the faith of Abraham; who is the father of us all,
4:16<version name="WYC">Therefore <i>rightwiseness is </i>of faith, that by grace promise be stable to each seed [that after grace promise be stable, <i>or</i> <i>steadfast</i>, to each seed], not to that seed only that is of the law, but to that that is of the faith of Abraham, which is father of us all.</version>
4:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以人得為後嗣是本於信，為要照著恩，使應許定然歸給一切後裔，不但歸給那本於律法的，也歸給那本於亞伯拉罕之信的。
4:17|ASV|(as it is written, A father of many nations have I made thee) before him whom he believed, even God, who giveth life to the dead, and calleth the things that are not, as though they were.
4:17|Darby|(according as it is written, I have made thee father of  many nations,) before the God whom he believed, who quickens  the dead, and calls the things which be not as being;
4:17|KJV|(As it is written, I have made thee a father of many nations,) before him whom he believed, even God, who quickeneth the dead, and calleth those things which be not as though they were.
4:17<version name="WYC">As it is written, For I have set thee father of many folks, before God to whom thou hast believed.  The which <i>God</i> quickeneth dead men [The which quickeneth the dead], and calleth those things that be not, as those that be.</version>
4:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞伯拉罕在他所信那叫死人復活，又稱無為有的神面前，是我們眾人的父，如經上所記：“我已經立你作多國的父。”
4:18|ASV|Who in hope believed against hope, to the end that he might become a father of many nations, according to that which had been spoken, So shall thy seed be.
4:18|Darby|who against hope believed in hope to his becoming father of  many nations, according to that which was spoken, So shall thy  seed be:
4:18|KJV|Who against hope believed in hope, that he might become the father of many nations, according to that which was spoken, So shall thy seed be.
4:18<version name="WYC">[The] Which <i>Abraham</i> against hope believed into hope, that he should be made father of many folks, as it was said to him [after that it is said to him], Thus shall thy seed be, as the stars of heaven, and as the gravel [and as gravel, <i>or sand</i>,] that is in the brink of the sea.</version>
4:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他在無可指望的時候，仍靠指望而信，就得以照先前所說，“你的後裔將要如此”的話，作多國的父。
4:19|ASV|And without being weakened in faith he considered his own body now as good as dead (he being about a hundred years old), and the deadness of Sarah's womb;
4:19|Darby|and not being weak in faith, he considered not his own body  already become dead, being about a hundred years old, and the  deadening of Sarah's womb,
4:19|KJV|And being not weak in faith, he considered not his own body now dead, when he was about an hundred years old, neither yet the deadness of Sarah's womb:
4:19|WYC|And he was not made unsteadfast in the belief, neither he beheld his body then nigh dead [neither he beheld his body now nigh dead], when he was almost of an hundred years, nor the womb of Sarah nigh dead.
4:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他將近百歲的時候，雖然想到自己的身體如同已死，撒拉的生育也已斷絕，他的信還是不軟弱，
4:20|ASV|yet, looking unto the promise of God, he wavered not through unbelief, but waxed strong through faith, giving glory to God,
4:20|Darby|and hesitated not at the promise of God through unbelief;  but found strength in faith, giving glory to God;
4:20|KJV|He staggered not at the promise of God through unbelief; but was strong in faith, giving glory to God;
4:20|WYC|Also in the promise of God he doubted not with untrust; but he was comforted in belief, giving glory to God,
4:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|總沒有因不信而疑惑神的應許，反倒因信得著加力，將榮耀歸與神，
4:21|ASV|and being fully assured that what he had promised, he was able also to perform.
4:21|Darby|and being fully persuaded that what he has promised he is  able also to do;
4:21|KJV|And being fully persuaded that, what he had promised, he was able also to perform.
4:21|WYC|witting most fully that whatever things God hath promised, he is mighty also to do.
4:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|且滿心確信，神所應許的，祂也必能作成；
4:22|ASV|Wherefore also it was reckoned unto him for righteousness.
4:22|Darby|wherefore also it was reckoned to him as righteousness.
4:22|KJV|And therefore it was imputed to him for righteousness.
4:22|WYC|Therefore it was areckoned [reckoned] to him to rightwiseness.
4:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以這就算為他的義。
4:23|ASV|Now it was not written for his sake alone, that it was reckoned unto him;
4:23|Darby|Now it was not written on his account alone that it was  reckoned to him,
4:23|KJV|Now it was not written for his sake alone, that it was imputed to him;
4:23|WYC|And it is not written only for him, that it was areckoned [reckoned] to him to rightwiseness,
4:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|算為他的義這句話，不是單為他寫的，
4:24|ASV|but for our sake also, unto whom it shall be reckoned, who believe on him that raised Jesus our Lord from the dead,
4:24|Darby|but on ours also, to whom, believing on him who has raised  from among [the] dead Jesus our Lord,
4:24|KJV|But for us also, to whom it shall be imputed, if we believe on him that raised up Jesus our Lord from the dead;
4:24|WYC|but also for us, to whom it shall be areckoned [reckoned], that believe in him that raised our Lord Jesus Christ from death [from dead].
4:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|也是為我們將來得算為義的人，就是為我們這些信靠那使我們的主耶穌從死人中復活者的人寫的。
4:25<version name="ASV">who was delivered up for our trespasses, and was raised for our justification. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:25<version name="Darby">who has been delivered for our offences and has been raised  for our justification, it will be reckoned. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:25<version name="KJV">Who was delivered for our offences, and was raised again for our justification.</p><p /><br /></version>
4:25|WYC|Which was betaken for our sins, and rose again for our justifying.
4:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶穌被交給人是為我們的過犯，復活是為我們的稱義。
5:1|ASV|Being therefore justified by faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ;
5:1|Darby|Therefore having been justified on the principle of faith,  we have peace towards God through our Lord Jesus Christ;
5:1|KJV|Therefore being justified by faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ:
5:1|WYC|Therefore we, justified of faith, have we peace at God by our Lord Jesus Christ.
5:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，我們既本於信得稱義，就藉著我們的主耶穌基督，對神有了和平。
5:2|ASV|through whom also we have had our access by faith into this grace wherein we stand; and we rejoice in hope of the glory of God.
5:2|Darby|by whom we have also access by faith into this favour in  which we stand, and we boast in hope of the glory of God.
5:2|KJV|By whom also we have access by faith into this grace wherein we stand, and rejoice in hope of the glory of God.
5:2<version name="WYC">By whom we have nigh going to [By whom we have access, <i>or nigh going to</i>], by faith into this grace, in which we stand, and have glory in the hope of the glory of God's children.</version>
5:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們又藉著祂，因信得進入現在所站的這恩典中，並且因盼望神的榮耀而誇耀。
5:3|ASV|And not only so, but we also rejoice in our tribulations: knowing that tribulation worketh stedfastness;
5:3|Darby|And not only [that], but we also boast in tribulations,  knowing that tribulation works endurance;
5:3|KJV|And not only so, but we glory in tribulations also: knowing that tribulation worketh patience;
5:3|WYC|And not this only, but also we glory in tribulations, witting that tribulation worketh patience,
5:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不但如此，就是在患難中，我們也是誇耀，因為知道患難生忍耐，
5:4|ASV|and stedfastness, approvedness; and approvedness, hope:
5:4|Darby|and endurance, experience; and experience, hope;
5:4|KJV|And patience, experience; and experience, hope:
5:4|WYC|and patience proving, and proving hope.
5:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|忍耐生老練，老練生盼望，
5:5|ASV|and hope putteth not to shame; because the love of God hath been shed abroad in our hearts through the Holy Spirit which was given unto us.
5:5|Darby|and hope does not make ashamed, because the love of God is  shed abroad in our hearts by [the] Holy Spirit which has been  given to us:
5:5|KJV|And hope maketh not ashamed; because the love of God is shed abroad in our hearts by the Holy Ghost which is given unto us.
5:5|WYC|And hope confoundeth not, for the charity of God is spread abroad in our hearts by the Holy Ghost, that is given to us.
5:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|盼望不至於蒙羞；因為神的愛已經藉著所賜給我們的聖靈，澆灌在我們心裡。
5:6|ASV|For while we were yet weak, in due season Christ died for the ungodly.
5:6|Darby|for we being still without strength, in [the] due time  Christ has died for [the] ungodly.
5:6|KJV|For when we were yet without strength, in due time Christ died for the ungodly.
5:6|WYC|And while that we were frail [When we were yet sick] after the time, what died Christ for wicked men?
5:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因我們還軟弱的時候，基督就照所定的時期為不虔者死了。
5:7|ASV|For scarcely for a righteous man will one die: for peradventure for the good man some one would even dare to die.
5:7|Darby|For scarcely for [the] just [man] will one die, for perhaps  for [the] good [man] some one might also dare to die;
5:7|KJV|For scarcely for a righteous man will one die: yet peradventure for a good man some would even dare to die.
5:7|WYC|For scarcely dieth any man for the just man; and yet for a good man peradventure some man dare die.
5:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|為義人死，是少有的；為仁人死，或者有敢作的；
5:8|ASV|But God commendeth his own love toward us, in that, while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us.
5:8|Darby|but God commends *his* love to us, in that, we being still  sinners, Christ has died for us.
5:8|KJV|But God commendeth his love toward us, in that, while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us.
5:8|WYC|But God commendeth his charity in us; for if when we were yet sinners, after the time Christ was dead for us,
5:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|惟有基督在我們還作罪人的時候，為我們死，神就在此將祂自己的愛向我們顯明了。
5:9|ASV|Much more then, being now justified by his blood, shall we be saved from the wrath of God through him.
5:9|Darby|Much rather therefore, having been now justified in [the  power of] his blood, we shall be saved by him from wrath.
5:9|KJV|Much more then, being now justified by his blood, we shall be saved from wrath through him.
5:9|WYC|then much more now we justified in his blood, shall be safe from wrath by him.
5:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|現在我們既因祂的血得稱義，就更要藉著祂得救脫離忿怒。
5:10|ASV|For if, while we were enemies, we were reconciled to God through the death of his Son, much more, being reconciled, shall we be saved by his life;
5:10|Darby|For if, being enemies, we have been reconciled to God  through the death of his Son, much rather, having been  reconciled, we shall be saved in [the power of] his life.
5:10|KJV|For if, when we were enemies, we were reconciled to God by the death of his Son, much more, being reconciled, we shall be saved by his life.
5:10|WYC|For if when we were enemies, we be reconciled to God by the death of his Son, much more we reconciled shall be safe in the life of him.
5:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們作仇敵的時候，且藉著神兒子的死得與神和好，既已和好，就更要在祂的生命裡得救了。
5:11|ASV|and not only so, but we also rejoice in God through our Lord Jesus Christ, through whom we have now received the reconciliation.
5:11|Darby|And not only [that], but [we are] making our boast in God,  through our Lord Jesus Christ, through whom now we have  received the reconciliation.
5:11|KJV|And not only so, but we also joy in God through our Lord Jesus Christ, by whom we have now received the atonement.
5:11<version name="WYC">And not only this, but also we glory in God, by our Lord Jesus Christ, by whom we have received now reconciling [by whom we have received now reconciling, <i>or according</i>].</version>
5:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不但如此，我們現今既藉著我們的主耶穌基督，得與神和好，也就要藉著祂，在神裡面誇耀著，在祂的生命裡得救了。
5:12|ASV|Therefore, as through one man sin entered into the world, and death through sin; and so death passed unto all men, for that all sinned:--
5:12|Darby|For this [cause], even as by one man sin entered into the  world, and by sin death; and thus death passed upon all men,  for that all have sinned:
5:12|KJV|Wherefore, as by one man sin entered into the world, and death by sin; and so death passed upon all men, for that all have sinned:
5:12<version name="WYC">Therefore as by one man sin entered into this world [sin entered into the world], and by sin death, and so death passed forth into all men, in which <i>man</i> all men sinned.</version>
5:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這就如罪是藉著一人入了世界，死又是藉著罪來的，於是死就遍及眾人，因為眾人都犯了罪。
5:13|ASV|for until the law sin was in the world; but sin is not imputed when there is no law.
5:13|Darby|(for until law sin was in [the] world; but sin is not put  to account when there is no law;
5:13|KJV|(For until the law sin was in the world: but sin is not imputed when there is no law.
5:13|WYC|For unto the law [Soothly till to the law] sin was in the world; but sin was not reckoned, when [the] law was not.
5:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|沒有律法之先，罪已經在世上；但沒有律法，罪也不算在賬上。
5:14|ASV|Nevertheless death reigned from Adam until Moses, even over them that had not sinned after the likeness of Adam's transgression, who is a figure of him that was to come.
5:14|Darby|but death reigned from Adam until Moses, even upon those  who had not sinned in the likeness of Adam's transgression, who  is [the] figure of him to come.
5:14|KJV|Nevertheless death reigned from Adam to Moses, even over them that had not sinned after the similitude of Adam's transgression, who is the figure of him that was to come.
5:14<version name="WYC">But death reigned from Adam unto Moses [But death reigned from Adam till to Moses], also into them that sinned not in likeness of the trespassing of Adam, the which is likeness of <i>Christ</i> to coming [the which is form, <i>or likeness</i>, of <i>one</i> to come].</version>
5:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而從亞當到摩西，死就作了王，連那些不照亞當過犯樣式犯罪的，也在牠的權下；亞當乃是那以後要來者的豫像。
5:15|ASV|But not as the trespass, so also is the free gift. For if by the trespass of the one the many died, much more did the grace of God, and the gift by the grace of the one man, Jesus Christ, abound unto the many.
5:15|Darby|But [shall] not the act of favour [be] as the offence? For  if by the offence of one the many have died, much rather has  the grace of God, and the free gift in grace, which [is] by the  one man Jesus Christ, abounded unto the many.
5:15|KJV|But not as the offence, so also is the free gift. For if through the offence of one many be dead, much more the grace of God, and the gift by grace, which is by one man, Jesus Christ, hath abounded unto many.
5:15<version name="WYC">But not as [the] guilt, so the gift; for if through the guilt of one many be dead <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21080a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>, much more the grace of God and the gift in the grace of one man Jesus Christ hath abounded into many men.</version>
5:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只是過犯不如恩賜；若因一人的過犯，多人都死了，神的恩典，與耶穌基督一人恩典中白白的恩賜，就更加洋溢的臨到多人。
5:16|ASV|And not as through one that sinned, so is the gift: for the judgment came of one unto condemnation, but the free gift came of many trespasses unto justification.
5:16|Darby|And [shall] not as by one that has sinned [be] the gift?  For the judgment [was] of one to condemnation, but the act of  favour, of many offences unto justification.
5:16|KJV|And not as it was by one that sinned, so is the gift: for the judgment was by one to condemnation, but the free gift is of many offences unto justification.
5:16<version name="WYC">And not as by one sin, so by the gift; for the doom of one into condemnation, but the grace of many guilts into justification [for why soothly doom of one into condemnation, grace forsooth of many guilts, <i>or trespassings</i>, into justification].</version>
5:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且一人犯罪的結果，也不如白白的恩賜；因為審判是由於一次過犯而定罪，恩賜乃是由於許多過犯而稱義。
5:17|ASV|For if, by the trespass of the one, death reigned through the one; much more shall they that receive the abundance of grace and of the gift of righteousness reign in life through the one, even Jesus Christ.
5:17|Darby|For if by the offence of the one death reigned by the one,  much rather shall those who receive the abundance of grace, and  of the free gift of righteousness, reign in life by the one  Jesus Christ:)
5:17|KJV|For if by one man's offence death reigned by one; much more they which receive abundance of grace and of the gift of righteousness shall reign in life by one, Jesus Christ.)
5:17|WYC|For if in the guilt of one death reigned through one, much more men that take plenty of grace, and of giving, and of rightwiseness, shall reign in life by one Jesus Christ.
5:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若因一人的過犯，死就藉著這一人作了王，那些受洋溢之恩，並洋溢之義恩賜的，就更要藉著耶穌基督一人，在生命中作王了。
5:18|ASV|So then as through one trespass the judgment came unto all men to condemnation; even so through one act of righteousness the free gift came unto all men to justification of life.
5:18|Darby|so then as [it was] by one offence towards all men to  condemnation, so by one righteousness towards all men for  justification of life.
5:18|KJV|Therefore as by the offence of one judgment came upon all men to condemnation; even so by the righteousness of one the free gift came upon all men unto justification of life.
5:18|WYC|Therefore as by the guilt of one into all men into condemnation, so [and] by the rightwiseness of one into all men into justifying of life.
5:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|如此說來，藉著一次的過犯，眾人都被定罪，照樣，藉著一次的義行，眾人也都被稱義得生命了。
5:19|ASV|For as through the one man's disobedience the many were made sinners, even so through the obedience of the one shall the many be made righteous.
5:19|Darby|For as indeed by the disobedience of the one man the many  have been constituted sinners, so also by the obedience of the  one the many will be constituted righteous.
5:19|KJV|For as by one man's disobedience many were made sinners, so by the obedience of one shall many be made righteous.
5:19|WYC|For as by unobedience of one man many be made sinners, so by the obedience of one many shall be [ordained] just.
5:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|藉著一人的悖逆，多人構成了罪人，照樣，藉著一人的順從，多人也要構成義的了。
5:20|ASV|And the law came in besides, that the trespass might abound; but where sin abounded, grace did abound more exceedingly:
5:20|Darby|But law came in, in order that the offence might abound;  but where sin abounded grace has overabounded,
5:20|KJV|Moreover the law entered, that the offence might abound. But where sin abounded, grace did much more abound:
5:20<version name="WYC">And the law entered, that guilt should be plenteous; but where guilt was plenteous, grace was more plenteous [grace abounded, <i>or was plenteous</i>].</version>
5:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|律法插進來，是叫過犯增多，只是罪在那裡增多，恩典就更洋溢了，
5:21<version name="ASV">that, as sin reigned in death, even so might grace reign through righteousness unto eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:21<version name="Darby">in order that, even as sin has reigned in [the power of]  death, so also grace might reign through righteousness to  eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:21<version name="KJV">That as sin hath reigned unto death, even so might grace reign through righteousness unto eternal life by Jesus Christ our Lord.</p><p /><br /></version>
5:21|WYC|That as sin reigned into death, so [and] grace reign by rightwiseness into everlasting life, by Jesus Christ our Lord.
5:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|使罪怎樣在死中作王，恩典也照樣藉著義作王，叫人藉著我們的主耶穌基督得永遠的生命。
6:1|ASV|What shall we say then? Shall we continue in sin, that grace may abound?
6:1|Darby|What then shall we say? Should we continue in sin that grace  may abound?
6:1|KJV|What shall we say then? Shall we continue in sin, that grace may abound?
6:1|WYC|Therefore what shall we say?  Shall we dwell in sin, that grace be plenteous?
6:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我們可說甚麼？我們可以仍留在罪中，叫恩典增多麼？
6:2|ASV|God forbid. We who died to sin, how shall we any longer live therein?
6:2|Darby|Far be the thought. We who have died to sin, how shall we  still live in it?
6:2|KJV|God forbid. How shall we, that are dead to sin, live any longer therein?
6:2|WYC|God forbid [Far be it].  For how shall we that be dead to sin, live yet therein?
6:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|絕對不可！我們這向罪死了的人，豈可仍在罪中活著？
6:3|ASV|Or are ye ignorant that all we who were baptized into Christ Jesus were baptized into his death?
6:3|Darby|Are you ignorant that we, as many as have been baptised unto  Christ Jesus, have been baptised unto his death?
6:3|KJV|Know ye not, that so many of us as were baptized into Jesus Christ were baptized into his death?
6:3|WYC|Whether, brethren, ye know not, that whichever we be baptized in Christ Jesus, we be baptized in his death?
6:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|豈不知我們這浸入基督耶穌的人，是浸入祂的死麼？
6:4|ASV|We were buried therefore with him through baptism unto death: that like as Christ was raised from the dead through the glory of the Father, so we also might walk in newness of life.
6:4|Darby|We have been buried therefore with him by baptism unto  death, in order that, even as Christ has been raised up from  among [the] dead by the glory of the Father, so *we* also  should walk in newness of life.
6:4|KJV|Therefore we are buried with him by baptism into death: that like as Christ was raised up from the dead by the glory of the Father, even so we also should walk in newness of life.
6:4|WYC|For we be together buried with him by baptism into death; that as Christ arose from death [that as Christ rose from dead] by the glory of the Father, so [and] walk we in a newness of life.
6:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我們藉著浸入死，和祂一同埋葬，好叫我們在生命的新樣中生活行動，像基督藉著父的榮耀，從死人中復活一樣。
6:5|ASV|For if we have become united with him in the likeness of his death, we shall be also in the likeness of his resurrection;
6:5|Darby|For if we are become identified with [him] in the likeness  of his death, so also we shall be of [his] resurrection;
6:5|KJV|For if we have been planted together in the likeness of his death, we shall be also in the likeness of his resurrection:
6:5|WYC|For if we planted together be made to the likeness of his death, also we shall be of the likeness of his rising again;
6:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們若在祂死的樣式裡與祂聯合生長，也必要在祂復活的樣式裡與祂聯合生長；
6:6|ASV|knowing this, that our old man was crucified with him, that the body of sin might be done away, that so we should no longer be in bondage to sin;
6:6|Darby|knowing this, that our old man has been crucified with  [him], that the body of sin might be annulled, that we should  no longer serve sin.
6:6|KJV|Knowing this, that our old man is crucified with him, that the body of sin might be destroyed, that henceforth we should not serve sin.
6:6|WYC|witting this thing, that our old man is crucified together, that the body of sin be destroyed, that we serve no more to sin.
6:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|知道我們的舊人已經與祂同釘十字架，使罪的身體失效，叫我們不再作罪的奴僕，
6:7|ASV|for he that hath died is justified from sin.
6:7|Darby|For he that has died is justified from sin.
6:7|KJV|For he that is dead is freed from sin.
6:7<version name="WYC">For he that is dead [<i>to sin</i>], is justified from sin.</version>
6:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為已死的人，是已經從罪開釋了。
6:8|ASV|But if we died with Christ, we believe that we shall also live with him;
6:8|Darby|Now if we have died with Christ, we believe that we shall  also live with him,
6:8|KJV|Now if we be dead with Christ, we believe that we shall also live with him:
6:8|WYC|And if we be dead with Christ, we believe that also we shall live together with him;
6:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們若與基督同死，就信也必與祂同活，
6:9|ASV|knowing that Christ being raised from the dead dieth no more; death no more hath dominion over him.
6:9|Darby|knowing that Christ having been raised up from among [the]  dead dies no more: death has dominion over him no more.
6:9|KJV|Knowing that Christ being raised from the dead dieth no more; death hath no more dominion over him.
6:9|WYC|witting that Christ, rising again from death [rising again from dead], now dieth not, death shall no more have lordship on him.
6:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|知道基督既從死人中復活，就不再死，死也不再作主管轄祂了。
6:10|ASV|For the death that he died, he died unto sin once: but the life that he liveth, he liveth unto God.
6:10|Darby|For in that he has died, he has died to sin once for all;  but in that he lives, he lives to God.
6:10|KJV|For in that he died, he died unto sin once: but in that he liveth, he liveth unto God.
6:10|WYC|For that he was dead to sin, he was dead once; but that he liveth, he liveth to God.
6:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為祂死，是一次永遠的向罪死了；祂活，是向神活著。
6:11|ASV|Even so reckon ye also yourselves to be dead unto sin, but alive unto God in Christ Jesus.
6:11|Darby|So also *ye*, reckon yourselves dead to sin and alive to  God in Christ Jesus.
6:11|KJV|Likewise reckon ye also yourselves to be dead indeed unto sin, but alive unto God through Jesus Christ our Lord.
6:11|WYC|So [and] ye deem yourselves to be dead [soothly] to sin, but living to God in Jesus Christ our Lord.
6:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，你們在基督耶穌裡，向罪也當算自己是死的，向神卻當算自己是活的。
6:12|ASV|Let not sin therefore reign in your mortal body, that ye should obey the lusts thereof:
6:12|Darby|Let not sin therefore reign in your mortal body to obey its  lusts.
6:12|KJV|Let not sin therefore reign in your mortal body, that ye should obey it in the lusts thereof.
6:12|WYC|Therefore reign not sin in your deadly body, that ye obey to his covetings.
6:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以不要讓罪在你們必死的身體裡作王，使你們順從身體的私慾，
6:13|ASV|neither present your members unto sin as instruments of unrighteousness; but present yourselves unto God, as alive from the dead, and your members as instruments of righteousness unto God.
6:13|Darby|Neither yield your members instruments of unrighteousness  to sin, but yield yourselves to God as alive from among [the]  dead, and your members instruments of righteousness to God.
6:13|KJV|Neither yield ye your members as instruments of unrighteousness unto sin: but yield yourselves unto God, as those that are alive from the dead, and your members as instruments of righteousness unto God.
6:13|WYC|Neither give ye your members arms of wickedness to sin, but give ye yourselves to God, as they that live of dead men, and your members arms of rightwiseness to God.
6:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|也不要將你們的肢體獻給罪作不義的兵器；倒要像從死人中活過來的人，將自己獻給神，並將你們的肢體獻給神作義的兵器。
6:14|ASV|For sin shall not have dominion over you: for ye are not under law, but under grace.
6:14|Darby|For sin shall not have dominion over *you*, for ye are not  under law but under grace.
6:14|KJV|For sin shall not have dominion over you: for ye are not under the law, but under grace.
6:14|WYC|For sin shall not have lordship over you; for ye be not under the law, but under grace.
6:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|罪必不能作主管轄你們，因你們不在律法之下，乃在恩典之下。
6:15|ASV|What then? shall we sin, because we are not under law, but under grace? God forbid.
6:15|Darby|What then? should we sin because we are not under law but  under grace? Far be the thought.
6:15|KJV|What then? shall we sin, because we are not under the law, but under grace? God forbid.
6:15|WYC|What therefore?  Shall we do sin [Shall we sin], for we be not under the law, but under grace?  God forbid [Far be it].
6:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這卻怎麼樣？因我們不在律法之下，乃在恩典之下，就可以犯罪麼？絕對不可！
6:16|ASV|Know ye not, that to whom ye present yourselves as servants unto obedience, his servants ye are whom ye obey; whether of sin unto death, or of obedience unto righteousness?
6:16|Darby|Know ye not that to whom ye yield yourselves bondmen for  obedience, ye are bondmen to him whom ye obey, whether of sin  unto death, or of obedience unto righteousness?
6:16|KJV|Know ye not, that to whom ye yield yourselves servants to obey, his servants ye are to whom ye obey; whether of sin unto death, or of obedience unto righteousness?
6:16<version name="WYC">Know ye not, that to whom ye give your<i>selves</i> servants to obey to, ye be servants of that thing, to which ye have obeyed [Know ye not, for to whom ye give you servants to obey, ye be servants of that thing, to whom ye have obeyed], either of sin to death, either of obedience to rightwiseness?</version>
6:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|豈不曉得你們將自己獻給誰作奴僕，以至於順從，就作了你們所順從者的奴僕麼？或作罪的奴僕，以至於死，或作順從的奴僕，以至於義。
6:17|ASV|But thanks be to God, that, whereas ye were servants of sin, ye became obedient from the heart to that form of teaching whereunto ye were delivered;
6:17|Darby|But thanks [be] to God, that ye were bondmen of sin, but  have obeyed from the heart the form of teaching into which ye  were instructed.
6:17|KJV|But God be thanked, that ye were the servants of sin, but ye have obeyed from the heart that form of doctrine which was delivered you.
6:17|WYC|But I thank God, that ye were servants of sin; but ye have obeyed of heart into that form of teaching, in which ye be betaken.
6:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|感謝神，你們從前雖然作罪的奴僕，現今卻從心裡順從了你們被交於其中之教訓的規模。
6:18|ASV|and being made free from sin, ye became servants of righteousness.
6:18|Darby|Now, having got your freedom from sin, ye have become  bondmen to righteousness.
6:18|KJV|Being then made free from sin, ye became the servants of righteousness.
6:18|WYC|And ye delivered from sin, be made servants of rightwiseness.
6:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們既從罪裡得了釋放，就作了義的奴僕。
6:19|ASV|I speak after the manner of men because of the infirmity of your flesh: for as ye presented your members as servants to uncleanness and to iniquity unto iniquity, even so now present your members  as servants to righteousness unto sanctification.
6:19|Darby|I speak humanly on account of the weakness of your flesh.  For even as ye have yielded your members in bondage to  uncleanness and to lawlessness unto lawlessness, so now yield  your members in bondage to righteousness unto holiness.
6:19|KJV|I speak after the manner of men because of the infirmity of your flesh: for as ye have yielded your members servants to uncleanness and to iniquity unto iniquity; even so now yield your members servants to righteousness unto holiness.
6:19<version name="WYC">I say that thing that is of man, for the unsteadfastness of your flesh [for the infirmity, <i>or unstableness</i>, of your flesh].  But as ye have given your members to serve to uncleanness, and to wickedness into wickedness, so now give ye your members to serve to rightwiseness into holiness.</version>
6:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我因你們肉體的軟弱，就照著人的常情說，你們從前怎樣將肢體獻給不潔不法作奴僕，以至於不法，現今也要照樣將肢體獻給義作奴僕，以至於聖別。
6:20|ASV|For when ye were servants of sin, ye were free in regard of righteousness.
6:20|Darby|For when ye were bondmen of sin ye were free from  righteousness.
6:20|KJV|For when ye were the servants of sin, ye were free from righteousness.
6:20|WYC|For when ye were servants of sin, ye were free of rightwiseness.
6:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為你們作罪之奴僕的時候，就不受義的約束。
6:21|ASV|What fruit then had ye at that time in the things whereof ye are now ashamed? for the end of those things is death.
6:21|Darby|What fruit therefore had ye *then* in the things of which  ye are *now* ashamed? for the end of *them* [is] death.
6:21|KJV|What fruit had ye then in those things whereof ye are now ashamed? for the end of those things is death.
6:21|WYC|Therefore what fruit had ye then in those things, in which ye shame now?  For the end of them is death.
6:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時你們有甚麼果子？不過是你們現今所看為羞恥的事，那些事的結局就是死。
6:22|ASV|But now being made free from sin and become servants to God, ye have your fruit unto sanctification, and the end eternal life.
6:22|Darby|But *now*, having got your freedom from sin, and having  become bondmen to God, ye have your fruit unto holiness, and  the end eternal life.
6:22|KJV|But now being made free from sin, and become servants to God, ye have your fruit unto holiness, and the end everlasting life.
6:22|WYC|But now ye delivered from sin, and made servants to God, have your fruit into holiness, and the end everlasting life.
6:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但現今你們既從罪裡得了釋放，作了神的奴僕，就有聖別的果子，結局就是永遠的生命。
6:23<version name="ASV">For the wages of sin is death; but the free gift of God is eternal life in Christ Jesus our Lord. </p><p /><br /></version>
6:23<version name="Darby">For the wages of sin [is] death; but the act of favour of  God, eternal life in Christ Jesus our Lord. </p><p /><br /></version>
6:23<version name="KJV">For the wages of sin is death; but the gift of God is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p><p /><br /></version>
6:23<version name="WYC">For the wages of sin <i>is</i> death; the grace of God <i>is</i> everlasting life in Christ Jesus our Lord.</version>
6:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為罪的工價乃是死，惟有神的恩賜，在我們的主基督耶穌裡，乃是永遠的生命。
7:1|ASV|Or are ye ignorant, brethren (for I speak to men who know the law), that the law hath dominion over a man for so long time as he liveth?
7:1|Darby|Are ye ignorant, brethren, (for I speak to those knowing  law,) that law rules over a man as long as he lives?
7:1|KJV|Know ye not, brethren, (for I speak to them that know the law,) how that the law hath dominion over a man as long as he liveth?
7:1|WYC|Brethren, whether ye know not; for I speak to men that know the law; for the law hath lordship in a man, as long time as he liveth?
7:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，我現在對明白律法的人說，你們豈不知律法作主管轄人，是在他活著的時候麼？
7:2|ASV|For the woman that hath a husband is bound by law to the husband while he liveth; but if the husband die, she is discharged from the law of the husband.
7:2|Darby|For the married woman is bound by law to her husband so long  as he is alive; but if the husband should die, she is clear  from the law of the husband:
7:2|KJV|For the woman which hath an husband is bound by the law to her husband so long as he liveth; but if the husband be dead, she is loosed from the law of her husband.
7:2<version name="WYC">For that woman that is under an husband, is bound to the law, while the husband liveth; but if her husband is dead, she is delivered from the law of the husband [soothly if her husband be dead, she is delivered, <i>or</i> <i>unbound</i>, from the law of the husband].</version>
7:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|女人有了丈夫，丈夫還活著，就受律法約束，歸與丈夫；丈夫若死了，就脫離了丈夫的律法。
7:3|ASV|So then if, while the husband liveth, she be joined to another man, she shall be called an adulteress: but if the husband die, she is free from the law, so that she is no adulteress, though she be joined to another man.
7:3|Darby|so then, the husband being alive, she shall be called an  adulteress if she be to another man; but if the husband should  die, she is free from the law, so as not to be an adulteress,  though she be to another man.
7:3|KJV|So then if, while her husband liveth, she be married to another man, she shall be called an adulteress: but if her husband be dead, she is free from that law; so that she is no adulteress, though she be married to another man.
7:3|WYC|Therefore she shall be called adulteress, if she be with another man, while the husband liveth [Therefore living the man, she shall be called adulteress, if she be with another man]; but if her husband is dead [forsooth if her husband be dead], she is delivered from the law of the husband, that she be not adulteress, if she be with another man.
7:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，丈夫活著，她若歸與別的男人，便叫淫婦；丈夫若死了，她就脫離了那律法，雖然歸與別的男人，也不是淫婦。
7:4|ASV|Wherefore, my brethren, ye also were made dead to the law through the body of Christ; that ye should be joined to another, even to him who was raised from the dead, that we might bring forth fruit unto God.
7:4|Darby|So that, my brethren, *ye* also have been made dead to the  law by the body of the Christ, to be to another, who has been  raised up from among [the] dead, in order that we might bear  fruit to God.
7:4|KJV|Wherefore, my brethren, ye also are become dead to the law by the body of Christ; that ye should be married to another, even to him who is raised from the dead, that we should bring forth fruit unto God.
7:4<version name="WYC">And so, my brethren, ye be made dead to the law by the body of Christ, that ye be of another, that rose again from death, that ye bear fruit to God. <woj>Therefore, my brethren, and ye be made dead to the law by the body of Christ, that ye be another's, that rose from dead, that we bear fruit to God.</woj></version>
7:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的弟兄們，這樣說來，你們藉著基督的身體，向著律法也已經是死的了，叫你們歸與別人，就是歸與那從死人中復活的，使我們結果子給神。
7:5|ASV|For when we were in the flesh, the sinful passions, which were through the law, wrought in our members to bring forth fruit unto death.
7:5|Darby|For when we were in the flesh the passions of sins, which  [were] by the law, wrought in our members to bring forth fruit  to death;
7:5|KJV|For when we were in the flesh, the motions of sins, which were by the law, did work in our members to bring forth fruit unto death.
7:5|WYC|For when we were in flesh, passions of sins, that were by the law, wrought in our members, to bear fruit to death.
7:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們在肉體中的時候，那藉著律法活動的罪慾，就在我們肢體中發動，以致結果子給死。
7:6|ASV|But now we have been discharged from the law, having died to that wherein we were held; so that we serve in newness of the spirit, and not in oldness of the letter.
7:6|Darby|but now we are clear from the law, having died in that in  which we were held, so that we should serve in newness of  spirit, and not in oldness of letter.
7:6|KJV|But now we are delivered from the law, that being dead wherein we were held; that we should serve in newness of spirit, and not in the oldness of the letter.
7:6|WYC|But now we be unbound from the law of death, in which we were held [in which we were holden], so that we serve in newness of spirit, and not in oldness of letter.
7:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但我們既然在捆我們的律法上死了，現今就脫離了律法，叫我們在靈的新樣裡服事，不在字句的舊樣裡。
7:7|ASV|What shall we say then? Is the law sin? God forbid. Howbeit, I had not known sin, except through the law: for I had not known coveting, except the law had said, Thou shalt not covet:
7:7|Darby|What shall we say then? [is] the law sin? Far be the  thought. But I had not known sin, unless by law: for I had not  had conscience also of lust unless the law had said, Thou shalt  not lust;
7:7|KJV|What shall we say then? Is the law sin? God forbid. Nay, I had not known sin, but by the law: for I had not known lust, except the law had said, Thou shalt not covet.
7:7|WYC|What therefore shall we say?  The law is sin?  God forbid [Far be it].  But I knew not sin, but by [the] law; for I knew not that coveting was sin, but for the law said, Thou shalt not covet.
7:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我們可說甚麼？律法是罪麼？絕對不是！只是非藉律法，我就不知何為罪；非律法說，“不可起貪心，”我就不知何為貪心。
7:8|ASV|but sin, finding occasion, wrought in me through the commandment all manner of coveting: for apart from the law sin is dead.
7:8|Darby|but sin, getting a point of attack by the commandment,  wrought in me every lust; for without law sin [was] dead.
7:8|KJV|But sin, taking occasion by the commandment, wrought in me all manner of concupiscence. For without the law sin was dead.
7:8<version name="WYC">And through occasion taken, sin by the commandment hath wrought in me all covetousness [sin by the commandment hath wrought in me all coveting, <i>or covetousness</i>]; for without the law, sin was dead.</version>
7:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而罪藉著誡命得著機會，叫諸般的貪心在我裡面發動，因為沒有律法，罪是死的。
7:9|ASV|And I was alive apart from the law once: but when the commandment came, sin revived, and I died;
7:9|Darby|But *I* was alive without law once; but the commandment  having come, sin revived, but *I* died.
7:9|KJV|For I was alive without the law once: but when the commandment came, sin revived, and I died.
7:9|WYC|And I lived [Forsooth I lived] without the law sometime; but when the commandment was come, sin lived again.  But I was dead,
7:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我以前沒有律法是活著的，但是誡命來到，罪又活了，我就死了。
7:10|ASV|and the commandment, which was unto life, this I found to be unto death:
7:10|Darby|And the commandment, which [was] for life, was found, [as]  to me, itself [to be] unto death:
7:10|KJV|And the commandment, which was ordained to life, I found to be unto death.
7:10|WYC|and this commandment [and the commandment] that was to life, was found to me, to be to death.
7:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那本來叫人得生命的誡命，反倒成了叫我死的；
7:11|ASV|for sin, finding occasion, through the commandment beguiled me, and through it slew me.
7:11|Darby|for sin, getting a point of attack by the commandment,  deceived me, and by it slew [me].
7:11|KJV|For sin, taking occasion by the commandment, deceived me, and by it slew me.
7:11<version name="WYC">For sin, through occasion taken by the commandment, deceived me, and by that it slew <i>me</i> [and by it slew <i>me</i>].</version>
7:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為罪藉著誡命得著機會，誘騙了我，並且藉著誡命殺了我。
7:12|ASV|So that the law is holy, and the commandment holy, and righteous, and good.
7:12|Darby|So that the law indeed [is] holy, and the commandment holy,  and just, and good.
7:12|KJV|Wherefore the law is holy, and the commandment holy, and just, and good.
7:12<version name="WYC">Therefore the law <i>is</i> holy, and the commandment <i>is</i> holy, and just, and good.</version>
7:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣看來，律法是聖的，誡命也是聖的、義的並善的。
7:13|ASV|Did then that which is good become death unto me? God forbid. But sin, that it might be shown to be sin, by working death to me through that which is good; --that through the commandment sin might become exceeding sinful.
7:13|Darby|Did then that which is good become death to me? Far be the  thought. But sin, that it might appear sin, working death to me  by that which is good; in order that sin by the commandment  might become exceeding sinful.
7:13|KJV|Was then that which is good made death unto me? God forbid. But sin, that it might appear sin, working death in me by that which is good; that sin by the commandment might become exceeding sinful.
7:13<version name="WYC">Is then that thing that is good, made death to me?  God forbid [Far be it].  But sin, that it seem sin, through good thing wrought death to me, that me sin over manner through the commandment [But sin, that it appear sin, through good thing wrought death to me, that there be made sin sinning over manner, <i>or</i> <i>measure</i>, by commandment].</version>
7:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，那善的是叫我死麼？絕對不是！然而罪為要顯出真是罪，就藉著那善的叫我死，使罪藉著誡命成為極其罪惡的。
7:14|ASV|For we know that the law is spiritual: but I am carnal, sold under sin.
7:14|Darby|For we know that the law is spiritual: but *I* am fleshly,  sold under sin.
7:14|KJV|For we know that the law is spiritual: but I am carnal, sold under sin.
7:14|WYC|And we know, that the law is spiritual; but I am fleshly, sold under sin.
7:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們原曉得律法是屬靈的，但我是屬肉的，是已經賣給罪了。
7:15|ASV|For that which I do I know not: for not what I would, that do I practise; but what I hate, that I do.
7:15|Darby|For that which I do, I do not own: for not what I will,  this I do; but what I hate, this I practise.
7:15|KJV|For that which I do I allow not: for what I would, that do I not; but what I hate, that do I.
7:15|WYC|For I understand not that that I work; for I do not the good thing that I will, but I do that evil thing that I hate.
7:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我所行出來的，我不認可；我所願意的，我並不作；我所恨惡的，我倒去作。
7:16|ASV|But if what I would not, that I do, I consent unto the law that it is good.
7:16|Darby|But if what I do not will, this I practise, I consent to  the law that [it is] right.
7:16|KJV|If then I do that which I would not, I consent unto the law that it is good.
7:16|WYC|And if I do that thing that I will not, I consent to the law, that it is good.
7:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若我所作的，是我所不願意的，我就同意律法是善的。
7:17|ASV|So now it is no more I that do it, but sin which dwelleth in me.
7:17|Darby|Now then [it is] no longer *I* [that] do it, but the sin  that dwells in me.
7:17|KJV|Now then it is no more I that do it, but sin that dwelleth in me.
7:17|WYC|But now I work not it now, but the sin that dwelleth in me.
7:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|其實，不是我行出來的，乃是住在我裡面的罪行出來的。
7:18|ASV|For I know that in me, that is, in my flesh, dwelleth no good thing: for to will is present with me, but to do that which is good is not.
7:18|Darby|For I know that in me, that is, in my flesh, good does not  dwell: for to will is there with me, but to do right [I find]  not.
7:18|KJV|For I know that in me (that is, in my flesh,) dwelleth no good thing: for to will is present with me; but how to perform that which is good I find not.
7:18<version name="WYC">But I know, that in me, that is, in my flesh, dwelleth no good; for will lieth to me (for will lieth <i>before</i> me), but I find not to perform good thing [truly to perform good thing I find not].</version>
7:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我知道住在我裡面，就是我肉體之中，並沒有善，因為立志為善由得我，只是行出來由不得我。
7:19|ASV|For the good which I would I do not: but the evil which I would not, that I practise.
7:19|Darby|For I do not practise the good that I will; but the evil I  do not will, that I do.
7:19|KJV|For the good that I would I do not: but the evil which I would not, that I do.
7:19|WYC|For I do not that good thing that I will, but I do that evil thing that I will not.
7:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我所願意的善，我反不作；我所不願意的惡，我倒去作。
7:20|ASV|But if what I would not, that I do, it is no more I that do it, but sin which dwelleth in me.
7:20|Darby|But if what *I* do not will, this I practise, [it is] no  longer *I* [that] do it, but the sin that dwells in me.
7:20|KJV|Now if I do that I would not, it is no more I that do it, but sin that dwelleth in me.
7:20<version name="WYC">And if I do that <i>evil </i>thing that I will not [Soothly if I do that thing that I will not], I work not it, but the sin that dwelleth in me.</version>
7:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若我去作所不願意的，就不是我行出來的，乃是住在我裡面的罪行出來的。
7:21|ASV|I find then the law, that, to me who would do good, evil is present.
7:21|Darby|I find then the law upon *me* who will to practise what is  right, that with *me* evil is there.
7:21|KJV|I find then a law, that, when I would do good, evil is present with me.
7:21<version name="WYC">Therefore I find the law to me willing to do good thing [Therefore I find a law to me willing to do good thing], for evil thing lieth to me (for evil thing lieth <i>before</i> me).</version>
7:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是我發現那律與我這願意為善的人同在，就是那惡與我同在。
7:22|ASV|For I delight in the law of God after the inward man:
7:22|Darby|For I delight in the law of God according to the inward  man:
7:22|KJV|For I delight in the law of God after the inward man:
7:22|WYC|For I delight together to the law of God, after the inner man.
7:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為按著裡面的人，我是喜歡神的律，
7:23|ASV|but I see a different law in my members, warring against the law of my mind, and bringing me into captivity under the law of sin which is in my members.
7:23|Darby|but I see another law in my members, warring in opposition  to the law of my mind, and bringing me into captivity to the  law of sin which exists in my members.
7:23|KJV|But I see another law in my members, warring against the law of my mind, and bringing me into captivity to the law of sin which is in my members.
7:23|WYC|But I see another law in my members, fighting against the law of my soul, and making me captive in the law of sin, that is in my members.
7:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但我看出我肢體中另有個律，和我心思的律交戰，藉著那在我肢體中罪的律，把我擄去。
7:24|ASV|Wretched man that I am! who shall deliver me out of the body of this death?
7:24|Darby|O wretched man that I [am]! who shall deliver me out of  this body of death?
7:24|KJV|O wretched man that I am! who shall deliver me from the body of this death?
7:24<version name="WYC">I am an unhappy man [I <i>am</i> a woeful man]; who shall deliver me from the body of this sin?</version>
7:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我是個苦惱的人！誰要救我脫離那屬這死的身體？
7:25<version name="ASV">I thank God through Jesus Christ our Lord. So then I of myself with the mind, indeed, serve the law of God; but with the flesh the law of sin. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:25<version name="Darby">I thank God, through Jesus Christ our Lord. So then *I*  *myself* with the mind serve God's law; but with the flesh  sin's law. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:25<version name="KJV">I thank God through Jesus Christ our Lord. So then with the mind I myself serve the law of God; but with the flesh the law of sin.</p><p /><br /></version>
7:25|WYC|[Forsooth] The grace of God, by Jesus Christ our Lord.  Therefore I myself by the soul serve to the law of God; but by the flesh to the law of sin.
7:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|感謝神，藉著我們的主耶穌基督！這樣看來，我自己用心思服事神的律，卻用肉體服事罪的律。
8:1|ASV|There is therefore now no condemnation to them that are in Christ Jesus.
8:1|Darby|[There is] then now no condemnation to those in Christ  Jesus.
8:1|KJV|There is therefore now no condemnation to them which are in Christ Jesus, who walk not after the flesh, but after the Spirit.
8:1|WYC|Therefore now nothing of condemnation is to them that be in Christ Jesus, which wander not after the flesh.
8:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|如此，現今那些在基督耶穌裡的，就沒有定罪了。
8:2|ASV|For the law of the Spirit of life in Christ Jesus made me free from the law of sin and of death.
8:2|Darby|For the law of the Spirit of life in Christ Jesus has set me  free from the law of sin and of death.
8:2|KJV|For the law of the Spirit of life in Christ Jesus hath made me free from the law of sin and death.
8:2|WYC|For the law of the Spirit of life in Christ Jesus hath delivered me from the law of sin, and of death [hath delivered me from the law of sin, and death].
8:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為生命之靈的律，在基督耶穌裡已經釋放了我，使我脫離了罪與死的律。
8:3|ASV|For what the law could not do, in that it was weak through the flesh, God, sending his own Son in the likeness of sinful flesh and for sin, condemned sin in the flesh:
8:3|Darby|For what the law could not do, in that it was weak through  the flesh, God, having sent his own Son, in likeness of flesh  of sin, and for sin, has condemned sin in the flesh,
8:3|KJV|For what the law could not do, in that it was weak through the flesh, God sending his own Son in the likeness of sinful flesh, and for sin, condemned sin in the flesh:
8:3<version name="WYC">For that that was impossible to the law, in what thing it was frail by flesh, God sent his Son into the likeness of flesh of sin [in that thing it was sick, <i>or frail</i>, by flesh, God sending his Son into the likeness of flesh of sin], and of sin condemned sin in flesh;</version>
8:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|律法因肉體而軟弱，有所不能的，神，既在罪之肉體的樣式裡，並為著罪，差來了自己的兒子，就在肉體中定罪了罪，
8:4|ASV|that the ordinance of the law might be fulfilled in us, who walk not after the flesh, but after the Spirit.
8:4|Darby|in order that the righteous requirement of the law should be  fulfilled in us, who do not walk according to flesh but  according to Spirit.
8:4|KJV|That the righteousness of the law might be fulfilled in us, who walk not after the flesh, but after the Spirit.
8:4|WYC|that the justifying of the law were fulfilled in us, that go not after the flesh [that not after the flesh we wander], but after the Spirit.
8:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|使律法義的要求，成就在我們這不照著肉體，只照著靈而行的人身上。
8:5|ASV|For they that are after the flesh mind the things of the flesh; but they that are after the Spirit the things of the Spirit.
8:5|Darby|For they that are according to flesh mind the things of the  flesh; and they that are according to Spirit, the things of the  Spirit.
8:5|KJV|For they that are after the flesh do mind the things of the flesh; but they that are after the Spirit the things of the Spirit.
8:5|WYC|For they that be after the flesh, understand those things [savour those things] that be of the flesh; but they that be after the Spirit, feel those things that be of the Spirit.
8:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為照著肉體的人，思念肉體的事；照著靈的人，思念那靈的事。
8:6|ASV|For the mind of the flesh is death; but the mind of the Spirit is life and peace:
8:6|Darby|For the mind of the flesh [is] death; but the mind of the  Spirit life and peace.
8:6|KJV|For to be carnally minded is death; but to be spiritually minded is life and peace.
8:6<version name="WYC">For the prudence of flesh is death; but the prudence of Spirit <i>is </i>life and peace.</version>
8:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為心思置於肉體，就是死；心思置於靈，乃是生命平安。
8:7|ASV|because the mind of the flesh is enmity against God; for it is not subject to the law of God, neither indeed can it be:
8:7|Darby|Because the mind of the flesh is enmity against God: for it  is not subject to the law of God; for neither indeed can it be:
8:7|KJV|Because the carnal mind is enmity against God: for it is not subject to the law of God, neither indeed can be.
8:7<version name="WYC">For the wisdom of the flesh is enemy to God; for it is not subject to the law of God, for neither it may [soothly neither it may<i> be subject to the law</i>].</version>
8:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為置於肉體的心思，是與神為仇，因牠不服神的律法，也是不能服；
8:8|ASV|and they that are in the flesh cannot please God.
8:8|Darby|and they that are in flesh cannot please God.
8:8|KJV|So then they that are in the flesh cannot please God.
8:8|WYC|And they that be in flesh, be not able to please to God. [For they that be in flesh, may not please to God.]
8:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|而且在肉體裡的人，不能得神的喜悅。
8:9|ASV|But ye are not in the flesh but in the Spirit, if so be that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you. But if any man hath not the Spirit of Christ, he is none of his.
8:9|Darby|But *ye* are not in flesh but in Spirit, if indeed God's  Spirit dwell in you; but if any one has not [the] Spirit of  Christ *he* is not of him:
8:9|KJV|But ye are not in the flesh, but in the Spirit, if so be that the Spirit of God dwell in you. Now if any man have not the Spirit of Christ, he is none of his.
8:9|WYC|But ye be not in flesh, but in Spirit; if nevertheless the Spirit of God dwelleth in you [dwell in you].  But if any man hath not the Spirit of Christ, this is not his.
8:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但神的靈若住在你們裡面，你們就不在肉體裡，乃在靈裡了；然而人若沒有基督的靈，就不是屬基督的。
8:10|ASV|And if Christ is in you, the body is dead because of sin; but the spirit is life because of righteousness.
8:10|Darby|but if Christ be in you, the body is dead on account of  sin, but the Spirit life on account of righteousness.
8:10|KJV|And if Christ be in you, the body is dead because of sin; but the Spirit is life because of righteousness.
8:10|WYC|For if Christ is in you, the body is dead for sin [the body is dead from sin], but the Spirit liveth for justifying.
8:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但基督若在你們裡面，身體固然因罪是死的，靈卻因義是生命。
8:11|ASV|But if the Spirit of him that raised up Jesus from the dead dwelleth in you, he that raised up Christ Jesus from the dead shall give life also to your mortal bodies through his Spirit that dwelleth in you.
8:11|Darby|But if the Spirit of him that has raised up Jesus from  among [the] dead dwell in you, he that has raised up Christ  from among [the] dead shall quicken your mortal bodies also on  account of his Spirit which dwells in you.
8:11|KJV|But if the Spirit of him that raised up Jesus from the dead dwell in you, he that raised up Christ from the dead shall also quicken your mortal bodies by his Spirit that dwelleth in you.
8:11<version name="WYC">And if the Spirit of him that raised Jesus Christ from death dwelleth in you, he that raised Jesus Christ from death, shall quicken also your deadly bodies, for the Spirit of him that dwelleth in you. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21145a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
8:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而那叫耶穌從死人中復活者的靈，若住在你們裡面，那叫基督從死人中復活的，也必藉著祂住在你們裡面的靈，賜生命給你們必死的身體。
8:12|ASV|So then, brethren, we are debtors, not to the flesh, to live after the flesh:
8:12|Darby|So then, brethren, we are debtors, not to the flesh, to  live according to flesh;
8:12|KJV|Therefore, brethren, we are debtors, not to the flesh, to live after the flesh.
8:12|WYC|Therefore, brethren, we be debtors, not to the flesh, that we live after the flesh.
8:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，這樣，我們並不是欠肉體的債，去照肉體活著。
8:13|ASV|for if ye live after the flesh, ye must die; but if by the Spirit ye put to death the deeds of the body, ye shall live.
8:13|Darby|for if ye live according to flesh, ye are about to die; but  if, by the Spirit, ye put to death the deeds of the body, ye  shall live:
8:13|KJV|For if ye live after the flesh, ye shall die: but if ye through the Spirit do mortify the deeds of the body, ye shall live.
8:13|WYC|For if ye live after the flesh, ye shall die; but if ye by the Spirit [shall] slay the deeds of the flesh, ye shall live.
8:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為你們若照肉體活著，必要死；但你們若靠著那靈治死身體的行為，必要活著。
8:14|ASV|For as many as are led by the Spirit of God, these are sons of God.
8:14|Darby|for as many as are led by [the] Spirit of God, *these* are  sons of God.
8:14|KJV|For as many as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the sons of God.
8:14|WYC|For whoever be led by the Spirit of God, these be the sons of God.
8:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為凡被神的靈引導的，都是神的兒子。
8:15|ASV|For ye received not the spirit of bondage again unto fear; but ye received the spirit of adoption, whereby we cry, Abba, Father.
8:15|Darby|For ye have not received a spirit of bondage again for  fear, but ye have received a spirit of adoption, whereby we  cry, Abba, Father.
8:15|KJV|For ye have not received the spirit of bondage again to fear; but ye have received the Spirit of adoption, whereby we cry, Abba, Father.
8:15|WYC|For ye have not taken again the spirit of servage in dread, but ye have taken the Spirit of adoption of sons, in which we cry, Abba, Father.
8:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們所受的不是奴役的靈，仍舊害怕；所受的乃是兒子名分的靈，在這靈裡，我們呼叫：阿爸，父。
8:16|ASV|The Spirit himself beareth witness with our spirit, that we are children of God:
8:16|Darby|The Spirit itself bears witness with our spirit, that we  are children of God.
8:16|KJV|The Spirit itself beareth witness with our spirit, that we are the children of God:
8:16|WYC|And that Spirit yieldeth witnessing to our spirit, that we be the sons of God;
8:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那靈自己同我們的靈見證我們是神的兒女。
8:17|ASV|and if children, then heirs; heirs of God, and joint-heirs with Christ; if so be that we suffer with him, that we may be also glorified with him.
8:17|Darby|And if children, heirs also: heirs of God, and Christ's  joint heirs; if indeed we suffer with [him], that we may also  be glorified with [him].
8:17|KJV|And if children, then heirs; heirs of God, and joint-heirs with Christ; if so be that we suffer with him, that we may be also glorified together.
8:17|WYC|if sons, and heirs, heirs forsooth of God, and heirs together with Christ [forsooth if sons, and heirs, soothly heirs of God, truly even-heirs of Christ]; if nevertheless we suffer together, that also we be glorified together.
8:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|既是兒女，便是後嗣，就是神的後嗣，和基督同作後嗣，只要我們與祂一同受苦，好叫我們也與祂一同得榮耀。
8:18|ASV|For I reckon that the sufferings of this present time are not worthy to be compared with the glory which shall be revealed to us-ward.
8:18|Darby|For I reckon that the sufferings of this present time are  not worthy [to be compared] with the coming glory to be  revealed to us.
8:18|KJV|For I reckon that the sufferings of this present time are not worthy to be compared with the glory which shall be revealed in us.
8:18|WYC|And I deem, that the passions of this time be not worthy to the glory to coming [be not even worthy to the glory to come], that shall be showed in us.
8:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我算定今時的苦楚，不配與將來要顯於我們的榮耀相比。
8:19|ASV|For the earnest expectation of the creation waiteth for the revealing of the sons of God.
8:19|Darby|For the anxious looking out of the creature expects the  revelation of the sons of God:
8:19|KJV|For the earnest expectation of the creature waiteth for the manifestation of the sons of God.
8:19|WYC|For the abiding of creature abideth the showing of the sons of God.
8:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|受造之物正在專切期望著，熱切等待神的眾子顯示出來。
8:20|ASV|For the creation was subjected to vanity, not of its own will, but by reason of him who subjected it, in hope
8:20|Darby|for the creature has been made subject to vanity, not of  its will, but by reason of him who has subjected [the same], in  hope
8:20|KJV|For the creature was made subject to vanity, not willingly, but by reason of him who hath subjected the same in hope,
8:20|WYC|But the creature is subject to vanity, not willing(ly), but for him that made it subject in hope; [Soothly the creature is subject to vanity, not willing, but for him that subjected it in hope;]
8:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為受造之物服在虛空之下，不是自己願意的，乃是因那叫牠服的，
8:21|ASV|that the creation itself also shall be delivered from the bondage of corruption into the liberty of the glory of the children of God.
8:21|Darby|that the creature itself also shall be set free from the  bondage of corruption into the liberty of the glory of the  children of God.
8:21|KJV|Because the creature itself also shall be delivered from the bondage of corruption into the glorious liberty of the children of God.
8:21|WYC|for that creature [for and that creature] shall be delivered from servage of corruption into the liberty of the glory of the sons of God.
8:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|指望著受造之物自己，也要從敗壞的奴役得著釋放，得享神兒女之榮耀的自由。
8:22|ASV|For we know that the whole creation groaneth and travaileth in pain together until now.
8:22|Darby|For we know that the whole creation groans together and  travails in pain together until now.
8:22|KJV|For we know that the whole creation groaneth and travaileth in pain together until now.
8:22|WYC|And we know, that each creature sorroweth, and travaileth with pain till yet.
8:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們知道一切受造之物一同歎息，一同受生產之苦，直到如今。
8:23|ASV|And not only so, but ourselves also, who have the first-fruits of the Spirit, even we ourselves groan within ourselves, waiting for our adoption, to wit, the redemption of our body.
8:23|Darby|And not only [that], but even *we* ourselves, who have the  first-fruits of the Spirit, we also ourselves groan in  ourselves, awaiting adoption, [that is] the redemption of our  body.
8:23|KJV|And not only they, but ourselves also, which have the firstfruits of the Spirit, even we ourselves groan within ourselves, waiting for the adoption, to wit, the redemption of our body.
8:23|WYC|And not only it, but also we us selves [but and we ourselves], that have the first fruits of the Spirit, and we us selves sorrow within us [and we ourselves sorrow within us] for the adoption of God's sons, abiding the again-buying of our body.
8:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不但如此，就是我們這有那靈作初熟果子的，也是自己裡面歎息，熱切等待兒子的名分，就是我們的身體得贖。
8:24|ASV|For in hope were we saved: but hope that is seen is not hope: for who hopeth for that which he seeth?
8:24|Darby|For we have been saved in hope; but hope seen is not hope;  for what any one sees, why does he also hope?
8:24|KJV|For we are saved by hope: but hope that is seen is not hope: for what a man seeth, why doth he yet hope for?
8:24|WYC|But by hope we be made safe.  For hope that is seen, is not hope; for who hopeth that thing, that he seeth? [Soothly by hope we be made safe.  Forsooth the hope that is seen, is not hope; for why what hopeth a man that thing, that he seeth?]
8:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們是在盼望中得救的；只是所見的盼望不是盼望，誰還盼望他所見的？
8:25|ASV|But if we hope for that which we see not, then do we with patience wait for it.
8:25|Darby|But if what we see not we hope, we expect in patience.
8:25|KJV|But if we hope for that we see not, then do we with patience wait for it.
8:25|WYC|And if we hope that thing that we see not, we abide by patience.
8:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但我們若盼望所不見的，就必忍耐著熱切等待。
8:26|ASV|And in like manner the Spirit also helpeth our infirmity: for we know not how to pray as we ought; but the Spirit himself maketh intercession for us with groanings which cannot be uttered;
8:26|Darby|And in like manner the Spirit joins also its help to our  weakness; for we do not know what we should pray for as is  fitting, but the Spirit itself makes intercession with  groanings which cannot be uttered.
8:26|KJV|Likewise the Spirit also helpeth our infirmities: for we know not what we should pray for as we ought: but the Spirit itself maketh intercession for us with groanings which cannot be uttered.
8:26|WYC|And also the Spirit helpeth our infirmity; for what we shall pray, as it behooveth, we know not, but that Spirit asketh for us with sorrowings, that may not be told out [but that Spirit asketh for us with sorrowings, that be not able to be told out].
8:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|況且，那靈也照樣幫同擔負我們的軟弱；我們本不曉得當怎樣禱告，只是那靈親自用說不出來的歎息，為我們代求。
8:27|ASV|and he that searcheth the hearts knoweth what is the mind of the Spirit, because he maketh intercession for the saints according to the will of God.
8:27|Darby|But he who searches the hearts knows what [is] the mind of  the Spirit, because he intercedes for saints according to God.
8:27|KJV|And he that searcheth the hearts knoweth what is the mind of the Spirit, because he maketh intercession for the saints according to the will of God.
8:27<version name="WYC">For he that seeketh the hearts, knoweth what the Spirit desireth, for by God [for after God, <i>that is, at God's</i> <i>will</i>,] he asketh for holy men.</version>
8:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那鑒察人心的，曉得那靈的意思，因為祂是照著神為聖徒代求。
8:28|ASV|And we know that to them that love God all things work together for good, even to them that are called according to his purpose.
8:28|Darby|But we *do* know that all things work together for good to  those who love God, to those who are called according to  purpose.
8:28|KJV|And we know that all things work together for good to them that love God, to them who are the called according to his purpose.
8:28|WYC|And we know, that to men that love God, all things work together into good, to them that after purpose be called saints.
8:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|還有，我們曉得萬有都互相效力，叫愛神的人得益處，就是按祂旨意被召的人。
8:29|ASV|For whom he foreknew, he also foreordained to be conformed to the image of his Son, that he might be the firstborn among many brethren:
8:29|Darby|Because whom he has foreknown, he has also predestinated  [to be] conformed to the image of his Son, so that he should be  [the] firstborn among many brethren.
8:29|KJV|For whom he did foreknow, he also did predestinate to be conformed to the image of his Son, that he might be the firstborn among many brethren.
8:29|WYC|For those that he knew before [For why and whom he knew before], he before-ordained by grace to be made like to the image of his Son, that he be the first begotten among many brethren.
8:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神所豫知的人，祂也豫定他們模成神兒子的形像，使祂兒子在許多弟兄中作長子。
8:30|ASV|and whom he foreordained, them he also called: and whom he called, them he also justified: and whom he justified, them he also glorified.
8:30|Darby|But whom he has predestinated, these also he has called;  and whom he has called, these also he has justified; but whom  he has justified, these also he has glorified.
8:30|KJV|Moreover whom he did predestinate, them he also called: and whom he called, them he also justified: and whom he justified, them he also glorified.
8:30|WYC|And those that he before-ordained to bless, them he called; and whom he called, them he justified; and whom he justified, them he glorified. [Soothly whom he before-ordained to bless, and them he called; and whom he called, and them he justified; soothly whom he justified, and them he glorified.]
8:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂所豫定的人，又召他們來；所召來的人，又稱他們為義；所稱為義的人，又叫他們得榮耀。
8:31|ASV|What then shall we say to these things? If God is for us, who is against us?
8:31|Darby|What shall we then say to these things? If God [be] for us,  who against us?
8:31|KJV|What shall we then say to these things? If God be for us, who can be against us?
8:31<version name="WYC">What then shall we say to these things?  If God <i>be</i> for us, who <i>is</i> against us?</version>
8:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，對這些事，我們可說甚麼？神若幫助我們，誰能抵擋我們？
8:32|ASV|He that spared not his own Son, but delivered him up for us all, how shall he not also with him freely give us all things?
8:32|Darby|He who, yea, has not spared his own Son, but delivered him  up for us all, how shall he not also with him grant us all  things?
8:32|KJV|He that spared not his own Son, but delivered him up for us all, how shall he not with him also freely give us all things?
8:32|WYC|Which also spared not his own Son, but betook him for us all, how also gave he not to us all things with him?
8:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神既不吝惜自己的兒子，為我們眾人捨了，豈不也把萬有和祂一同白白的賜給我們麼？
8:33|ASV|Who shall lay anything to the charge of God's elect? It is God that justifieth;
8:33|Darby|Who shall bring an accusation against God's elect? [It is]  God who justifies:
8:33|KJV|Who shall lay any thing to the charge of God's elect? It is God that justifieth.
8:33|WYC|Who shall accuse against the chosen men of God?  It is God that justifieth,
8:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|誰能控告神所揀選的人？有神稱我們為義了。
8:34|ASV|who is he that condemneth? It is Christ Jesus that died, yea rather, that was raised from the dead, who is at the right hand of God, who also maketh intercession for us.
8:34|Darby|who is he that condemns? [It is] Christ who has died, but  rather has been [also] raised up; who is also at the right hand  of God; who also intercedes for us.
8:34|KJV|Who is he that condemneth? It is Christ that died, yea rather, that is risen again, who is even at the right hand of God, who also maketh intercession for us.
8:34|WYC|who is it that condemneth?  It is Jesus Christ that was dead, yea, the which rose again, the which is on the right half of God, and the which prayeth for us [the which and rose again, the which is on the right half of God, the which prayeth for us].
8:34|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|誰能定我們的罪？有基督耶穌已經死了，而且已經復活了，現今在神的右邊，還為我們代求。
8:35|ASV|Who shall separate us from the love of Christ? shall tribulation, or anguish, or persecution, or famine, or nakedness, or peril, or sword?
8:35|Darby|Who shall separate us from the love of Christ? tribulation  or distress, or persecution, or famine, or nakedness, or  danger, or sword?
8:35|KJV|Who shall separate us from the love of Christ? shall tribulation, or distress, or persecution, or famine, or nakedness, or peril, or sword?
8:35|WYC|Who then shall separate us [Who therefore shall part us] from the charity of Christ? tribulation, or anguish, or hunger, or nakedness, or persecution, or peril, or sword?
8:35|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|誰能使我們與基督的愛隔絕？難道是患難麼？是困苦麼？是逼迫麼？是飢餓麼？是赤身麼？是危險麼？是刀劍麼？
8:36|ASV|Even as it is written, For thy sake we are killed all the day long; We were accounted as sheep for the slaughter.
8:36|Darby|According as it is written, For thy sake we are put to  death all the day long; we have been reckoned as sheep for  slaughter.
8:36|KJV|As it is written, For thy sake we are killed all the day long; we are accounted as sheep for the slaughter.
8:36|WYC|As it is written, For we be slain all day for thee; we be guessed as sheep of slaughter [we be guessed as sheep to slaughter].
8:36|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|如經上所記：“我們為你的緣故，終日被殺，人看我們如將宰的羊。”
8:37|ASV|Nay, in all these things we are more than conquerors through him that loved us.
8:37|Darby|But in all these things we more than conquer through him  that has loved us.
8:37|KJV|Nay, in all these things we are more than conquerors through him that loved us.
8:37|WYC|But in all these things we overcome, for him that loved us.
8:37|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而藉著那愛我們的，在這一切的事上，我們已經得勝有餘了。
8:38|ASV|For I am persuaded, that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor things present, nor things to come, nor powers,
8:38|Darby|For I am persuaded that neither death, nor life, nor  angels, nor principalities, nor things present, nor things to  come, nor powers,
8:38|KJV|For I am persuaded, that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things present, nor things to come,
8:38|WYC|But I am certain [Soothly I am certain], that neither death, neither life, neither angels, neither principats, neither virtues, neither present things, neither things to coming [neither things to come],
8:38|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我深信，無論是死，是生，是天使，是掌權的，是現今的事，是要來的事，是有能的，
8:39<version name="ASV">nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, shall be able to separate us from the love of God, which is in Christ Jesus our Lord. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:39<version name="Darby">nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, shall be  able to separate us from the love of God, which [is] in Christ  Jesus our Lord. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:39<version name="KJV">Nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, shall be able to separate us from the love of God, which is in Christ Jesus our Lord.</p><p /><br /></version>
8:39|WYC|neither strength, neither height, neither deepness, neither any other creature may separate us [shall be able to part us] from the charity of God, that is in Christ Jesus our Lord.
8:39|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|是高，是深，或是別的受造之物，都不能叫我們與神的愛隔絕，這愛是在我們的主基督耶穌裡的。
9:1|ASV|I say the truth in Christ, I lie not, my conscience bearing witness with me in the Holy Spirit,
9:1|Darby|I say [the] truth in Christ, I lie not, my conscience  bearing witness with me in [the] Holy Spirit,
9:1|KJV|I say the truth in Christ, I lie not, my conscience also bearing me witness in the Holy Ghost,
9:1|WYC|I say truth in Christ Jesus, I lie not, for my conscience beareth witnessing to me in the Holy Ghost, [I say truth in Christ Jesus, I lie not, my conscience bearing witness to me in the Holy Ghost,]
9:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在基督裡說真話，並不說謊，有我的良心在聖靈裡同我作見證，
9:2|ASV|that I have great sorrow and unceasing pain in my heart.
9:2|Darby|that I have great grief and uninterrupted pain in my heart,
9:2|KJV|That I have great heaviness and continual sorrow in my heart.
9:2|WYC|for great heaviness is to me, and continual sorrow to my heart.
9:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我是大有憂愁，心裡不住的傷痛。
9:3|ASV|For I could wish that I myself were anathema from Christ for my brethren's sake, my kinsmen according to the flesh:
9:3|Darby|for I have wished, I myself, to be a curse from the Christ  for my brethren, my kinsmen, according to flesh;
9:3|KJV|For I could wish that myself were accursed from Christ for my brethren, my kinsmen according to the flesh:
9:3<version name="WYC">For I myself desired to be separated from Christ for my brethren [Forsooth I myself desired to be cursed, <i>or parted</i>, from Christ for my brethren], that be my cousins after the flesh,</version>
9:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|為我弟兄，我肉身的親人，我寧願自己被咒詛，與基督分離。
9:4|ASV|who are Israelites; whose is the adoption, and the glory, and the covenants, and the giving of the law, and the service of God, and the promises;
9:4|Darby|who are Israelites; whose [is] the adoption, and the glory,  and the covenants, and the law-giving, and the service, and the  promises;
9:4|KJV|Who are Israelites; to whom pertaineth the adoption, and the glory, and the covenants, and the giving of the law, and the service of God, and the promises;
9:4|WYC|that be men of Israel [that be Israelites]; whose is adoption of sons, and glory, and testament, and giving of the law, and service, and promises;
9:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們是以色列人，那兒子的名分、榮耀、諸約、律法的頒賜、事奉和應許，都是他們的；
9:5|ASV|whose are the fathers, and of whom is Christ as concerning the flesh, who is over all, God blessed for ever. Amen.
9:5|Darby|whose [are] the fathers; and of whom, as according to flesh,  [is] the Christ, who is over all, God blessed for ever. Amen.
9:5|KJV|Whose are the fathers, and of whom as concerning the flesh Christ came, who is over all, God blessed for ever. Amen.
9:5<version name="WYC">whose be the fathers, and of which <i>is </i>Christ after the flesh <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21178a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>, that is God above all things, blessed into worlds.  Amen.</version>
9:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|列祖是他們的，按肉體說，基督也是出於他們的，祂是在萬有之上，永遠受頌讚的神。阿們。
9:6|ASV|But it is not as though the word of God hath come to nought. For they are not all Israel, that are of Israel:
9:6|Darby|Not however as though the word of God had failed; for not  all [are] Israel which [are] of Israel;
9:6|KJV|Not as though the word of God hath taken none effect. For they are not all Israel, which are of Israel:
9:6<version name="WYC">But not that the word of God hath fallen down [Soothly not that the word of God hath fallen down, <i>or failed unfulfilled</i>].  For not all that be of Israel, these be Israelites.</version>
9:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但這不是說，神的話落了空，因為從以色列生的，不都是以色列人；
9:7|ASV|neither, because they are Abraham's seed, are they all children: but, In Isaac shall thy seed be called.
9:7|Darby|nor because they are seed of Abraham [are] all children:  but, In Isaac shall a seed be called to thee.
9:7|KJV|Neither, because they are the seed of Abraham, are they all children: but, In Isaac shall thy seed be called.
9:7|WYC|Neither they that be [the] seed of Abraham, all be sons; but in Isaac the seed shall be called to thee;
9:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|也不因為是亞伯拉罕的後裔，就都是兒女，惟獨“從以撒生的，纔要稱為你的後裔。”
9:8|ASV|That is, it is not the children of the flesh that are children of God; but the children of the promise are reckoned for a seed.
9:8|Darby|That is, [they that are] the children of the flesh, these  [are] not the children of God; but the children of the promise  are reckoned as seed.
9:8|KJV|That is, They which are the children of the flesh, these are not the children of God: but the children of the promise are counted for the seed.
9:8<version name="WYC">that is to say, not they that be sons of the flesh, <i>be</i> sons of God, but they that be sons of [the] promise be deemed in the seed.</version>
9:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這就是說，肉體的兒女不就是神的兒女，惟獨那應許的兒女纔算是後裔。
9:9|ASV|For this is a word of promise, According to this season will I come, and Sarah shall have a son.
9:9|Darby|For this word [is] of promise, According to this time I will  come, and there shall be a son to Sarah.
9:9|KJV|For this is the word of promise, At this time will I come, and Sarah shall have a son.
9:9|WYC|For why this is the word of promise, After this time I shall come, and a son shall be to Sarah.
9:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為所應許的話是這樣：“到明年這時候我要來，撒拉必生一個兒子。”
9:10|ASV|And not only so; but Rebecca also having conceived by one, even by our father Isaac--
9:10|Darby|And not only [that], but Rebecca having conceived by one,  Isaac our father,
9:10|KJV|And not only this; but when Rebecca also had conceived by one, even by our father Isaac;
9:10<version name="WYC">And not only she, but also Rebecca had two sons of one lying-by of Isaac, our father. [Forsooth not only she, but and Rebecca, of one lying-by, <i>or</i> <i>of one knowing of man</i>, having two sons of Isaac, our father.]</version>
9:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不但如此，還有利百加，既從一個人，就是從我們的祖宗以撒懷了孕，
9:11|ASV|for the children being not yet born, neither having done anything good or bad, that the purpose of God according to election might stand, not of works, but of him that calleth,
9:11|Darby|[the children] indeed being not yet born, or having done  anything good or worthless (that the purpose of God according  to election might abide, not of works, but of him that calls),
9:11|KJV|(For the children being not yet born, neither having done any good or evil, that the purpose of God according to election might stand, not of works, but of him that calleth;)
9:11|WYC|And when they were not yet born, neither had done any thing of good either evil [or evil], that the purpose of God should dwell by election [that the purpose of God should dwell after election], not of works, but of God calling,
9:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|雙子還沒有生下來，善惡也沒有作出來，（只因要堅定神揀選人的旨意，不是本於行為，乃是本於那呼召人的，）
9:12|ASV|it was said unto her, The elder shall serve the younger.
9:12|Darby|it was said to her, The greater shall serve the less:
9:12|KJV|It was said unto her, The elder shall serve the younger.
9:12|WYC|it was said to him, That the more should serve the less, [it is said to her, For the more shall serve to the less,]
9:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神就對利百加說，“將來大的要服事小的。”
9:13|ASV|Even as it is written, Jacob I loved, but Esau I hated.
9:13|Darby|according as it is written, I have loved Jacob, and I have  hated Esau.
9:13|KJV|As it is written, Jacob have I loved, but Esau have I hated.
9:13|WYC|as it is written, I loved Jacob, but I hated Esau. [as it is written, I loved Jacob, forsooth Esau I had in hate.]
9:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|正如經上所記：“雅各是我所愛的，以掃是我所恨的。”
9:14|ASV|What shall we say then? Is there unrighteousness with God? God forbid.
9:14|Darby|What shall we say then? [Is there] unrighteousness with  God? Far be the thought.
9:14|KJV|What shall we say then? Is there unrighteousness with God? God forbid.
9:14|WYC|What therefore shall we say?  Whether wickedness be with God?  God forbid [Far be it].
9:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我們可說甚麼？難道在神有不義麼？絕對沒有！
9:15|ASV|For he saith to Moses, I will have mercy on whom I have mercy, and I will have compassion on whom I have compassion.
9:15|Darby|For he says to Moses, I will shew mercy to whom I will shew  mercy, and I will feel compassion for whom I will feel  compassion.
9:15|KJV|For he saith to Moses, I will have mercy on whom I will have mercy, and I will have compassion on whom I will have compassion.
9:15|WYC|For he saith to Moses, I shall have mercy on whom I shall have mercy; and I shall give mercy on whom I shall have mercy.
9:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為祂對摩西說，“我要向誰施憐憫，就向誰施憐憫；要對誰動憐恤，就對誰動憐恤。”
9:16|ASV|So then it is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that hath mercy.
9:16|Darby|So then [it is] not of him that wills, nor of him that  runs, but of God that shews mercy.
9:16|KJV|So then it is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that sheweth mercy.
9:16|WYC|Therefore it is not neither of man willing [Therefore it is not neither of a man willing], neither running, but of God having mercy.
9:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣看來，這不在於那定意的，也不在於那奔跑的，只在於那施憐憫的神。
9:17|ASV|For the scripture saith unto Pharaoh, For this very purpose did I raise thee up, that I might show in thee my power, and that my name might be published abroad in all the earth.
9:17|Darby|For the scripture says to Pharaoh, For this very thing I  have raised thee up from amongst [men], that I might thus shew  in thee my power, and so that my name should be declared in all  the earth.
9:17|KJV|For the scripture saith unto Pharaoh, Even for this same purpose have I raised thee up, that I might shew my power in thee, and that my name might be declared throughout all the earth.
9:17|WYC|And the scripture saith to Pharaoh [Forsooth the scripture saith to Pharaoh], For to this thing I have stirred thee, that I show in thee my virtue, and that my name be told in all [the] earth.
9:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為經上對法老說，“我特意將你興起來，為要在你身上顯示我的權能，並要使我的名傳遍全地。”
9:18|ASV|So then he hath mercy on whom he will, and whom he will be hardeneth.
9:18|Darby|So then, to whom he will he shews mercy, and whom he will  he hardens.
9:18|KJV|Therefore hath he mercy on whom he will have mercy, and whom he will he hardeneth.
9:18<version name="WYC">Therefore of whom God will, he hath mercy; and whom he will, he endureth [and whom he will, he endureth, <i>or hardeneth</i>].</version>
9:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣看來，神願意向誰施憐憫，就向誰施憐憫；願意叫誰剛硬，就叫誰剛硬。
9:19|ASV|Thou wilt say then unto me, Why doth he still find fault? For who withstandeth his will?
9:19|Darby|Thou wilt say to me then, Why does he yet find fault? for  who resists his purpose?
9:19|KJV|Thou wilt say then unto me, Why doth he yet find fault? For who hath resisted his will?
9:19|WYC|Then sayest thou to me, What is sought yet [What thing is yet sought]? for who withstandeth his will?
9:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，你必對我說，祂為甚麼還指責人？有誰抗拒祂的旨意？
9:20|ASV|Nay but, O man, who art thou that repliest against God? Shall the thing formed say to him that formed it, Why didst thou make me thus?
9:20|Darby|Aye, but thou, O man, who art *thou* that answerest again  to God? Shall the thing formed say to him that has formed it,  Why hast thou made me thus?
9:20|KJV|Nay but, O man, who art thou that repliest against God? Shall the thing formed say to him that formed it, Why hast thou made me thus?
9:20|WYC|O! man, who art thou, that answerest to God?  Whether a made thing saith to him that made it, What hast thou made me so?
9:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|人哪，你是誰，竟向神頂嘴？被塑造者豈能對塑造他者說，你為甚麼這樣造我？
9:21|ASV|Or hath not the potter a right over the clay, from the same lump to make one part a vessel unto honor, and another unto dishonor?
9:21|Darby|Or has not the potter authority over the clay, out of the  same lump to make one vessel to honour, and another to  dishonour?
9:21|KJV|Hath not the potter power over the clay, of the same lump to make one vessel unto honour, and another unto dishonour?
9:21<version name="WYC">Whether a potter of clay hath not power to make of the same gobbet one vessel into honour, another into despite? [Whether a potter of clay hath not power of the same gobbet to make soothly one vessel into honour, another forsooth into despite, <i>or low office</i>?]</version>
9:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|窯匠難道沒有權柄，從同一團泥裡，拿一塊作成貴重的器皿，又拿一塊作成卑賤的器皿麼？
9:22|ASV|What if God, willing to show his wrath, and to make his power known, endured with much longsuffering vessels of wrath fitted unto destruction:
9:22|Darby|And if God, minded to shew his wrath and to make his power  known, endured with much long-suffering vessels of wrath fitted  for destruction;
9:22|KJV|What if God, willing to shew his wrath, and to make his power known, endured with much longsuffering the vessels of wrath fitted to destruction:
9:22<version name="WYC">And if God willing to show his wrath, and to make his power known, hath suffered in great patience vessels of wrath able into death, [That if God willing to show wrath, and to make his power known, sustained in great patience the vessels of wrath able into perdition, <i>or damnation</i>,]</version>
9:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若是神願意顯示祂的忿怒，彰顯祂的能力，就多用恆忍寬容那些可怒、豫備遭毀滅的器皿，
9:23|ASV|and that he might make known the riches of his glory upon vessels of mercy, which he afore prepared unto glory,
9:23|Darby|and that he might make known the riches of his glory upon  vessels of mercy, which he had before prepared for glory,
9:23|KJV|And that he might make known the riches of his glory on the vessels of mercy, which he had afore prepared unto glory,
9:23|WYC|to show the riches of his glory [that he should show the riches of his glory] into vessels of mercy, which he made ready into glory.
9:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|且要在那些蒙憐憫、早豫備得榮耀的器皿上，彰顯祂榮耀的豐富；
9:24|ASV|even us, whom he also called, not from the Jews only, but also from the Gentiles?
9:24|Darby|us, whom he has also called, not only from amongst [the]  Jews, but also from amongst [the] nations?
9:24|KJV|Even us, whom he hath called, not of the Jews only, but also of the Gentiles?
9:24|WYC|Which also he called [us,] not only of the Jews, but also of heathen men,
9:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這器皿就是我們這蒙祂所召的，不但從猶太人中，也從外邦人中，這有甚麼不可？
9:25|ASV|As he saith also in Hosea, I will call that my people, which was not my people; And her beloved, that was not beloved.
9:25|Darby|As he says also in Hosea, I will call not-my-people My  people; and the-not-beloved Beloved.
9:25|KJV|As he saith also in Osee, I will call them my people, which were not my people; and her beloved, which was not beloved.
9:25|WYC|as he saith in Osee, I shall call not my people my people, and not my loved my loved, and not getting mercy getting mercy [and not having mercy having mercy];
9:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就如神在何西阿書上也說，“那本來不是我子民的，我要稱為我的子民；本來不是蒙愛的，我要稱為蒙愛的；
9:26|ASV|And it shall be, that in the place where it was said unto them, Ye are not my people, There shall they be called sons of the living God.
9:26|Darby|And it shall be, in the place where it was said to them,  *Ye* [are] not my people, there shall they be called Sons of  [the] living God.
9:26|KJV|And it shall come to pass, that in the place where it was said unto them, Ye are not my people; there shall they be called the children of the living God.
9:26|WYC|and it shall be in the place, where it is said to them, Not ye my people, there they shall be called the sons of living God.
9:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|從前在甚麼地方對他們說，你們不是我的子民，將來就在那裡稱他們為活神的兒子。”
9:27|ASV|And Isaiah crieth concerning Israel, If the number of the children of Israel be as the sand of the sea, it is the remnant that shall be saved:
9:27|Darby|But Esaias cries concerning Israel, Should the number of  the children of Israel be as the sand of the sea, the remnant  shall be saved:
9:27|KJV|Esaias also crieth concerning Israel, Though the number of the children of Israel be as the sand of the sea, a remnant shall be saved:
9:27|WYC|But Esaias crieth for Israel [Forsooth Esaias crieth for Israel], If the number of children of Israel shall be as [the] gravel of the sea, the remnants [the reliefs] shall be made safe.
9:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以賽亞指著以色列人喊著：“以色列子孫的數目雖如海沙，得救的不過是剩下的餘數；
9:28|ASV|for the Lord will execute his word upon the earth, finishing it and cutting it short.
9:28|Darby|for [he] is bringing the matter to an end, and [cutting  [it] short in righteousness; because] a cutting short of the  matter will [the] Lord accomplish upon the earth.
9:28|KJV|For he will finish the work, and cut it short in righteousness: because a short work will the Lord make upon the earth.
9:28<version name="WYC">Forsooth a word making an end, and abridging in equity, for the Lord shall make a word abridged on all the earth <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21201b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup>.</version>
9:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為主要在地上實行祂的話，要將祂的話完成且截短。”
9:29|ASV|And, as Isaiah hath said before, Except the Lord of Sabaoth had left us a seed, We had become as Sodom, and had been made like unto Gomorrah.
9:29|Darby|And according as Esaias said before, Unless [the] Lord of  hosts had left us a seed, we had been as Sodom, and made like  even as Gomorrha.
9:29|KJV|And as Esaias said before, Except the Lord of Sabaoth had left us a seed, we had been as Sodoma, and been made like unto Gomorrha.
9:29|WYC|And as Esaias before-said, But God of hosts had left to us seed, we had been made as Sodom, and we had been like as Gomorrha.
9:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又如以賽亞先前說過，“若不是萬軍之主給我們存留餘種，我們早已成了所多瑪，並像蛾摩拉的樣子了。”
9:30|ASV|What shall we say then? That the Gentiles, who followed not after righteousness, attained to righteousness, even the righteousness which is of faith:
9:30|Darby|What then shall we say? That [they of the] nations, who did  not follow after righteousness, have attained righteousness,  but [the] righteousness that is on the principle of faith.
9:30|KJV|What shall we say then? That the Gentiles, which followed not after righteousness, have attained to righteousness, even the righteousness which is of faith.
9:30|WYC|Therefore what shall we say? That heathen men that followed not rightwiseness, have gotten rightwiseness [have caught rightwiseness], yea, the rightwiseness that is of faith.
9:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我們可說甚麼？那未曾追求義的外邦人，反得著了義，就是本於信的義。
9:31|ASV|but Israel, following after a law of righteousness, did not arrive at  that law.
9:31|Darby|But Israel, pursuing after a law of righteousness, has not  attained to [that] law.
9:31|KJV|But Israel, which followed after the law of righteousness, hath not attained to the law of righteousness.
9:31|WYC|But Israel following the law of rightwiseness, came not perfectly to [into] the law of rightwiseness.
9:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但那追求律法之義的以色列人，並未達到那律法。
9:32|ASV|Wherefore? Because they sought it not by faith, but as it were by works. They stumbled at the stone of stumbling;
9:32|Darby|Wherefore? Because [it was] not on the principle of faith,  but as of works. They have stumbled at the stumblingstone,
9:32|KJV|Wherefore? Because they sought it not by faith, but as it were by the works of the law. For they stumbled at that stumblingstone;
9:32<version name="WYC">Why?  For not of faith, but as of works.  And they spurned against the stone of offence [Soothly they offended against the stone of offence, <i>or</i> <i>spurning</i>],</version>
9:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這是為甚麼？因為不是本於信，而是本於行。他們正碰跌在那絆腳石上，
9:33<version name="ASV">even as it is written, Behold, I lay in Zion a stone of stumbling and a rock of offence: And he that believeth on him shall not be put to shame. </p><p /><br /></version>
9:33<version name="Darby">according as it is written, Behold, I place in Zion a stone  of stumbling and rock of offence: and he that believes on him  shall not be ashamed. </p><p /><br /></version>
9:33<version name="KJV">As it is written, Behold, I lay in Sion a stumblingstone and rock of offence: and whosoever believeth on him shall not be ashamed.</p><p /><br /></version>
9:33<version name="WYC">as it is written, Lo! I put a stone of offence in Sion, and a stone of stumbling; and each that shall believe in it, shall not be confounded. [as it is written, Lo! I put a stone of <i>spurning</i> in Sion, and a stone of offence; and each that shall believe into it, shall not be confounded, <i>or shamed</i>.]</version>
9:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就如經上所記：“看哪，我在錫安放一塊絆腳的石頭，並跌人的磐石，信靠祂的，必不至於羞愧。”
10:1|ASV|Brethren, my heart's desire and my supplication to God is for them, that they may be saved.
10:1|Darby|Brethren, the delight of my own heart and my supplication  which [I address] to God for them is for salvation.
10:1|KJV|Brethren, my heart's desire and prayer to God for Israel is, that they might be saved.
10:1|WYC|Brethren, the will of mine heart and my beseeching is made to God for them into health.
10:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，我心裡所喜悅的，並我向神為以色列人所祈求的，是要他們得救。
10:2|ASV|For I bear them witness that they have a zeal for God, but not according to knowledge.
10:2|Darby|For I bear them witness that they have zeal for God, but  not according to knowledge.
10:2|KJV|For I bear them record that they have a zeal of God, but not according to knowledge.
10:2|WYC|But I bear witnessing to them [Forsooth I bear witnessing to them], that they have the love of God, but not after knowing.
10:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我可以為他們作見證，他們對神有熱心，但不是按著完全的知識；
10:3|ASV|For being ignorant of God's righteousness, and seeking to establish their own, they did not subject themselves to the righteousness of God.
10:3|Darby|For they, being ignorant of God's righteousness, and  seeking to establish their own [righteousness], have not  submitted to the righteousness of God.
10:3|KJV|For they being ignorant of God's righteousness, and going about to establish their own righteousness, have not submitted themselves unto the righteousness of God.
10:3<version name="WYC">For they not knowing God's rightwiseness [For they unknowing God's rightwiseness], and seeking to make steadfast their own <i>rightwiseness</i>, be not subject to the rightwiseness of God.</version>
10:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為不知道神的義，又想要建立自己的義，就不服神的義了。
10:4|ASV|For Christ is the end of the law unto righteousness to every one that believeth.
10:4|Darby|For Christ is [the] end of law for righteousness to every  one that believes.
10:4|KJV|For Christ is the end of the law for righteousness to every one that believeth.
10:4<version name="WYC">For the end of the law <i>is</i> Christ, to rightwiseness to each man that believeth.</version>
10:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|原來律法的總結就是基督，使凡信的都得著義。
10:5|ASV|For Moses writeth that the man that doeth the righteousness which is of the law shall live thereby.
10:5|Darby|For Moses lays down in writing the righteousness which is  of the law, The man who has practised those things shall live  by them.
10:5|KJV|For Moses describeth the righteousness which is of the law, That the man which doeth those things shall live by them.
10:5|WYC|For Moses wrote, For the man that shall do rightwiseness that is of the law, shall live in it.
10:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|論到那本於律法的義，摩西寫著：“行這些事的，必因這些事活著。”
10:6|ASV|But the righteousness which is of faith saith thus, Say not in thy heart, Who shall ascend into heaven? (that is, to bring Christ down:)
10:6|Darby|But the righteousness of faith speaks thus: Do not say in  thine heart, Who shall ascend to the heavens? that is, to bring  Christ down;
10:6|KJV|But the righteousness which is of faith speaketh on this wise, Say not in thine heart, Who shall ascend into heaven? (that is, to bring Christ down from above:)
10:6|WYC|But the rightwiseness that is of belief, saith thus, Say thou not in thine heart, Who shall ascend into heaven? that is to say, to lead down Christ;
10:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但那本於信的義如此說，“你不要心裡說，誰要升到天上？”就是要領下基督來，
10:7|ASV|or, Who shall descend into the abyss? (That is, to bring Christ up from the dead.)
10:7|Darby|or, Who shall descend into the abyss? that is, to bring up  Christ from among [the] dead.
10:7|KJV|Or, Who shall descend into the deep? (that is, to bring up Christ again from the dead.)
10:7<version name="WYC">or who shall go down into hell? that is, to again-call Christ from death. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21213a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
10:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|或說，“誰要下到無底坑？”就是要領基督從死人中上來。
10:8|ASV|But what saith it? The word is nigh thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart: that is, the word of faith, which we preach:
10:8|Darby|But what says it? The word is near thee, in thy mouth and  in thy heart: that is, the word of faith, which we preach:
10:8|KJV|But what saith it? The word is nigh thee, even in thy mouth, and in thy heart: that is, the word of faith, which we preach;
10:8|WYC|But what saith the scripture?  The word is nigh in thy mouth, and in thine heart; this is the word of belief, which we preach.
10:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這義到底怎麼說？牠說，“這話與你相近，就在你口裡，也在你心裡。”這就是我們所傳信主的話，
10:9|ASV|because if thou shalt confess with thy mouth Jesus as Lord, and shalt believe in thy heart that God raised him from the dead, thou shalt be saved:
10:9|Darby|that if thou shalt confess with thy mouth Jesus as Lord,  and shalt believe in thine heart that God has raised him from  among [the] dead, thou shalt be saved.
10:9|KJV|That if thou shalt confess with thy mouth the Lord Jesus, and shalt believe in thine heart that God hath raised him from the dead, thou shalt be saved.
10:9|WYC|That if thou acknowledge in thy mouth the Lord Jesus Christ, and believest in thine heart, that God raised him from death [that God raised him from dead], thou shalt be safe.
10:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就是你若口裡認耶穌為主，心裡信神叫祂從死人中復活，就必得救；
10:10|ASV|for with the heart man believeth unto righteousness; and with the mouth confession is made unto salvation.
10:10|Darby|For with [the] heart is believed to righteousness; and  with [the] mouth confession made to salvation.
10:10|KJV|For with the heart man believeth unto righteousness; and with the mouth confession is made unto salvation.
10:10|WYC|For by heart me believeth to rightwiseness [Forsooth by heart men believeth to rightwiseness], but by mouth acknowledging is made to health.
10:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為人心裡信，就得著義；口裡承認，就得救。
10:11|ASV|For the scripture saith, Whosoever believeth on him shall not be put to shame.
10:11|Darby|For the scripture says, No one believing on him shall be  ashamed.
10:11|KJV|For the scripture saith, Whosoever believeth on him shall not be ashamed.
10:11|WYC|For why the scripture saith, Each that believeth in him, shall not be confounded.
10:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為經上說，“凡信靠祂的，必不至於羞愧。”
10:12|ASV|For there is no distinction between Jew and Greek: for the same Lord is Lord of all, and is rich unto all that call upon him:
10:12|Darby|For there is no difference of Jew and Greek; for the same  Lord of all [is] rich towards all that call upon him.
10:12|KJV|For there is no difference between the Jew and the Greek: for the same Lord over all is rich unto all that call upon him.
10:12<version name="WYC">And there is no distinction of Jew and of Greek; for the same Lord of all <i>is</i> rich into all, that inwardly call him [that in-call him].</version>
10:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為猶太人和希利尼人並沒有分別，眾人同有一位主，祂對一切呼求祂的人是豐富的。
10:13|ASV|for, Whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved.
10:13|Darby|For every one whosoever, who shall call on the name of the  Lord, shall be saved.
10:13|KJV|For whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved.
10:13|WYC|For each man, whoever shall inwardly call [whoever shall in-call] the name of the Lord, shall be safe.
10:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為“凡呼求主名的，就必得救。”
10:14|ASV|How then shall they call on him in whom they have not believed? and how shall they believe in him whom they have not heard? and how shall they hear without a preacher?
10:14|Darby|How then shall they call upon him in whom they have not  believed? and how shall they believe on him of whom they have  not heard? and how shall they hear without one who preaches?
10:14|KJV|How then shall they call on him in whom they have not believed? and how shall they believe in him of whom they have not heard? and how shall they hear without a preacher?
10:14|WYC|How then shall they inwardly call him [How therefore shall they in-call him], into whom they have not believed? or how shall they believe to him, whom they have not heard?  How shall they hear, without a preacher?
10:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而人所未曾信入的，怎能呼求？所未曾聽見的，怎能信入？沒有傳道的，怎能聽見？
10:15|ASV|and how shall they preach, except they be sent? even as it is written, How beautiful are the feet of them that bring glad tidings of good things!
10:15|Darby|and how shall they preach unless they have been sent?  according as it is written, How beautiful the feet of them that  announce glad tidings of peace, of them that announce glad  tidings of good things!
10:15|KJV|And how shall they preach, except they be sent? as it is written, How beautiful are the feet of them that preach the gospel of peace, and bring glad tidings of good things!
10:15<version name="WYC">and how shall they preach, but they be sent?  As it is written, How fair <i>be</i> the feet of them that preach peace, of them that preach good things [As it is written, How fair the feet of men evangelizing peace, of preaching good things].</version>
10:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若非奉差遣，怎能傳道？如經上所記：“傳福音報喜信的人，他們的腳蹤何等佳美！”
10:16|ASV|But they did not all hearken to the glad tidings. For Isaiah saith, Lord, who hath believed our report?
10:16|Darby|But they have not all obeyed the glad tidings. For Esaias  says, Lord, who has believed our report?
10:16|KJV|But they have not all obeyed the gospel. For Esaias saith, Lord, who hath believed our report?
10:16|WYC|But not all men obey to the gospel [But not all obey to the gospel].  For Esaias saith, Lord, who believed to our hearing?
10:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|只是人沒有都順從福音，因為以賽亞說，“主阿，我們所傳給人聽的，有誰信？”
10:17|ASV|So belief cometh of hearing, and hearing by the word of Christ.
10:17|Darby|So faith then [is] by a report, but the report by God's  word.
10:17|KJV|So then faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God.
10:17<version name="WYC">Therefore faith <i>is</i> of hearing [Therefore faith by hearing], but hearing by the word of Christ.</version>
10:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|可見信是由於聽，聽是藉著基督的話。
10:18|ASV|But I say, Did they not hear? Yea, verily, Their sound went out into all the earth, And their words unto the ends of the world.
10:18|Darby|But I say, Have they not heard? Yea, surely, Their voice  has gone out into all the earth, and their words to the  extremities of the habitable world.
10:18|KJV|But I say, Have they not heard? Yes verily, their sound went into all the earth, and their words unto the ends of the world.
10:18|WYC|But I say, Whether they heard not?  Yes, soothly the sound of them went out into all the earth, and their words into the ends of the world.
10:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但我說，他們未曾聽見麼？的確聽見了：“他們的聲音傳遍全地，他們的言語達到地極。”
10:19|ASV|But I say, Did Israel not know? First Moses saith, I will provoke you to jealousy with that which is no nation, With a nation void of understanding will I anger you.
10:19|Darby|But I say, Has not Israel known? First, Moses says, *I*  will provoke you to jealousy through [them that are] not a  nation: through a nation without understanding I will anger  you.
10:19|KJV|But I say, Did not Israel know? First Moses saith, I will provoke you to jealousy by them that are no people, and by a foolish nation I will anger you.
10:19|WYC|But I say, Whether Israel knew not?  First Moses saith, I shall lead you to envy, that ye be no folk; that ye be an unwise folk, I shall send you into wrath [First Moses saith, I shall lead you to envy, into not a folk; into an unwise folk, I shall send you into wrath].
10:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但我說，以色列人不知道麼？先有摩西說，“我要用那不是國民的，惹動你們妒忌；我要用那無知的民，觸動你們發怒。”
10:20|ASV|And Isaiah is very bold, and saith, I was found of them that sought me not; I became manifest unto them that asked not of me.
10:20|Darby|But Esaias is very bold, and says, I have been found by  those not seeking me; I have become manifest to those not  inquiring after me.
10:20|KJV|But Esaias is very bold, and saith, I was found of them that sought me not; I was made manifest unto them that asked not after me.
10:20|WYC|And Esaias is bold, and saith, I am found of men that seek me not; openly I appeared to them, that asked not me.
10:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又有以賽亞放膽說，“沒有尋找我的，我叫他們遇見；沒有求問我的，我向他們顯現。”
10:21<version name="ASV">But as to Israel he saith, All the day long did I spread out my hands unto a disobedient and gainsaying people. </p><p /><br /></version>
10:21<version name="Darby">But unto Israel he says, All the day long I have stretched  out my hands unto a people disobeying and opposing. </p><p /><br /></version>
10:21<version name="KJV">But to Israel he saith, All day long I have stretched forth my hands unto a disobedient and gainsaying people.</p><p /><br /></version>
10:21|WYC|But to Israel he saith, All day I stretched out mine hands to a people that believed not, but gainsaid me. [Forsooth to Israel, he saith, All day I stretched out my hands to a people not believing to me, but again-saying to me.]
10:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於以色列人，他卻說，“我整天向那悖逆頂嘴的百姓伸手招呼。”
11:1|ASV|I say then, Did God cast off his people? God forbid. For I also am an Israelite, of the seed of Abraham, of the tribe of Benjamin.
11:1|Darby|I say then, Has God cast away his people? Far be the  thought. For *I* also am an Israelite, of [the] seed of  Abraham, of [the] tribe of Benjamin.
11:1|KJV|I say then, Hath God cast away his people? God forbid. For I also am an Israelite, of the seed of Abraham, of the tribe of Benjamin.
11:1|WYC|Therefore I say, Whether God hath put away his people?  God forbid [Far be it].  For [and] I am an Israelite, of the seed of Abraham, of the lineage of Benjamin.
11:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我說，神棄絕了祂的百姓麼？絕對沒有！因為我也是以色列人，出於亞伯拉罕的後裔，屬便雅憫支派的。
11:2|ASV|God did not cast off his people which he foreknew. Or know ye not what the scripture saith of Elijah? how he pleadeth with God against Israel:
11:2|Darby|God has not cast away his people whom he foreknew. Know ye  not what the scripture says in [the history of] Elias, how he  pleads with God against Israel?
11:2|KJV|God hath not cast away his people which he foreknew. Wot ye not what the scripture saith of Elias? how he maketh intercession to God against Israel saying,
11:2|WYC|God hath not put away his people, which he before-knew.  Whether ye know not [Whether ye witen not], what the scripture saith in Elias?  How he prayeth God against Israel,
11:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神並沒有棄絕祂豫先所知道的百姓。你們豈不曉得經上論到以利亞是怎麼說的？他怎樣向神控告以色列人說，
11:3|ASV|Lord, they have killed thy prophets, they have digged down thine altars; and I am left alone, and they seek my life.
11:3|Darby|Lord, they have killed thy prophets, they have dug down  thine altars; and *I* have been left alone, and they seek my  life.
11:3|KJV|Lord, they have killed thy prophets, and digged down thine altars; and I am left alone, and they seek my life.
11:3|WYC|Lord, they have slain thy prophets, they have under-delved thine altars, and I am left alone, and they seek my life.
11:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|“主阿，他們殺了你的申言者，拆了你的祭壇，只剩下我一個人，他們還要尋索我的命。”
11:4|ASV|But what saith the answer of God unto him? I have left for myself seven thousand men, who have not bowed the knee to Baal.
11:4|Darby|But what says the divine answer to him? I have left to  myself seven thousand men, who have not bowed knee to Baal.
11:4|KJV|But what saith the answer of God unto him? I have reserved to myself seven thousand men, who have not bowed the knee to the image of Baal.
11:4|WYC|But what saith God's answer to him?  I have left to me seven thousands of men [I have left to me seven thousand of men], that have not bowed their knees before Baal.
11:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但神的回話是怎麼對他說的？是說，“我為自己留下七千人，是未曾向巴力屈膝的。”
11:5|ASV|Even so then at this present time also there is a remnant according to the election of grace.
11:5|Darby|Thus, then, in the present time also there has been a  remnant according to election of grace.
11:5|KJV|Even so then at this present time also there is a remnant according to the election of grace.
11:5|WYC|So therefore also in this time, the remnants [the reliefs] be made safe, by the choosing [after the choosing] of the grace of God.
11:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在現今的時候，也是這樣，照著恩典的揀選，還有剩下的餘數。
11:6|ASV|But if it is by grace, it is no more of works: otherwise grace is no more grace.
11:6|Darby|But if by grace, no longer of works: since [otherwise]  grace is no more grace.
11:6|KJV|And if by grace, then is it no more of works: otherwise grace is no more grace. But if it be of works, then it is no more grace: otherwise work is no more work.
11:6<version name="WYC">And if <i>it be </i>by the grace of God, <i>it is </i>not now of works; else grace is not now grace.</version>
11:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|既是照著恩典，就不再是本於行為；不然，恩典就不再是恩典了。
11:7|ASV|What then? that which Israel seeketh for, that he obtained not; but the election obtained it, and the rest were hardened:
11:7|Darby|What [is it] then? What Israel seeks for, that he has not  obtained; but the election has obtained, and the rest have been  blinded,
11:7|KJV|What then? Israel hath not obtained that which he seeketh for; but the election hath obtained it, and the rest were blinded.
11:7|WYC|What then? Israel hath not gotten this that he sought [Israel hath not gotten that that he sought], but election hath gotten; and the others be blinded.
11:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這怎麼樣？以色列人所切求的，他們沒有得著，惟有蒙揀選的人得著了，其餘的都成了頑梗不化的。
11:8|ASV|according as it is written, God gave them a spirit of stupor, eyes that they should not see, and ears that they should not hear, unto this very day.
11:8|Darby|according as it is written, God has given to them a spirit  of slumber, eyes not to see, and ears not to hear, unto this  day.
11:8|KJV|(According as it is written, God hath given them the spirit of slumber, eyes that they should not see, and ears that they should not hear;) unto this day.
11:8|WYC|As it is written, God gave to them a spirit of compunction, eyes that they see not, and ears, that they hear not, into this day.
11:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|如經上所記：“神給他們昏睡的靈，看不見的眼，聽不見的耳，直到今日。”
11:9|ASV|And David saith, Let their table be made a snare, and a trap, And a stumblingblock, and a recompense unto them:
11:9|Darby|And David says, Let their table be for a snare, and for a  gin, and for a fall-trap, and for a recompense to them:
11:9|KJV|And David saith, Let their table be made a snare, and a trap, and a stumblingblock, and a recompence unto them:
11:9|WYC|And David saith, Be the board of them made into a snare before them, and into catching, and into cause of stumbling, and into yielding to them [and into catching, and into offence, and into yielding again to them].
11:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|大衛也說，“願他們的筵席成為陷阱，成為網羅，成為絆腳石，作對他們的報應；
11:10|ASV|Let their eyes be darkened, that they may not see, And bow thou down their back always.
11:10|Darby|let their eyes be darkened not to see, and bow down their  back alway.
11:10|KJV|Let their eyes be darkened, that they may not see, and bow down their back alway.
11:10|WYC|Be the eyes of them made dark, that they see not; and bow thou down always the back of them [and bow down all-gates the back of them].
11:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願他們的眼睛昏矇，不能看見；願你時常彎下他們的脊背。”
11:11|ASV|I say then, Did they stumble that they might fall? God forbid: but by their fall salvation is come unto the Gentiles, to provoke them to jealousy.
11:11|Darby|I say then, Have they stumbled in order that they might  fall? Far be the thought: but by their fall [there is]  salvation to the nations to provoke them to jealousy.
11:11|KJV|I say then, Have they stumbled that they should fall? God forbid: but rather through their fall salvation is come unto the Gentiles, for to provoke them to jealousy.
11:11|WYC|Therefore I say, Whether they offended so, that they should fall down?  God forbid [Far be it].  But by the guilt of them health is made to heathen men, that they follow them.
11:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我說，他們失腳是要他們跌倒麼？絕對不是！反倒因他們的過失，救恩便臨到外邦人，好惹動他們妒忌。
11:12|ASV|Now if their fall, is the riches of the world, and their loss the riches of the Gentiles; how much more their fulness?
11:12|Darby|But if their fall [be the] world's wealth, and their loss  [the] wealth of [the] nations, how much rather their fulness?
11:12|KJV|Now if the fall of them be the riches of the world, and the diminishing of them the riches of the Gentiles; how much more their fulness?
11:12<version name="WYC">That if the guilt of them be riches of the world, and the making less of them be riches of heathen men [and the diminishing, <i>or making less</i>, of them be riches of heathen men], how much more the plenty of them?</version>
11:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若他們的過失成為世人的富足，他們的缺乏成為外邦人的富足，何況他們的豐滿？
11:13|ASV|But I speak to you that are Gentiles. Inasmuch then as I am an apostle of Gentiles, I glorify my ministry;
11:13|Darby|For I speak to you, the nations, inasmuch as *I* am  apostle of nations, I glorify my ministry;
11:13|KJV|For I speak to you Gentiles, inasmuch as I am the apostle of the Gentiles, I magnify mine office:
11:13<version name="WYC">But I say to you [Soothly I say to you], heathen men, for as long as I am apostle of heathen men, I shall honour my ministry [I shall honour my ministry, <i>or</i> <i>service</i>],</version>
11:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我是對你們外邦人說的，因我是外邦人的使徒，所以榮耀我的職事，
11:14|ASV|if by any means I may provoke to jealousy them that are my flesh, and may save some of them.
11:14|Darby|if by any means I shall provoke to jealousy [them which  are] my flesh, and shall save some from among them.
11:14|KJV|If by any means I may provoke to emulation them which are my flesh, and might save some of them.
11:14|WYC|if in any manner I stir my flesh for to follow, and that I make some of them safe. [if on any manner I stir my flesh to follow, and I make some of them safe.]
11:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|或者可以惹動我骨肉之親妒忌，好救他們一些人。
11:15|ASV|For if the casting away of them is the reconciling of the world, what shall the receiving of them be, but life from the dead?
11:15|Darby|For if their casting away [be the] world's reconciliation,  what [their] reception but life from among [the] dead?
11:15|KJV|For if the casting away of them be the reconciling of the world, what shall the receiving of them be, but life from the dead?
11:15<version name="WYC">For if the loss of them is the reconciling of the world, what <i>is</i> the taking up [<i>of them</i>], but life of dead <i>men </i>[but life of dead]?</version>
11:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若他們被丟棄，世人就得與神和好，他們被收納，豈不是從死人中復生麼？
11:16|ASV|And if the firstfruit is holy, so is the lump: and if the root is holy, so are the branches.
11:16|Darby|Now if the first-fruit [be] holy, the lump also; and if  the root [be] holy, the branches also.
11:16|KJV|For if the firstfruit be holy, the lump is also holy: and if the root be holy, so are the branches.
11:16<version name="WYC">For if a little part of that that is tasted be holy, the whole gobbet <i>is holy</i>; and if the root is holy, also the branches.</version>
11:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所獻麵團的頭一部分若是聖的，全團也是聖的；樹根若是聖的，樹枝也是聖的。
11:17|ASV|But if some of the branches were broken off, and thou, being a wild olive, wast grafted in among them, and didst become partaker with them of the root of the fatness of the olive tree;
11:17|Darby|Now if some of the branches have been broken out, and  *thou*, being a wild olive tree, hast been grafted in amongst  them, and hast become a fellow-partaker of the root and of the  fatness of the olive tree,
11:17|KJV|And if some of the branches be broken off, and thou, being a wild olive tree, wert grafted in among them, and with them partakest of the root and fatness of the olive tree;
11:17|WYC|What if any of the branches be broken, when thou were a wild olive tree, art grafted among them, and art made fellow of the root, and of the fatness of the olive tree, [That if any of the branches be broken, thou soothly, when thou were a wild olive tree, wert set in among them, and wert made fellow of the root, and of fatness of the olive tree,]
11:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若有幾根枝子被折下來，你這野橄欖得在其中接上去，一同有分於橄欖根的肥汁，
11:18|ASV|glory not over the branches: but if thou gloriest, it is not thou that bearest the root, but the root thee.
11:18|Darby|boast not against the branches; but if thou boast, [it is]  not *thou* bearest the root, but the root thee.
11:18|KJV|Boast not against the branches. But if thou boast, thou bearest not the root, but the root thee.
11:18|WYC|do not thou have glory against the branches [do not thou glory against the branches].  For if thou gloriest, thou bearest not the root, but the root thee.
11:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你就不可向那些枝子誇口；縱然誇口，也不是你托著根，乃是根托著你。
11:19|ASV|Thou wilt say then, Branches were broken off, that I might be grafted in.
11:19|Darby|Thou wilt say then, The branches have been broken out in  order that *I* might be grafted in.
11:19|KJV|Thou wilt say then, The branches were broken off, that I might be grafted in.
11:19|WYC|Therefore thou sayest, The branches be broken, that I be grafted in [that I be inset].
11:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，你要說，那些枝子被折下來，是特為叫我接上去。
11:20|ASV|Well; by their unbelief they were broken off, and thou standest by thy faith. Be not highminded, but fear:
11:20|Darby|Right: they have been broken out through unbelief, and  *thou* standest through faith. Be not high-minded, but fear:
11:20|KJV|Well; because of unbelief they were broken off, and thou standest by faith. Be not highminded, but fear:
11:20|WYC|Well, for unbelief the branches be broken; but thou standest by faith.  Do not thou understand high things [Do not thou savour high thing], but dread thou,
11:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不錯，他們因著不信，所以被折下來，你因著信，所以站立得住。你不可心思高傲，倒要懼怕；
11:21|ASV|for if God spared not the natural branches, neither will he spare thee.
11:21|Darby|if God indeed has not spared the natural branches; lest it  might be he spare not thee either.
11:21|KJV|For if God spared not the natural branches, take heed lest he also spare not thee.
11:21<version name="WYC">for if God spared not the natural branches, [<i>see thou</i>] lest peradventure he spare not thee.</version>
11:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神若不吝惜本來的枝子，也必不吝惜你。
11:22|ASV|Behold then the goodness and severity of God: toward them that fell, severity; but toward thee, God's goodness, if thou continue in his goodness: otherwise thou also shalt be cut off.
11:22|Darby|Behold then [the] goodness and severity of God: upon them  who have fallen, severity; upon thee goodness of God, if thou  shalt abide in goodness, since [otherwise] *thou* also wilt be  cut away.
11:22|KJV|Behold therefore the goodness and severity of God: on them which fell, severity; but toward thee, goodness, if thou continue in his goodness: otherwise thou also shalt be cut off.
11:22|WYC|Therefore see the goodness, and the fierceness of God; yea, the fierceness into them that fell down, but the goodness of God into thee, if thou dwellest in goodness [if thou shalt dwell in goodness], else also thou shalt be cut down.
11:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你看神的恩慈和嚴厲：對那跌倒的人是嚴厲，對你卻是神的恩慈，只要你常留在祂的恩慈中；不然，你也要被砍下來。
11:23|ASV|And they also, if they continue not in their unbelief, shall be grafted in: for God is able to graft them in again.
11:23|Darby|And *they* too, if they abide not in unbelief, shall be  grafted in; for God is able again to graft them in.
11:23|KJV|And they also, if they abide not still in unbelief, shall be grafted in: for God is able to graft them in again.
11:23|WYC|Yea, and they shall be set in, if they dwell not in unbelief.  For God is mighty, to set them in again. [But, and they shall be inset, if they shall not dwell in unbelief.  Forsooth God is mighty, again to inset them.]
11:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|而且他們若不是常留於不信中，仍要被接上，因為神能彀把他們重新接上。
11:24|ASV|For if thou wast cut out of that which is by nature a wild olive tree, and wast grafted contrary to nature into a good olive tree; how much more shall these, which are the natural  branches, be grafted into their own olive tree?
11:24|Darby|For if *thou* hast been cut out of the olive tree wild by  nature, and, contrary to nature, hast been grafted into the  good olive tree, how much rather shall they, who are according  to nature be grafted into their own olive tree?
11:24|KJV|For if thou wert cut out of the olive tree which is wild by nature, and wert grafted contrary to nature into a good olive tree: how much more shall these, which be the natural branches, be grafted into their own olive tree?
11:24<version name="WYC">For if thou art cut down of the natural wild olive tree, and against kind art set into a good olive tree, how much more they that <i>be</i> by kind, shall be set in their olive tree? <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21251a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
11:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你是從那天然的野橄欖樹上砍下來的，尚且逆著性得接在栽種的橄欖樹上，何況這些天然的枝子，豈不更要接在自己的橄欖樹上麼？
11:25|ASV|For I would not, brethren, have you ignorant of this mystery, lest ye be wise in your own conceits, that a hardening in part hath befallen Israel, until the fulness of the Gentiles be come in;
11:25|Darby|For I do not wish you to be ignorant, brethren, of this  mystery, that ye may not be wise in your own conceits, that  blindness in part is happened to Israel, until the fulness of  the nations be come in;
11:25|KJV|For I would not, brethren, that ye should be ignorant of this mystery, lest ye should be wise in your own conceits; that blindness in part is happened to Israel, until the fulness of the Gentiles be come in.
11:25|WYC|But, brethren, I will not that ye not know this mystery, that ye be not wise to yourselves; for blindness hath fallen a part in Israel, till that the plenty of heathen men entered, [Forsooth, brethren, I will not that ye unknow this mystery, that ye be not wise to yourselves; for blindness hath felled of part in Israel, till the plenty of heathen men entered,]
11:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，我不願意你們不知道這奧祕，（恐怕你們自以為精明，）就是以色列人有幾分硬心，直到外邦人的數目添滿了，
11:26|ASV|and so all Israel shall be saved: even as it is written, There shall come out of Zion the Deliverer; He shall turn away ungodliness from Jacob:
11:26|Darby|and so all Israel shall be saved. According as it is  written, The deliverer shall come out of Zion; he shall turn  away ungodliness from Jacob.
11:26|KJV|And so all Israel shall be saved: as it is written, There shall come out of Sion the Deliverer, and shall turn away ungodliness from Jacob:
11:26|WYC|and so all Israel should be made safe.  As it is written, He shall come of Sion, that shall deliver, and turn away the wickedness of Jacob [and turn away the unpiety of Jacob].
11:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是以色列全家都要得救，如經上所記：“必有拯救者從錫安出來，祂要從雅各家消除不虔。
11:27|ASV|And this is my covenant unto them, When I shall take away their sins.
11:27|Darby|And this is the covenant from me to them, when I shall  have taken away their sins.
11:27|KJV|For this is my covenant unto them, when I shall take away their sins.
11:27|WYC|And this testament to them of me, when I shall do away their sins.
11:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我除去他們罪的時候，這就是我與他們所立的約。”
11:28|ASV|As touching the gospel, they are enemies for your sake: but as touching the election, they are beloved for the fathers' sake.
11:28|Darby|As regards the glad tidings, [they are] enemies on your  account; but as regards election, beloved on account of the  fathers.
11:28|KJV|As concerning the gospel, they are enemies for your sakes: but as touching the election, they are beloved for the father's sakes.
11:28<version name="WYC">After the gospel <i>they be </i>enemies for you, but <i>they be</i> most dear-worthy by the election [after the election] for the fathers.</version>
11:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就著福音說，他們因你們的緣故是仇敵；但就著揀選說，他們因列祖的緣故是蒙愛的。
11:29|ASV|For the gifts and the calling of God are not repented of.
11:29|Darby|For the gifts and the calling of God [are] not subject to  repentance.
11:29|KJV|For the gifts and calling of God are without repentance.
11:29|WYC|And the gifts and the calling of God be without repenting. [Soothly the gifts and calling of God be without repenting.]
11:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神的恩賜和呼召，是沒有後悔的。
11:30|ASV|For as ye in time past were disobedient to God, but now have obtained mercy by their disobedience,
11:30|Darby|For as indeed *ye* [also] once have not believed in God,  but now have been objects of mercy through the unbelief of  *these*;
11:30|KJV|For as ye in times past have not believed God, yet have now obtained mercy through their unbelief:
11:30|WYC|And as sometime also ye believed not to God, but now ye have gotten mercy for the unbelief of them;
11:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們從前不信從神，如今卻因他們的不信從，蒙了憐憫；
11:31|ASV|even so have these also now been disobedient, that by the mercy shown to you they also may now obtain mercy.
11:31|Darby|so these also have now not believed in your mercy, in  order that *they* also may be objects of mercy.
11:31|KJV|Even so have these also now not believed, that through your mercy they also may obtain mercy.
11:31|WYC|so and these now believed not into your mercy [so and these now believed not to your mercy], that also they get mercy.
11:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|照樣，他們現今也是不信從的，叫他們因著你們所蒙的憐憫，現今也就蒙憐憫。
11:32|ASV|For God hath shut up all unto disobedience, that he might have mercy upon all.
11:32|Darby|For God hath shut up together all in unbelief, in order  that he might shew mercy to all.
11:32|KJV|For God hath concluded them all in unbelief, that he might have mercy upon all.
11:32|WYC|For God closed all things together in unbelief [Forsooth God closed together all things in unbelief], that he have mercy on all.
11:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神將眾人都圈在不信從之中，為要憐憫眾人。
11:33|ASV|O the depth of the riches both of the wisdom and the knowledge of God! how unsearchable are his judgments, and his ways past tracing out!
11:33|Darby|O depth of riches both of [the] wisdom and knowledge of  God! how unsearchable his judgments, and untraceable his ways!
11:33|KJV|O the depth of the riches both of the wisdom and knowledge of God! how unsearchable are his judgments, and his ways past finding out!
11:33<version name="WYC">O! the highness of the riches of the wisdom and of the knowing of God; how incomprehensible be his dooms, and his ways <i>be</i> unsearchable. [O! the depth of the riches of wisdom and knowing of God; how incomprehensible be his dooms, and his ways unsearchable.]</version>
11:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|深哉，神的豐富、智慧和知識！祂的判斷何其難測，祂的道路何其難尋！
11:34|ASV|For who hath known the mind of the Lord? or who hath been his counsellor?
11:34|Darby|For who has known [the] mind of [the] Lord, or who has  been his counsellor?
11:34|KJV|For who hath known the mind of the Lord? or who hath been his counsellor?
11:34|WYC|For why who knew the wit of the Lord, or who was his counsellor?
11:34|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|誰曾知道主的心思，誰曾作過祂的策士？
11:35|ASV|or who hath first given to him, and it shall be recompensed unto him again?
11:35|Darby|or who has first given to him, and it shall be rendered to  him?
11:35|KJV|Or who hath first given to him, and it shall be recompensed unto him again?
11:35|WYC|or who former gave to him, and it shall be requited [again] to him?
11:35|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|誰曾先給了祂，使祂後來償還？
11:36<version name="ASV">For of him, and through him, and unto him, are all things. To him be the glory for ever. Amen. </p><p /><br /></version>
11:36<version name="Darby">For of him, and through him, and for him [are] all things:  to him be glory for ever. Amen. </p><p /><br /></version>
11:36<version name="KJV">For of him, and through him, and to him, are all things: to whom be glory for ever. Amen.</p><p /><br /></version>
11:36<version name="WYC">For of him, and by him, and in him be all things.  To him <i>be</i> glory into worlds [of worlds].  Amen.</version>
11:36|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為萬有都是本於祂、藉著祂、並歸於祂；願榮耀歸與祂，直到永遠。阿們。
12:1|ASV|I beseech you therefore, brethren, by the mercies of God, to present your bodies a living sacrifice, holy, acceptable to God, which is your spiritual service.
12:1|Darby|I beseech you therefore, brethren, by the compassions of  God, to present your bodies a living sacrifice, holy,  acceptable to God, [which is] your intelligent service.
12:1|KJV|I beseech you therefore, brethren, by the mercies of God, that ye present your bodies a living sacrifice, holy, acceptable unto God, which is your reasonable service.
12:1|WYC|Therefore, brethren, I beseech you by the mercy of God, that ye give your bodies a living sacrifice, holy, pleasing to God, and your service reasonable.
12:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以弟兄們，我藉著神的憐恤勸你們，將身體獻上，當作聖別並討神喜悅的活祭，這是你們合理的事奉。
12:2|ASV|And be not fashioned according to this world: but be ye transformed by the renewing of your mind, and ye may prove what is the good and acceptable and perfect will of God.
12:2|Darby|And be not conformed to this world, but be transformed by  the renewing of [your] mind, that ye may prove what [is] the  good and acceptable and perfect will of God.
12:2|KJV|And be not conformed to this world: but be ye transformed by the renewing of your mind, that ye may prove what is that good, and acceptable, and perfect, will of God.
12:2|WYC|And do not ye be conformed to this world, but be ye reformed in newness of your wit, that ye prove which is the will of God, good, and well pleasing, and perfect.
12:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不要模倣這世代，反要藉著心思的更新而變化，叫你們驗證何為神那美好、可喜悅、並純全的旨意。
12:3|ASV|For I say, through the grace that was given me, to every man that is among you, not to think of himself more highly than he ought to think; but to think as to think soberly, according as God hath dealt to each man a measure of faith.
12:3|Darby|For I say, through the grace which has been given to me, to  every one that is among you, not to have high thoughts above  what he should think; but to think so as to be wise, as God has  dealt to each a measure of faith.
12:3|KJV|For I say, through the grace given unto me, to every man that is among you, not to think of himself more highly than he ought to think; but to think soberly, according as God hath dealt to every man the measure of faith.
12:3<version name="WYC">For I say, by the grace that is given to me, to all that be among you, that ye understand not more than it behooveth to understand, but for to understand to soberness [to not savour,<i> or know, </i>more than it behooveth to know, but to know to soberness]; and to each man, as God hath parted the measure of faith.</version>
12:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我藉著所賜給我的恩典，對你們各人說，不要看自己過於所當看的，乃要照著神所分給各人信心的度量，看得清明適度。
12:4|ASV|For even as we have many members in one body, and all the members have not the same office:
12:4|Darby|For, as in one body we have many members, but all the  members have not the same office;
12:4|KJV|For as we have many members in one body, and all members have not the same office:
12:4<version name="WYC">For as in one body we have many members, but all the members have not the same deed [soothly all the members have not the same act, <i>or deed</i>];</version>
12:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|正如我們一個身體上有好些肢體，但肢體不都有一樣的功用；
12:5|ASV|so we, who are many, are one body in Christ, and severally members one of another.
12:5|Darby|thus we, [being] many, are one body in Christ, and each one  members one of the other.
12:5|KJV|So we, being many, are one body in Christ, and every one members one of another.
12:5<version name="WYC">so we many be one body in Christ [so we be many, one body in Christ], and each <i>be</i> members one of another.</version>
12:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們這許多人，在基督裡是一個身體，並且各個互相作肢體，也是如此。
12:6|ASV|And having gifts differing according to the grace that was given to us, whether prophecy, let us prophesy according to the proportion of our faith;
12:6|Darby|But having different gifts, according to the grace which  has been given to us, whether [it be] prophecy, [let us  prophesy] according to the proportion of faith;
12:6|KJV|Having then gifts differing according to the grace that is given to us, whether prophecy, let us prophesy according to the proportion of faith;
12:6|WYC|Therefore we that have gifts diversing [Therefore having gifts diversing], after the grace that is given to us, either prophecy, after the reason of faith;
12:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|照著所賜給我們的恩典，我們得了不同的恩賜：或申言，就當照著信心的程度申言；
12:7|ASV|or ministry, let us give ourselves to our ministry; or he that teacheth, to his teaching;
12:7|Darby|or service, [let us occupy ourselves] in service; or he  that teaches, in teaching;
12:7|KJV|Or ministry, let us wait on our ministering: or he that teacheth, on teaching;
12:7<version name="WYC">either service, in ministering; either he that teacheth, in teaching; [either ministry, <i>or service</i>, in ministering; or he that teacheth, in teaching;]</version>
12:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|或服事，就當忠於服事；或作教導的，就當忠於教導；
12:8|ASV|or he that exhorteth, to his exhorting: he that giveth, let him do it with liberality; he that ruleth, with diligence; he that showeth mercy, with cheerfulness.
12:8|Darby|or he that exhorts, in exhortation; he that gives, in  simplicity; he that leads, with diligence; he that shews mercy,  with cheerfulness.
12:8|KJV|Or he that exhorteth, on exhortation: he that giveth, let him do it with simplicity; he that ruleth, with diligence; he that sheweth mercy, with cheerfulness.
12:8<version name="WYC">he that stirreth softly, in admonishing [he that stirreth softly, in exhortation, <i>or admonishing</i>]; he that giveth, in simpleness; he that is sovereign <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21271a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>, in busyness; he that hath mercy, in gladness.</version>
12:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|或作勸勉的，就當忠於勸勉；分授的，就當單純；帶領的，就當殷勤；憐憫人的，就當甘心樂意。
12:9|ASV|Let love be without hypocrisy. Abhor that which is evil; cleave to that which is good.
12:9|Darby|Let love be unfeigned; abhorring evil; cleaving to good:
12:9|KJV|Let love be without dissimulation. Abhor that which is evil; cleave to that which is good.
12:9<version name="WYC">Love without feigning, hating evil, drawing to good [cleaving, <i>or fast drawing</i>, to good thing];</version>
12:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|愛不可假冒，惡要厭棄，善要貼近。
12:10|ASV|In love of the brethren be tenderly affectioned one to another; in honor preferring one another;
12:10|Darby|as to brotherly love, kindly affectioned towards one  another: as to honour, each taking the lead in paying it to the  other:
12:10|KJV|Be kindly affectioned one to another with brotherly love; in honour preferring one another;
12:10|WYC|loving together the charity of brotherhood.  Each come before to worship (the) other [Coming before together in honour];
12:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|愛弟兄，要彼此親熱；恭敬人，要互相爭先。
12:11|ASV|in diligence not slothful; fervent in spirit; serving the Lord;
12:11|Darby|as to diligent zealousness, not slothful; in spirit  fervent; serving the Lord.
12:11|KJV|Not slothful in business; fervent in spirit; serving the Lord;
12:11|WYC|not slow in busyness, fervent in spirit, serving to the Lord,
12:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|殷勤不可懶惰，要靈裡火熱，常常服事主。
12:12|ASV|rejoicing in hope; patient in tribulation; continuing stedfastly in prayer;
12:12|Darby|As regards hope, rejoicing: as regards tribulation,  enduring: as regards prayer, persevering:
12:12|KJV|Rejoicing in hope; patient in tribulation; continuing instant in prayer;
12:12|WYC|joying in hope, patient in tribulation, busy in prayer,
12:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在指望中要喜樂，在患難中要忍耐，在禱告上要堅定持續，
12:13|ASV|communicating to the necessities of the saints; given to hospitality.
12:13|Darby|distributing to the necessities of the saints; given to  hospitality.
12:13|KJV|Distributing to the necessity of saints; given to hospitality.
12:13|WYC|giving good to the needs of saints, keeping hospitality.
12:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在聖徒缺乏上要有交通，待客要追尋機會。
12:14|ASV|Bless them that persecute you; bless, and curse not.
12:14|Darby|Bless them that persecute you; bless, and curse not.
12:14|KJV|Bless them which persecute you: bless, and curse not.
12:14|WYC|Bless ye men that pursue you; bless ye, and do not ye curse;
12:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|逼迫你們的，要為他們祝福；只要祝福，不可咒詛。
12:15|ASV|Rejoice with them that rejoice; weep with them that weep.
12:15|Darby|Rejoice with those that rejoice, weep with those that  weep.
12:15|KJV|Rejoice with them that do rejoice, and weep with them that weep.
12:15|WYC|for to joy with men that joy, for to weep with men that weep.
12:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|與喜樂的人要同樂，與哀哭的人要同哭。
12:16|ASV|Be of the same mind one toward another. Set not your mind on high things, but condescend to things that are lowly. Be not wise in your own conceits.
12:16|Darby|Have the same respect one for another, not minding high  things, but going along with the lowly: be not wise in your own  eyes:
12:16|KJV|Be of the same mind one toward another. Mind not high things, but condescend to men of low estate. Be not wise in your own conceits.
12:16<version name="WYC">Feel ye the same thing together; not understanding high things, but consenting to meek things <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21279b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup>.  Do not ye be prudent with yourselves;</version>
12:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|要彼此思念相同的事，不要思念高傲的事，倒要俯就卑微的人，不要自以為精明。
12:17|ASV|Render to no man evil for evil. Take thought for things honorable in the sight of all men.
12:17|Darby|recompensing to no one evil for evil: providing things  honest before all men:
12:17|KJV|Recompense to no man evil for evil. Provide things honest in the sight of all men.
12:17|WYC|to no man yielding evil for evil, but purvey ye good things, not only before God, but also before all men.
12:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不要以惡報惡，要準備在眾人面前作善美的事。
12:18|ASV|If it be possible, as much as in you lieth, be at peace with all men.
12:18|Darby|if possible, as far as depends on you, living in peace  with all men;
12:18|KJV|If it be possible, as much as lieth in you, live peaceably with all men.
12:18|WYC|If it may be done, that that is of you, have ye peace with all men.
12:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若是可能，總要盡力與眾人和睦。
12:19|ASV|Avenge not yourselves, beloved, but give place unto the wrath of God: for it is written, Vengeance belongeth unto me; I will recompense, saith the Lord.
12:19|Darby|not avenging yourselves, beloved, but give place to wrath;  for it is written, Vengeance [belongs] to me, *I* will  recompense, saith the Lord.
12:19|KJV|Dearly beloved, avenge not yourselves, but rather give place unto wrath: for it is written, Vengeance is mine; I will repay, saith the Lord.
12:19<version name="WYC">Ye most dear brethren, not defending yourselves, but give ye place to wrath [Ye most dear-worthy brethren, not defending, <i>or venging</i>, yourselves, but give ye place to ire, <i>or</i> <i>wrath</i>]; for it is written, The Lord saith, To me vengeance, and I shall yield [again].</version>
12:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|親愛的，不要為自己伸冤，寧可給神的忿怒留地步，因為經上記著：“主說，伸冤在我，我必報應。”
12:20|ASV|But if thine enemy hunger, feed him; if he thirst, give him to drink: for in so doing thou shalt heap coals of fire upon his head.
12:20|Darby|If therefore thine enemy should hunger, feed him; if he  should thirst, give him drink; for, so doing, thou shalt heap  coals of fire upon his head.
12:20|KJV|Therefore if thine enemy hunger, feed him; if he thirst, give him drink: for in so doing thou shalt heap coals of fire on his head.
12:20|WYC|But if thine enemy hungereth, feed thou him; if he thirsteth, give thou drink to him; for thou doing this thing shalt gather together coals on his head. [But if thine enemy shall hunger, feed him; if he thirsteth, give drink to him; forsooth doing these things thou shalt gather together coals on his head.]
12:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|反而“你的仇敵若餓了，就給他喫，若渴了，就給他喝，因為你這樣行，就是把炭火堆在他的頭上。”
12:21<version name="ASV">Be not overcome of evil, but overcome evil with good. </p><p /><br /></version>
12:21<version name="Darby">Be not overcome by evil, but overcome evil with good. </p><p /><br /></version>
12:21<version name="KJV">Be not overcome of evil, but overcome evil with good.</p><p /><br /></version>
12:21|WYC|Do not thou be overcome of evil, but overcome thou evil by good.
12:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你不可為惡所勝，反要以善勝惡。
13:1|ASV|Let every soul be in subjection to the higher powers: for there is no power but of God; and the powers that be are ordained of God.
13:1|Darby|Let every soul be subject to the authorities that are above  [him]. For there is no authority except from God; and those  that exist are set up by God.
13:1|KJV|Let every soul be subject unto the higher powers. For there is no power but of God: the powers that be are ordained of God.
13:1|WYC|Every soul be subject to higher powers.  For there is no power but of God, and those things that be of God, be ordained.
13:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在上有權柄的，人人都當服從，因為沒有權柄不是從神來的，凡掌權的都是神所設立的。
13:2|ASV|Therefore he that resisteth the power, withstandeth the ordinance of God: and they that withstand shall receive to themselves judgment.
13:2|Darby|So that he that sets himself in opposition to the authority  resists the ordinance of God; and they who [thus] resist shall  bring sentence of guilt on themselves.
13:2|KJV|Whosoever therefore resisteth the power, resisteth the ordinance of God: and they that resist shall receive to themselves damnation.
13:2|WYC|Therefore he that against-standeth power, against-standeth the ordinance of God; and they that against-stand, get to themselves damnation.
13:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以抗拒掌權的，就是抗拒神的設立；抗拒的必自招處罰。
13:3|ASV|For rulers are not a terror to the good work, but to the evil. And wouldest thou have no fear of the power? do that which is good, and thou shalt have praise from the same:
13:3|Darby|For rulers are not a terror to a good work, but to an evil  [one]. Dost thou desire then not to be afraid of the authority?  practise [what is] good, and thou shalt have praise from it;
13:3|KJV|For rulers are not a terror to good works, but to the evil. Wilt thou then not be afraid of the power? do that which is good, and thou shalt have praise of the same:
13:3|WYC|For princes be not to the dread of good work, but of evil.  But wilt thou, that thou dread not power?  Do thou good thing, and thou shalt have praising of it [Soothly wilt thou not dread power?  Do good, and thou shalt have praising of it];
13:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|作官的原不是叫行善的懼怕，乃是叫作惡的懼怕。你願意不懼怕掌權的麼？你只要行善，就可得他的稱讚，
13:4|ASV|for he is a minister of God to thee for good. But if thou do that which is evil, be afraid; for he beareth not the sword in vain: for he is a minister of God, an avenger for wrath to him that doeth evil.
13:4|Darby|for it is God's minister to thee for good. But if thou  practisest evil, fear; for it bears not the sword in vain; for  it is God's minister, an avenger for wrath to him that does  evil.
13:4|KJV|For he is the minister of God to thee for good. But if thou do that which is evil, be afraid; for he beareth not the sword in vain: for he is the minister of God, a revenger to execute wrath upon him that doeth evil.
13:4|WYC|for he is the minister of God to thee into good.  But if thou doest evil, dread thou [Soothly, if thou doest evil, dread]; for not without cause he beareth the sword, for he is the minister of God, venger into wrath to him that doeth evil.
13:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為他是神的僕人，是與你有益的。但你若作惡，就當懼怕，因為他不是徒然佩劍，他是神的僕人，是伸冤的，使忿怒臨到那作惡的。
13:5|ASV|Wherefore ye must needs be in subjection, not only because of the wrath, but also for conscience' sake.
13:5|Darby|Wherefore it is necessary to be subject, not only on  account of wrath, but also on account of conscience.
13:5|KJV|Wherefore ye must needs be subject, not only for wrath, but also for conscience sake.
13:5|WYC|And therefore by need be ye subject, not only for wrath, but also for conscience.
13:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以你們必須服從，不但是因為忿怒，也是因為良心。
13:6|ASV|For this cause ye pay tribute also; for they are ministers of God's service, attending continually upon this very thing.
13:6|Darby|For on this account ye pay tribute also; for they are God's  officers, attending continually on this very thing.
13:6|KJV|For for this cause pay ye tribute also: for they are God's ministers, attending continually upon this very thing.
13:6|WYC|For therefore [and] ye give tributes, they be the ministers of God, and serve for this same thing [for this same thing serving].
13:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們上稅也為這緣故，因他們是神的僕役，為這差事專責服役。
13:7|ASV|Render to all their dues: tribute to whom tribute is due; custom to whom custom; fear to whom fear; honor to whom honor.
13:7|Darby|Render to all their dues: to whom tribute [is due],  tribute; to whom custom, custom; to whom fear, fear; to whom  honour, honour.
13:7|KJV|Render therefore to all their dues: tribute to whom tribute is due; custom to whom custom; fear to whom fear; honour to whom honour.
13:7<version name="WYC">Therefore yield ye to all men debts, to whom tribute, tribute, to whom toll, toll [to whom toll, <i>or custom for things borne about</i>, toll, <i>or such custom</i>], to whom dread, dread, to whom honour, honour.</version>
13:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡人所當得的，就給他們：當得稅的，就給他上稅；當得捐的，就給他納捐；當懼怕的，就懼怕他；當尊敬的，就尊敬他。
13:8|ASV|Owe no man anything, save to love one another: for he that loveth his neighbor hath fulfilled the law.
13:8|Darby|Owe no one anything, unless to love one another: for he  that loves another has fulfilled the law.
13:8|KJV|Owe no man any thing, but to love one another: for he that loveth another hath fulfilled the law.
13:8|WYC|To no man owe ye any thing, but that ye love together.  For he that loveth his neighbour, hath fulfilled the law.
13:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|凡事都不可虧欠人，惟有彼此相愛，要常以為虧欠，因為愛人的就完全了律法。
13:9|ASV|For this, Thou shalt not commit adultery, Thou shalt not kill, Thou shalt not steal, Thou shalt not covet, and if there be any other commandment, it is summed up in this word, namely, Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself.
13:9|Darby|For, Thou shalt not commit adultery, Thou shalt not kill,  Thou shalt not steal, Thou shalt not lust; and if there be any  other commandment, it is summed up in this word, namely, Thou  shalt love thy neighbour as thyself.
13:9|KJV|For this, Thou shalt not commit adultery, Thou shalt not kill, Thou shalt not steal, Thou shalt not bear false witness, Thou shalt not covet; and if there be any other commandment, it is briefly comprehended in this saying, namely, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself.
13:9<version name="WYC">For, Thou shalt do no lechery [Thou shalt not do lechery], Thou shalt not slay, Thou shalt not steal, Thou shalt not say false witnessing, Thou shalt not covet the thing of thy neighbour, and if there be any other commandment, it is enstored, <i>or included</i> [it is enstored, <i>or enclosed</i>], in this word, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself.</version>
13:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為“不可姦淫，不可殺人，不可偷盜，不可貪心，”以及任何別的誡命，都總括在“要愛鄰舍如同自己”這一句話裡面了。
13:10|ASV|Love worketh no ill to his neighbor: love therefore is the fulfilment of the law.
13:10|Darby|Love works no ill to its neighbour; love therefore [is  the] whole law.
13:10|KJV|Love worketh no ill to his neighbour: therefore love is the fulfilling of the law.
13:10|WYC|The love of thy neighbour worketh not evil; therefore love is the fulfilling of the law.
13:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|愛是不加害與鄰舍的，所以愛乃是律法的完滿。
13:11|ASV|And this, knowing the season, that already it is time for you to awake out of sleep: for now is salvation nearer to us than when we first believed.
13:11|Darby|This also, knowing the time, that it is already time that  *we* should be aroused out of sleep; for now [is] our salvation  nearer than when we believed.
13:11|KJV|And that, knowing the time, that now it is high time to awake out of sleep: for now is our salvation nearer than when we believed.
13:11<version name="WYC">And we know this time, that the hour is now, that we rise from sleep; for now is our health near(er), than when we believed. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21295a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
13:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|再者，你們曉得這時期，現在就是你們該睡醒的時刻了，因為我們得救，現今比初信的時候更近了。
13:12|ASV|The night is far spent, and the day is at hand: let us therefore cast off the works of darkness, and let us put on the armor of light.
13:12|Darby|The night is far spent, and the day is near; let us cast  away therefore the works of darkness, and let us put on the  armour of light.
13:12|KJV|The night is far spent, the day is at hand: let us therefore cast off the works of darkness, and let us put on the armour of light.
13:12|WYC|The night went before, but the day hath approached [forsooth the day hath nighed].  Therefore cast we away the works of darknesses, and be we clothed in the armours of light [and be we clothed with the armours of light].
13:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|黑夜已深，白晝將近，所以我們當脫去黑暗的行為，穿上光的兵器。
13:13|ASV|Let us walk becomingly, as in the day; not in revelling and drunkenness, not in chambering and wantonness, not in strife and jealousy.
13:13|Darby|As in the day, let us walk becomingly; not in rioting and  drunkenness, not in chambering and lasciviousness, not in  strife and emulation.
13:13|KJV|Let us walk honestly, as in the day; not in rioting and drunkenness, not in chambering and wantonness, not in strife and envying.
13:13|WYC|As in [the] day wander we honestly, not in superfluous feasts [not in oft eatings] and drunkennesses, not in beds [not in bedchambers] and unchastities, not in strife and in envy;
13:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|行事為人要端正得體，好像在白晝；不可荒宴醉酒，不可縱慾淫蕩，不可爭競嫉妒；
13:14<version name="ASV">But put ye on the Lord Jesus Christ, and make not provision for the flesh, to fulfil the lusts thereof. </p><p /><br /></version>
13:14<version name="Darby">But put on the Lord Jesus Christ, and do not take  forethought for the flesh to [fulfil its] lusts. </p><p /><br /></version>
13:14<version name="KJV">But put ye on the Lord Jesus Christ, and make not provision for the flesh, to fulfil the lusts thereof.</p><p /><br /></version>
13:14<version name="WYC">but be ye clothed in the Lord Jesus Christ, and do ye not the busyness of flesh in desires [and do ye not the care, <i>or</i> <i>busyness</i>, of flesh in desires].</version>
13:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|總要穿上主耶穌基督，不要為肉體打算，去放縱私慾。
14:1|ASV|But him that is weak in faith receive ye, yet not for decision of scruples.
14:1|Darby|Now him that is weak in the faith receive, not to [the]  determining of questions of reasoning.
14:1|KJV|Him that is weak in the faith receive ye, but not to doubtful disputations.
14:1<version name="WYC">But take ye a frail man in belief, not in deemings of thoughts. [Forsooth take ye a sick man in belief, not in deceptions, <i>or</i> <i>disputations</i>, of thoughts.]</version>
14:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|信心軟弱的，你們要接納，但不是為判斷所爭論的事。
14:2|ASV|One man hath faith to eat all things: but he that is weak eateth herbs.
14:2|Darby|One man is assured that he may eat all things; but the weak  eats herbs.
14:2|KJV|For one believeth that he may eat all things: another, who is weak, eateth herbs.
14:2<version name="WYC">For another man believeth, that he may eat all things; but he that is frail [but he that is sick, <i>or unsteadfast</i>], eat worts.</version>
14:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有人信百物都可喫，但那軟弱的，只喫蔬菜。
14:3|ASV|Let not him that eateth set at nought him that eateth not; and let not him that eateth not judge him that eateth: for God hath received him.
14:3|Darby|Let not him that eats make little of him that eats not; and  let not him that eats not judge him that eats: for God has  received him.
14:3|KJV|Let not him that eateth despise him that eateth not; and let not him which eateth not judge him that eateth: for God hath received him.
14:3|WYC|He that eateth, despise not him that eateth not; and he that eateth not, deem not him that eateth.  For God hath taken him to him(self) [For why God hath taken him].
14:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|喫的人不可輕視不喫的人，不喫的人也不可審判喫的人，因為神已經接納他了。
14:4|ASV|Who art thou that judgest the servant of another? to his own lord he standeth or falleth. Yea, he shall be made to stand; for the Lord hath power to make him stand.
14:4|Darby|Who art *thou* that judgest the servant of another? to his  own master he stands or falls. And he shall be made to stand;  for the Lord is able to make him stand.
14:4|KJV|Who art thou that judgest another man's servant? to his own master he standeth or falleth. Yea, he shall be holden up: for God is able to make him stand.
14:4<version name="WYC">Who art thou, that deemest another's servant?  To his lord he standeth, or falleth <i>from him</i>.  But he shall stand; for the Lord is mighty to make him perfect <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21302a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup>.</version>
14:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你是誰，竟審判別人的家僕？他或站住或跌倒，自有他的主人在，而且他也必要站住，因為主能使他站住。
14:5|ASV|One man esteemeth one day above another: another esteemeth every day alike. Let each man be fully assured in his own mind.
14:5|Darby|One man esteems day more than day; another esteems every  day [alike]. Let each be fully persuaded in his own mind.
14:5|KJV|One man esteemeth one day above another: another esteemeth every day alike. Let every man be fully persuaded in his own mind.
14:5|WYC|For why one deemeth a day betwixt [between] a day, another deemeth each day.  Each man increase in his wit.
14:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有人斷定這日比那日強，有人斷定日日都一樣，只是各人自己的心思要堅信不移。
14:6|ASV|He that regardeth the day, regardeth it unto the Lord: and he that eateth, eateth unto the Lord, for he giveth God thanks; and he that eateth not, unto the Lord he eateth not, and giveth God thanks.
14:6|Darby|He that regards the day, regards it to [the] Lord. And he  that eats, eats to [the] Lord, for he gives God thanks; and he  that does not eat, [it is] to [the] Lord he does not eat, and  gives God thanks.
14:6|KJV|He that regardeth the day, regardeth it unto the Lord; and he that regardeth not the day, to the Lord he doth not regard it. He that eateth, eateth to the Lord, for he giveth God thanks; and he that eateth not, to the Lord he eateth not, and giveth God thanks.
14:6<version name="WYC">He that understandeth the day, understandeth to the Lord [He that savoureth, <i>or understandeth</i>, the day, understandeth to the Lord].  And he that eateth, eateth to the Lord, for he doeth thankings to God.  And he that eateth not, eateth not to the Lord, and doeth thankings to God.</version>
14:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|守日的人是向主守的，喫的人是向主喫的，因為他感謝神；不喫的人是向主不喫的，他也感謝神。
14:7|ASV|For none of us liveth to himself, and none dieth to himself.
14:7|Darby|For none of us lives to himself, and none dies to himself.
14:7|KJV|For none of us liveth to himself, and no man dieth to himself.
14:7|WYC|For no man of us liveth to himself, and no man dieth to himself.
14:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們沒有一個人向自己活，也沒有一個人向自己死；
14:8|ASV|For whether we live, we live unto the Lord; or whether we die, we die unto the Lord: whether we live therefore, or die, we are the Lord's.
14:8|Darby|For both if we should live, [it is] to the Lord we live;  and if we should die, [it is] to the Lord we die: both if we  should live then, and if we should die, we are the Lord's.
14:8|KJV|For whether we live, we live unto the Lord; and whether we die, we die unto the Lord: whether we live therefore, or die, we are the Lord's.
14:8|WYC|For whether we live, we live to the Lord; and whether we die, we die to the Lord.  Therefore whether we live or die, we be of the Lord [we be (the) Lord's].
14:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們若活著，是向主活；若死了，是向主死。所以我們或活或死，總是主的人。
14:9|ASV|For to this end Christ died and lived again, that he might be Lord of both the dead and the living.
14:9|Darby|For to this [end] Christ has died and lived [again], that  he might rule over both dead and living.
14:9|KJV|For to this end Christ both died, and rose, and revived, that he might be Lord both of the dead and living.
14:9|WYC|For why for this thing Christ was dead, and rose again, that he be Lord both of quick and of dead men [that he be Lord and of quick and of dead].
14:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此基督死了，又活了，為要作死人並活人的主。
14:10|ASV|But thou, why dost thou judge thy brother? or thou again, why dost thou set at nought thy brother? for we shall all stand before the judgment-seat of God.
14:10|Darby|But thou, why judgest thou thy brother? or again, thou,  why dost thou make little of thy brother? for we shall all be  placed before the judgment-seat of God.
14:10|KJV|But why dost thou judge thy brother? or why dost thou set at nought thy brother? for we shall all stand before the judgment seat of Christ.
14:10|WYC|But what deemest thou thy brother? or why despisest thou thy brother? for all we shall stand before the throne of Christ.
14:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你為甚麼審判你的弟兄？又為甚麼輕視你的弟兄？我們都要站在神的審判臺前，
14:11|ASV|For it is written, As I live, saith the Lord, to me every knee shall bow, And every tongue shall confess to God.
14:11|Darby|For it is written, *I* live, saith [the] Lord, that to me  shall bow every knee, and every tongue shall confess to God.
14:11|KJV|For it is written, As I live, saith the Lord, every knee shall bow to me, and every tongue shall confess to God.
14:11|WYC|For it is written, I live, saith the Lord, for to me each knee shall be bowed, and each tongue shall acknowledge to God.
14:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為經上記著：“主說，我指著我的生存起誓，萬膝必向我跪拜，萬口也必向神公開承認。”
14:12|ASV|So then each one of us shall give account of himself to God.
14:12|Darby|So then each of us shall give an account concerning  himself to God.
14:12|KJV|So then every one of us shall give account of himself to God.
14:12|WYC|Therefore each of us [And so each of us] shall yield reason to God for himself.
14:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣看來，我們各人必要將自己的事向神陳明。
14:13|ASV|Let us not therefore judge one another any more: but judge ye this rather, that no man put a stumblingblock in his brother's way, or an occasion of falling.
14:13|Darby|Let us no longer therefore judge one another; but judge ye  this rather, not to put a stumbling-block or a fall-trap before  his brother.
14:13|KJV|Let us not therefore judge one another any more: but judge this rather, that no man put a stumblingblock or an occasion to fall in his brother's way.
14:13|WYC|Therefore no more deem we each other; but more deem ye this thing, that ye put not hurting, or cause of stumbling [or offence], to a brother.
14:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我們不可再彼此審判，寧可這樣斷定：不給弟兄放下絆腳石或跌人之物。
14:14|ASV|I know, and am persuaded in the Lord Jesus, that nothing is unclean of itself: save that to him who accounteth anything to be unclean, to him it is unclean.
14:14|Darby|I know, and am persuaded in the Lord Jesus, that nothing  is unclean of itself; except to him who reckons anything to be  unclean, to that man [it is] unclean.
14:14|KJV|I know, and am persuaded by the Lord Jesus, that there is nothing unclean of itself: but to him that esteemeth any thing to be unclean, to him it is unclean.
14:14|WYC|I know and trust in the Lord Jesus, that nothing is unclean by him, no but to him that deemeth any thing to be unclean [but to him that deemeth any thing to be unclean], to him it is unclean.
14:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我在主耶穌裡確知深信，凡物本身沒有不潔淨的，惟獨人算為不潔淨的，在他就不潔淨了。
14:15|ASV|For if because of meat thy brother is grieved, thou walkest no longer in love. Destroy not with thy meat him for whom Christ died.
14:15|Darby|For if on account of meat thy brother is grieved, thou  walkest no longer according to love. Destroy not him with thy  meat for whom Christ has died.
14:15|KJV|But if thy brother be grieved with thy meat, now walkest thou not charitably. Destroy not him with thy meat, for whom Christ died.
14:15<version name="WYC">And if thy brother be made sorry in conscience for meat [Soothly if thy brother be made sorry, <i>or heavy in conscience</i>, for meat], now thou walkest not after charity.  Do not thou through thy meat destroy him [Do not through thy meat lose him], for whom Christ died.</version>
14:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你若因食物叫弟兄憂愁，就不再是照著愛而行。基督已經替他死了，你不可因你的食物敗壞他。
14:16|ASV|Let not then your good be evil spoken of:
14:16|Darby|Let not then your good be evil spoken of;
14:16|KJV|Let not then your good be evil spoken of:
14:16<version name="WYC">Therefore be not your good thing blasphemed. [Therefore be not our good thing blasphemed, <i>or</i>  <i>despised</i>.]</version>
14:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以，不可叫你們的善被人毀謗，
14:17|ASV|for the kingdom of God is not eating and drinking, but righteousness and peace and joy in the Holy Spirit.
14:17|Darby|for the kingdom of God is not eating and drinking, but  righteousness, and peace, and joy in [the] Holy Spirit.
14:17|KJV|For the kingdom of God is not meat and drink; but righteousness, and peace, and joy in the Holy Ghost.
14:17|WYC|For why the realm of God is not meat and drink, but rightwiseness and peace and joy in the Holy Ghost.
14:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神的國不在於喫喝，乃在於公義、和平、並聖靈中的喜樂。
14:18|ASV|For he that herein serveth Christ is well-pleasing to God, and approved of men.
14:18|Darby|For he that in this serves the Christ [is] acceptable to  God and approved of men.
14:18|KJV|For he that in these things serveth Christ is acceptable to God, and approved of men.
14:18|WYC|And he that in this thing serveth Christ, pleaseth God, and is approved to men [and is proved to men].
14:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣服事基督的，就為神所喜悅，又為人所稱許。
14:19|ASV|So then let us follow after things which make for peace, and things whereby we may edify one another.
14:19|Darby|So then let us pursue the things which tend to peace, and  things whereby one shall build up another.
14:19|KJV|Let us therefore follow after the things which make for peace, and things wherewith one may edify another.
14:19|WYC|Therefore follow we those things that be of peace, and keep we together those things that be of edification [and keep we those things together that be of edification].
14:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以我們務要追求和平的事，以及彼此建造的事。
14:20|ASV|Overthrow not for meat's sake the work of God. All things indeed are clean; howbeit it is evil for that man who eateth with offence.
14:20|Darby|For the sake of meat do not destroy the work of God. All  things indeed [are] pure; but [it is] evil to that man who eats  while stumbling [in doing so].
14:20|KJV|For meat destroy not the work of God. All things indeed are pure; but it is evil for that man who eateth with offence.
14:20|WYC|Do not thou for meat destroy the work of God.  For all things be clean, but it is evil to the man that eateth by offending.
14:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不可因食物拆毀神的工程。凡物固然潔淨，但人喫了，以致成了絆腳石，就是他的惡了。
14:21|ASV|It is good not to eat flesh, nor to drink wine, nor to do anything whereby thy brother stumbleth.
14:21|Darby|[It is] right not to eat meat, nor drink wine, nor [do  anything] in which thy brother stumbles, or is offended, or is  weak.
14:21|KJV|It is good neither to eat flesh, nor to drink wine, nor any thing whereby thy brother stumbleth, or is offended, or is made weak.
14:21<version name="WYC">It is good to not eat flesh, and to not drink wine, neither in what thing thy brother offendeth, or is caused to stumble, or is made frail [neither in what thing thy brother offendeth, or is caused to offend, or is made sick, <i>or unsteadfast</i>].</version>
14:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|無論是喫肉，是喝酒，或是甚麼別的絆跌你弟兄的事，一概不作纔好。
14:22|ASV|The faith which thou hast, have thou to thyself before God. Happy is he that judgeth not himself in that which he approveth.
14:22|Darby|Hast *thou* faith? have [it] to thyself before God.  Blessed [is] he who does not judge himself in what he allows.
14:22|KJV|Hast thou faith? have it to thyself before God. Happy is he that condemneth not himself in that thing which he alloweth.
14:22<version name="WYC">Thou hast faith with thyself, have thou before God.  Blessed is he that deemeth not himself in that thing that he approveth [Blessed is he that deemeth not, <i>or condemneth not</i>, himself in that thing that he proveth].</version>
14:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你有信心，就當自己在神面前持守。人在自己所稱許的事上，不審判自己，就有福了。
14:23<version name="ASV">But he that doubteth is condemned if he eat, because he eateth not of faith; and whatsoever is not of faith is sin. </p><p /><br /></version>
14:23<version name="Darby">But he that doubts, if he eat, is condemned; because [it  is] not of faith; but whatever [is] not of faith is sin. </p><p /><br /></version>
14:23<version name="KJV">And he that doubteth is damned if he eat, because he eateth not of faith: for whatsoever is not of faith is sin.</p><p /><br /></version>
14:23<version name="WYC">For he that deemeth, is condemned, if he eateth; for it is not of faith.  And all thing that is not of faith, is sin. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21321b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
14:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但那疑惑的人若喫了，就必被定罪，因為不是出於信心。凡不是出於信心的，都是罪。
15:1|ASV|Now we that are strong ought to bear the infirmities of the weak, and not to please ourselves.
15:1|Darby|But *we* ought, we that are strong, to bear the infirmities  of the weak, and not to please ourselves.
15:1|KJV|We then that are strong ought to bear the infirmities of the weak, and not to please ourselves.
15:1<version name="WYC">But we firmer men owe to sustain the feeblenesses of frail men, and not please to ourselves. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21322a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
15:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們剛強的人，應該擔代不剛強之人的軟弱，不求自己的喜悅。
15:2|ASV|Let each one of us please his neighbor for that which is good, unto edifying.
15:2|Darby|Let each one of us please his neighbour with a view to what  is good, to edification.
15:2|KJV|Let every one of us please his neighbour for his good to edification.
15:2|WYC|Each of us please to his neighbour in good [into good], to edification.
15:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們各人要叫鄰舍喜悅，使他得益處，被建造。
15:3|ASV|For Christ also pleased not himself; but, as it is written, The reproaches of them that reproached thee fell upon me.
15:3|Darby|For the Christ also did not please himself; but according  as it is written, The reproaches of them that reproach thee  have fallen upon me.
15:3|KJV|For even Christ pleased not himself; but, as it is written, The reproaches of them that reproached thee fell on me.
15:3<version name="WYC">For Christ pleased not to himself, as it is written, The reproves of men despising thee, felled on me. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21324b" title="See footnote b">b</a>]</sup></version>
15:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為基督也不求自己的喜悅，反而如經上所記：“辱罵你之人的辱罵，都落在我身上。”
15:4|ASV|For whatsoever things were written aforetime were written for our learning, that through patience and through comfort of the scriptures we might have hope.
15:4|Darby|For as many things as have been written before have been  written for our instruction, that through endurance and through  encouragement of the scriptures we might have hope.
15:4|KJV|For whatsoever things were written aforetime were written for our learning, that we through patience and comfort of the scriptures might have hope.
15:4|WYC|For whatever things be written, those be written to our teaching [they be written to our teaching], that by patience and comfort of scriptures we have hope.
15:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|從前所寫的，都是為教訓我們寫的，使我們藉著忍耐，並藉著經書的鼓勵，可以得著盼望。
15:5|ASV|Now the God of patience and of comfort grant you to be of the same mind one with another according to Christ Jesus:
15:5|Darby|Now the God of endurance and of encouragement give to you  to be like-minded one toward another, according to Christ  Jesus;
15:5|KJV|Now the God of patience and consolation grant you to be likeminded one toward another according to Christ Jesus:
15:5|WYC|But God of patience and of solace give to you to understand the same thing, each into (the) other after Jesus Christ,
15:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但願那賜忍耐與鼓勵的神，叫你們照著基督耶穌，彼此思念相同的事，
15:6|ASV|that with one accord ye may with one mouth glorify the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.
15:6|Darby|that ye may with one accord, with one mouth, glorify the  God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.
15:6|KJV|That ye may with one mind and one mouth glorify God, even the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.
15:6|WYC|that ye of one will with one mouth worship God and the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.
15:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|使你們同心合意，用同一的口，榮耀我們主耶穌基督的神與父。
15:7|ASV|Wherefore receive ye one another, even as Christ also received you, to the glory of God.
15:7|Darby|Wherefore receive ye one another, according as the Christ  also has received you to [the] glory of God.
15:7|KJV|Wherefore receive ye one another, as Christ also received us to the glory of God.
15:7|WYC|For which thing take ye together, as also Christ took you into the honour of God.
15:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以你們要彼此接納，如同基督接納你們一樣，使榮耀歸與神。
15:8|ASV|For I say that Christ hath been made a minister of the circumcision for the truth of God, that he might confirm the promises given unto the fathers,
15:8|Darby|For I say that Jesus Christ became a minister of [the]  circumcision for [the] truth of God, to confirm the promises of  the fathers;
15:8|KJV|Now I say that Jesus Christ was a minister of the circumcision for the truth of God, to confirm the promises made unto the fathers:
15:8|WYC|For I say, that Jesus Christ was a minister of circumcision for the truth of God, to confirm the promises of fathers.
15:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我說，基督是為神的真實，作了受割禮之人的執事，要證實對列祖的應許，
15:9|ASV|and that the Gentiles might glorify God for his mercy; as it is written, Therefore will I give praise unto thee among the Gentiles, And sing unto thy name.
15:9|Darby|and that the nations should glorify God for mercy;  according as it is written, For this cause I will confess to  thee among [the] nations, and will sing to thy name.
15:9|KJV|And that the Gentiles might glorify God for his mercy; as it is written, For this cause I will confess to thee among the Gentiles, and sing unto thy name.
15:9|WYC|And heathen men owe to honour God for mercy; as it is written, Therefore, Lord, I shall acknowledge to thee among heathen men, and I shall sing to thy name.
15:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並叫外邦人，因著神的憐憫榮耀神，如經上所記：“因此我要在外邦中頌揚你，歌頌你的名。”
15:10|ASV|And again he saith, Rejoice, ye Gentiles, with his people.
15:10|Darby|And again he says, Rejoice, nations, with his people.
15:10|KJV|And again he saith, Rejoice, ye Gentiles, with his people.
15:10<version name="WYC">And again he saith, Ye heathen men, be ye glad with his people. [And again he saith, Glad, <i>or joy</i>, ye heathen men with his people.]</version>
15:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又說，“外邦人阿，你們當與祂的百姓一同快樂。”
15:11|ASV|And again, Praise the Lord, all ye Gentiles; And let all the peoples praise him.
15:11|Darby|And again, Praise the Lord, all [ye] nations, and let all  the peoples laud him.
15:11|KJV|And again, Praise the Lord, all ye Gentiles; and laud him, all ye people.
15:11|WYC|And again, All heathen men, praise ye the Lord; and all peoples, magnify ye him.
15:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又說，“萬邦阿，你們都當讚美主，願萬民都稱讚祂。”
15:12|ASV|And again, Isaiah saith, There shall be the root of Jesse, And he that ariseth to rule over the Gentiles; On him shall the Gentiles hope.
15:12|Darby|And again, Esaias says, There shall be the root of Jesse,  and one that arises, to rule over [the] nations: in him shall  [the] nations hope.
15:12|KJV|And again, Esaias saith, There shall be a root of Jesse, and he that shall rise to reign over the Gentiles; in him shall the Gentiles trust.
15:12|WYC|And again Esaias saith, There shall be a root of Jesse, that shall rise up to govern heathen men [that shall rise to govern heathen men], and heathen men shall hope in him.
15:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又有以賽亞說，“將來有耶西的根，就是那興起來要治理外邦的，外邦人都要寄望於祂。”
15:13|ASV|Now the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace in believing, that ye may abound in hope, in the power of the Holy Spirit.
15:13|Darby|Now the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace in  believing, so that ye should abound in hope by [the] power of  [the] Holy Spirit.
15:13|KJV|Now the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace in believing, that ye may abound in hope, through the power of the Holy Ghost.
15:13|WYC|And God of hope full-fill you in all joy and peace in believing, that ye increase in hope and virtue of the Holy Ghost [that ye abound in hope and virtue of the Holy Ghost].
15:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但願那賜盼望的神，因信將一切喜樂平安充滿你們，使你們靠聖靈的能力，充盈滿溢的有盼望。
15:14|ASV|And I myself also am persuaded of you, my brethren, that ye yourselves are full of goodness, filled with all knowledge, able also to admonish one another.
15:14|Darby|But I am persuaded, my brethren, I myself also, concerning  you, that yourselves also are full of goodness, filled with all  knowledge, able also to admonish one another.
15:14|KJV|And I myself also am persuaded of you, my brethren, that ye also are full of goodness, filled with all knowledge, able also to admonish one another.
15:14<version name="WYC">And, brethren, I myself am certain of you, that also ye be full of love, and ye be filled with all knowing, so that ye be able to admonish each other. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-21335c" title="See footnote c">c</a>]</sup></version>
15:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的弟兄們，我自己也深信你們是滿有良善，充滿了各樣的知識，也能彼此勸戒。
15:15|ASV|But I write the more boldly unto you in some measure, as putting you again in remembrance, because of the grace that was given me of God,
15:15|Darby|But I have written to you the more boldly, [brethren,] in  part, as putting you in mind, because of the grace given to me  by God,
15:15|KJV|Nevertheless, brethren, I have written the more boldly unto you in some sort, as putting you in mind, because of the grace that is given to me of God,
15:15|WYC|And, brethren, more boldly I wrote to you a part [more hardily I wrote to you of part], as bringing you into mind, for the grace that is given to me of God,
15:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但在有些點上，我更加放膽的寫給你們，是要題醒你們，特因神所賜我的恩典，
15:16|ASV|that I should be a minister of Christ Jesus unto the Gentiles, ministering the gospel of God, that the offering up of the Gentiles might be made acceptable, being sanctified by the Holy Spirit.
15:16|Darby|for me to be minister of Christ Jesus to the nations,  carrying on as a sacrificial service the [message of] glad  tidings of God, in order that the offering up of the nations  might be acceptable, sanctified by [the] Holy Spirit.
15:16|KJV|That I should be the minister of Jesus Christ to the Gentiles, ministering the gospel of God, that the offering up of the Gentiles might be acceptable, being sanctified by the Holy Ghost.
15:16|WYC|that I be the minister of Christ Jesus among heathen men.  And I hallow the gospel of God, that the offering of heathen men be accepted, and hallowed in the Holy Ghost [I hallowing the gospel of God, that the offering of heathen men be made acceptable, and hallowed in the Holy Ghost].
15:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|使我為外邦人作基督耶穌的僕役，作神福音勤奮的祭司，叫所獻上的外邦人，在聖靈裡得以聖別，可蒙悅納。
15:17|ASV|I have therefore my glorifying in Christ Jesus in things pertaining to God.
15:17|Darby|I have therefore [whereof to] boast in Christ Jesus in the  things which pertain to God.
15:17|KJV|I have therefore whereof I may glory through Jesus Christ in those things which pertain to God.
15:17|WYC|Therefore I have glory in Christ Jesus to God.
15:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所以論到神的事，我在基督耶穌裡有可誇的。
15:18|ASV|For I will not dare to speak of any things save those which Christ wrought through me, for the obedience of the Gentiles, by word and deed,
15:18|Darby|For I will not dare to speak anything of the things which  Christ has not wrought by me, for [the] obedience of [the]  nations, by word and deed,
15:18|KJV|For I will not dare to speak of any of those things which Christ hath not wrought by me, to make the Gentiles obedient, by word and deed,
15:18|WYC|For I dare not speak any thing of those things, which Christ doeth not by me [which Christ maketh not by me], into obedience of heathen men, in word and deeds,
15:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|除了基督藉我作成的那些事，我甚麼都不敢題，只題祂藉著我的言語和行為，用神蹟奇事的能力，並那靈的能力，使外邦人順從；
15:19|ASV|in the power of signs and wonders, in the power of the Holy Spirit; so that from Jerusalem, and round about even unto Illyricum, I have fully preached the gospel of Christ;
15:19|Darby|in [the] power of signs and wonders, in [the] power of  [the] Spirit of God; so that I, from Jerusalem, and in a  circuit round to Illyricum, have fully preached the glad  tidings of the Christ;
15:19|KJV|Through mighty signs and wonders, by the power of the Spirit of God; so that from Jerusalem, and round about unto Illyricum, I have fully preached the gospel of Christ.
15:19<version name="WYC">in virtue of tokens and great wonders, in virtue of the Holy Ghost, so that from Jerusalem by compass to the Illyricum sea I have filled the gospel of Christ [so that from Jerusalem by compass, <i>or environ</i>, till unto Illyricum I have full-filled the gospel of Christ].</version>
15:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，我從耶路撒冷，直轉到以利哩古，到處傳了基督的福音。
15:20|ASV|yea, making it my aim so to preach the gospel, not where Christ was  already named, that I might not build upon another man's foundation;
15:20|Darby|and so aiming to announce the glad tidings, not where  Christ has been named, that I might not build upon another's  foundation;
15:20|KJV|Yea, so have I strived to preach the gospel, not where Christ was named, lest I should build upon another man's foundation:
15:20|WYC|And so I have preached this gospel, not where Christ was named, lest I build upon another's ground,
15:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我立定志向，不在基督的名被稱過的地方傳福音，免得建造在別人的根基上，
15:21|ASV|but, as it is written, They shall see, to whom no tidings of him came, And they who have not heard shall understand.
15:21|Darby|but according as it is written, To whom there was nothing  told concerning him, they shall see; and they that have not  heard shall understand.
15:21|KJV|But as it is written, To whom he was not spoken of, they shall see: and they that have not heard shall understand.
15:21|WYC|but as it is written, For to whom it is not told of him, they shall see, and they that heard not, shall understand.
15:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|就如經上所記：“未曾得知祂信息的，將要看見；未曾聽過的，將要領悟。”
15:22|ASV|Wherefore also I was hindered these many times from coming to you:
15:22|Darby|Wherefore also I have been often hindered from coming to  you.
15:22|KJV|For which cause also I have been much hindered from coming to you.
15:22|WYC|For which thing I was hindered full much to come to you, and I am hindered till this time. [For which thing I was letted full much to come to you, and I am forbidden till unto yet.]
15:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此，我也多次被攔阻，總不得到你們那裡去。
15:23|ASV|but now, having no more any place in these regions, and having these many years a longing to come unto you,
15:23|Darby|But now, having no longer place in these regions, and  having great desire to come to you these many years,
15:23|KJV|But now having no more place in these parts, and having a great desire these many years to come unto you;
15:23<version name="WYC">And now I have not further place in these countries, but I have desire to come to you, of many years that be passed. [Forsooth now I not having further place, <i>or cause of longer dwelling</i>, in these countries, soothly having covetousness of coming to you, of many years now going before.]</version>
15:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但如今這一帶地方已無處可傳，而且多年來我一直想望，當我去西班牙的時候，可以到你們那裡，
15:24|ASV|whensoever I go unto Spain (for I hope to see you in my journey, and to be brought on my way thitherward by you, if first in some measure I shall have been satisfied with your company)--
15:24|Darby|whenever I should go to Spain; (for I hope to see you as I  go through, and by you to be set forward thither, if first I  shall have been in part filled with your company;)
15:24|KJV|Whensoever I take my journey into Spain, I will come to you: for I trust to see you in my journey, and to be brought on my way thitherward by you, if first I be somewhat filled with your company.
15:24|WYC|When I [shall] begin to pass into Spain, I hope that in my going I shall see you [I hope that I passing forth shall see you], and of you I shall be led thither, if I use you first in part.
15:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|盼望從你們那裡經過，得見你們，先與你們交往，稍得滿足，然後蒙你們送行到那裡去。
15:25|ASV|but now, I say, I go unto Jerusalem, ministering unto the saints.
15:25|Darby|but now I go to Jerusalem, ministering to the saints;
15:25|KJV|But now I go unto Jerusalem to minister unto the saints.
15:25|WYC|Therefore now I shall pass forth to Jerusalem, to minister to saints.
15:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但現在我往耶路撒冷去，供給聖徒。
15:26|ASV|For it hath been the good pleasure of Macedonia and Achaia to make a certain contribution for the poor among the saints that are at Jerusalem.
15:26|Darby|for Macedonia and Achaia have been well pleased to make a  certain contribution for the poor of the saints who [are] in  Jerusalem.
15:26|KJV|For it hath pleased them of Macedonia and Achaia to make a certain contribution for the poor saints which are at Jerusalem.
15:26<version name="WYC">For Macedonia and Achaia have assayed to make some gift to poor men of saints, that be in Jerusalem. [Forsooth Macedonia and Achaia proved to make some collection, <i>or gathering of money</i>, into poor men of saints, that be in Jerusalem.]</version>
15:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為馬其頓和亞該亞人，樂意對耶路撒冷聖徒中的窮人有些交通。
15:27|ASV|Yea, it hath been their good pleasure; and their debtors they are. For if the Gentiles have been made partakers of their spiritual things, they owe it to them also to minister unto them in carnal things.
15:27|Darby|They have been well pleased indeed, and they are their  debtors; for if the nations have participated in their  spiritual things, they ought also in fleshly to minister to  them.
15:27|KJV|It hath pleased them verily; and their debtors they are. For if the Gentiles have been made partakers of their spiritual things, their duty is also to minister unto them in carnal things.
15:27|WYC|For it pleased to them [Soothly it pleased to them], and they be debtors of them; for if heathen men be made partners of their ghostly things, they owe also in fleshly things to minister to them.
15:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這是他們樂意的，其實也是他們所欠的債。因外邦人既然分享猶太人屬靈的事物，就當供給他們肉身之物。
15:28|ASV|When therefore I have accomplished this, and have sealed to them this fruit, I will go on by you unto Spain.
15:28|Darby|Having finished this therefore, and having sealed to them  this fruit, I will set off by you into Spain.
15:28|KJV|When therefore I have performed this, and have sealed to them this fruit, I will come by you into Spain.
15:28|WYC|Therefore when I have ended this thing, and have assigned to them this fruit, I shall pass by you into Spain.
15:28|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|等我辦完了這事，把這果子向他們交付妥當，就要路過你們那裡，往西班牙去。
15:29|ASV|And I know that, when I come unto you, I shall come in the fulness of the blessing of Christ.
15:29|Darby|But I know that, coming to you, I shall come in [the]  fulness of [the] blessing of Christ.
15:29|KJV|And I am sure that, when I come unto you, I shall come in the fulness of the blessing of the gospel of Christ.
15:29<version name="WYC">And I know, that I coming to you, shall come in the abundance of the blessing of Christ [shall come into the abundance, <i>or</i> <i>plenty</i>, of the blessing of Christ].</version>
15:29|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我也曉得，我去的時候，必帶著基督之福的豐滿而去。
15:30|ASV|Now I beseech you, brethren, by our Lord Jesus Christ, and by the love of the Spirit, that ye strive together with me in your prayers to God for me;
15:30|Darby|But I beseech you, brethren, by our Lord Jesus Christ, and  by the love of the Spirit, that ye strive together with me in  prayers for me to God;
15:30|KJV|Now I beseech you, brethren, for the Lord Jesus Christ's sake, and for the love of the Spirit, that ye strive together with me in your prayers to God for me;
15:30|WYC|Therefore, brethren, I beseech you by our Lord Jesus Christ, and by the charity of the Holy Ghost, that ye help me in your prayers [for me] to the Lord,
15:30|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，我藉著我們的主耶穌基督，並藉著那靈的愛，懇求你們在為我向神的禱告中，與我一同竭力，
15:31|ASV|that I may be delivered from them that are disobedient in Judaea, and that my ministration which I have for Jerusalem may be acceptable to the saints;
15:31|Darby|that I may be saved from those that do not believe in  Judaea; and that my ministry which [I have] for Jerusalem may  be acceptable to the saints;
15:31|KJV|That I may be delivered from them that do not believe in Judaea; and that my service which I have for Jerusalem may be accepted of the saints;
15:31|WYC|that I be delivered from the unfaithful men, that be in Judaea, and that the offering of my service be accepted in Jerusalem to saints;
15:31|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|叫我可以得救，脫離猶太地不信從的人，也叫我對耶路撒冷的服事，可蒙聖徒悅納，
15:32|ASV|that I may come unto you in joy through the will of God, and together with you find rest.
15:32|Darby|in order that I may come to you in joy by God's will, and  that I may be refreshed with you.
15:32|KJV|That I may come unto you with joy by the will of God, and may with you be refreshed.
15:32|WYC|that I come to you in joy, by the will of God, and that I be refreshed with you.
15:32|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並叫我藉著神的旨意，歡歡喜喜的到你們那裡，與你們同得安息暢快。
15:33<version name="ASV">Now the God of peace be with you all. Amen. </p><p /><br /></version>
15:33<version name="Darby">And the God of peace be with you all. Amen. </p><p /><br /></version>
15:33<version name="KJV">Now the God of peace be with you all. Amen.</p><p /><br /></version>
15:33|WYC|And God of peace be with you all.  Amen.
15:33|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願平安的神與你們眾人同在。阿們。
16:1|ASV|I commend unto you Phoebe our sister, who is a servant of the church that is at Cenchreae:
16:1|Darby|But I commend to you Phoebe, our sister, who is minister of  the assembly which is in Cenchrea;
16:1|KJV|I commend unto you Phebe our sister, which is a servant of the church which is at Cenchrea:
16:1|WYC|And I commend to you Phebe, our sister, which is in the service of the church that is at Cenchrea,
16:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我向你們推薦我們的姊妹非比，她是在堅革哩的召會的女執事，
16:2|ASV|that ye receive her in the Lord, worthily of the saints, and that ye assist her in whatsoever matter she may have need of you: for she herself also hath been a helper of many, and of mine own self.
16:2|Darby|that ye may receive her in [the] Lord worthily of saints,  and that ye may assist her in whatever matter she has need of  you; for *she* also has been a helper of many, and of myself.
16:2|KJV|That ye receive her in the Lord, as becometh saints, and that ye assist her in whatsoever business she hath need of you: for she hath been a succourer of many, and of myself also.
16:2|WYC|that ye receive her in the Lord worthily to saints, and that ye help her in whatever cause she shall need of you.  For she hath helped many men, and myself.
16:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|請你們在主裡面照著與聖徒相配的接待她。她在何事上需要你們，你們就輔助她，因她素來護助許多人，也護助了我。
16:3|ASV|Salute Prisca and Aquila my fellow-workers in Christ Jesus,
16:3|Darby|Salute Prisca and Aquila, my fellow-workmen in Christ  Jesus,
16:3|KJV|Greet Priscilla and Aquila my helpers in Christ Jesus:
16:3|WYC|Greet Priscilla and Aquila, mine helpers in Christ Jesus,
16:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|問我在基督耶穌裡的同工，百基拉和亞居拉安；
16:4|ASV|who for my life laid down their own necks; unto whom not only I give thanks, but also all the churches of the Gentiles:
16:4|Darby|(who for my life staked their own neck; to whom not *I*  only am thankful, but also all the assemblies of the nations,)
16:4|KJV|Who have for my life laid down their own necks: unto whom not only I give thanks, but also all the churches of the Gentiles.
16:4|WYC|which under-putted [which under-put] their necks for my life; to whom not I alone do thankings, but also all the churches of heathen men.
16:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們為我的性命，將自己的頸項置於度外，不但我感謝他們，就是外邦的眾召會也感謝他們；
16:5|ASV|and salute the church that is in their house. Salute Epaenetus my beloved, who is the first-fruits of Asia unto Christ.
16:5|Darby|and the assembly at their house. Salute Epaenetus, my  beloved, who is [the] first-fruits of Asia for Christ.
16:5|KJV|Likewise greet the church that is in their house. Salute my well-beloved Epaenetus, who is the firstfruits of Achaia unto Christ.
16:5|WYC|And greet ye well their household church [And greet ye well their home-church].  Greet well Epaenetus, loved to me, that is the first of Asia in Christ Jesus.
16:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又問在他們家中的召會安。問我所親愛的以拜尼土安，他是亞西亞歸基督初結的果子。
16:6|ASV|Salute Mary, who bestowed much labor on you.
16:6|Darby|Salute Maria, who laboured much for you.
16:6|KJV|Greet Mary, who bestowed much labour on us.
16:6|WYC|Greet well Mary, the which hath travailed much in us. [Greet well Mary, that hath travailed much in us.]
16:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|問為你們多多勞苦的馬利亞安。
16:7|ASV|Salute Andronicus and Junias, my kinsmen, and my fellow-prisoners, who are of note among the apostles, who also have been in Christ before me.
16:7|Darby|Salute Andronicus and Junias, my kinsmen and  fellow-captives, who are of note among the apostles; who were  also in Christ before me.
16:7|KJV|Salute Andronicus and Junia, my kinsmen, and my fellow-prisoners, who are of note among the apostles, who also were in Christ before me.
16:7|WYC|Greet well Andronicus and Junia, my cousins, and mine even-prisoners, which be noble among the apostles, and which were before me in Christ.
16:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|問我親屬與我一同坐監的安多尼古和猶尼亞安，他們是使徒中著名的，且比我先在基督裡。
16:8|ASV|Salute Ampliatus my beloved in the Lord.
16:8|Darby|Salute Amplias, my beloved in the Lord.
16:8|KJV|Greet Amplias my beloved in the Lord.
16:8|WYC|Greet well Amplias, most dear-worthy to me in the Lord.
16:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|問我在主裡所親愛的暗伯利安。
16:9|ASV|Salute Urbanus our fellow-worker in Christ, and Stachys my beloved.
16:9|Darby|Salute Urbanus, our fellow-workman in Christ, and Stachys,  my beloved.
16:9|KJV|Salute Urbane, our helper in Christ, and Stachys my beloved.
16:9|WYC|Greet well Urbane, our helper in Christ Jesus, and Stachys, my darling [and Stachys, my loved].
16:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|問我們在基督裡的同工耳巴奴，並我所親愛的士大古安。
16:10|ASV|Salute Apelles the approved in Christ. Salute them that are of the household of Aristobulus.
16:10|Darby|Salute Apelles, approved in Christ. Salute those who  belong to Aristobulus.
16:10|KJV|Salute Apelles approved in Christ. Salute them which are of Aristobulus' household.
16:10|WYC|Greet well Apelles, the noble in Christ [Greet well Apelles, noble in Christ].  Greet well them that be of Aristobulus' house.
16:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|問在基督裡經過試驗而蒙稱許的亞比利安。問那些屬於亞利多布的人安。
16:11|ASV|Salute Herodion my kinsman. Salute them of the household of Narcissus, that are in the Lord.
16:11|Darby|Salute Herodion, my kinsman. Salute those who belong to  Narcissus, who are in [the] Lord.
16:11|KJV|Salute Herodion my kinsman. Greet them that be of the household of Narcissus, which are in the Lord.
16:11|WYC|Greet well Herodion, my cousin.  Greet well them that be of Narcissus' house, that be in the Lord.
16:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|問我親屬希羅天安。問那些屬於拿其數，在主裡的人安。
16:12|ASV|Salute Tryphaena and Tryphosa, who labor in the Lord. Salute Persis the beloved, who labored much in the Lord.
16:12|Darby|Salute Tryphaena and Tryphosa, who labour in [the] Lord.  Salute Persis, the beloved, who has laboured much in [the]  Lord.
16:12|KJV|Salute Tryphena and Tryphosa, who labour in the Lord. Salute the beloved Persis, which laboured much in the Lord.
16:12<version name="WYC">Greet well Tryphena and Tryphosa, which <i>women</i> travail in the Lord.  Greet well Persis, most dear-worthy <i>woman</i>, that hath travailed much in the Lord.</version>
16:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|問在主裡勞苦的土非拿氏和土富撒氏安。問可親愛在主裡多受勞苦的彼息氏安。
16:13|ASV|Salute Rufus the chosen in the Lord, and his mother and mine.
16:13|Darby|Salute Rufus, chosen in [the] Lord; and his mother and  mine.
16:13|KJV|Salute Rufus chosen in the Lord, and his mother and mine.
16:13|WYC|Greet well Rufus, chosen in the Lord, and his mother, and mine.
16:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|問在主裡蒙揀選的魯孚和他母親，也就是我的母親安。
16:14|ASV|Salute Asyncritus, Phlegon, Hermes, Patrobas, Hermas, and the brethren that are with them.
16:14|Darby|Salute Asyncritus, Phlegon, Hermes, Patrobas, Hermas, and  the brethren with them.
16:14|KJV|Salute Asyncritus, Phlegon, Hermas, Patrobas, Hermes, and the brethren which are with them.
16:14|WYC|Greet well Asyncritus, Phlegon, Hermes, Patrobas, Hermas, and brethren that be with them.
16:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|問亞遜其土，弗勒干，黑米，八羅巴，黑馬，並與他們同在的弟兄們安。
16:15|ASV|Salute Philologus and Julia, Nereus and his sister, and Olympas, and all the saints that are with them.
16:15|Darby|Salute Philologus, and Julia, Nereus, and his sister, and  Olympas, and all the saints with them.
16:15|KJV|Salute Philologus, and Julia, Nereus, and his sister, and Olympas, and all the saints which are with them.
16:15|WYC|Greet well Philologus, and Julia, and Nereus, and his sister, and Olympas, and all the saints that be with them.
16:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|問非羅羅古和猶利亞，尼利亞和他姊妹，同阿林巴，並與他們同在的眾聖徒安。
16:16|ASV|Salute one another with a holy kiss. All the churches of Christ salute you.
16:16|Darby|Salute one another with a holy kiss. All the assemblies of  Christ salute you.
16:16|KJV|Salute one another with an holy kiss. The churches of Christ salute you.
16:16|WYC|Greet ye well together in holy kiss [Greet well together in holy kiss].  All the churches of Christ greet you well.
16:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們要用聖別的親嘴彼此問安。基督的眾召會都問你們安。
16:17|ASV|Now I beseech you, brethren, mark them that are causing the divisions and occasions of stumbling, contrary to the doctrine which ye learned: and turn away from them.
16:17|Darby|But I beseech you, brethren, to consider those who create  divisions and occasions of falling, contrary to the doctrine  which *ye* have learnt, and turn away from them.
16:17|KJV|Now I beseech you, brethren, mark them which cause divisions and offences contrary to the doctrine which ye have learned; and avoid them.
16:17<version name="WYC">But, brethren, I pray you, that ye espy them that make dissensions and hurtings [that ye espy them that make dissensions and hurtings, <i>or offences</i>], besides the doctrine that ye have learned, and bow away from them.</version>
16:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|弟兄們，那些造成分立和絆跌之事，違反你們所學之教訓的人，我懇求你們要留意，並要避開他們。
16:18|ASV|For they that are such serve not our Lord Christ, but their own belly; and by their smooth and fair speech they beguile the hearts of the innocent.
16:18|Darby|For such serve not our Lord Christ, but their own belly,  and by good words and fair speeches deceive the hearts of the  unsuspecting.
16:18|KJV|For they that are such serve not our Lord Jesus Christ, but their own belly; and by good words and fair speeches deceive the hearts of the simple.
16:18|WYC|For such men serve not to the Lord Christ, but to their womb, and by sweet words and blessings deceive the hearts of innocent men.
16:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為這樣的人不服事我們的主基督，只服事自己的肚腹，且用花言巧語，誘騙那些老實人的心。
16:19|ASV|For your obedience is come abroad unto all men. I rejoice therefore over you: but I would have you wise unto that which is good, and simple unto that which is evil.
16:19|Darby|For your obedience has reached to all. I rejoice therefore  as it regards you; but I wish you to be wise [as] to that which  is good, and simple [as] to evil.
16:19|KJV|For your obedience is come abroad unto all men. I am glad therefore on your behalf: but yet I would have you wise unto that which is good, and simple concerning evil.
16:19|WYC|But your obedience is published into every place, therefore I have joy in you.  But I will that ye be wise in good thing [But I will you to be wise in good thing], and simple in evil.
16:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們的順從已經傳於眾人，所以我為你們歡樂，不過我還願意你們在善上智慧，在惡上單純。
16:20|ASV|And the God of peace shall bruise Satan under your feet shortly. The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you.
16:20|Darby|But the God of peace shall bruise Satan under your feet  shortly. The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ [be] with you.
16:20|KJV|And the God of peace shall bruise Satan under your feet shortly. The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you. Amen.
16:20|WYC|And God of peace tread Satan under your feet swiftly.  The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you.
16:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|平安的神快要將撒但踐踏在你們的腳下。願我們主耶穌的恩，與你們同在。
16:21|ASV|Timothy my fellow-worker saluteth you; and Lucius and Jason and Sosipater, my kinsmen.
16:21|Darby|Timotheus, my fellow-workman, and Lucius, and Jason, and  Sosipater, my kinsmen, salute you.
16:21|KJV|Timotheus my workfellow, and Lucius, and Jason, and Sosipater, my kinsmen, salute you.
16:21|WYC|Timothy, mine helper, greeteth you well, and also Lucius, and Jason, and Sosipater, my cousins.
16:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的同工提摩太，並我的親屬路求，耶孫和所西巴德，問你們安。
16:22|ASV|I Tertius, who write the epistle, salute you in the Lord.
16:22|Darby|I Tertius, who have written this epistle, salute you in  [the] Lord.
16:22|KJV|I Tertius, who wrote this epistle, salute you in the Lord.
16:22|WYC|I Tertius greet you well, that wrote this epistle, in the Lord.
16:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我這代筆寫信的德丟，在主裡問你們安。
16:23|ASV|Gaius my host, and of the whole church, saluteth you. Erastus the treasurer of the city saluteth you, and Quartus the brother.
16:23|Darby|Gaius, my host and of the whole assembly, salutes you.  Erastus, the steward of the city, salutes you, and the brother  Quartus.
16:23|KJV|Gaius mine host, and of the whole church, saluteth you. Erastus the chamberlain of the city saluteth you, and Quartus a brother.
16:23<version name="WYC">Gaius, mine host, greeteth you well, and all the church.  Erastus, treasurer of the city [Erastus<i>, </i>treasurer,<i> or keeper</i>, of the city], greeteth you well, and Quartus [the] brother.</version>
16:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那接待我，也接待全召會的該猶，問你們安。本城的司庫以拉都和弟兄括土，問你們安。
16:24|ASV|The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen.
16:24|Darby|The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ [be] with you all.  Amen.
16:24|KJV|The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen.
16:24<version name="WYC">The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ <i>be</i> with you all.  Amen.</version>
16:24|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|見24註1。
16:25|ASV|Now to him that is able to establish you according to my gospel and the preaching of Jesus Christ, according to the revelation of the mystery which hath been kept in silence through times eternal,
16:25|Darby|Now to him that is able to establish you, according to my  glad tidings and the preaching of Jesus Christ, according to  [the] revelation of [the] mystery, as to which silence has been  kept in [the] times of the ages,
16:25|KJV|Now to him that is of power to stablish you according to my gospel, and the preaching of Jesus Christ, according to the revelation of the mystery, which was kept secret since the world began,
16:25<version name="WYC">And honour and glory be to him, that is mighty to confirm you by my gospel, and preaching of Jesus Christ, by the revelation of mystery held still in times everlasting; [Forsooth to him, that is mighty to confirm you by my gospel, and preaching of Jesus Christ, after the revelation of mystery holden still, <i>that is,</i> <i>not showed</i>, in times everlasting;]</version>
16:25|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|神能照我的福音，就是關於耶穌基督的傳揚，照歷世以來密而不宣之奧祕的啟示，堅固你們；
16:26|ASV|but now is manifested, and by the scriptures of the prophets, according to the commandment of the eternal God, is made known unto all the nations unto obedience of faith:
16:26|Darby|but [which] has now been made manifest, and by prophetic  scriptures, according to commandment of the eternal God, made  known for obedience of faith to all the nations --
16:26|KJV|But now is made manifest, and by the scriptures of the prophets, according to the commandment of the everlasting God, made known to all nations for the obedience of faith:
16:26<version name="WYC">which <i>mystery </i>is now made open by scriptures of prophets, by the commandment of God without beginning and ending, to the obedience of faith in all heathen men, [the which is now made open by scriptures of prophets, after the commandment of God without beginning and ending, to the obedience of faith in all heathen men,]</version>
16:26|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這奧祕如今顯明出來，且照永遠之神的命令，藉著眾申言者所寫的，指示萬國，使他們順從信仰。
16:27<version name="ASV">to the only wise God, through Jesus Christ, to whom be the glory for ever. Amen. </p><p /><br /></version>
16:27<version name="Darby">[the] only wise God, through Jesus Christ, to whom be  glory for ever. Amen. </p><p /><br /></version>
16:27<version name="KJV">To God only wise, be glory through Jesus Christ for ever. Amen.</p><p /><br /></version>
16:27<version name="WYC"><i>the mystery </i>known by Jesus Christ to God alone wise [<i>the mystery</i> known to God alone wise, by Jesus Christ], to whom <i>be</i> honour and glory into worlds of worlds.  Amen.</version>
16:27|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願榮耀藉著耶穌基督，歸與這位獨一、智慧的神，直到永永遠遠。阿們。
