1:1|ASV|And it came to pass in the days when the judges judged, that there was a famine in the land. And a certain man of Bethlehem-judah went to sojourn in the country of Moab, he, and his wife, and his two sons.
1:1|Darby|And it came to pass in the days when the judges ruled, that  there was a famine in the land. And a certain man went from  Bethlehem-Judah, to sojourn in the country of Moab, he, and his  wife, and his two sons.
1:1|KJV|Now it came to pass in the days when the judges ruled, that there was a famine in the land. And a certain man of Bethlehemjudah went to sojourn in the country of Moab, he, and his wife, and his two sons.
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當士師秉政的時候，以色列地遭遇饑荒。有一個人帶著妻子和兩個兒子，從猶大的伯利恆往摩押鄉間去寄居。
1:2|ASV|And the name of the man was Elimelech, and the name of his wife Naomi, and the name of his two sons Mahlon and Chilion, Ephrathites of Bethlehem-judah. And they came into the country of Moab, and continued there.
1:2|Darby|And the name of the man was Elimelech, and the name of his  wife Naomi, and the name of his two sons Mahlon and Chilion,  Ephrathites of Bethlehem-Judah. And they came into the country  of Moab, and continued there.
1:2|KJV|And the name of the man was Elimelech, and the name of his wife Naomi, and the name of his two sons Mahlon and Chilion, Ephrathites of Bethlehemjudah. And they came into the country of Moab, and continued there.
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這人名叫以利米勒，他妻子名叫拿俄米；他兩個兒子，一個名叫瑪倫，一個名叫基連，都是猶大伯利恆的以法他人。他們到了摩押鄉間，就住在那堙C
1:3|ASV|And Elimelech, Naomi's husband, died; and she was left, and her two sons.
1:3|Darby|And Elimelech Naomi's husband died; and she was left, and  her two sons.
1:3|KJV|And Elimelech Naomi's husband died; and she was left, and her two sons.
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|後來拿俄米的丈夫以利米勒死了，剩下婦人和她兩個兒子。
1:4|ASV|And they took them wives of the women of Moab; the name of the one was Orpah, and the name of the other Ruth: and they dwelt there about ten years.
1:4|Darby|And they took them Moabitish wives; the name of the one was  Orpah, and the name of the second Ruth: and they abode there  about ten years.
1:4|KJV|And they took them wives of the women of Moab; the name of the one was Orpah, and the name of the other Ruth: and they dwelled there about ten years.
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這兩個兒子娶了摩押女子為妻，一個名叫俄珥巴，一個名叫路得，在那埵矰F約有十年。
1:5|ASV|And Mahlon and Chilion died both of them; and the woman was left of her two children and of her husband.
1:5|Darby|And Mahlon and Chilion died also, both of them; and the  woman was left of her two children and of her husband.
1:5|KJV|And Mahlon and Chilion died also both of them; and the woman was left of her two sons and her husband.
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|瑪倫和基連二人也死了，剩下婦人拿俄米，兩個孩子沒有了，丈夫也沒有了。
1:6|ASV|Then she arose with her daughters-in-law, that she might return from the country of Moab: for she had heard in the country of Moab how that Jehovah had visited his people in giving them bread.
1:6|Darby|And she arose, she and her daughters-in-law, and returned  from the fields of Moab; for she had heard in the fields of  Moab how that Jehovah had visited his people to give them  bread.
1:6|KJV|Then she arose with her daughters in law, that she might return from the country of Moab: for she had heard in the country of Moab how that the LORD had visited his people in giving them bread.
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|她就與兩個兒媳起身，要從摩押鄉間歸回；因為她在摩押鄉間聽見耶和華眷顧祂的百姓，賜糧食與他們。
1:7|ASV|And she went forth out of the place where she was, and her two daughters-in-law with her; and they went on the way to return unto the land of Judah.
1:7|Darby|Wherefore she went forth out of the place where she had  been, and her two daughters-in-law with her; and they went on  the way to return to the land of Judah.
1:7|KJV|Wherefore she went forth out of the place where she was, and her two daughters in law with her; and they went on the way to return unto the land of Judah.
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是她帶同兩個兒媳，起行離開所在的地方，上路回猶大地去。
1:8|ASV|And Naomi said unto her two daughters-in-law, Go, return each of you to her mother's house: Jehovah deal kindly with you, as ye have dealt with the dead, and with me.
1:8|Darby|And Naomi said to her two daughters-in-law, Go, return each  to her mother's house. Jehovah deal kindly with you, as ye have  dealt with the dead and with me.
1:8|KJV|And Naomi said unto her two daughters in law, Go, return each to her mother's house: the LORD deal kindly with you, as ye have dealt with the dead, and with me.
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|拿俄米對兩個兒媳說，你們各人回娘家去罷。願耶和華以恩慈待你們，像你們以恩慈待已死的人與我一樣。
1:9|ASV|Jehovah grant you that ye may find rest, each of you in the house of her husband. Then she kissed them, and they lifted up their voice, and wept.
1:9|Darby|Jehovah grant you that ye may find rest, each in the house  of her husband. And she kissed them; and they lifted up their  voice and wept.
1:9|KJV|The LORD grant you that ye may find rest, each of you in the house of her husband. Then she kissed them; and they lifted up their voice, and wept.
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願耶和華使你們各在新夫家中尋得安息。於是拿俄米與她們親嘴，她們就放聲而哭，
1:10|ASV|And they said unto her, Nay, but we will return with thee unto thy people.
1:10|Darby|And they said to her, We will certainly return with thee to  thy people.
1:10|KJV|And they said unto her, Surely we will return with thee unto thy people.
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|說，不然，我們必與你一同回你本民那堨h。
1:11|ASV|And Naomi said, Turn again, my daughters: why will ye go with me? have I yet sons in my womb, that they may be your husbands?
1:11|Darby|And Naomi said, Return, my daughters: why will ye go with  me? Are there yet sons in my womb, that they could be your  husbands?
1:11|KJV|And Naomi said, Turn again, my daughters: why will ye go with me? are there yet any more sons in my womb, that they may be your husbands?
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|拿俄米說，我女兒們哪，回去罷。為何要跟我去呢？我腹中還有兒子可以作你們的丈夫麼？
1:12|ASV|Turn again, my daughters, go your way; for I am too old to have a husband. If I should say, I have hope, if I should even have a husband to-night, and should also bear sons;
1:12|Darby|Return, my daughters, go; for I am too old to have a  husband. If I should say, I have hope, should I even have a  husband to-night, and should I also bear sons,
1:12|KJV|Turn again, my daughters, go your way; for I am too old to have an husband. If I should say, I have hope, if I should have an husband also to night, and should also bear sons;
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我女兒們哪，回去罷；我年紀老邁，不能再有丈夫。即或我說，我還有指望，今夜有丈夫可以生子，
1:13|ASV|would ye therefore tarry till they were grown? would ye therefore stay from having husbands? nay, my daughters, for it grieveth me much for your sakes, for the hand of Jehovah is gone forth against me.
1:13|Darby|would ye wait on that account till they were grown? Would  ye stay on that account from having husbands? No, my daughters,  for I am in much more bitterness than you; for the hand of  Jehovah is gone out against me.
1:13|KJV|Would ye tarry for them till they were grown? would ye stay for them from having husbands? nay, my daughters; for it grieveth me much for your sakes that the hand of the LORD is gone out against me.
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你們豈能等著他們長大呢？你們豈能為他們守身不嫁人呢？我女兒們哪，不要這樣。我比你們更是愁苦，因為耶和華伸手攻擊我。
1:14|ASV|And they lifted up their voice, and wept again: and Orpah kissed her mother-in-law, but Ruth clave unto her.
1:14|Darby|And they lifted up their voice and wept again. And Orpah  kissed her mother-in-law, but Ruth clave to her.
1:14|KJV|And they lifted up their voice, and wept again: and Orpah kissed her mother in law; but Ruth clave unto her.
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|兩個兒媳又放聲而哭；俄珥巴與婆婆親嘴而別，只是路得緊緊隨著婆婆。
1:15|ASV|And she said, Behold, thy sister-in-law is gone back unto her people, and unto her god: return thou after thy sister-in-law.
1:15|Darby|And she said, Behold, thy sister-in-law is gone back to her  people and to her gods: return after thy sister-in-law.
1:15|KJV|And she said, Behold, thy sister in law is gone back unto her people, and unto her gods: return thou after thy sister in law.
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|拿俄米說，看哪，你嫂子已經回她本民和她的神那堨h了，你也跟著你嫂子回去罷。
1:16|ASV|And Ruth said, Entreat me not to leave thee, and to return from following after thee, for whither thou goest, I will go; and where thou lodgest, I will lodge; thy people shall be my people, and thy God my God;
1:16|Darby|And Ruth said, Do not intreat me to leave thee, to return  from [following] after thee; for whither thou goest I will go,  and where thou lodgest I will lodge: thy people shall be my  people, and thy God my God;
1:16|KJV|And Ruth said, Intreat me not to leave thee, or to return from following after thee: for whither thou goest, I will go; and where thou lodgest, I will lodge: thy people shall be my people, and thy God my God:
1:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|路得說，不要催我離開你回去不跟隨你。你往那堨h，我也往那堨h；你在那埵穜J，我也在那埵穜J；你的民就是我的民，你的神就是我的神。
1:17|ASV|where thou diest, will I die, and there will I be buried: Jehovah do so to me, and more also, if aught but death part thee and me.
1:17|Darby|where thou diest will I die, and there will I be buried.  Jehovah do so to me, and more also, if aught but death part me  and thee!
1:17|KJV|Where thou diest, will I die, and there will I be buried: the LORD do so to me, and more also, if ought but death part thee and me.
1:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你在那埵滿A我也在那埵滿A也葬在那堙C除非死能使你我相離，不然，願耶和華重重的降罰與我。
1:18|ASV|And when she saw that she was stedfastly minded to go with her, she left off speaking unto her.
1:18|Darby|And when she saw that she was stedfastly minded to go with  her, she left off speaking to her.
1:18|KJV|When she saw that she was stedfastly minded to go with her, then she left speaking unto her.
1:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|拿俄米見路得定意要跟隨自己去，就不再對她說甚麼了。
1:19|ASV|So they two went until they came to Bethlehem. And it came to pass, when they were come to Bethlehem, that all the city was moved about them, and the women said, Is this Naomi?
1:19|Darby|And they two went until they came to Bethlehem. And it came  to pass, when they came to Bethlehem, that all the city was  moved about them, and the [women] said, Is this Naomi?
1:19|KJV|So they two went until they came to Bethlehem. And it came to pass, when they were come to Bethlehem, that all the city was moved about them, and they said, Is this Naomi?
1:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是二人同行，來到伯利恆。她們到了伯利恆，合城的人就都因她們驚動；婦女們說，這不是拿俄米麼？
1:20|ASV|And she said unto them, Call me not Naomi, call me Mara; for the Almighty hath dealt very bitterly with me.
1:20|Darby|And she said to them, Call me not Naomi -- call me Mara;  for the Almighty has dealt very bitterly with me.
1:20|KJV|And she said unto them, Call me not Naomi, call me Mara: for the Almighty hath dealt very bitterly with me.
1:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|拿俄米對她們說，不要叫我拿俄米，要叫我瑪拉，因為全足者使我受了大苦。
1:21|ASV|I went out full, and Jehovah hath brought me home again empty; why call ye me Naomi, seeing Jehovah hath testified against me, and the Almighty hath afflicted me?
1:21|Darby|I went out full, and Jehovah has brought me home again  empty. Why do ye call me Naomi, seeing Jehovah has brought me  low, and the Almighty has afflicted me?
1:21|KJV|I went out full and the LORD hath brought me home again empty: why then call ye me Naomi, seeing the LORD hath testified against me, and the Almighty hath afflicted me?
1:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我滿滿的出去，耶和華使我空空的回來。耶和華使我受苦，全足者以禍患待我。既是這樣，你們為何還叫我拿俄米呢？
1:22<version name="ASV">So Naomi returned, and Ruth the Moabitess, her daughter-in-law, with her, who returned out of the country of Moab: and they came to Bethlehem in the beginning of barley harvest. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:22<version name="Darby">So Naomi returned, and Ruth the Moabitess, her  daughter-in-law, with her, who returned out of the fields of  Moab; and they came to Bethlehem in the beginning of the  barley-harvest. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:22<version name="KJV">So Naomi returned, and Ruth the Moabitess, her daughter in law, with her, which returned out of the country of Moab: and they came to Bethlehem in the beginning of barley harvest.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|拿俄米和她兒媳摩押女子路得，從摩押鄉間回來；她們到了伯利恆，正是動手割大麥的時候。
2:1|ASV|And Naomi had a kinsman of her husband's, a mighty man of wealth, of the family of Elimelech, and his name was Boaz.
2:1|Darby|And Naomi had a relation of her husband's, a mighty man of  wealth, of the family of Elimelech, and his name was Boaz.
2:1|KJV|And Naomi had a kinsman of her husband's, a mighty man of wealth, of the family of Elimelech; and his name was Boaz.
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|拿俄米在她丈夫以利米勒的家族中，有一個相識的人，是個大財主，名叫波阿斯。
2:2|ASV|And Ruth the Moabitess said unto Naomi, Let me now go to the field, and glean among the ears of grain after him in whose sight I shall find favor. And she said unto her, Go, my daughter.
2:2|Darby|And Ruth the Moabitess said to Naomi, Let me, I pray, go to  the field and glean among the ears of corn after [him] in whose  sight I shall find favour. And she said to her, Go, my  daughter.
2:2|KJV|And Ruth the Moabitess said unto Naomi, Let me now go to the field, and glean ears of corn after him in whose sight I shall find grace. And she said unto her, Go, my daughter.
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|摩押女子路得對拿俄米說，請你讓我往田間去，我在誰的眼中蒙恩，就在誰的身後拾取麥穗。拿俄米說，女兒阿，你只管去。
2:3|ASV|And she went, and came and gleaned in the field after the reapers: and her hap was to light on the portion of the field belonging unto Boaz, who was of the family of Elimelech.
2:3|Darby|And she went; and she came and gleaned in the fields after  the reapers; and she chanced to light on an allotment of Boaz,  who was of the family of Elimelech.
2:3|KJV|And she went, and came, and gleaned in the field after the reapers: and her hap was to light on a part of the field belonging unto Boaz, who was of the kindred of Elimelech.
2:3<version name="&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;">路得就去了。她來到田間，在收割的人身後拾取麥穗，恰巧是在以利米勒家族的人波阿斯那塊田堙C</FONT</version>
2:4|ASV|And, behold, Boaz came from Bethlehem, and said unto the reapers, Jehovah be with you. And they answered him, Jehovah bless thee.
2:4|Darby|And behold, Boaz came from Bethlehem; and he said to the  reapers, Jehovah be with you! And they said to him, Jehovah  bless thee!
2:4|KJV|And, behold, Boaz came from Bethlehem, and said unto the reapers, The LORD be with you. And they answered him, The LORD bless thee.
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|波阿斯正從伯利恆來，對收割的人說，願耶和華與你們同在。他們回答說，願耶和華賜福與你。
2:5|ASV|Then said Boaz unto his servant that was set over the reapers, Whose damsel is this?
2:5|Darby|And Boaz said to his servant that was set over the reapers,  Whose maiden is this?
2:5|KJV|Then said Boaz unto his servant that was set over the reapers, Whose damsel is this?
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|波阿斯對監管收割之人的僕人說，那是誰家的女子？
2:6|ASV|And the servant that was set over the reapers answered and said, It is the Moabitish damsel that came back with Naomi out of the country of Moab:
2:6|Darby|And the servant that was set over the reapers answered and  said, It is the Moabitish maiden who came back with Naomi out  of the fields of Moab;
2:6|KJV|And the servant that was set over the reapers answered and said, It is the Moabitish damsel that came back with Naomi out of the country of Moab:
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|監管收割之人的僕人回答說，是那摩押女子，隨同拿俄米從摩押鄉間回來的。
2:7|ASV|And she said, Let me glean, I pray you, and gather after the reapers among the sheaves. So she came, and hath continued even from the morning until now, save that she tarried a little in the house.
2:7|Darby|and she said, I pray you, let me glean and gather among the  sheaves after the reapers. And she came, and has continued from  the morning until now: her sitting in the house has been little  as yet.
2:7|KJV|And she said, I pray you, let me glean and gather after the reapers among the sheaves: so she came, and hath continued even from the morning until now, that she tarried a little in the house.
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|她說，請你讓我在收割的人身後，拾取打捆剩下的麥穗。她早晨就來了，直到如今，除了在屋子塈中@會兒，一直留在這堙C
2:8|ASV|Then said Boaz unto Ruth, Hearest thou not, my daughter? Go not to glean in another field, neither pass from hence, but abide here fast by my maidens.
2:8|Darby|And Boaz said to Ruth, Hearest thou not, my daughter? Go not  to glean in another field, neither go from here, but keep here  with my maidens.
2:8|KJV|Then said Boaz unto Ruth, Hearest thou not, my daughter? Go not to glean in another field, neither go from hence, but abide here fast by my maidens:
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|波阿斯對路得說，女兒阿，聽我說，不要往別人田堿B取麥穗，也不要離開這堙A要緊隨著我的使女們。
2:9|ASV|Let thine eyes be on the field that they do reap, and go thou after them: have I not charged the young men that they shall not touch thee? and when thou art athirst, go unto the vessels, and drink of that which the young men have drawn.
2:9|Darby|Let thine eyes be on the field which is being reaped, and go  thou after them; have I not charged the young men not to touch  thee? And when thou art athirst, go to the vessels and drink of  what the young men draw.
2:9|KJV|Let thine eyes be on the field that they do reap, and go thou after them: have I not charged the young men that they shall not touch thee? and when thou art athirst, go unto the vessels, and drink of that which the young men have drawn.
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要留意她們在那塊田收割，你就跟著她們去。我已經吩咐僕人不可觸犯你；你若渴了，就可以到器皿那堻僊略H打來的水。
2:10|ASV|Then she fell on her face, and bowed herself to the ground, and said unto him, Why have I found favor in thy sight, that thou shouldest take knowledge of me, seeing I am a foreigner?
2:10|Darby|Then she fell on her face, and bowed herself to the ground,  and said to him, Why have I found favour in thine eyes, that  thou shouldest regard me, seeing I am a foreigner?
2:10|KJV|Then she fell on her face, and bowed herself to the ground, and said unto him, Why have I found grace in thine eyes, that thou shouldest take knowledge of me, seeing I am a stranger?
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|路得就面伏於地叩拜，對他說，我既是外邦人，怎麼在你眼中蒙恩，使你這樣顧恤我呢？
2:11|ASV|And Boaz answered and said unto her, It hath fully been showed me, all that thou hast done unto thy mother-in-law since the death of thy husband; and how thou hast left thy father and thy mother, and the land of thy nativity, and art come unto a people that thou knewest not heretofore.
2:11|Darby|And Boaz answered and said to her, It has fully been shewn  me, all that thou hast done to thy mother-in-law since the  death of thy husband; and how thou hast left thy father and thy  mother, and the land of thy nativity, and art come to a people  that thou hast not known heretofore.
2:11|KJV|And Boaz answered and said unto her, It hath fully been shewed me, all that thou hast done unto thy mother in law since the death of thine husband: and how thou hast left thy father and thy mother, and the land of thy nativity, and art come unto a people which thou knewest not heretofore.
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|波阿斯回答說，自從你丈夫死後，凡你向婆婆所行的，並你離開父母和出生地，到素不認識的民中，這一切事人全都告訴我了。
2:12|ASV|Jehovah recompense thy work, and a full reward be given thee of Jehovah, the God of Israel, under whose wings thou art come to take refuge.
2:12|Darby|Jehovah recompense thy work, and let thy reward be full  from Jehovah the God of Israel, under whose wings thou art come  to take refuge.
2:12|KJV|The LORD recompense thy work, and a full reward be given thee of the LORD God of Israel, under whose wings thou art come to trust.
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願耶和華照你所行的報答你；你來投靠耶和華以色列神的翅膀下，願你滿得祂的酬報。
2:13|ASV|Then she said, Let me find favor in thy sight, my lord, for that thou hast comforted me, and for that thou hast spoken kindly unto thy handmaid, though I be not as one of thy handmaidens.
2:13|Darby|And she said, Let me find favour in thine eyes, my lord;  for that thou hast comforted me, and for that thou hast spoken  kindly to thy handmaid, though I am not like one of thy  handmaidens.
2:13|KJV|Then she said, Let me find favour in thy sight, my lord; for that thou hast comforted me, and for that thou hast spoken friendly unto thine handmaid, though I be not like unto one of thine handmaidens.
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|路得說，我主阿，願我在你眼前蒙恩；我雖然不及你的一個婢女，你還安慰我，親切的與你的婢女說話。
2:14|ASV|And at meal-time Boaz said unto her, Come hither, and eat of the bread, and dip thy morsel in the vinegar. And she sat beside the reapers, and they reached her parched grain, and she did eat, and was sufficed, and left thereof.
2:14|Darby|And Boaz said to her at mealtime, Come hither and eat of  the bread, and dip thy morsel in the vinegar. And she sat  beside the reapers; and he reached her parched corn, and she  ate and was sufficed, and reserved [some].
2:14|KJV|And Boaz said unto her, At mealtime come thou hither, and eat of the bread, and dip thy morsel in the vinegar. And she sat beside the reapers: and he reached her parched corn, and she did eat, and was sufficed, and left.
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|到了喫飯的時候，波阿斯對路得說，你到這堥茬蟟I餅，將餅蘸在醋堙C路得就在收割的人旁邊坐下；波阿斯把烘了的穗子遞給她。她喫飽了，還有餘剩的。
2:15|ASV|And when she was risen up to glean, Boaz commanded his young men, saying, Let her glean even among the sheaves, and reproach her not.
2:15|Darby|And when she rose up to glean, Boaz commanded his young  men, saying, Let her glean even among the sheaves, and ye shall  not reproach her.
2:15|KJV|And when she was risen up to glean, Boaz commanded his young men, saying, Let her glean even among the sheaves, and reproach her not:
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|她起來又拾取麥穗，波阿斯吩咐僕人說，她就是在禾捆中拾取麥穗，也可以容她，不可羞辱她；
2:16|ASV|And also pull out some for her from the bundles, and leave it, and let her glean, and rebuke her not.
2:16|Darby|And ye shall also sometimes draw out for her [some ears]  out of the handfuls, and leave them that she may glean, and  rebuke her not.
2:16|KJV|And let fall also some of the handfuls of purpose for her, and leave them, that she may glean them, and rebuke her not.
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並要從捆堜漭X些來，留給她拾取，不可斥責她。
2:17|ASV|So she gleaned in the field until even; and she beat out that which she had gleaned, and it was about an ephah of barley.
2:17|Darby|And she gleaned in the field until even, and beat out what  she had gleaned; and it was about an ephah of barley.
2:17|KJV|So she gleaned in the field until even, and beat out that she had gleaned: and it was about an ephah of barley.
2:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這樣，路得在田間拾取麥穗，直到晚上；將所拾取的打了，約有一伊法大麥。
2:18|ASV|And she took it up, and went into the city; and her mother-in-law saw what she had gleaned: and she brought forth and gave to her that which she had left after she was sufficed.
2:18|Darby|And she took [it] up, and came into the city, and her  mother-in-law saw what she had gleaned; and she brought forth  and gave to her that which she had reserved after she was  sufficed.
2:18|KJV|And she took it up, and went into the city: and her mother in law saw what she had gleaned: and she brought forth, and gave to her that she had reserved after she was sufficed.
2:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|她就把所拾取的帶進城去給婆婆看，又把她喫飽了所剩的拿出來給婆婆。
2:19|ASV|And her mother-in-law said unto her, Where hast thou gleaned to-day? and where hast thou wrought? blessed be he that did take knowledge of thee. And she showed her mother-in-law with whom she had wrought, and said, The man's name with whom I wrought to-day is Boaz.
2:19|Darby|And her mother-in-law said to her, Where hast thou gleaned  to-day? and where hast thou wrought? Blessed be he that did  regard thee! And she told her mother-in-law with whom she had  wrought, and said, The man's name with whom I wrought to-day is  Boaz.
2:19|KJV|And her mother in law said unto her, Where hast thou gleaned to day? and where wroughtest thou? blessed be he that did take knowledge of thee. And she shewed her mother in law with whom she had wrought, and said, The man's name with whom I wrought to day is Boaz.
2:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|婆婆對她說，你今日在那堿B取麥穗，在那塈@工呢？願那顧恤你的蒙福。路得就告訴婆婆她在誰那塈@工，說，我今日在一個名叫波阿斯的人那塈@工。
2:20|ASV|And Naomi said unto her daughter-in-law, Blessed be he of Jehovah, who hath not left off his kindness to the living and to the dead. And Naomi said unto her, The man is nigh of kin unto us, one of our near kinsmen.
2:20|Darby|And Naomi said to her daughter-in-law, Blessed be he of  Jehovah, who has not left off his kindness to the living and to  the dead! And Naomi said to her, The man is near of kin to us,  one of those who have the right of our redemption.
2:20|KJV|And Naomi said unto her daughter in law, Blessed be he of the LORD, who hath not left off his kindness to the living and to the dead. And Naomi said unto her, The man is near of kin unto us, one of our next kinsmen.
2:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|拿俄米對兒媳說，願那人蒙耶和華賜福，因為他不斷以慈愛待活人和死人。拿俄米又說，那人與我們相近，是我們的親人。
2:21|ASV|And Ruth the Moabitess said, Yea, he said unto me, Thou shalt keep fast by my young men, until they have ended all my harvest.
2:21|Darby|And Ruth the Moabitess said, He said to me also, Thou shalt  keep with my young men until they have ended all my harvest.
2:21|KJV|And Ruth the Moabitess said, He said unto me also, Thou shalt keep fast by my young men, until they have ended all my harvest.
2:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|摩押女子路得說，他也對我說，你要緊隨我的僕人拾取麥穗，直等他們收完了我的莊稼。
2:22|ASV|And Naomi said unto Ruth her daughter-in-law, It is good, my daughter, that thou go out with his maidens, and that they meet thee not in any other field.
2:22|Darby|And Naomi said to Ruth her daughter-in-law, It is good, my  daughter, that thou go out with his maidens, that they meet  thee not in any other field.
2:22|KJV|And Naomi said unto Ruth her daughter in law, It is good, my daughter, that thou go out with his maidens, that they meet thee not in any other field.
2:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|拿俄米對兒媳路得說，女兒阿，你跟著他的使女出去，不叫人遇見你在別人田間，這纔為好。
2:23<version name="ASV">So she kept fast by the maidens of Boaz, to glean unto the end of barley harvest and of wheat harvest; and she dwelt with her mother-in-law. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:23<version name="Darby">So she kept with the maidens of Boaz to glean, until the  end of the barley-harvest and of the wheat-harvest. And she  dwelt with her mother-in-law. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:23<version name="KJV">So she kept fast by the maidens of Boaz to glean unto the end of barley harvest and of wheat harvest; and dwelt with her mother in law.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:23|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是路得緊隨波阿斯的使女拾取麥穗，直到收完了大麥和小麥；路得仍與婆婆同住。
3:1|ASV|And Naomi her mother-in-law said unto her, My daughter, shall I not seek rest for thee, that it may be well with thee?
3:1|Darby|And Naomi her mother-in-law said to her, My daughter, shall  I not seek rest for thee, that it may be well with thee?
3:1|KJV|Then Naomi her mother in law said unto her, My daughter, shall I not seek rest for thee, that it may be well with thee?
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|路得的婆婆拿俄米對她說，女兒阿，我不當為你找個安身之處，使你享福麼？
3:2|ASV|And now is not Boaz our kinsman, with whose maidens thou wast? Behold, he winnoweth barley to-night in the threshing-floor.
3:2|Darby|And now, is not Boaz of our kindred, with whose maidens thou  wast? Behold, he is winnowing barley in the threshing-floor  to-night.
3:2|KJV|And now is not Boaz of our kindred, with whose maidens thou wast? Behold, he winnoweth barley to night in the threshingfloor.
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你與波阿斯的使女常在一處，波阿斯不是我們相識的人麼？看哪，他今夜在禾場上簸大麥。
3:3|ASV|Wash thyself therefore, and anoint thee, and put thy raiment upon thee, and get thee down to the threshing-floor, but make not thyself known unto the man, until he shall have done eating and drinking.
3:3|Darby|Wash thyself therefore, and anoint thyself, and put thy  raiment upon thee, and go down to the floor; make not thyself  known to the man, until he shall have done eating and drinking.
3:3|KJV|Wash thyself therefore, and anoint thee, and put thy raiment upon thee, and get thee down to the floor: but make not thyself known unto the man, until he shall have done eating and drinking.
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要沐浴抹膏，換上衣服，下到禾場上，卻不要使那人認出你來，直等他喫喝完了。
3:4|ASV|And it shall be, when he lieth down, that thou shalt mark the place where he shall lie, and thou shalt go in, and uncover his feet, and lay thee down; and he will tell thee what thou shalt do.
3:4|Darby|And it shall be, when he lies down, that thou shalt mark the  place where he shall have lain down, and thou shalt go in, and  uncover his feet, and lay thyself down; and he will shew thee  what thou shalt do.
3:4|KJV|And it shall be, when he lieth down, that thou shalt mark the place where he shall lie, and thou shalt go in, and uncover his feet, and lay thee down; and he will tell thee what thou shalt do.
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|到他躺下的時候，你看準他躺臥的地方，就進去掀開他腳上的被，躺臥在那堙F他必告訴你所當作的事。
3:5|ASV|And she said unto her, All that thou sayest I will do.
3:5|Darby|And she said to her, All that thou sayest will I do.
3:5|KJV|And she said unto her, All that thou sayest unto me I will do.
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|路得說，凡你所說的，我必遵行。
3:6|ASV|And she went down unto the threshing-floor, and did according to all that her mother-in-law bade her.
3:6|Darby|And she went down to the floor, and did according to all  that her mother-in-law had bidden her.
3:6|KJV|And she went down unto the floor, and did according to all that her mother in law bade her.
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|路得就下到禾場上，照她婆婆所吩咐她的一切而行。
3:7|ASV|And when Boaz had eaten and drunk, and his heart was merry, he went to lie down at the end of the heap of grain: and she came softly, and uncovered his feet, and laid her down.
3:7|Darby|And Boaz ate and drank, and his heart was merry, and he went  to lie down at the end of the heap of corn. Then she went  softly, and uncovered his feet, and laid herself down.
3:7|KJV|And when Boaz had eaten and drunk, and his heart was merry, he went to lie down at the end of the heap of corn: and she came softly, and uncovered his feet, and laid her down.
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|波阿斯喫喝完了，心媗w暢，就到麥堆儘邊去躺下。路得便悄悄的來掀開他腳上的被，躺臥在那堙C
3:8|ASV|And it came to pass at midnight, that the man was afraid, and turned himself; and, behold, a woman lay at his feet.
3:8|Darby|And it came to pass at midnight, that the man was startled,  and turned himself; and behold, a woman lay at his feet.
3:8|KJV|And it came to pass at midnight, that the man was afraid, and turned himself: and, behold, a woman lay at his feet.
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|到了夜半，那人忽然驚醒，翻過身來，不料有女子躺在他的腳邊。
3:9|ASV|And he said, Who art thou? And she answered, I am Ruth thy handmaid: spread therefore thy skirt over thy handmaid; for thou art a near kinsman.
3:9|Darby|And he said, Who art thou? And she answered, I am Ruth, thy  handmaid: spread thy skirt over thy handmaid; for thou hast the  right of redemption.
3:9|KJV|And he said, Who art thou? And she answered, I am Ruth thine handmaid: spread therefore thy skirt over thine handmaid; for thou art a near kinsman.
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他就說，你是誰？她回答說，我是你的婢女路得。請你展開你的衣邊遮蓋你的婢女，因為你是我的親人。
3:10|ASV|And he said, Blessed be thou of Jehovah, my daughter: thou hast showed more kindness in the latter end than at the beginning, inasmuch as thou followedst not young men, whether poor or rich.
3:10|Darby|And he said, Blessed be thou of Jehovah, my daughter! Thou  hast shewn more kindness at the end than at the first, inasmuch  as thou followedst not young men, whether poor or rich.
3:10|KJV|And he said, Blessed be thou of the LORD, my daughter: for thou hast shewed more kindness in the latter end than at the beginning, inasmuch as thou followedst not young men, whether poor or rich.
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|波阿斯說，女兒阿，願你蒙耶和華賜福。你末後所顯出的恩慈比先前的更美；因為少年人無論貧富，你都沒有跟從。
3:11|ASV|And now, my daughter, fear not; I will do to thee all that thou sayest; for all the city of my people doth know that thou art a worthy woman.
3:11|Darby|And now, my daughter, fear not: all that thou sayest will I  do to thee; for all the gate of my people knows that thou art a  woman of worth.
3:11|KJV|And now, my daughter, fear not; I will do to thee all that thou requirest: for all the city of my people doth know that thou art a virtuous woman.
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|女兒阿，現在不要懼怕；凡你所說的，我必為你行，因我本城的人都知道你是個賢德的女子。
3:12|ASV|And now it is true that I am a near kinsman; howbeit there is a kinsman nearer than I.
3:12|Darby|And now, truly I am one that has the right of redemption,  yet there is one that has the right of redemption who is nearer  than I.
3:12|KJV|And now it is true that I am thy near kinsman: howbeit there is a kinsman nearer than I.
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我實在是你的親人，只是還有一個親人比我更近。
3:13|ASV|Tarry this night, and it shall be in the morning, that if he will perform unto thee the part of a kinsman, well; let him do the kinsman's part: but if he will not do the part of a kinsman to thee, then will I do the part of a kinsman to thee, as Jehovah liveth: lie down until the morning.
3:13|Darby|Stay over to-night, and it shall be in the morning, if he  will redeem thee, well -- let him redeem; but if he like not to  redeem thee, then will I redeem thee, [as] Jehovah liveth. Lie  down until the morning.
3:13|KJV|Tarry this night, and it shall be in the morning, that if he will perform unto thee the part of a kinsman, well; let him do the kinsman's part: but if he will not do the part of a kinsman to thee, then will I do the part of a kinsman to thee, as the LORD liveth: lie down until the morning.
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你今夜在這埵穜J，明早他若肯為你盡親人的本分，就由他盡好了。倘若不肯，我指著永活的耶和華起誓，我必為你盡親人的本分，你只管躺到黎明。
3:14|ASV|And she lay at his feet until the morning. And she rose up before one could discern another. For he said, Let it not be known that the woman came to the threshing-floor.
3:14|Darby|And she lay at his feet until the morning; and she rose up  before one could know another. And he said, Let it not be known  that a woman came into the threshing-floor.
3:14|KJV|And she lay at his feet until the morning: and she rose up before one could know another. And he said, Let it not be known that a woman came into the floor.
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|路得便在他腳邊躺到黎明，人彼此還不能辨認的時候就起來了；因為波阿斯說，不可使人知道有女子到禾場上來。
3:15|ASV|And he said, Bring the mantle that is upon thee, and hold it; and she held it; and he measured six measures of barley, and laid it on her: and he went into the city.
3:15|Darby|And he said, Bring the cloak that thou hast upon thee, and  hold it. And she held it, and he measured six [measures] of  barley, and laid [it] on her; and he went into the city.
3:15|KJV|Also he said, Bring the vail that thou hast upon thee, and hold it. And when she held it, he measured six measures of barley, and laid it on her: and she went into the city.
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他又說，把你所披的外衣拿來打開。她打開了，波阿斯就量了六簸箕大麥，放在她肩上，他便進城去了。
3:16|ASV|And when she came to her mother-in-law, she said, Who art thou, my daughter? And she told her all that the man had done to her.
3:16|Darby|And she came to her mother-in-law; and she said, Who art  thou, my daughter? And she told her all that the man had done  to her.
3:16|KJV|And when she came to her mother in law, she said, Who art thou, my daughter? And she told her all that the man had done to her.
3:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|路得回到婆婆那堙A婆婆說，女兒阿，怎麼樣了？路得就將那人為她所行的一切都告訴婆婆，
3:17|ASV|And she said, These six  measures of barley gave he me; for he said, Go not empty unto thy mother-in-law.
3:17|Darby|And she said, These six [measures] of barley gave he me;  for he said to me, Go not empty to thy mother-in-law.
3:17|KJV|And she said, These six measures of barley gave he me; for he said to me, Go not empty unto thy mother in law.
3:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|又說，他給了我這六簸箕大麥，因他說，你不可空手回去見你的婆婆。
3:18<version name="ASV">Then said she, Sit still, my daughter, until thou know how the matter will fall; for the man will not rest, until he have finished the thing this day. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:18<version name="Darby">Then she said, Be still, my daughter, until thou know how  the matter will fall; for the man will not rest until he have  completed the matter this day. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:18<version name="KJV">Then said she, Sit still, my daughter, until thou know how the matter will fall: for the man will not be in rest, until he have finished the thing this day.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|婆婆說，女兒阿，你只管安坐等候，看這事怎樣成就，因為那人今日不辦成這事必不休息。
4:1|ASV|Now Boaz went up to the gate, and sat him down there: and, behold, the near kinsman of whom Boaz spake came by; unto whom he said, Ho, such a one! turn aside, sit down here. And he turned aside, and sat down.
4:1|Darby|And Boaz went up to the gate, and sat down there. And  behold, he that had the right of redemption, of whom Boaz had  spoken, came by. And he said, Thou, such a one, turn aside, sit  down here. And he turned aside and sat down.
4:1|KJV|Then went Boaz up to the gate, and sat him down there: and, behold, the kinsman of whom Boaz spake came by; unto whom he said, Ho, such a one! turn aside, sit down here. And he turned aside, and sat down.
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|波阿斯上城門去，坐在那堙A恰巧波阿斯所說的那親人經過。波阿斯說，某人哪，你轉過來坐在這堙C他就轉過來坐下。
4:2|ASV|And he took ten men of the elders of the city, and said, Sit ye down here. And they sat down.
4:2|Darby|And he took ten men of the elders of the city, and said, Sit  down here. And they sat down.
4:2|KJV|And he took ten men of the elders of the city, and said, Sit ye down here. And they sat down.
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|波阿斯又從本城的長老中選取了十個人，對他們說，請你們坐在這堙C他們就都坐下。
4:3|ASV|And he said unto the near kinsman, Naomi, that is come again out of the country of Moab, selleth the parcel of land, which was our brother Elimelech's:
4:3|Darby|And he said to him that had the right of redemption: Naomi,  who is come back out of the country of Moab, sells the  allotment that was our brother Elimelech's.
4:3|KJV|And he said unto the kinsman, Naomi, that is come again out of the country of Moab, selleth a parcel of land, which was our brother Elimelech's:
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|波阿斯對那親人說，從摩押鄉間回來的拿俄米，現在要賣我們弟兄以利米勒的那塊田地；
4:4|ASV|And I thought to disclose it unto thee, saying, Buy it before them that sit here, and before the elders of my people. If thou wilt redeem it, redeem it: but if thou wilt not redeem it, then tell me, that I may know; for there is none to redeem it besides thee; and I am after thee. And he said, I will redeem it.
4:4|Darby|And I thought I would apprise thee of it and say, Buy [it]  in the presence of the inhabitants, and in the presence of the  elders of my people. If thou wilt redeem [it], redeem; but if  thou wilt not redeem, tell me, that I may know; for there is  none to redeem besides thee; and I am after thee. And he said,  I will redeem [it].
4:4|KJV|And I thought to advertise thee, saying, Buy it before the inhabitants, and before the elders of my people. If thou wilt redeem it, redeem it: but if thou wilt not redeem it, then tell me, that I may know: for there is none to redeem it beside thee; and I am after thee. And he said, I will redeem it.
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我想我應當向你表明，說，你可以在這塈今菄漱H面前和我族人的長老面前買這塊田地。你若肯贖就贖，若不肯贖就告訴我，讓我知道；因為只有你可以贖，其次就是我。那人回答說，我肯贖。
4:5|ASV|Then said Boaz, What day thou buyest the field of the hand of Naomi, thou must buy it also of Ruth the Moabitess, the wife of the dead, to raise up the name of the dead upon his inheritance.
4:5|Darby|And Boaz said, On the day thou buyest the field of the hand  of Naomi, thou must buy [it] also of Ruth the Moabitess, the  wife of the dead, to raise up the name of the dead upon his  inheritance.
4:5|KJV|Then said Boaz, What day thou buyest the field of the hand of Naomi, thou must buy it also of Ruth the Moabitess, the wife of the dead, to raise up the name of the dead upon his inheritance.
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|波阿斯說，你從拿俄米手中買這田地的時候，也當娶死人的妻摩押女子路得，叫死人的名得以在他的產業上存立。
4:6|ASV|And the near kinsman said, I cannot redeem it for myself, lest I mar mine own inheritance: take thou my right of redemption on thee; for I cannot redeem it.
4:6|Darby|And he that had the right of redemption said, I cannot  redeem [it] for myself, lest I mar mine own inheritance. Redeem  thou for thyself what I should redeem, for I cannot redeem  [it].
4:6|KJV|And the kinsman said, I cannot redeem it for myself, lest I mar mine own inheritance: redeem thou my right to thyself; for I cannot redeem it.
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那親人說，這樣我自己就不能贖了，恐怕於我的產業有損。你自己可以贖我所當贖的，因我不能贖了。
4:7|ASV|Now this was the custom in former time in Israel concerning redeeming and concerning exchanging, to confirm all things: a man drew off his shoe, and gave it to his neighbor; and this was the manner of attestation in Israel.
4:7|Darby|Now this [was the custom] in former time in Israel  concerning redemption and concerning exchange, to confirm the  whole matter: a man drew off his sandal, and gave it to his  neighbour, and this was the [mode of] attestation in Israel.
4:7|KJV|Now this was the manner in former time in Israel concerning redeeming and concerning changing, for to confirm all things; a man plucked off his shoe, and gave it to his neighbour: and this was a testimony in Israel.
4:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|從前，在以色列中要確立甚麼事，或贖回，或交易，這人就脫鞋給那人。以色列中乃是以此為證據。
4:8|ASV|So the near kinsman said unto Boaz, Buy it for thyself. And he drew off his shoe.
4:8|Darby|And he that had the right of redemption said to Boaz, Buy  for thyself; and he drew off his sandal.
4:8|KJV|Therefore the kinsman said unto Boaz, Buy it for thee. So he drew off his shoe.
4:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那親人對波阿斯說，你自己買罷；於是將鞋脫下來了。
4:9|ASV|And Boaz said unto the elders, and unto all the people, Ye are witnesses this day, that I have bought all that was Elimelech's, and all that was Chilion's and Mahlon's, of the hand of Naomi.
4:9|Darby|And Boaz said to the elders and all the people, Ye are  witnesses this day, that I have bought all that was  Elimelech's, and all that was Chilion's and Mahlon's, of the  hand of Naomi;
4:9|KJV|And Boaz said unto the elders, and unto all the people, Ye are witnesses this day, that I have bought all that was Elimelech's, and all that was Chilion's and Mahlon's, of the hand of Naomi.
4:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|波阿斯對長老和眾民說，你們今日作見證，凡屬以利米勒和基連、瑪倫的，我都從拿俄米手中置買了；
4:10|ASV|Moreover Ruth the Moabitess, the wife of Mahlon, have I purchased to be my wife, to raise up the name of the dead upon his inheritance, that the name of the dead be not cut off from among his brethren, and from the gate of his place: ye are witnesses this day.
4:10|Darby|moreover Ruth the Moabitess, the wife of Mahlon, have I  purchased to be my wife, to raise up the name of the dead upon  his inheritance, that the name of the dead be not cut off from  among his brethren and from the gate of his place: ye are  witnesses this day.
4:10|KJV|Moreover Ruth the Moabitess, the wife of Mahlon, have I purchased to be my wife, to raise up the name of the dead upon his inheritance, that the name of the dead be not cut off from among his brethren, and from the gate of his place: ye are witnesses this day.
4:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我又娶了瑪倫的妻摩押女子路得為妻，好叫死人的名得以在他的產業上存立，免得死人的名從他的弟兄中，並從他本鄉滅沒。你們今日可以作見證。
4:11|ASV|And all the people that were in the gate, and the elders, said, We are witnesses. Jehovah make the woman that is come into thy house like Rachel and like Leah, which two did build the house of Israel: and do thou worthily in Ephrathah, and be famous in Bethlehem:
4:11|Darby|And all the people that were in the gate and the elders  said, [We are] witnesses. Jehovah make the woman that cometh  into thy house like Rachel and like Leah, which two did build  the house of Israel; and acquire power in Ephratah, and make  thyself a name in Bethlehem;
4:11|KJV|And all the people that were in the gate, and the elders, said, We are witnesses. The LORD make the woman that is come into thine house like Rachel and like Leah, which two did build the house of Israel: and do thou worthily in Ephratah, and be famous in Bethlehem:
4:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在城門坐著的眾民和長老都說，我們作見證。願耶和華使進你家的這女子，像建立以色列家的拉結、利亞二人一樣。又願你在以法他得財富，在伯利恆得名聲。
4:12|ASV|and let thy house be like the house of Perez, whom Tamar bare unto Judah, of the seed which Jehovah shall give thee of this young woman.
4:12|Darby|and let thy house become like the house of Pherez, whom  Tamar bore to Judah, of the seed which Jehovah shall give thee  of this young woman.
4:12|KJV|And let thy house be like the house of Pharez, whom Tamar bare unto Judah, of the seed which the LORD shall give thee of this young woman.
4:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願耶和華從這少年女子賜你後裔，使你的家像他瑪從猶大所生法勒斯的家一般。
4:13|ASV|So Boaz took Ruth, and she became his wife; and he went in unto her, and Jehovah gave her conception, and she bare a son.
4:13|Darby|And Boaz took Ruth, and she became his wife; and he went in  unto her, and Jehovah gave her conception, and she bore a son.
4:13|KJV|So Boaz took Ruth, and she was his wife: and when he went in unto her, the LORD gave her conception, and she bare a son.
4:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|於是，波阿斯娶了路得為妻，與她同房。耶和華使她懷孕，她就生了一個兒子。
4:14|ASV|And the women said unto Naomi, Blessed be Jehovah, who hath not left thee this day without a near kinsman; and let his name be famous in Israel.
4:14|Darby|And the women said to Naomi, Blessed be Jehovah who hath  not left thee this day without one that has the right of  redemption, and may his name be famous in Israel!
4:14|KJV|And the women said unto Naomi, Blessed be the LORD, which hath not left thee this day without a kinsman, that his name may be famous in Israel.
4:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|婦人們對拿俄米說，耶和華是當受頌讚的，祂今日沒有撇下你使你無親人；願這孩子在以色列中得名聲。
4:15|ASV|And he shall be unto thee a restorer of life, and a nourisher of thine old age, for thy daughter-in-law, who loveth thee, who is better to thee than seven sons, hath borne him.
4:15|Darby|And he shall be to thee a restorer of thy life, and a  nourisher of thine old age; for thy daughter-in-law who loves  thee, who is better to thee than seven sons, has borne him.
4:15|KJV|And he shall be unto thee a restorer of thy life, and a nourisher of thine old age: for thy daughter in law, which loveth thee, which is better to thee than seven sons, hath born him.
4:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他必使你的精神復甦，並且奉養你的老，因為他是那愛你的兒媳所生的；有這兒媳比有七個兒子還好。
4:16|ASV|And Naomi took the child, and laid it in her bosom, and became nurse unto it.
4:16|Darby|And Naomi took the child, and laid it in her bosom, and  became nurse to it.
4:16|KJV|And Naomi took the child, and laid it in her bosom, and became nurse unto it.
4:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|拿俄米就把孩子抱在懷中，作他的養母。
4:17|ASV|And the women her neighbors gave it a name, saying, There is a son born to Naomi; and they called his name Obed: he is the father of Jesse, the father of David.
4:17|Darby|And the women [her] neighbours gave it a name, saying,  There is a son born to Naomi. And they called his name Obed. He  is the father of Jesse, the father of David.
4:17|KJV|And the women her neighbours gave it a name, saying, There is a son born to Naomi; and they called his name Obed: he is the father of Jesse, the father of David.
4:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|鄰舍的婦人給孩子起名，說，拿俄米得兒子了；就給他起名叫俄備得。這俄備得是耶西的父，耶西是大衛的父。
4:18|ASV|Now these are the generations of Perez: Perez begat Hezron,
4:18|Darby|Now these are the generations of Pherez. Pherez begot  Hezron,
4:18|KJV|Now these are the generations of Pharez: Pharez begat Hezron,
4:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|法勒斯的後代記在下面：法勒斯生希斯崙，
4:19|ASV|and Hezron begat Ram, and Ram begat Amminadab,
4:19|Darby|and Hezron begot Ram, and Ram begot Amminadab,
4:19|KJV|And Hezron begat Ram, and Ram begat Amminadab,
4:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|希斯崙生蘭，蘭生亞米拿達，
4:20|ASV|and Amminadab begat Nahshon, and Nahshon begat Salmon,
4:20|Darby|and Amminadab begot Nahshon, and Nahshon begot Salmon,
4:20|KJV|And Amminadab begat Nahshon, and Nahshon begat Salmon,
4:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|亞米拿達生拿順，拿順生撒門，
4:21|ASV|and Salmon begat Boaz, and Boaz begat Obed,
4:21|Darby|and Salmon begot Boaz, and Boaz begot Obed,
4:21|KJV|And Salmon begat Boaz, and Boaz begat Obed,
4:21|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|撒門生波阿斯，波阿斯生俄備得，
4:22<version name="ASV">and Obed begat Jesse, and Jesse begat David. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:22<version name="Darby">and Obed begot Jesse, and Jesse begot David. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:22<version name="KJV">And Obed begat Jesse, and Jesse begat David.</p><p /><br /></version>
4:22|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|俄備得生耶西，耶西生大衛。
