1:1|ASV|The Song of songs, which is Solomon's.
1:1|Darby|The song of songs, which is Solomon's.
1:1|KJV|The song of songs, which is Solomon's.
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|歌中的歌，就是所羅門的歌。
1:2|ASV|Let him kiss me with the kisses of his mouth; For thy love is better than wine.
1:2|Darby|Let him kiss me with the kisses of his mouth; For thy love  is better than wine.
1:2|KJV|Let him kiss me with the kisses of his mouth: for thy love is better than wine.
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|願他用口與我親嘴！因你的愛情比酒更美。
1:3|ASV|Thine oils have a goodly fragrance; Thy name is as oil poured forth; Therefore do the virgins love thee.
1:3|Darby|Thine ointments savour sweetly; Thy name is an ointment  poured forth: Therefore do the virgins love thee.
1:3|KJV|Because of the savour of thy good ointments thy name is as ointment poured forth, therefore do the virgins love thee.
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你的膏油馨香；你的名如同倒出來的香膏，所以眾童女都愛你。
1:4|ASV|Draw me; we will run after thee: The king hath brought me into his chambers; We will be glad and rejoice in thee; We will make mention of thy love more than of wine: Rightly do they love thee.
1:4|Darby|Draw me, we will run after thee! -- The king hath brought me  into his chambers -- We will be glad and rejoice in thee, We  will remember thy love more than wine. They love thee  uprightly.
1:4|KJV|Draw me, we will run after thee: the king hath brought me into his chambers: we will be glad and rejoice in thee, we will remember thy love more than wine: the upright love thee.
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王帶我進了他的內室－我們必因你歡喜快樂；我們要稱讚你的愛情，勝似稱讚美酒。她們愛你是理所當然的。
1:5|ASV|I am black, but comely, Oh ye daughters of Jerusalem, As the tents of Kedar, As the curtains of Solomon.
1:5|Darby|I am black, but comely, daughters of Jerusalem, As the tents  of Kedar, As the curtains of Solomon.
1:5|KJV|I am black, but comely, O ye daughters of Jerusalem, as the tents of Kedar, as the curtains of Solomon.
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶路撒冷的眾女子阿，我雖然黑，卻是秀美，如同基達的帳棚，好像所羅門的幔子。
1:6|ASV|Look not upon me, because I am swarthy, Because the sun hath scorched me. My mother's sons were incensed against me; They made me keeper of the vineyards; But mine own vineyard have I not kept.
1:6|Darby|Look not upon me, because I am black; Because the sun hath  looked upon me. My mother's children were angry with me: They  made me keeper of the vineyards; Mine own vineyard have I not  kept.
1:6|KJV|Look not upon me, because I am black, because the sun hath looked upon me: my mother's children were angry with me; they made me the keeper of the vineyards; but mine own vineyard have I not kept.
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不要看我，因為我是黑的，因為日頭把我曬黑了。我同母的弟兄向我發怒；他們使我看守葡萄園；我自己的葡萄園，我卻沒有看守。
1:7|ASV|Tell me, O thou whom my soul loveth, Where thou feedest thy flock, Where thou makest it to rest at noon: For why should I be as one that is veiled Beside the flocks of thy companions?
1:7|Darby|Tell me, thou whom my soul loveth, Where thou feedest [thy  flock], Where thou makest it to rest at noon; For why should I  be as one veiled Beside the flocks of thy companions?
1:7|KJV|Tell me, O thou whom my soul loveth, where thou feedest, where thou makest thy flock to rest at noon: for why should I be as one that turneth aside by the flocks of thy companions?
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我心所愛的阿，求你告訴我，你在何處牧放羊群？晌午在何處使羊群歇臥？我何必在你眾同伴的羊群旁邊，好像蒙著臉的人呢？
1:8|ASV|If thou know not, O thou fairest among women, Go thy way forth by the footsteps of the flock, And feed thy kids beside the shepherds' tents.
1:8|Darby|If thou know not, thou fairest among women, Go thy way forth  by the footsteps of the flock, And feed thy kids beside the  shepherds' booths.
1:8|KJV|If thou know not, O thou fairest among women, go thy way forth by the footsteps of the flock, and feed thy kids beside the shepherds' tents.
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你這女子中極美麗的，你若不知道，只管出去跟隨羊群的腳蹤，把你的山羊羔牧放在牧人帳棚的旁邊。
1:9|ASV|I have compared thee, O my love, To a steed in Pharaoh's chariots.
1:9|Darby|I compare thee, my love, To a steed in Pharaoh's chariots.
1:9|KJV|I have compared thee, O my love, to a company of horses in Pharaoh's chariots.
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的佳偶，我將你比作法老車上套的駿馬。
1:10|ASV|Thy cheeks are comely with plaits of hair, Thy neck with strings of jewels.
1:10|Darby|Thy cheeks are comely with bead-rows, Thy neck with  ornamental chains.
1:10|KJV|Thy cheeks are comely with rows of jewels, thy neck with chains of gold.
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你的兩腮，因髮辮的妝飾而秀美；你的頸項，因珠串而美麗。
1:11|ASV|We will make thee plaits of gold With studs of silver.
1:11|Darby|We will make thee bead-rows of gold With studs of silver.
1:11|KJV|We will make thee borders of gold with studs of silver.
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們要為你編上金辮，鑲上銀釘。
1:12|ASV|While the king sat at his table, My spikenard sent forth its fragrance.
1:12|Darby|While the king is at his table, My spikenard sendeth forth  its fragrance.
1:12|KJV|While the king sitteth at his table, my spikenard sendeth forth the smell thereof.
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王正坐席的時候，我的哪噠香膏發出香味。
1:13|ASV|My beloved is unto me as a bundle of myrrh, That lieth betwixt my breasts.
1:13|Darby|A bundle of myrrh is my beloved unto me; He shall pass the  night between my breasts.
1:13|KJV|A bundle of myrrh is my well-beloved unto me; he shall lie all night betwixt my breasts.
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我以我的良人為一袋沒藥，夜堹d在我的胸懷間。
1:14|ASV|My beloved is unto me as a cluster of henna-flowers In the vineyards of En-gedi.
1:14|Darby|My beloved is unto me a cluster of henna-flowers In the  vineyards of Engedi.
1:14|KJV|My beloved is unto me as a cluster of camphire in the vineyards of Engedi.
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我以我的良人為一束鳳仙花，在隱基底的葡萄園中。
1:15|ASV|Behold, thou art fair, my love; Behold thou art fair; Thine eyes are as doves.
1:15|Darby|Behold, thou art fair, my love; Behold, thou art fair:  thine eyes are doves.
1:15|KJV|Behold, thou art fair, my love; behold, thou art fair; thou hast doves' eyes.
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|看哪，我的佳偶，你是美麗的！你是美麗的！你的眼好像鴿子。
1:16|ASV|Behold, thou art fair, my beloved, yea, pleasant: Also our couch is green.
1:16|Darby|Behold, thou art fair, my beloved, yea, pleasant; Also our  bed is green.
1:16|KJV|Behold, thou art fair, my beloved, yea, pleasant: also our bed is green.
1:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們的床榻是翠綠的，
1:17<version name="ASV">The beams of our house are cedars, And our rafters are firs. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:17<version name="Darby">The beams of our houses are cedars, Our rafters are  cypresses. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:17<version name="KJV">The beams of our house are cedar, and our rafters of fir.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們房屋的棟梁是香柏木，椽子是松木。
2:1|ASV|I am a rose of Sharon, A lily of the valleys.
2:1|Darby|I am a narcissus of Sharon, A lily of the valleys.
2:1|KJV|I am the rose of Sharon, and the lily of the valleys.
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我是沙崙的玫瑰花，是谷中的百合花。
2:2|ASV|As a lily among thorns, So is my love among the daughters.
2:2|Darby|As the lily among thorns, So is my love among the daughters.
2:2|KJV|As the lily among thorns, so is my love among the daughters.
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的佳偶在女子中，好像百合花在荊棘中。
2:3|ASV|As the apple-tree among the trees of the wood, So is my beloved among the sons. I sat down under his shadow with great delight, And his fruit was sweet to my taste.
2:3|Darby|As the apple-tree among the trees of the wood, So is my  beloved among the sons: In his shadow have I rapture and sit  down; And his fruit is sweet to my taste.
2:3|KJV|As the apple tree among the trees of the wood, so is my beloved among the sons. I sat down under his shadow with great delight, and his fruit was sweet to my taste.
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的良人在男子中，如同蘋果樹在樹林中。
2:4|ASV|He brought me to the banqueting-house, And his banner over me was love.
2:4|Darby|He hath brought me to the house of wine, And his banner over  me is love.
2:4|KJV|He brought me to the banqueting house, and his banner over me was love.
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他帶我進入筵宴所，以愛為旗在我以上。
2:5|ASV|Stay ye me with raisins, refresh me with apples; For I am sick from love.
2:5|Darby|Sustain ye me with raisin-cakes, Refresh me with apples; For  I am sick of love.
2:5|KJV|Stay me with flagons, comfort me with apples: for I am sick of love.
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|求你們用葡萄餅增補我力，用蘋果使我甦醒，因為我因愛成病。
2:6|ASV|His left hand is under my head, And his right hand doth embrace me.
2:6|Darby|His left hand is under my head, And his right hand doth  embrace me.
2:6|KJV|His left hand is under my head, and his right hand doth embrace me.
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他的左手在我頭下，他的右手將我抱住。
2:7|ASV|I adjure you, O daughters of Jerusalem, By the roes, or by the hinds of the field, That ye stir not up, nor awake my love, Until he please.
2:7|Darby|I charge you, daughters of Jerusalem, By the gazelles, or by  the hinds of the field, That ye stir not up, nor awake [my]  love, till he please.
2:7|KJV|I charge you, O ye daughters of Jerusalem, by the roes, and by the hinds of the field, that ye stir not up, nor awake my love, till he please.
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶路撒冷的眾女子阿，我指著羚羊或田野的母鹿鄭重的囑咐你們，不要驚動，不要叫醒我所愛的，等她自己情願。
2:8|ASV|The voice of my beloved! behold, he cometh, Leaping upon the mountains, Skipping upon the hills.
2:8|Darby|The voice of my beloved! Behold, he cometh Leaping upon the  mountains, Skipping upon the hills.
2:8|KJV|The voice of my beloved! behold, he cometh leaping upon the mountains, skipping upon the hills.
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|聽阿，是我良人的聲音；看哪，他躥山越嶺而來。
2:9|ASV|My beloved is like a roe or a young hart: Behold, he standeth behind our wall; He looketh in at the windows; He glanceth through the lattice.
2:9|Darby|My beloved is like a gazelle or a young hart. Behold, he  standeth behind our wall, He looketh in through the windows,  Glancing through the lattice.
2:9|KJV|My beloved is like a roe or a young hart: behold, he standeth behind our wall, he looketh forth at the windows, shewing himself through the lattice.
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的良人好像羚羊，或像小牡鹿。他站在我們牆壁後，從窗戶往媃[看，從窗櫺往堭斯齱C
2:10|ASV|My beloved spake, and said unto me, Rise up, my love, my fair one, and come away.
2:10|Darby|My beloved spake and said unto me, Rise up, my love, my  fair one, and come away.
2:10|KJV|My beloved spake, and said unto me, Rise up, my love, my fair one, and come away.
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我良人回應我說，我的佳偶，我的美人，起來，與我同去；
2:11|ASV|For, lo, the winter is past; The rain is over and gone;
2:11|Darby|For behold, the winter is past, The rain is over, it is  gone:
2:11|KJV|For, lo, the winter is past, the rain is over and gone;
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為冬天已過，雨水也止住過去了。
2:12|ASV|The flowers appear on the earth; The time of the singing of birds is come, And the voice of the turtle-dove is heard in our land;
2:12|Darby|The flowers appear on the earth; The time of singing is  come, And the voice of the turtle-dove is heard in our land;
2:12|KJV|The flowers appear on the earth; the time of the singing of birds is come, and the voice of the turtle is heard in our land;
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|地上百花開放，百鳥鳴叫的時候已經來到；斑鳩的聲音在我們境內也聽見了。
2:13|ASV|The fig-tree ripeneth her green figs, And the vines are in blossom; They give forth their fragrance. Arise, my love, my fair one, and come away.
2:13|Darby|The fig-tree melloweth her winter figs, And the vines in  bloom give forth [their] fragrance. Arise, my love, my fair  one, and come away!
2:13|KJV|The fig tree putteth forth her green figs, and the vines with the tender grape give a good smell. Arise, my love, my fair one, and come away.
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|無花果樹的果子漸漸成熟，葡萄樹開花放香。我的佳偶，我的美人，起來，與我同去。
2:14|ASV|O my dove, that art in the clefts of the rock, In the covert of the steep place, Let me see thy countenance, Let me hear thy voice; For sweet is thy voice, and thy countenance is comely.
2:14|Darby|My dove, in the clefts of the rock, In the covert of the  precipice, Let me see thy countenance, let me hear thy voice;  For sweet is thy voice, and thy countenance is comely.
2:14|KJV|O my dove, that art in the clefts of the rock, in the secret places of the stairs, let me see thy countenance, let me hear thy voice; for sweet is thy voice, and thy countenance is comely.
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的鴿子阿，你在磐石穴中，在陡巖的隱密處，求你讓我得見你的面貌，得聽你的聲音；因為你的聲音甘甜，你的面貌秀美。
2:15|ASV|Take us the foxes, the little foxes, That spoil the vineyards; For our vineyards are in blossom.
2:15|Darby|Take us the foxes, The little foxes, that spoil the  vineyards; For our vineyards are in bloom.
2:15|KJV|Take us the foxes, the little foxes, that spoil the vines: for our vines have tender grapes.
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|要給我們擒拿狐狸，就是毀壞葡萄園的小狐狸；因為我們的葡萄園正在開花。
2:16|ASV|My beloved is mine, and I am his: He feedeth his flock among the lilies.
2:16|Darby|My beloved is mine, and I am his; He feedeth [his flock]  among the lilies,
2:16|KJV|My beloved is mine, and I am his: he feedeth among the lilies.
2:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的良人屬我，我也屬他；他在百合花中牧放群羊。
2:17<version name="ASV">Until the day be cool, and the shadows flee away, Turn, my beloved, and be thou like a roe or a young hart Upon the mountains of Bether. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:17<version name="Darby">Until the day dawn, and the shadows flee away. Turn, my  beloved: be thou like a gazelle or a young hart, Upon the  mountains of Bether. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:17<version name="KJV">Until the day break, and the shadows flee away, turn, my beloved, and be thou like a roe or a young hart upon the mountains of Bether.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的良人哪，等到天亮，黑影飛去的時候，你要轉回，好像羚羊，或像小牡鹿在比特山上。
3:1|ASV|By night on my bed I sought him whom my soul loveth: I sought him, but I found him not.
3:1|Darby|On my bed, in the nights, I sought him whom my soul loveth:  I sought him, but I found him not.
3:1|KJV|By night on my bed I sought him whom my soul loveth: I sought him, but I found him not.
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我夜夜在床上尋找我心所愛的；我尋找他，卻尋不見。
3:2|ASV|I said, I will rise now, and go about the city; In the streets and in the broad ways I will seek him whom my soul loveth: I sought him, but I found him not.
3:2|Darby|I will rise now, and go about the city; In the streets and  in the broadways Will I seek him whom my soul loveth: I sought  him, but I found him not.
3:2|KJV|I will rise now, and go about the city in the streets, and in the broad ways I will seek him whom my soul loveth: I sought him, but I found him not.
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我說，我要起來，繞行城中，在街道上，在寬闊處，尋找我心所愛的。我尋找他，卻尋不見。
3:3|ASV|The watchmen that go about the city found me; To whom I said, Saw ye him whom my soul loveth?
3:3|Darby|The watchmen that go about the city found me: -- Have ye  seen him whom my soul loveth?
3:3|KJV|The watchmen that go about the city found me: to whom I said, Saw ye him whom my soul loveth?
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|城中巡邏看守的人遇見我；我問他們：你們看見我心所愛的沒有？
3:4|ASV|It was but a little that I passed from them, When I found him whom my soul loveth: I held him, and would not let him go, Until I had brought him into my mother's house, And into the chamber of her that conceived me.
3:4|Darby|-- Scarcely had I passed from them, When I found him whom my  soul loveth: I held him, and would not let him go, Until I had  brought him into my mother's house, And into the chamber of her  that conceived me.
3:4|KJV|It was but a little that I passed from them, but I found him whom my soul loveth: I held him, and would not let him go, until I had brought him into my mother's house, and into the chamber of her that conceived me.
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我剛離開他們，就遇見我心所愛的；我拉住他，不讓他走，直到領他進我母家，到懷我者的內室。
3:5|ASV|I adjure you, O daughters of Jerusalem, By the roes, or by the hinds of the field, That ye stir not up, nor awake my love, Until he please.
3:5|Darby|I charge you, daughters of Jerusalem, By the gazelles, or by  the hinds of the field, That ye stir not up, nor awake [my]  love, till he please.
3:5|KJV|I charge you, O ye daughters of Jerusalem, by the roes, and by the hinds of the field, that ye stir not up, nor awake my love, till he please.
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶路撒冷的眾女子阿，我指著羚羊或田野的母鹿鄭重的囑咐你們，不要驚動，不要叫醒我所愛的，等她自己情願。
3:6|ASV|Who is this that cometh up from the wilderness Like pillars of smoke, Perfumed with myrrh and frankincense, With all powders of the merchant?
3:6|Darby|Who is this, [she] that cometh up from the wilderness Like  pillars of smoke, Perfumed with myrrh and frankincense, With  all powders of the merchant? ...
3:6|KJV|Who is this that cometh out of the wilderness like pillars of smoke, perfumed with myrrh and frankincense, with all powders of the merchant?
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那從曠野上來，形狀如煙柱，以沒藥和乳香，並商人各樣香粉薰的，是誰呢？
3:7|ASV|Behold, it is the litter of Solomon; Threescore mighty men are about it, Of the mighty men of Israel.
3:7|Darby|Behold his couch, Solomon's own: Threescore mighty men are  about it, Of the mighty of Israel.
3:7|KJV|Behold his bed, which is Solomon's; threescore valiant men are about it, of the valiant of Israel.
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|看哪，是所羅門的臥榻；四圍有六十個勇士，都是以色列中的勇士。
3:8|ASV|They all handle the sword, and are expert in war: Every man hath his sword upon his thigh, Because of fear in the night.
3:8|Darby|They all hold the sword, Experts in war; Each hath his sword  upon his thigh Because of alarm in the nights.
3:8|KJV|They all hold swords, being expert in war: every man hath his sword upon his thigh because of fear in the night.
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|個個都拿著刀，善於爭戰；人人腰間佩刀，防備夜間有驚慌。
3:9|ASV|King Solomon made himself a palanquin Of the wood of Lebanon.
3:9|Darby|King Solomon made himself a palanquin Of the wood of  Lebanon.
3:9|KJV|King Solomon made himself a chariot of the wood of Lebanon.
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所羅門王用利巴嫩木，為自己製造一乘華轎。
3:10|ASV|He made the pillars thereof of silver, The bottom thereof of gold, the seat of it of purple, The midst thereof being paved with love, From the daughters of Jerusalem.
3:10|Darby|Its pillars he made of silver, Its support of gold, Its  seat of purple; The midst thereof was paved [with] love By the  daughters of Jerusalem.
3:10|KJV|He made the pillars thereof of silver, the bottom thereof of gold, the covering of it of purple, the midst thereof being paved with love, for the daughters of Jerusalem.
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|轎柱是用銀作的，轎底是用金作的；坐墊是紫色的；其中所鋪的，是耶路撒冷眾女子的愛情。
3:11<version name="ASV">Go forth, O ye daughters of Zion, and behold king Solomon, With the crown wherewith his mother hath crowned him In the day of his espousals, And in the day of the gladness of his heart. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:11<version name="Darby">Go forth, daughters of Zion, And behold king Solomon With  the crown wherewith his mother crowned him In the day of his  espousals, And in the day of the gladness of his heart. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:11<version name="KJV">Go forth, O ye daughters of Zion, and behold king Solomon with the crown wherewith his mother crowned him in the day of his espousals, and in the day of the gladness of his heart.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|錫安的眾女子阿，你們出去觀看所羅門王戴著冠冕，就是在他婚娶的日子，心中喜樂的時候，他母親給他戴上的。
4:1|ASV|Behold, thou art fair, my love; behold, thou art fair; Thine eyes are as doves behind thy veil. Thy hair is as a flock of goats, That lie along the side of mount Gilead.
4:1|Darby|Behold, thou art fair, my love; behold, thou art fair; Thine  eyes are doves behind thy veil; Thy hair is as a flock of  goats, On the slopes of mount Gilead.
4:1|KJV|Behold, thou art fair, my love; behold, thou art fair; thou hast doves' eyes within thy locks: thy hair is as a flock of goats, that appear from mount Gilead.
4:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|看哪，我的佳偶，你是美麗的！你是美麗的！你的眼在帕子內好像鴿子；你的頭髮如同山羊群，安臥在基列山旁。
4:2|ASV|Thy teeth are like a flock of ewes that are newly shorn, Which are come up from the washing, Whereof every one hath twins, And none is bereaved among them.
4:2|Darby|Thy teeth are like a flock of shorn sheep, Which go up from  the washing; Which have all borne twins, And none is barren  among them.
4:2|KJV|Thy teeth are like a flock of sheep that are even shorn, which came up from the washing; whereof every one bear twins, and none is barren among them.
4:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你的牙齒如剪過毛的一群母羊，洗淨上來，個個都有雙生，沒有一隻喪掉子的。
4:3|ASV|Thy lips are like a thread of scarlet, And thy mouth is comely. Thy temples are like a piece of a pomegranate Behind thy veil.
4:3|Darby|Thy lips are like a thread of scarlet, And thy speech is  comely; As a piece of a pomegranate are thy temples Behind thy  veil.
4:3|KJV|Thy lips are like a thread of scarlet, and thy speech is comely: thy temples are like a piece of a pomegranate within thy locks.
4:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你的脣好像一條朱紅線，你的嘴也秀美。你的兩腮在帕子內，如同一塊石榴。
4:4|ASV|Thy neck is like the tower of David builded for an armory, Whereon there hang a thousand bucklers, All the shields of the mighty men.
4:4|Darby|Thy neck is like the tower of David, Built for an armoury: A  thousand bucklers hang thereon, All shields of mighty men.
4:4|KJV|Thy neck is like the tower of David builded for an armoury, whereon there hang a thousand bucklers, all shields of mighty men.
4:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你的頸項好像大衛建造收藏軍器的高樓，其上懸掛一千盾牌，都是勇士的擋牌。
4:5|ASV|Thy two breasts are like two fawns That are twins of a roe, Which feed among the lilies.
4:5|Darby|Thy two breasts are like two fawns, twins of a gazelle,  Which feed among the lilies.
4:5|KJV|Thy two breasts are like two young roes that are twins, which feed among the lilies.
4:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你的兩乳好像百合花中喫草的一對小羚羊，就是母羚羊雙生的。
4:6|ASV|Until the day be cool, and the shadows flee away, I will get me to the mountain of myrrh, And to the hill of frankincense.
4:6|Darby|Until the day dawn, and the shadows flee away, I will get me  to the mountain of myrrh, And to the hill of frankincense.
4:6|KJV|Until the day break, and the shadows flee away, I will get me to the mountain of myrrh, and to the hill of frankincense.
4:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我要往沒藥山和乳香岡去，直等到天亮，黑影飛去的時候。
4:7|ASV|Thou art all fair, my love; And there is no spot in thee.
4:7|Darby|Thou art all fair, my love; And there is no spot in thee.
4:7|KJV|Thou art all fair, my love; there is no spot in thee.
4:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的佳偶，你全然美麗，毫無瑕疵。
4:8|ASV|Come with me from Lebanon, my bride, With me from Lebanon: Look from the top of Amana, From the top of Senir and Hermon, From the lions' dens, From the mountains of the leopards.
4:8|Darby|[Come] with me, from Lebanon, [my] spouse, With me from  Lebanon, -- Come, look from the top of Amanah, From the top of  Senir and Hermon, From the lions' dens, From the mountains of  the leopards.
4:8|KJV|Come with me from Lebanon, my spouse, with me from Lebanon: look from the top of Amana, from the top of Shenir and Hermon, from the lions' dens, from the mountains of the leopards.
4:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的新婦，求你與我一同從利巴嫩來，與我一同從利巴嫩來，從亞瑪拿頂，從示尼珥與黑門頂，從有獅子的洞穴，從有豹子的山嶺，來觀看。
4:9|ASV|Thou hast ravished my heart, my sister, my bride; Thou hast ravished my heart with one of thine eyes, With one chain of thy neck.
4:9|Darby|Thou hast ravished my heart, my sister, [my] spouse; Thou  hast ravished my heart with one of thine eyes, With one chain  of thy neck.
4:9|KJV|Thou hast ravished my heart, my sister, my spouse; thou hast ravished my heart with one of thine eyes, with one chain of thy neck.
4:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我妹子，我新婦，你奪了我的心；你用眼一看，用你項上的一條鍊子，奪了我的心。
4:10|ASV|How fair is thy love, my sister, my bride! How much better is thy love than wine! And the fragrance of thine oils than all manner of spices!
4:10|Darby|How fair is thy love, my sister, [my] spouse! How much  better is thy love than wine! And the fragrance of thine  ointments than all spices!
4:10|KJV|How fair is thy love, my sister, my spouse! how much better is thy love than wine! and the smell of thine ointments than all spices!
4:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我妹子，我新婦，你的愛情何等美麗！你的愛情比酒更美！你膏油的香氣勝過一切香品！
4:11|ASV|Thy lips, O my bride, drop as the honeycomb: Honey and milk are under thy tongue; And the smell of thy garments is like the smell of Lebanon.
4:11|Darby|Thy lips, [my] spouse, drop [as] the honeycomb; Honey and  milk are under thy tongue; And the smell of thy garments is  like the smell of Lebanon.
4:11|KJV|Thy lips, O my spouse, drop as the honeycomb: honey and milk are under thy tongue; and the smell of thy garments is like the smell of Lebanon.
4:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我新婦，你的嘴脣滴下新蜜；你的舌下有蜜有奶；你衣服的香氣如同利巴嫩的香氣。
4:12|ASV|A garden shut up is my sister, my bride; A spring shut up, a fountain sealed.
4:12|Darby|A garden enclosed is my sister, [my] spouse; A spring shut  up, a fountain sealed.
4:12|KJV|A garden inclosed is my sister, my spouse; a spring shut up, a fountain sealed.
4:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我妹子，我新婦，乃是關鎖的園，禁閉的井，封閉的泉。
4:13|ASV|Thy shoots are an orchard of pomegranates, with precious fruits; Henna with spikenard plants,
4:13|Darby|Thy shoots are a paradise of pomegranates, with precious  fruits; Henna with spikenard plants;
4:13|KJV|Thy plants are an orchard of pomegranates, with pleasant fruits; camphire, with spikenard,
4:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你所種的萌芽，成了石榴園，有佳美的果子、鳳仙花與哪噠樹，
4:14|ASV|Spikenard and saffron, Calamus and cinnamon, with all trees of frankincense; Myrrh and aloes, with all the chief spices.
4:14|Darby|Spikenard and saffron; Calamus and cinnamon, with all trees  of frankincense; Myrrh and aloes, with all the chief spices:
4:14|KJV|Spikenard and saffron; calamus and cinnamon, with all trees of frankincense; myrrh and aloes, with all the chief spices:
4:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有哪噠和番紅花，菖蒲和肉桂，並各樣乳香木、沒藥、沉香，與一切上等的香料。
4:15|ASV|Thou art a fountain of gardens, A well of living waters, And flowing streams from Lebanon.
4:15|Darby|A fountain in the gardens, A well of living waters, Which  stream from Lebanon.
4:15|KJV|A fountain of gardens, a well of living waters, and streams from Lebanon.
4:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你是園中的泉，活水的井，從利巴嫩流下來的溪水。
4:16<version name="ASV">Awake, O north wind; and come, thou south; Blow upon my garden, that the spices thereof may flow out. Let my beloved come into his garden, And eat his precious fruits. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:16<version name="Darby">Awake, north wind, and come, [thou] south; Blow upon my  garden, [that] the spices thereof may flow forth. Let my  beloved come into his garden, And eat its precious fruits. </p><p /><br /></version>
4:16<version name="KJV">Awake, O north wind; and come, thou south; blow upon my garden, that the spices thereof may flow out. Let my beloved come into his garden, and eat his pleasant fruits.</p><p /><br /></version>
4:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|北風阿，醒起！南風阿，吹來！吹在我的園內，使其中的香氣散發出來。願我的良人進入自己園堙A喫他佳美的果子。
5:1|ASV|I am come into my garden, my sister, my bride: I have gathered my myrrh with my spice; I have eaten my honeycomb with my honey; I have drunk my wine with my milk. Eat, O friends; Drink, yea, drink abundantly, O beloved.
5:1|Darby|I am come into my garden, my sister, [my] spouse; I have  gathered my myrrh with my spice; I have eaten my honeycomb with  my honey; I have drunk my wine with my milk. Eat, O friends;  drink, yea, drink abundantly, beloved ones!
5:1|KJV|I am come into my garden, my sister, my spouse: I have gathered my myrrh with my spice; I have eaten my honeycomb with my honey; I have drunk my wine with my milk: eat, O friends; drink, yea, drink abundantly, O beloved.
5:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我妹子，我新婦，我進了我的園中，採了我的沒藥和香料，喫了我的蜜房和蜂蜜，喝了我的酒和奶。朋友們哪，請喫；親愛的阿，請喝，且多多的喝！
5:2|ASV|I was asleep, but my heart waked: It is the voice of my beloved that knocketh, saying, Open to me, my sister, my love, my dove, my undefiled; For my head is filled with dew, My locks with the drops of the night.
5:2|Darby|I slept, but my heart was awake. The voice of my beloved! he  knocketh: Open to me, my sister, my love, my dove, mine  undefiled; For my head is filled with dew, My locks with the  drops of the night.
5:2|KJV|I sleep, but my heart waketh: it is the voice of my beloved that knocketh, saying, Open to me, my sister, my love, my dove, my undefiled: for my head is filled with dew, and my locks with the drops of the night.
5:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我身睡臥，我心卻醒。這是我良人的聲音！他敲門說，我的妹子，我的佳偶，我的鴿子，我的完全人，求你給我開門；因我的頭滿了露水，我的頭髮有夜露滴落。
5:3|ASV|I have put off my garment; how shall I put it on? I have washed my feet; how shall I defile them?
5:3|Darby|-- I have put off my tunic, how should I put it on? I have  washed my feet, how should I pollute them? --
5:3|KJV|I have put off my coat; how shall I put it on? I have washed my feet; how shall I defile them?
5:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我回答說，我脫了衣裳，怎能再穿上呢？我洗了腳，怎能再玷污呢？
5:4|ASV|My beloved put in his hand by the hole of the door, And my heart was moved for him.
5:4|Darby|My beloved put in his hand by the hole [of the door]; And my  bowels yearned for him.
5:4|KJV|My beloved put in his hand by the hole of the door, and my bowels were moved for him.
5:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的良人從門孔埵鬤i手來，我便因他動了心腸。
5:5|ASV|I rose up to open to my beloved; And my hands droppeth with myrrh, And my fingers with liquid myrrh, Upon the handles of the bolt.
5:5|Darby|I rose up to open to my beloved; And my hands dropped with  myrrh, And my fingers with liquid myrrh, Upon the handles of  the lock.
5:5|KJV|I rose up to open to my beloved; and my hands dropped with myrrh, and my fingers with sweet smelling myrrh, upon the handles of the lock.
5:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我起來，要給我良人開門；我的兩手滴下沒藥，我的指頭有沒藥汁滴在閂把上。
5:6|ASV|I opened to my beloved; But my beloved had withdrawn himself, and was gone. My soul had failed me when he spake: I sought him, but I could not find him; I called him, but he gave me no answer.
5:6|Darby|I opened to my beloved; But my beloved had withdrawn  himself; he was gone: My soul went forth when he spoke. I  sought him, but I found him not; I called him, but he gave me  no answer.
5:6|KJV|I opened to my beloved; but my beloved had withdrawn himself, and was gone: my soul failed when he spake: I sought him, but I could not find him; I called him, but he gave me no answer.
5:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我給我的良人開了門；我的良人卻已轉身走了。他說話的時候，我魂不守舍；我尋找他，竟尋不見；我呼叫他，他卻不回答。
5:7|ASV|The watchmen that go about the city found me, They smote me, they wounded me; The keepers of the walls took away my mantle from me.
5:7|Darby|The watchmen that went about the city found me; They smote  me, they wounded me; The keepers of the walls took away my veil  from me.
5:7|KJV|The watchmen that went about the city found me, they smote me, they wounded me; the keepers of the walls took away my veil from me.
5:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|城中巡邏看守的人遇見我，打了我，傷了我；看守城牆的人奪去我的帕子。
5:8|ASV|I adjure you, O daughters of Jerusalem, If ye find my beloved, That ye tell him, that I am sick from love.
5:8|Darby|I charge you, daughters of Jerusalem, If ye find my beloved,  ... What will ye tell him? -- That I am sick of love.
5:8|KJV|I charge you, O daughters of Jerusalem, if ye find my beloved, that ye tell him, that I am sick of love.
5:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶路撒冷的眾女子阿，我鄭重的囑咐你們，若遇見我的良人，要告訴他甚麼呢？要告訴他，我因愛成病。
5:9|ASV|What is thy beloved more than another beloved, O thou fairest among women? What is thy beloved more than another beloved, That thou dost so adjure us?
5:9|Darby|What is thy beloved more than [another] beloved, Thou  fairest among women? What is thy beloved more than [another]  beloved, That thou dost so charge us?
5:9|KJV|What is thy beloved more than another beloved, O thou fairest among women? what is thy beloved more than another beloved, that thou dost so charge us?
5:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你這女子中極美麗的，你的良人比別人的良人有何強處？你的良人比別人的良人有何強處，你就這樣鄭重的囑咐我們？
5:10|ASV|My beloved is white and ruddy, The chiefest among ten thousand.
5:10|Darby|My beloved is white and ruddy, The chiefest among ten  thousand.
5:10|KJV|My beloved is white and ruddy, the chiefest among ten thousand.
5:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的良人白而且紅，超乎萬人之上。
5:11|ASV|His head is as the most fine gold; His locks are bushy, and black as a raven.
5:11|Darby|His head is [as] the finest gold; His locks are flowing,  black as the raven;
5:11|KJV|His head is as the most fine gold, his locks are bushy, and black as a raven.
5:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他的頭像至精的金子；他的頭髮鬈曲，黑如烏鴉。
5:12|ASV|His eyes are like doves beside the water-brooks, Washed with milk, and fitly set.
5:12|Darby|His eyes are like doves by the water-brooks, Washed with  milk, fitly set;
5:12|KJV|His eyes are as the eyes of doves by the rivers of waters, washed with milk, and fitly set.
5:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他的眼如溪水旁的鴿子，在奶中洗淨，安得合式。
5:13|ASV|His cheeks are as a bed of spices, As banks of sweet herbs: His lips are as lilies, dropping liquid myrrh.
5:13|Darby|His cheeks are as a bed of spices, raised beds of sweet  plants; His lips lilies, dropping liquid myrrh.
5:13|KJV|His cheeks are as a bed of spices, as sweet flowers: his lips like lilies, dropping sweet smelling myrrh.
5:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他的兩腮如香花畦，如香草臺；他的嘴脣像百合花，滴下沒藥汁。
5:14|ASV|His hands are as rings of gold set with beryl: His body is as ivory work overlaid with sapphires.
5:14|Darby|His hands gold rings, set with the chrysolite; His belly is  bright ivory, overlaid [with] sapphires;
5:14|KJV|His hands are as gold rings set with the beryl: his belly is as bright ivory overlaid with sapphires.
5:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他的兩手好像金管，鑲嵌水蒼玉；他的肚腹如同象牙作的，外面包著藍寶石。
5:15|ASV|His legs are as pillars of marble, set upon sockets of fine gold: His aspect is like Lebanon, excellent as the cedars.
5:15|Darby|His legs, pillars of marble, set upon bases of fine gold:  His bearing as Lebanon, excellent as the cedars;
5:15|KJV|His legs are as pillars of marble, set upon sockets of fine gold: his countenance is as Lebanon, excellent as the cedars.
5:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他的兩腿好像白玉石柱，安在金座上；他的形狀如利巴嫩，佳美如香柏樹。
5:16<version name="ASV">His mouth is most sweet; Yea, he is altogether lovely. This is my beloved, and this is my friend, O daughters of Jerusalem. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:16<version name="Darby">His mouth is most sweet: Yea, he is altogether lovely. This  is my beloved, yea, this is my friend, O daughters of  Jerusalem. </p><p /><br /></version>
5:16<version name="KJV">His mouth is most sweet: yea, he is altogether lovely. This is my beloved, and this is my friend, O daughters of Jerusalem.</p><p /><br /></version>
5:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他的口甘甜，他全然可愛。耶路撒冷的眾女子阿，這是我的良人，這是我的朋友。
6:1|ASV|Whither is thy beloved gone, O thou fairest among women? Whither hath thy beloved turned him, That we may seek him with thee?
6:1|Darby|Whither is thy beloved gone, Thou fairest among women?  Whither is thy beloved turned aside? And we will seek him with  thee.
6:1|KJV|Whither is thy beloved gone, O thou fairest among women? whither is thy beloved turned aside? that we may seek him with thee.
6:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你這女子中極美麗的，你的良人往何處去了？你的良人轉向何處去了？我們好與你同去尋找他。
6:2|ASV|My beloved is gone down to his garden, To the beds of spices, To feed in the gardens, and to gather lilies.
6:2|Darby|My beloved is gone down into his garden, to the beds of  spices, To feed in the gardens and to gather lilies.
6:2|KJV|My beloved is gone down into his garden, to the beds of spices, to feed in the gardens, and to gather lilies.
6:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的良人下入自己園中，到香花畦，在園內牧放群羊，採百合花。
6:3|ASV|I am my beloved's, and my beloved is mine; He feedeth his flock among the lilies,
6:3|Darby|I am my beloved's, and my beloved is mine: He feedeth [his  flock] among the lilies.
6:3|KJV|I am my beloved's, and my beloved is mine: he feedeth among the lilies.
6:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我屬我的良人，我的良人也屬我；他在百合花中牧放群羊。
6:4|ASV|Thou art fair, O my love, as Tirzah, Comely as Jerusalem, Terrible as an army with banners.
6:4|Darby|Thou art fair, my love, as Tirzah, Comely as Jerusalem,  Terrible as troops with banners:
6:4|KJV|Thou art beautiful, O my love, as Tirzah, comely as Jerusalem, terrible as an army with banners.
6:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的佳偶阿，你美麗如得撒，秀美如耶路撒冷，威武如展開旌旗的軍隊。
6:5|ASV|Turn away thine eyes from me, For they have overcome me. Thy hair is as a flock of goats, That lie along the side of Gilead.
6:5|Darby|Turn away thine eyes from me, For they overcome me. Thy hair  is as a flock of goats On the slopes of Gilead.
6:5|KJV|Turn away thine eyes from me, for they have overcome me: thy hair is as a flock of goats that appear from Gilead.
6:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|求你轉眼不看我，因你的眼目使我驚亂。你的頭髮如同山羊群，安臥在基列山旁。
6:6|ASV|Thy teeth are like a flock of ewes, Which are come up from the washing; Whereof every one hath twins, And none is bereaved among them.
6:6|Darby|Thy teeth are like a flock of sheep Which go up from the  washing; Which have all borne twins, And none is barren among  them.
6:6|KJV|Thy teeth are as a flock of sheep which go up from the washing, whereof every one beareth twins, and there is not one barren among them.
6:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你的牙齒如一群母羊，洗淨上來，個個都有雙生，沒有一隻喪掉子的。
6:7|ASV|Thy temples are like a piece of a pomegranate Behind thy veil.
6:7|Darby|As a piece of a pomegranate are thy temples Behind thy veil.
6:7|KJV|As a piece of a pomegranate are thy temples within thy locks.
6:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你的兩腮在帕子內，如同一塊石榴。
6:8|ASV|There are threescore queens, and fourscore concubines, And virgins without number.
6:8|Darby|There are threescore queens, and fourscore concubines, And  virgins without number:
6:8|KJV|There are threescore queens, and fourscore concubines, and virgins without number.
6:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有六十王后八十妃嬪，並有無數的童女。
6:9|ASV|My dove, my undefiled, is but one; She is the only one of her mother; She is the choice one of her that bare her. The daughters saw her, and called her blessed; Yea, the queens and the concubines, and they praised her.
6:9|Darby|My dove, mine undefiled, is but one; She is the only one of  her mother, She is the choice one of her that bore her. The  daughters saw her, and they called her blessed; The queens and  the concubines, and they praised her.
6:9|KJV|My dove, my undefiled is but one; she is the only one of her mother, she is the choice one of her that bare her. The daughters saw her, and blessed her; yea, the queens and the concubines, and they praised her.
6:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的鴿子，我的完全人，是獨一的，是她母親獨一的，是生養她者特愛的。眾女子見了就稱她有福；王后妃嬪見了也讚美她。
6:10|ASV|Who is she that looketh forth as the morning, Fair as the moon, Clear as the sun, Terrible as an army with banners?
6:10|Darby|Who is she that looketh forth as the dawn, Fair as the  moon, clear as the sun, Terrible as troops with banners?
6:10|KJV|Who is she that looketh forth as the morning, fair as the moon, clear as the sun, and terrible as an army with banners?
6:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那向前觀望如晨光，美麗如月亮，皎潔如日頭，威武如展開旌旗軍隊的是誰呢？
6:11|ASV|I went down into the garden of nuts, To see the green plants of the valley, To see whether the vine budded, And the pomegranates were in flower.
6:11|Darby|I went down into the garden of nuts, To see the verdure of  the valley, To see whether the vine budded, Whether the  pomegranates blossomed.
6:11|KJV|I went down into the garden of nuts to see the fruits of the valley, and to see whether the vine flourished and the pomegranates budded.
6:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我下到堅果園，要看谷中青綠的植物，要看葡萄發芽沒有，石榴開花沒有。
6:12|ASV|Before I was aware, my soul set me Among the chariots of my princely people.
6:12|Darby|Before I was aware, My soul set me upon the chariots of my  willing people.
6:12|KJV|Or ever I was aware, my soul made me like the chariots of Amminadib.
6:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不知不覺，我的魂將我安置在我君尊之民的車中。
6:13<version name="ASV">Return, return, O Shulammite; Return, return, that we may look upon thee. Why will ye look upon the Shulammite, As upon the dance of Mahanaim? </p><p /><br /></version>
6:13<version name="Darby">Return, return, O Shulamite; Return, return, that we may  look upon thee. -- What would ye look upon in the Shulamite? --  As it were the dance of two camps. </p><p /><br /></version>
6:13<version name="KJV">Return, return, O Shulamite; return, return, that we may look upon thee. What will ye see in the Shulamite? As it were the company of two armies.</p><p /><br /></version>
6:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|回來，回來，書拉密女阿；回來，回來，使我們得觀看你。你們為何要觀看書拉密女，像觀看二營軍兵跳舞呢？
7:1|ASV|How beautiful are thy feet in sandals, O prince's daughter! Thy rounded thighs are like jewels, The work of the hands of a skilful workman.
7:1|Darby|How beautiful are thy footsteps in sandals, O prince's  daughter! The roundings of thy thighs are like jewels, The work  of the hands of an artist.
7:1|KJV|How beautiful are thy feet with shoes, O prince's daughter! the joints of thy thighs are like jewels, the work of the hands of a cunning workman.
7:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|王女阿，你的腳在鞋中何等美麗！你的大腿圓潤，好像珍寶，是巧匠的手作成的。
7:2|ASV|Thy body is like a round goblet, Wherein no mingled wine is wanting: Thy waist is like a heap of wheat Set about with lilies.
7:2|Darby|Thy navel is a round goblet, [which] wanteth not mixed wine;  Thy belly a heap of wheat, set about with lilies;
7:2|KJV|Thy navel is like a round goblet, which wanteth not liquor: thy belly is like an heap of wheat set about with lilies.
7:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你的肚臍如圓杯，不缺調和的酒；你的肚腹如一堆麥子，周圍有百合花。
7:3|ASV|Thy two breasts are like two fawns That are twins of a roe.
7:3|Darby|Thy two breasts are like two fawns, twins of a gazelle;
7:3|KJV|Thy two breasts are like two young roes that are twins.
7:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你的兩乳好像一對小羚羊，就是母羚羊雙生的。
7:4|ASV|Thy neck is like the tower of ivory; Thine eyes as the pools in Heshbon, By the gate of Bath-rabbim; Thy nose is like the tower of Lebanon Which looketh toward Damascus.
7:4|Darby|Thy neck is as a tower of ivory; Thine eyes, [like] the  pools in Heshbon, By the gate of Bath-rabbim; Thy nose like the  tower of Lebanon, Which looketh toward Damascus;
7:4|KJV|Thy neck is as a tower of ivory; thine eyes like the fishpools in Heshbon, by the gate of Bathrabbim: thy nose is as the tower of Lebanon which looketh toward Damascus.
7:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你的頸項如象牙樓；你的眼目像希實本、巴特拉併門旁的水池；你的鼻子彷彿朝著大馬色的利巴嫩樓。
7:5|ASV|Thy head upon thee is like Carmel, And the hair of thy head like purple; The king is held captive in the tresses thereof.
7:5|Darby|Thy head upon thee is like Carmel, And the locks of thy head  like purple; The king is fettered by [thy] ringlets!
7:5|KJV|Thine head upon thee is like Carmel, and the hair of thine head like purple; the king is held in the galleries.
7:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你的頭在你身上好像迦密山；你頭上的髮像紫色。王被這下垂的髮綹監禁了。
7:6|ASV|How fair and how pleasant art thou, O love, for delights!
7:6|Darby|How fair and how pleasant art thou, [my] love, in delights!
7:6|KJV|How fair and how pleasant art thou, O love, for delights!
7:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我所愛的阿，你何等美麗！何等優雅可悅！
7:7|ASV|This thy stature is like to a palm-tree, And thy breasts to its clusters.
7:7|Darby|This thy stature is like to a palm-tree, And thy breasts to  grape clusters.
7:7|KJV|This thy stature is like to a palm tree, and thy breasts to clusters of grapes.
7:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你這身量好像棕樹，你的兩乳如同纍纍下垂的果子。
7:8|ASV|I said, I will climb up into the palm-tree, I will take hold of the branches thereof: Let thy breasts be as clusters of the vine, And the smell of thy breath like apples,
7:8|Darby|I said, I will go up to the palm-tree, I will take hold of  the boughs thereof; And thy breasts shall indeed be like  clusters of the vine, And the fragrance of thy nose like  apples,
7:8|KJV|I said, I will go up to the palm tree, I will take hold of the boughs thereof: now also thy breasts shall be as clusters of the vine, and the smell of thy nose like apples;
7:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我說，我要上這棕樹，抓住枝子；願你的兩乳好像葡萄纍纍下垂，你鼻子的氣味香如蘋果；
7:9|ASV|And thy mouth like the best wine, That goeth down smoothly for my beloved, Gliding through the lips of those that are asleep.
7:9|Darby|And the roof of thy mouth like the best wine, ... That goeth  down smoothly for my beloved, And stealeth over the lips of  them that are asleep.
7:9|KJV|And the roof of thy mouth like the best wine for my beloved, that goeth down sweetly, causing the lips of those that are asleep to speak.
7:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你的口如上好的酒－
7:10|ASV|I am my beloved's; And his desire is toward me.
7:10|Darby|I am my beloved's, And his desire is toward me.
7:10|KJV|I am my beloved's, and his desire is toward me.
7:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我屬我的良人，他也戀慕我。
7:11|ASV|Come, my beloved, let us go forth into the field; Let us lodge in the villages.
7:11|Darby|-- Come, my beloved, let us go forth into the fields; Let  us lodge in the villages.
7:11|KJV|Come, my beloved, let us go forth into the field; let us lodge in the villages.
7:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的良人，來罷，你我可以出到田間；你我可以在村莊住宿。
7:12|ASV|Let us get up early to the vineyards; Let us see whether the vine hath budded, And its blossom is open, And the pomegranates are in flower: There will I give thee my love.
7:12|Darby|We will go up early to the vineyards, We will see if the  vine hath budded, [If] the blossom is opening, And the  pomegranates are in bloom: There will I give thee my loves.
7:12|KJV|Let us get up early to the vineyards; let us see if the vine flourish, whether the tender grape appear, and the pomegranates bud forth: there will I give thee my loves.
7:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們清晨起來往葡萄園去，看看葡萄發芽開花沒有，石榴放蕊沒有；我在那堶n將我的愛情給你。
7:13<version name="ASV">The mandrakes give forth fragrance; And at our doors are all manner of precious fruits, new and old, Which I have laid up for thee, O my beloved. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:13<version name="Darby">The mandrakes yield fragrance; And at our gates are all  choice fruits, new and old: I have laid them up for thee, my  beloved. </p><p /><br /></version>
7:13<version name="KJV">The mandrakes give a smell, and at our gates are all manner of pleasant fruits, new and old, which I have laid up for thee, O my beloved.</p><p /><br /></version>
7:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|風茄放香，在我們的門口有各樣新陳佳美的果子。我的良人，這些都是我為你存留的。
8:1|ASV|Oh that thou wert as my brother, That sucked the breasts of my mother! When I should find thee without, I would kiss thee; Yea, and none would despise me.
8:1|Darby|Oh that thou wert as my brother, That sucked the breasts of  my mother! Should I find thee without, I would kiss thee; And  they would not despise me.
8:1|KJV|O that thou wert as my brother, that sucked the breasts of my mother! when I should find thee without, I would kiss thee; yea, I should not be despised.
8:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|哦，巴不得你像我的兄弟，像喫我母親奶的兄弟！我在外頭遇見你就與你親嘴，誰也不輕看我。
8:2|ASV|I would lead thee, and bring thee into my mother's house, Who would instruct me; I would cause thee to drink of spiced wine, Of the juice of my pomegranate.
8:2|Darby|I would lead thee, bring thee into my mother's house; Thou  wouldest instruct me: I would cause thee to drink of spiced  wine, Of the juice of my pomegranate.
8:2|KJV|I would lead thee, and bring thee into my mother's house, who would instruct me: I would cause thee to drink of spiced wine of the juice of my pomegranate.
8:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必引導你，領你進我母親的家；我領受了她的教訓；我要使你喝石榴汁釀的香酒。
8:3|ASV|His left hand should be under my head, And his right hand should embrace me.
8:3|Darby|His left hand would be under my head, And his right hand  embrace me.
8:3|KJV|His left hand should be under my head, and his right hand should embrace me.
8:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他的左手必在我頭下，他的右手必將我抱住。
8:4|ASV|I adjure you, O daughters of Jerusalem, That ye stir not up, nor awake my love, Until he please.
8:4|Darby|I charge you, daughters of Jerusalem, ... Why should ye stir  up, why awake [my] love, till he please?
8:4|KJV|I charge you, O daughters of Jerusalem, that ye stir not up, nor awake my love, until he please.
8:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶路撒冷的眾女子阿，我鄭重的囑咐你們，不要驚動，不要叫醒我所愛的，等她自己情願。
8:5|ASV|Who is this that cometh up from the wilderness, Leaning upon her beloved? Under the apple-tree I awakened thee: There thy mother was in travail with thee, There was she in travail that brought thee forth.
8:5|Darby|Who is this that cometh up from the wilderness, Leaning upon  her beloved? I awoke thee under the apple-tree: There thy  mother brought thee forth; There she brought thee forth [that]  bore thee.
8:5|KJV|Who is this that cometh up from the wilderness, leaning upon her beloved? I raised thee up under the apple tree: there thy mother brought thee forth: there she brought thee forth that bare thee.
8:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那從曠野上來，靠著她良人的是誰呢？我在蘋果樹下叫醒你：你母親在那堿飢A劬勞；生你的在那堿飢A劬勞。
8:6|ASV|Set me as a seal upon thy heart, As a seal upon thine arm: For love is strong as death; Jealousy is cruel as Sheol; The flashes thereof are flashes of fire, A very flame of Jehovah.
8:6|Darby|Set me as a seal upon thy heart, As a seal upon thine arm:  For love is strong as death; Jealousy is cruel as Sheol: The  flashes thereof are flashes of fire, Flames of Jah.
8:6|KJV|Set me as a seal upon thine heart, as a seal upon thine arm: for love is strong as death; jealousy is cruel as the grave: the coals thereof are coals of fire, which hath a most vehement flame.
8:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|求你將我放在你心上如印記，帶在你臂上如戳記；因為愛如死之堅強，嫉妒如陰間之殘忍；所閃的光是火的閃光，是耶和華的烈焰。
8:7|ASV|Many waters cannot quench love, Neither can floods drown it: If a man would give all the substance of his house for love, He would utterly be contemned.
8:7|Darby|Many waters cannot quench love, Neither do the floods drown  it: Even if a man gave all the substance of his house for love,  It would utterly be contemned.
8:7|KJV|Many waters cannot quench love, neither can the floods drown it: if a man would give all the substance of his house for love, it would utterly be contemned.
8:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這愛，眾水不能熄滅，洪水也不能淹沒。若有人拿家中所有的財寶要換這愛，就全被藐視。
8:8|ASV|We have a little sister, And she hath no breasts: What shall we do for our sister In the day when she shall be spoken for?
8:8|Darby|We have a little sister, And she hath no breasts: What shall  we do for our sister In the day when she shall be spoken for?  --
8:8|KJV|We have a little sister, and she hath no breasts: what shall we do for our sister in the day when she shall be spoken for?
8:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我們有一小妹；她的兩乳尚未長成：當我們的妹妹被人題親的日子，我們當為她怎樣辦理？
8:9|ASV|If she be a wall, We will build upon her a turret of silver: And if she be a door, We will inclose her with boards of cedar.
8:9|Darby|If she be a wall, We will build upon her a turret of silver;  And if she be a door, We will enclose her with boards of cedar.
8:9|KJV|If she be a wall, we will build upon her a palace of silver: and if she be a door, we will inclose her with boards of cedar.
8:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|她若是牆，我們要在其上建造銀的城垛；她若是門，我們要用香柏木板圍護她。
8:10|ASV|I am a wall, and my breasts like the towers thereof Then was I in his eyes as one that found peace.
8:10|Darby|I am a wall, and my breasts like towers; Then was I in his  eyes as one that findeth peace.
8:10|KJV|I am a wall, and my breasts like towers: then was I in his eyes as one that found favour.
8:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我是牆，我的兩乳像其上的樓；那時，我在他眼中像得著平安的人。
8:11|ASV|Solomon had a vineyard at Baal-hamon; He let out the vineyard unto keepers; Every one for the fruit thereof was to bring a thousand pieces of silver.
8:11|Darby|Solomon had a vineyard at Baal-hamon: He let out the  vineyard unto keepers; Every one for the fruit thereof was to  bring a thousand silver-pieces.
8:11|KJV|Solomon had a vineyard at Baalhamon; he let out the vineyard unto keepers; every one for the fruit thereof was to bring a thousand pieces of silver.
8:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|所羅門在巴力哈們有一葡萄園：他將這葡萄園交給看守的人，每人要為其中的果子交一千舍客勒銀子。
8:12|ASV|My vineyard, which is mine, is before me: Thou, O Solomon, shalt have the thousand, And those that keep the fruit thereof two hundred.
8:12|Darby|My vineyard, which is mine, is before me: The thousand  [silver-pieces] be to thee, Solomon; And to the keepers of its  fruit, two hundred.
8:12|KJV|My vineyard, which is mine, is before me: thou, O Solomon, must have a thousand, and those that keep the fruit thereof two hundred.
8:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我自己的葡萄園在我面前。所羅門哪，一千舍客勒歸你，二百舍客勒歸看守果子的人。
8:13|ASV|Thou that dwellest in the gardens, The companions hearken for thy voice: Cause me to hear it.
8:13|Darby|Thou that dwellest in the gardens, The companions hearken  to thy voice: Let me hear [it].
8:13|KJV|Thou that dwellest in the gardens, the companions hearken to thy voice: cause me to hear it.
8:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你這住在園中的，我的同伴都要聽你的聲音，求你使我也得聽見。
8:14<version name="ASV">Make haste, my beloved, And be thou like to a roe or to a young hart Upon the mountains of spices. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:14<version name="Darby">Haste, my beloved, And be thou like a gazelle or a young  hart Upon the mountains of spices. </p><p /><br /></version>
8:14<version name="KJV">Make haste, my beloved, and be thou like to a roe or to a young hart upon the mountains of spices.</p><p /><br /></version>
8:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我的良人哪，願你快來，如羚羊或小牡鹿在香草山上。
