1:1|ASV|Paul, a servant of God, and an apostle of Jesus Christ, according to the faith of God's elect, and the knowledge of the truth which is according to godliness,
1:1|Darby|Paul, bondman of God, and apostle of Jesus Christ according  to [the] faith of God's elect, and knowledge of [the] truth  which [is] according to piety;
1:1|KJV|Paul, a servant of God, and an apostle of Jesus Christ, according to the faith of God's elect, and the acknowledging of the truth which is after godliness;
1:1|WYC|Paul, the servant of God, and apostle of Jesus Christ, by the faith of the chosen of God, and by the knowing of the truth [after the faith of the chosen of God, and knowing of the truth], which is after piety,
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|照著神選民的信仰，與合乎敬虔之真理的知識，
1:2|ASV|in hope of eternal life, which God, who cannot lie, promised before times eternal;
1:2|Darby|in [the] hope of eternal life, which God, who cannot lie,  promised before the ages of time,
1:2|KJV|In hope of eternal life, which God, that cannot lie, promised before the world began;
1:2<version name="WYC">into the hope of everlasting life [in hope of everlasting life], which <i>life</i> God that lieth not, promised before times of the world [before worldly times];</version>
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|根據永遠生命的盼望，（就是那不能說謊的神，在歷世之前所應許，
1:3|ASV|but in his own seasons manifested his word in the message, wherewith I was intrusted according to the commandment of God our Saviour;
1:3|Darby|but has manifested in its own due season his word, in [the]  proclamation with which *I* have been entrusted, according to  [the] commandment of our Saviour God;
1:3|KJV|But hath in due times manifested his word through preaching, which is committed unto me according to the commandment of God our Saviour;
1:3|WYC|but he hath showed in his times his word in preaching, that is betaken to me by the commandment of God, our Saviour [after the commandment of our Saviour God],
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|到了適當的時期，藉著那按我們救主神的命令所託付我傳揚的福音，將祂的話顯明出來的，）作神的奴僕、並耶穌基督使徒的保羅，
1:4|ASV|to Titus, my true child after a common faith: Grace and peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Saviour.
1:4|Darby|to Titus, my own child according to [the] faith common [to  us]: Grace and peace from God [the] Father, and Christ Jesus  our Saviour.
1:4|KJV|To Titus, mine own son after the common faith: Grace, mercy, and peace, from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ our Saviour.
1:4|WYC|to Titus, most dear-worthy son by the common faith [to Titus, beloved son after the common faith], grace and peace of God the Father, and of Christ Jesus, our Saviour.
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|寫信給照著共同的信仰，作我真孩子的提多：願恩典與平安，從父神和我們的救主基督耶穌歸與你。
1:5|ASV|For this cause left I thee in Crete, that thou shouldest set in order the things that were wanting, and appoint elders in every city, as I gave thee charge;
1:5|Darby|For this cause I left thee in Crete, that thou mightest go  on to set right what remained [unordered], and establish elders  in each city, as *I* had ordered thee:
1:5|KJV|For this cause left I thee in Crete, that thou shouldest set in order the things that are wanting, and ordain elders in every city, as I had appointed thee:
1:5|WYC|For cause of this thing I left thee at Crete, that thou amend those things that fail, and ordain priests by cities, as also I assigned to thee [as and I disposed to thee].
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我從前留你在革哩底，是要你將我所未辦完的事辦理妥當，又照我所吩咐你的，在各城設立長老。
1:6|ASV|if any man is blameless, the husband of one wife, having children that believe, who are not accused of riot or unruly.
1:6|Darby|if any one be free from all charge [against him], husband of  one wife, having believing children not accused of excess or  unruly.
1:6|KJV|If any be blameless, the husband of one wife, having faithful children not accused of riot or unruly.
1:6<version name="WYC">If any man is without crime, an husband of one wife, and hath faithful sons [If any man is without crime, <i>or</i> <i>great sin</i>, husband of one wife, having faithful sons], not in accusation of lechery, or not subject.</version>
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|若有人無可指責，只作一個妻子的丈夫，兒女是信主的，沒有人告他們是放蕩、或不服約束的，就可以設立。
1:7|ASV|For the bishop must be blameless, as God's steward; not self-willed, not soon angry, no brawler, no striker, not greedy of filthy lucre;
1:7|Darby|For the overseer must be free from all charge [against him]  as God's steward; not headstrong, not passionate, not  disorderly through wine, not a striker, not seeking gain by  base means;
1:7|KJV|For a bishop must be blameless, as the steward of God; not selfwilled, not soon angry, not given to wine, no striker, not given to filthy lucre;
1:7<version name="WYC">For it behooveth a bishop to be without crime, [as] a dispenser of God, not proud, not wrathful, not given to drunkenness [not vinolent, <i>that is</i>,<i> much given to wine</i>], not [a] smiter, not covetous of foul winning;</version>
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為監督是神的管家，必須無可指責，不任性，不暴躁，不醉酒滋事，不打人，不貪卑鄙的利益；
1:8|ASV|but given to hospitality, as lover of good, sober-minded, just, holy, self-controlled;
1:8|Darby|but hospitable, a lover of goodness, discreet, just, pious,  temperate,
1:8|KJV|But a lover of hospitality, a lover of good men, sober, just, holy, temperate;
1:8|WYC|but holding hospitality, benign, prudent, sober, just, holy, continent,
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|卻樂意待客，喜愛良善，清明自守，義、聖、節制；
1:9|ASV|holding to the faithful word which is according to the teaching, that he may be able to exhort in the sound doctrine, and to convict the gainsayers.
1:9|Darby|clinging to the faithful word according to the doctrine  taught, that he may be able both to encourage with sound  teaching and refute gainsayers.
1:9|KJV|Holding fast the faithful word as he hath been taught, that he may be able by sound doctrine both to exhort and to convince the gainsayers.
1:9<version name="WYC">taking that true word, that is after doctrine; that he be mighty to admonish in wholesome teaching, and to reprove them that gainsay. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22919a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|堅守那按照使徒教訓可信靠的話，好能用健康的教訓勸勉人，又能使那些反對的人知罪自責。
1:10|ASV|For there are many unruly men, vain talkers and deceivers, specially they of the circumcision,
1:10|Darby|For there are many and disorderly vain speakers and  deceivers of people's minds, specially those of [the]  circumcision,
1:10|KJV|For there are many unruly and vain talkers and deceivers, specially they of the circumcision:
1:10|WYC|For there be many unobedient, and vain speakers, and deceivers, most they that be of circumcision,
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為有許多人不服約束，說虛空的話，欺哄人，那些奉割禮的人更是這樣，
1:11|ASV|whose mouths must be stopped; men who overthrow whole houses, teaching things which they ought not, for filthy lucre's sake.
1:11|Darby|who must have their mouths stopped, who subvert whole  houses, teaching things which ought not [to be taught] for the  sake of base gain.
1:11|KJV|Whose mouths must be stopped, who subvert whole houses, teaching things which they ought not, for filthy lucre's sake.
1:11|WYC|which it behooveth to be reproved [whom it behooveth to be reproved]; which subvert all houses, teaching which things it behooveth not, for [the] love of foul winning.
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些人的口必須堵住；他們為了卑鄙的利益，將不當教導的事教導人，就傾覆了人的全家。
1:12|ASV|One of themselves, a prophet of their own, said, Cretans are always liars, evil beasts, idle gluttons.
1:12|Darby|One of themselves, a prophet of their own, has said,  Cretans are always liars, evil wild beasts, lazy gluttons.
1:12|KJV|One of themselves, even a prophet of their own, said, the Cretians are alway liars, evil beasts, slow bellies.
1:12<version name="WYC">And one of them, their proper prophet said [Some one of them, the proper prophet of them, said], said, Men of Crete <i>be </i>evermore liars, evil beasts, of slow womb [slow of womb].</version>
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|有革哩底人中間的一位，就是他們自己的申言者，曾說，革哩底人常是說謊的，乃是惡獸，又饞又懶。
1:13|ASV|This testimony is true. For which cause reprove them sharply, that they may be sound in the faith,
1:13|Darby|This testimony is true; for which cause rebuke them  severely, that they may be sound in the faith,
1:13|KJV|This witness is true. Wherefore rebuke them sharply, that they may be sound in the faith;
1:13|WYC|This witnessing is true.  For which cause blame them sore, that they be whole in faith,
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這個見證是真的；為這緣故，你要嚴厲的責備他們，使他們在信仰上健康，
1:14|ASV|not giving heed to Jewish fables, and commandments of men who turn away from the truth.
1:14|Darby|not turning [their] minds to Jewish fables and commandments  of men turning away from the truth.
1:14|KJV|Not giving heed to Jewish fables, and commandments of men, that turn from the truth.
1:14|WYC|not giving attention to fables of Jews, and to commandments of men, that turn away them from truth [turning them away from truth].
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不注意猶太人虛構無稽之事，和轉離真理之人的誡命。
1:15|ASV|To the pure all things are pure: but to them that are defiled and unbelieving nothing is pure; but both their mind and their conscience are defiled.
1:15|Darby|All things [are] pure to the pure; but to the defiled and  unbelieving nothing [is] pure; but both their mind and their  conscience are defiled.
1:15|KJV|Unto the pure all things are pure: but unto them that are defiled and unbelieving is nothing pure; but even their mind and conscience is defiled.
1:15<version name="WYC">And all things be clean to clean men; but to unclean men and to unfaithful nothing is clean, for the soul and conscience of them be made unclean [but and the soul, <i>or</i> <i>reason</i>, and conscience of them be made unclean].</version>
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|對潔淨的人，凡物都潔淨；但對污穢不信的人，甚麼都不潔淨，反而連他們的心思和良心，也都污穢了。
1:16<version name="ASV">They profess that they know God; but by their works they deny him, being abominable, and disobedient, and unto every good work reprobate. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:16<version name="Darby">They profess to know God, but in works deny [him], being  abominable, and disobedient, and found worthless as to every  good work. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:16<version name="KJV">They profess that they know God; but in works they deny him, being abominable, and disobedient, and unto every good work reprobate.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:16<version name="WYC">They acknowledge that they know God, but by deeds they deny [<i>him</i>]; when they be abominable, and unbelieveful, and reprovable to all good work [to all good works].</version>
1:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們自稱認識神，卻在行為上否認祂，本是可憎惡的、悖逆的，在各樣善事上是不蒙稱許的。
2:1|ASV|But speak thou the things which befit the sound doctrine:
2:1|Darby|But do *thou* speak the things that become sound teaching;
2:1|KJV|But speak thou the things which become sound doctrine:
2:1|WYC|But speak thou those things that beseem wholesome teaching; [Forsooth speak thou the things that become wholesome teaching;]
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|至於你，要講那合乎健康教訓的話。
2:2|ASV|that aged men be temperate, grave, sober-minded, sound in faith, in love, in patience:
2:2|Darby|that the elder men be sober, grave, discreet, sound in  faith, in love, in patience;
2:2|KJV|That the aged men be sober, grave, temperate, sound in faith, in charity, in patience.
2:2|WYC|that old men be sober, chaste, prudent, whole in faith, in love, and patience;
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|勸老年人要節制適度、莊重、清明自守，在信、愛、忍耐上都要健康。
2:3|ASV|that aged women likewise be reverent in demeanor, not slanderers nor enslaved to much wine, teachers of that which is good;
2:3|Darby|that the elder women in like manner be in deportment as  becoming those who have to say to sacred things, not  slanderers, not enslaved to much wine, teachers of what is  right;
2:3|KJV|The aged women likewise, that they be in behaviour as becometh holiness, not false accusers, not given to much wine, teachers of good things;
2:3<version name="WYC">also old women in holy habit, not slanderers [not backbiters, <i>or saying false blame on other men</i>], not serving much to wine, well-teaching, that they teach prudence.</version>
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|勸老年婦人也是一樣，在舉止行動上，要和有分於聖事的人相稱，不說讒言，不被酒奴役，將善美的事教導人，
2:4|ASV|that they may train the young women to love their husbands, to love their children,
2:4|Darby|that they may admonish the young women to be attached to  [their] husbands, to be attached to [their] children,
2:4|KJV|That they may teach the young women to be sober, to love their husbands, to love their children,
2:4<version name="WYC"><i>Admonish thou</i> young women, that they love their husbands, that they love their children;</version>
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|好訓練年輕的婦人愛丈夫，愛兒女，
2:5|ASV|to be sober-minded, chaste, workers at home, kind, being in subjection to their own husbands, that the word of God be not blasphemed:
2:5|Darby|discreet, chaste, diligent in home work, good, subject to  their own husbands, that the word of God may not be evil spoken  of.
2:5|KJV|To be discreet, chaste, keepers at home, good, obedient to their own husbands, that the word of God be not blasphemed.
2:5|WYC|and that they be prudent, chaste, sober, having care of the house, benign, subject to their husbands, that the word of God be not blasphemed.
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|清明自守，貞潔，料理家務，良善，服從自己的丈夫，免得神的話被毀謗。
2:6|ASV|the younger men likewise exhort to be sober-minded:
2:6|Darby|The younger men in like manner exhort to be discreet:
2:6|KJV|Young men likewise exhort to be sober minded.
2:6|WYC|Also admonish young men, that they be sober.
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|勸青年人也是一樣，要清明自守。
2:7|ASV|in all things showing thyself an ensample of good works; in thy doctrine showing uncorruptness, gravity,
2:7|Darby|in all things affording thyself as a pattern of good works;  in teaching uncorruptedness, gravity,
2:7|KJV|In all things shewing thyself a pattern of good works: in doctrine shewing uncorruptness, gravity, sincerity,
2:7<version name="WYC">In all things give thyself ensample of good works, in teaching, in wholeness, in firmness. <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22933a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在凡事上你自己要顯出善行的榜樣，在教導上要不腐化，要莊重，
2:8|ASV|sound speech, that cannot be condemned; that he that is of the contrary part may be ashamed, having no evil thing to say of us.
2:8|Darby|a sound word, not to be condemned; that he who is opposed  may be ashamed, having no evil thing to say about us:
2:8|KJV|Sound speech, that cannot be condemned; that he that is of the contrary part may be ashamed, having no evil thing to say of you.
2:8|WYC|An wholesome word [An whole word], and unreprovable; that he that is of the contrary side, be ashamed, having none evil thing to say of you.
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|要用無可挑剔的健康言語，使那反對的人既沒有壞事可說到我們，便自覺羞愧。
2:9|ASV|Exhort servants to be in subjection to their own masters,  and to be well-pleasing to them in all things; not gainsaying;
2:9|Darby|bondmen to be subject to their own masters, to make  themselves acceptable in everything; not gainsaying;
2:9|KJV|Exhort servants to be obedient unto their own masters, and to please them well in all things; not answering again;
2:9<version name="WYC"><i>Admonish thou</i> servants to be subject to their lords; in all things pleasing, not again-saying,</version>
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|勸奴僕要凡事服從自己的主人，討他們的喜歡，不可頂撞他們，
2:10|ASV|not purloining, but showing all good fidelity; that they may adorn the doctrine of God our Saviour in all things.
2:10|Darby|not robbing [their masters], but shewing all good fidelity,  that they may adorn the teaching which [is] of our Saviour God  in all things.
2:10|KJV|Not purloining, but shewing all good fidelity; that they may adorn the doctrine of God our Saviour in all things.
2:10|WYC|not defrauding, but in all things showing good faith, that they honour in all things the doctrine of God, our Saviour [that they adorn in all things the doctrine of God, our Saviour].
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不可私拿東西，卻要顯為絕對優良可信，好使我們救主神的教訓在凡事上都得光榮。
2:11|ASV|For the grace of God hath appeared, bringing salvation to all men,
2:11|Darby|For the grace of God which carries with it salvation for  all men has appeared,
2:11|KJV|For the grace of God that bringeth salvation hath appeared to all men,
2:11|WYC|For the grace of God, our Saviour, hath appeared to all men,
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為神救萬人的恩典，已經顯現出來，
2:12|ASV|instructing us, to the intent that, denying ungodliness and worldly lusts, we should live soberly and righteously and godly in this present world;
2:12|Darby|teaching us that, having denied impiety and worldly lusts,  we should live soberly, and justly, and piously in the present  course of things,
2:12|KJV|Teaching us that, denying ungodliness and worldly lusts, we should live soberly, righteously, and godly, in this present world;
2:12|WYC|and taught us, that we forsake wickedness and worldly desires, and live soberly, and justly, and piously in this world, [teaching us, that we, forsaking unpiety, and worldly desires, live soberly, and justly, and piously, in this world,]
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|教導我們棄絕不敬虔和屬世的情慾，好在今世過自守、公義、敬虔的生活，
2:13|ASV|looking for the blessed hope and appearing of the glory of the great God and our Saviour Jesus Christ;
2:13|Darby|awaiting the blessed hope and appearing of the glory of our  great God and Saviour Jesus Christ;
2:13|KJV|Looking for that blessed hope, and the glorious appearing of the great God and our Saviour Jesus Christ;
2:13|WYC|abiding the blessed hope and the coming of the glory of the great God, and our Saviour Jesus Christ;
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|等候那有福的盼望，就是至大的神和我們的救主，耶穌基督之榮耀的顯現。
2:14|ASV|who gave himself for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity, and purify unto himself a people for his own possession, zealous of good works.
2:14|Darby|who gave himself for us, that he might redeem us from all  lawlessness, and purify to himself a peculiar people, zealous  for good works.
2:14|KJV|Who gave himself for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity, and purify unto himself a peculiar people, zealous of good works.
2:14|WYC|that gave himself for us, to again-buy us from all wickedness [that he should again-buy us from all wickedness], and make clean to himself a people acceptable, and follower of good works.
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂為我們捨了自己，要贖我們脫離一切的不法，並潔淨我們，歸祂自己成為獨特的子民，作祂特有的產業，熱心行善。
2:15<version name="ASV">These things speak and exhort and reprove with all authority. Let no man despise thee. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:15<version name="Darby">These things speak, and exhort, and rebuke with all  authority. Let no one despise thee. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:15<version name="KJV">These things speak, and exhort, and rebuke with all authority. Let no man despise thee.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:15<version name="WYC">Speak thou these things, and admonish thou, and reprove thou with all commandment; no man despise thee. [Speak thou these things, and admonish, and argue, <i>or reprove</i>, with all commandment; no man despise thee.]</version>
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這些事你要講說，也要用各等權柄勸勉人、責備人；不可叫人輕看你。
3:1|ASV|Put them in mind to be in subjection to rulers, to authorities, to be obedient, to be ready unto every good work,
3:1|Darby|Put them in mind to be subject to rulers, to authorities, to  be obedient to rule, to be ready to do every good work,
3:1|KJV|Put them in mind to be subject to principalities and powers, to obey magistrates, to be ready to every good work,
3:1|WYC|Admonish them to be subjects to princes [Admonish them to be subject to princes], and to powers; to obey to that that is said, and to be ready to all good work [to all good works];
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要題醒眾人服從執政的、掌權的，順從他們，豫備行各樣的善事。
3:2|ASV|to speak evil of no man, not to be contentious, to be gentle, showing all meekness toward all men.
3:2|Darby|to speak evil of no one, not to be contentious, [to be]  mild, shewing all meekness towards all men.
3:2|KJV|To speak evil of no man, to be no brawlers, but gentle, shewing all meekness unto all men.
3:2<version name="WYC">to blaspheme no man, to be not full of chiding, but temperate [to be not litigious, <i>or full of chiding</i>, but temperate, <i>or</i> <i>patient</i>], showing all mildness to all men.</version>
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|不要毀謗人，不要爭競，乃要謙讓宜人，向眾人顯出十分的溫柔。
3:3|ASV|For we also once were foolish, disobedient, deceived, serving divers lusts and pleasures, living in malice and envy, hateful, hating one another.
3:3|Darby|For we were once ourselves also without intelligence,  disobedient, wandering in error, serving various lusts and  pleasures, living in malice and envy, hateful, [and] hating one  another.
3:3|KJV|For we ourselves also were sometimes foolish, disobedient, deceived, serving divers lusts and pleasures, living in malice and envy, hateful, and hating one another.
3:3|WYC|For we were sometime unwise, unbelieveful, erring, and serving to desires, and to diverse lusts [and diverse lusts], doing in malice and envy, worthy to be hated, hating each other [hateful, hating together].
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為我們從前也是無知、悖逆、受迷惑的，給各樣的私慾和宴樂作奴僕，將生命時光耗費於惡毒和嫉妒，是可恨的，又是彼此相恨。
3:4|ASV|But when the kindness of God our Saviour, and his love toward man, appeared,
3:4|Darby|But when the kindness and love to man of our Saviour God  appeared,
3:4|KJV|But after that the kindness and love of God our Saviour toward man appeared,
3:4<version name="WYC">But when the benignity and the manhood of our Saviour God appeared, <sup>[<a href="#fen-WYC-22945a" title="See footnote a">a</a>]</sup></version>
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|然而，當我們救主神的恩慈，和祂對人的愛顯現的時候，
3:5|ASV|not by works done in righteousness, which we did ourselves, but according to his mercy he saved us, through the washing of regeneration and renewing of the Holy Spirit,
3:5|Darby|not on the principle of works which [have been done] in  righteousness which *we* had done, but according to his own  mercy he saved us through [the] washing of regeneration and  renewal of [the] Holy Spirit,
3:5|KJV|Not by works of righteousness which we have done, but according to his mercy he saved us, by the washing of regeneration, and renewing of the Holy Ghost;
3:5|WYC|not of works of rightwiseness that we did, but by his mercy [but after his mercy] he made us safe, by [the] washing of again-begetting, and again-newing of the Holy Ghost,
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂便救了我們，並不是本於我們所成就的義行，乃是照著祂的憐憫，藉著重生的洗滌，和聖靈的更新。
3:6|ASV|which he poured out upon us richly, through Jesus Christ our Saviour;
3:6|Darby|which he poured out on us richly through Jesus Christ our  Saviour;
3:6|KJV|Which he shed on us abundantly through Jesus Christ our Saviour;
3:6|WYC|whom he shedded [out] into us plenteously by Jesus Christ, our Saviour,
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這聖靈就是神藉著耶穌基督我們的救主，豐豐富富澆灌在我們身上的，
3:7|ASV|that, being justified by his grace, we might be made heirs according to the hope of eternal life.
3:7|Darby|that, having been justified by *his* grace, we should become  heirs according to [the] hope of eternal life.
3:7|KJV|That being justified by his grace, we should be made heirs according to the hope of eternal life.
3:7|WYC|that we justified by his grace, be heirs by hope [be heirs after hope] of everlasting life.
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|好叫我們既因祂的恩典得稱義，就可以照著永遠生命的盼望成為後嗣。
3:8|ASV|Faithful is the saying, and concerning these things I desire that thou affirm confidently, to the end that they who have believed God may be careful to maintain good works. These things are good and profitable unto men:
3:8|Darby|The word [is] faithful, and I desire that thou insist  strenuously on these things, that they who have believed God  may take care to pay diligent attention to good works. These  things are good and profitable to men.
3:8|KJV|This is a faithful saying, and these things I will that thou affirm constantly, that they which have believed in God might be careful to maintain good works. These things are good and profitable unto men.
3:8<version name="WYC">A true word is [<i>this</i>], and of these things I will that thou confirm others, that they that believe in God, be busy to be above others in good works [care, <i>or</i> <i>do</i> <i>busyness</i>, to be before in good works].  These things be good, and profitable to men.</version>
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這話是可信的，我也願你把這些事確實堅信的講明，使那些已信神的人留心作正經事業。這些都是美事，並且與人有益。
3:9|ASV|but shun foolish questionings, and genealogies, and strifes, and fightings about law; for they are unprofitable and vain.
3:9|Darby|But foolish questions, and genealogies, and strifes, and  contentions about the law, shun; for they are unprofitable and  vain.
3:9|KJV|But avoid foolish questions, and genealogies, and contentions, and strivings about the law; for they are unprofitable and vain.
3:9|WYC|And eschew thou foolish questions, and genealogies, and strivings [and strives], and fightings of the law; for those be unprofitable and vain.
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|但要遠避愚拙的辯論、家譜、爭競、以及因律法而起的爭論，因為這些都是無益虛妄的。
3:10|ASV|A factious man after a first and second admonition refuse;
3:10|Darby|An heretical man after a first and second admonition have  done with,
3:10|KJV|A man that is an heretick after the first and second admonition reject;
3:10<version name="WYC">Eschew thou a man heretic, after one and the second correction; [Shun thou a man heretic, after one and the second correction, <i>or</i> <i>reproving</i>;]</version>
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|分門結黨的人，警戒過一兩次，就要拒絕；
3:11|ASV|knowing that such a one is perverted, and sinneth, being self-condemned.
3:11|Darby|knowing that such a one is perverted, and sins, being  self-condemned.
3:11|KJV|Knowing that he that is such is subverted, and sinneth, being condemned of himself.
3:11<version name="WYC">witting that he that is such a manner <i>man</i> is subverted, and trespasseth, and is condemned by his own doom.</version>
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|知道這等人已經深入歧途，雖定自己的罪，仍是犯罪。
3:12|ASV|When I shall send Artemas unto thee, or Tychicus, give diligence to come unto me to Nicopolis: for there I have determined to winter.
3:12|Darby|When I shall send Artemas to thee, or Tychicus, use  diligence to come to me to Nicopolis; for I have decided to  winter there.
3:12|KJV|When I shall send Artemas unto thee, or Tychicus, be diligent to come unto me to Nicopolis: for I have determined there to winter.
3:12<version name="WYC">When I [shall] send to thee Artemas, or Tychicus, hie thou to come to me to Nicopolis [hie,<i> or haste</i>, thou to come to me to Nicopolis]; for I have purposed to dwell in winter there.</version>
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我打發亞提馬或推基古到你那裡去的時候，你要趕緊往尼哥波立去見我，因為我已經定意在那裡過冬。
3:13|ASV|Set forward Zenas the lawyer and Apollos on their journey diligently, that nothing be wanting unto them.
3:13|Darby|Zenas the lawyer and Apollos set forward diligently on  their way, that nothing may be lacking to them;
3:13|KJV|Bring Zenas the lawyer and Apollos on their journey diligently, that nothing be wanting unto them.
3:13|WYC|Busily before send Zenas [Busily send before Zenas], a wise man of law, and Apollos, that nothing fail to them.
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要趕緊給律法師西納和亞波羅送行，叫他們沒有缺乏。
3:14|ASV|And let our  people also learn to maintain good works for necessary uses, that they be not unfruitful.
3:14|Darby|and let ours also learn to apply themselves to good works  for necessary wants, that they may not be unfruitful.
3:14|KJV|And let our's also learn to maintain good works for necessary uses, that they be not unfruitful.
3:14|WYC|They that be of ours, learn to be governors in good works, to necessary uses, that they be not without fruit. [Forsooth and our men learn to be before in good works, to necessary uses, that they be not unfruitous.]
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|並且我們的人也要學習作正經事業，好應必需，免得不結果子。
3:15<version name="ASV">All that are with me salute thee. Salute them that love us in faith. Grace be with you all. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:15<version name="Darby">All with me salute thee. Salute those who love us in [the]  faith. Grace [be] with you all. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:15<version name="KJV">All that are with me salute thee. Greet them that love us in the faith. Grace be with you all. Amen.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:15<version name="WYC">All men that be with me greet thee well.  Greet thou well them, that love us in [the] faith.  The grace of God <i>be</i> with you all.  Amen.</version>
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|同我在一起的眾人都問你安。請代問那些因信愛我們的人安。願恩典與你們眾人同在。
