1:1|ASV|The word of Jehovah which came unto Zephaniah the son of Cushi, the son of Gedaliah, the son of Amariah, the son of Hezekiah, in the days of Josiah the son of Amon, king of Judah.
1:1|Darby|The word of Jehovah that came unto Zephaniah the son of  Cushi, the son of Gedaliah, the son of Amariah, the son of  Hezekiah, in the days of Josiah the son of Amon, king of Judah.
1:1|KJV|The word of the LORD which came unto Zephaniah the son of Cushi, the son of Gedaliah, the son of Amariah, the son of Hizkiah, in the days of Josiah the son of Amon, king of Judah.
1:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當猶大王亞們的兒子約西亞在位的日子，耶和華的話臨到希西家的玄孫，亞瑪利雅的曾孫，基大利的孫子，古示的兒子西番雅。
1:2|ASV|I will utterly consume all things from off the face of the ground, saith Jehovah.
1:2|Darby|I will utterly take away everything from off the face of the  ground, saith Jehovah:
1:2|KJV|I will utterly consume all things from off the land, saith the LORD.
1:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華說，我必從地面上全然除滅萬類。
1:3|ASV|I will consume man and beast; I will consume the birds of the heavens, and the fishes of the sea, and the stumblingblocks with the wicked; and I will cut off man from off the face of the ground, saith Jehovah.
1:3|Darby|I will take away man and beast; I will take away the fowl of  the heavens and the fishes of the sea, and the stumbling-blocks  with the wicked, and I will cut off mankind from off the face  of the ground, saith Jehovah.
1:3|KJV|I will consume man and beast; I will consume the fowls of the heaven, and the fishes of the sea, and the stumbling blocks with the wicked: and I will cut off man from off the land, saith the LORD.
1:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必除滅人和走獸，除滅空中的鳥、海堛熙翩B以及絆腳石和惡人；我必將人從地面上剪除，這是耶和華說的。
1:4|ASV|And I will stretch out my hand upon Judah, and upon all the inhabitants of Jerusalem; and I will cut off the remnant of Baal from this place, and the name of the Chemarim with the priests;
1:4|Darby|And I will stretch forth my hand upon Judah, and upon all  the inhabitants of Jerusalem; and I will cut off the remnant of  Baal from this place, the name of the Chemarim with the  priests;
1:4|KJV|I will also stretch out mine hand upon Judah, and upon all the inhabitants of Jerusalem; and I will cut off the remnant of Baal from this place, and the name of the Chemarims with the priests;
1:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必伸手攻擊猶大和耶路撒冷的一切居民；也必從這地方剪除所餘剩的巴力，並偶像祭司的名和祭司，
1:5|ASV|and them that worship the host of heaven upon the housetops; and them that worship, that swear to Jehovah and swear by Malcam;
1:5|Darby|and them that bow down to the host of the heavens upon the  housetops; and them that bow down to Jehovah, that swear by  [him], and swear by Malcham;
1:5|KJV|And them that worship the host of heaven upon the housetops; and them that worship and that swear by the LORD, and that swear by Malcham;
1:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|與那些在房頂上敬拜天上萬象的，並那些敬拜耶和華，指著祂起誓，又指著瑪勒堪起誓的，
1:6|ASV|and them that are turned back from following Jehovah; and those that have not sought Jehovah, nor inquired after him.
1:6|Darby|and them that turn back from after Jehovah, and that do not  seek Jehovah, nor inquire for him.
1:6|KJV|And them that are turned back from the LORD; and those that have not sought the LORD, nor enquired for him.
1:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|與那些轉去不跟從耶和華的，和不尋求耶和華，也不求問祂的。
1:7|ASV|Hold thy peace at the presence of the Lord Jehovah; for the day of Jehovah is at hand: for Jehovah hath prepared a sacrifice, he hath consecrated his guests.
1:7|Darby|Be silent at the presence of the Lord Jehovah; for the day  of Jehovah is at hand; for Jehovah hath prepared a sacrifice,  he hath hallowed his guests.
1:7|KJV|Hold thy peace at the presence of the Lord GOD: for the day of the LORD is at hand: for the LORD hath prepared a sacrifice, he hath bid his guests.
1:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|你要在主耶和華面前靜默無聲，因為耶和華的日子近了；耶和華已經豫備祭物，將祂所召的分別為聖。
1:8|ASV|And it shall come to pass in the day of Jehovah's sacrifice, that I will punish the princes, and the king's sons, and all such as are clothed with foreign apparel.
1:8|Darby|And it shall come to pass in the day of Jehovah's sacrifice,  that I will punish the princes, and the king's sons, and all  such as are clothed with foreign apparel.
1:8|KJV|And it shall come to pass in the day of the LORD's sacrifice, that I will punish the princes, and the king's children, and all such as are clothed with strange apparel.
1:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|在耶和華獻祭的日子，我必懲罰首領和王子，並一切穿外邦衣服的。
1:9|ASV|And in that day I will punish all those that leap over the threshold, that fill their master's house with violence and deceit.
1:9|Darby|And in that day will I punish all those that leap over the  threshold, who fill their master's house with violence and  deceit.
1:9|KJV|In the same day also will I punish all those that leap on the threshold, which fill their masters' houses with violence and deceit.
1:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|到那日，我必懲罰一切跳過門檻，將強暴和詭詐充滿他們主人房屋的。
1:10|ASV|And in that day, saith Jehovah, there shall be the noise of a cry from the fish gate, and a wailing from the second quarter, and a great crashing from the hills.
1:10|Darby|And in that day, saith Jehovah, there shall be the noise of  a cry from the fish-gate, and a howling from the second  [quarter], and a great crashing from the hills.
1:10|KJV|And it shall come to pass in that day, saith the LORD, that there shall be the noise of a cry from the fish gate, and an howling from the second, and a great crashing from the hills.
1:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華說，當那日從魚門必發出哀聲，從第二城區發出哀號，從山間發出大破裂的響聲。
1:11|ASV|Wail, ye inhabitants of Maktesh; for all the people of Canaan are undone; all they that were laden with silver are cut off.
1:11|Darby|Howl, ye inhabitants of Maktesh; for all the people of  Canaan are cut down, all they that are laden with silver are  cut off.
1:11|KJV|Howl, ye inhabitants of Maktesh, for all the merchant people are cut down; all they that bear silver are cut off.
1:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|瑪革提施的居民哪，你們要哀號，因為迦南的民都滅亡了；凡滿載銀子的，都被剪除。
1:12|ASV|And it shall come to pass at that time, that I will search Jerusalem with lamps; and I will punish the men that are settled on their lees, that say in their heart, Jehovah will not do good, neither will he do evil.
1:12|Darby|And it shall come to pass at that time, [that] I will  search Jerusalem with lamps, and punish the men that are  settled on their lees, that say in their heart, Jehovah will  not do good, neither will he do evil.
1:12|KJV|And it shall come to pass at that time, that I will search Jerusalem with candles, and punish the men that are settled on their lees: that say in their heart, The LORD will not do good, neither will he do evil.
1:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時，我必用燈巡查耶路撒冷，我必懲罰那些如酒在渣滓上澄清的，他們心婸﹛A耶和華必不降福，也不降禍。
1:13|ASV|And their wealth shall become a spoil, and their houses a desolation: yea, they shall build houses, but shall not inhabit them; and they shall plant vineyards, but shall not drink the wine thereof.
1:13|Darby|And their wealth shall become a booty, and their houses a  desolation; and they shall build houses, and not inhabit them;  and they shall plant vineyards, and not drink the wine thereof.
1:13|KJV|Therefore their goods shall become a booty, and their houses a desolation: they shall also build houses, but not inhabit them; and they shall plant vineyards, but not drink the wine thereof.
1:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|他們的財寶必成為掠物，他們的房屋必變為荒場。他們建造房屋，卻不得住在其內；栽種葡萄園，卻不得喝所出的酒。
1:14|ASV|The great day of Jehovah is near, it is near and hasteth greatly, even the voice of the day of Jehovah; the mighty man crieth there bitterly.
1:14|Darby|The great day of Jehovah is near, it is near, and hasteth  greatly. The voice of the day of Jehovah: the mighty man shall  cry there bitterly.
1:14|KJV|The great day of the LORD is near, it is near, and hasteth greatly, even the voice of the day of the LORD: the mighty man shall cry there bitterly.
1:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華的大日臨近，臨近而且來得甚快。這是耶和華日子的聲音！勇士在那媯h痛的哭號。
1:15|ASV|That day is a day of wrath, a day of trouble and distress, a day of wasteness and desolation, a day of darkness and gloominess, a day of clouds and thick darkness,
1:15|Darby|That day is a day of wrath, a day of trouble and distress,  a day of ruin and desolation, a day of darkness and gloom, a  day of clouds and gross darkness,
1:15|KJV|That day is a day of wrath, a day of trouble and distress, a day of wasteness and desolation, a day of darkness and gloominess, a day of clouds and thick darkness,
1:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那日是盛怒的日子，是急難困苦的日子，是荒廢淒涼的日子，是黑暗幽冥的日子，是密雲烏黑的日子，
1:16|ASV|a day of the trumpet and alarm, against the fortified cities, and against the high battlements.
1:16|Darby|a day of the trumpet and alarm, against the fenced cities  and against the high battlements.
1:16|KJV|A day of the trumpet and alarm against the fenced cities, and against the high towers.
1:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|是吹角吶喊的日子，要攻擊堅固城，和高聳的角樓。
1:17|ASV|And I will bring distress upon men, that they shall walk like blind men, because they have sinned against Jehovah; and their blood shall be poured out as dust, and their flesh as dung.
1:17|Darby|And I will bring distress upon men, and they shall walk  like blind men; for they have sinned against Jehovah; and their  blood shall be poured out as dust, and their flesh as dung:
1:17|KJV|And I will bring distress upon men, that they shall walk like blind men, because they have sinned against the LORD: and their blood shall be poured out as dust, and their flesh as the dung.
1:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必使災難臨到那些人，使他們行走如同瞎子，因為他們得罪了我耶和華；他們的血必倒出如灰塵，他們的肉必拋棄如糞土。
1:18<version name="ASV">Neither their silver nor their gold shall be able to deliver them in the day of Jehovah's wrath; but the whole land shall be devoured by the fire of his jealousy: for he will make an end, yea, a terrible end, of all them that dwell in the land. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:18<version name="Darby">their silver and their gold shall not be able to deliver  them, in the day of Jehovah's wrath; but the whole land shall  be devoured by the fire of his jealousy: for a full end, yea, a  sudden [end], shall he make of all them that dwell in the land. </p><p /><br /></version>
1:18<version name="KJV">Neither their silver nor their gold shall be able to deliver them in the day of the LORD's wrath; but the whole land shall be devoured by the fire of his jealousy: for he shall make even a speedy riddance of all them that dwell in the land.</p><p /><br /></version>
1:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當耶和華盛怒的日子，他們的金銀不能救他們；全地必被祂嫉憤的火燒滅，因為祂要將這地的一切居民，急速毀滅淨盡。
2:1|ASV|Gather yourselves together, yea, gather together, O nation that hath no shame;
2:1|Darby|Collect yourselves and gather together, O nation without  shame,
2:1|KJV|Gather yourselves together, yea, gather together, O nation not desired;
2:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|無恥的國民哪，你們要聚集，聚集一起，
2:2|ASV|before the decree bring forth, before the day pass as the chaff, before the fierce anger of Jehovah come upon you, before the day of Jehovah's anger come upon you.
2:2|Darby|before the decree bring forth, [before] the day pass away as  chaff, before the fierce anger of Jehovah come upon you, before  the day of Jehovah's anger come upon you.
2:2|KJV|Before the decree bring forth, before the day pass as the chaff, before the fierce anger of the LORD come upon you, before the day of the LORD's anger come upon you.
2:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|趁命令沒有發出，（日子過去如風前的糠秕，）耶和華的烈怒尚未臨到你們，祂發怒的日子未到以先，你們要聚集。
2:3|ASV|Seek ye Jehovah, all ye meek of the earth, that have kept his ordinances; seek righteousness, seek meekness: it may be ye will be hid in the day of Jehovah's anger.
2:3|Darby|Seek Jehovah, all ye meek of the land, who have performed  his ordinance; seek righteousness, seek meekness: it may be ye  shall be hid in the day of Jehovah's anger.
2:3|KJV|Seek ye the LORD, all ye meek of the earth, which have wrought his judgment; seek righteousness, seek meekness: it may be ye shall be hid in the day of the LORD's anger.
2:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|地上一切遵行耶和華典章的卑微人哪，你們都當尋求耶和華。當尋求公義，尋求卑微，或者在耶和華發怒的日子，可以隱藏起來。
2:4|ASV|For Gaza shall be forsaken, and Ashkelon a desolation; they shall drive out Ashdod at noonday, and Ekron shall be rooted up.
2:4|Darby|For Gazah shall be forsaken, and Ashkelon shall be a  desolation; they shall drive out Ashdod at noonday, and Ekron  shall be rooted up.
2:4|KJV|For Gaza shall be forsaken, and Ashkelon a desolation: they shall drive out Ashdod at the noon day, and Ekron shall be rooted up.
2:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因為迦薩必至見棄，亞實基倫必然荒涼；人在正午必趕出亞實突的民，以革倫也被拔出根來。
2:5|ASV|Woe unto the inhabitants of the sea-coast, the nation of the Cherethites! The word of Jehovah is against you, O Canaan, the land of the Philistines; I will destroy thee, that there shall be no inhabitant.
2:5|Darby|Woe unto the inhabitants of the sea-coast, the nation of the  Cherethites! The word of Jehovah is against you, O Canaan, land  of the Philistines: I will destroy thee, that there shall be no  inhabitant;
2:5|KJV|Woe unto the inhabitants of the sea coast, the nation of the Cherethites! the word of the LORD is against you; O Canaan, the land of the Philistines, I will even destroy thee, that there shall be no inhabitant.
2:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|沿海之地的居民，基利提族的民哪，你們有禍了！非利士人之地迦南阿，耶和華的話與你反對，說，我必毀滅你，以致你那媯L人居住。
2:6|ASV|And the sea-coast shall be pastures, with cottages for shepherds and folds for flocks.
2:6|Darby|and the sea-coast shall be cave-dwellings for shepherds, and  folds for flocks.
2:6|KJV|And the sea coast shall be dwellings and cottages for shepherds, and folds for flocks.
2:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|沿海之地要變為草場，其上有牧人的洞穴和羊群的圈。
2:7|ASV|And the coast shall be for the remnant of the house of Judah; they shall feed  their flocks thereupon; in the houses of Ashkelon shall they lie down in the evening; for Jehovah their God will visit them, and bring back their captivity.
2:7|Darby|And the coast shall be for the remnant of the house of  Judah; they shall feed thereon: in the houses of Ashkelon shall  they lie down in the evening: for Jehovah their God shall visit  them, and turn again their captivity.
2:7|KJV|And the coast shall be for the remnant of the house of Judah; they shall feed thereupon: in the houses of Ashkelon shall they lie down in the evening: for the LORD their God shall visit them, and turn away their captivity.
2:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這地帶必為猶大家餘剩的人所得；他們必在其上牧放群羊。他們在晚上必躺臥在亞實基倫的房屋中，因為耶和華他們的神必眷顧他們，使他們被擄的人歸回。
2:8|ASV|I have heard the reproach of Moab, and the revilings of the children of Ammon, wherewith they have reproached my people, and magnified themselves against their border.
2:8|Darby|I have heard the reproach of Moab, and the revilings of the  children of Ammon, wherewith they have reproached my people,  and magnified themselves against their border.
2:8|KJV|I have heard the reproach of Moab, and the revilings of the children of Ammon, whereby they have reproached my people, and magnified themselves against their border.
2:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我聽見摩押人的辱罵，和亞捫人的毀謗，就是辱罵我的百姓，自誇自大，侵犯他們的境界。
2:9|ASV|Therefore as I live, saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, Surely Moab shall be as Sodom, and the children of Ammon as Gomorrah, a possession of nettles, and saltpits, and a perpetual desolation: the residue of my people shall make a prey of them, and the remnant of my nation shall inherit them.
2:9|Darby|Therefore, [as] I live, saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of  Israel, Moab shall certainly be as Sodom, and the children of  Ammon as Gomorrah, a possession of nettles, and salt-pits, and  a perpetual desolation; the remnant of my people shall spoil  them, and the residue of my nation shall possess them.
2:9|KJV|Therefore as I live, saith the LORD of hosts, the God of Israel, Surely Moab shall be as Sodom, and the children of Ammon as Gomorrah, even the breeding of nettles, and saltpits, and a perpetual desolation: the residue of my people shall spoil them, and the remnant of my people shall possess them.
2:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|因此萬軍之耶和華以色列的神說，我指著我的生存起誓，摩押必像所多瑪，亞捫人必像蛾摩拉，都變為刺草、鹽坑之地，永遠荒廢；我百姓所餘剩的必擄掠他們，我國中所剩下的必承受他們的地。
2:10|ASV|This shall they have for their pride, because they have reproached and magnified themselves against the people of Jehovah of hosts.
2:10|Darby|This shall they have for their pride, because they have  reproached and magnified themselves against the people of  Jehovah of hosts.
2:10|KJV|This shall they have for their pride, because they have reproached and magnified themselves against the people of the LORD of hosts.
2:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這事臨到他們，是因他們驕傲，自誇自大，辱罵萬軍之耶和華的百姓。
2:11|ASV|Jehovah will be terrible unto them; for he will famish all the gods of the earth; and men shall worship him, every one from his place, even all the isles of the nations.
2:11|Darby|Jehovah will be terrible unto them; for he will famish all  the gods of the earth; and all the isles of the nations shall  worship him, every one from his place.
2:11|KJV|The LORD will be terrible unto them: for he will famish all the gods of the earth; and men shall worship him, every one from his place, even all the isles of the heathen.
2:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華必向他們顯為可畏；因祂必使地上的諸神消滅，列國眾海島的居民，各在自己的地方敬拜祂。
2:12|ASV|Ye Ethiopians also, ye shall be slain by my sword.
2:12|Darby|Ye Ethiopians also, ye shall be the slain of my sword.
2:12|KJV|Ye Ethiopians also, ye shall be slain by my sword.
2:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|古實人哪，你們也必被我的刀所殺。
2:13|ASV|And he will stretch out his hand against the north, and destroy Assyria, and will make Nineveh a desolation, and dry like the wilderness.
2:13|Darby|And he will stretch out his hand against the north, and  destroy Assyria; and will make Nineveh a desolation, a place of  drought like the wilderness.
2:13|KJV|And he will stretch out his hand against the north, and destroy Assyria; and will make Nineveh a desolation, and dry like a wilderness.
2:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|祂必伸手攻擊北方，毀滅亞述，使尼尼微荒涼，乾旱如同曠野。
2:14|ASV|And herds shall lie down in the midst of her, all the beasts of the nations: both the pelican and the porcupine shall lodge in the capitals thereof; their voice shall sing in the windows; desolation shall be in the thresholds: for he hath laid bare the cedar-work.
2:14|Darby|And flocks shall lie down in the midst of her, all the  crowd of beasts; both the pelican and the bittern shall lodge  in the chapiters thereof; a voice shall sing in the windows;  desolation shall be on the thresholds: for he hath laid bare  the cedar work.
2:14|KJV|And flocks shall lie down in the midst of her, all the beasts of the nations: both the cormorant and the bittern shall lodge in the upper lintels of it; their voice shall sing in the windows; desolation shall be in the thresholds; for he shall uncover the cedar work.
2:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|群畜和各類的走獸，必躺臥在其中；鵜鶘和箭豬要宿在柱頂上。在窗戶內有鳴叫的聲音；門檻都必毀壞；因祂已使香柏木露出。
2:15<version name="ASV">This is the joyous city that dwelt carelessly, that said in her heart, I am, and there is none besides me: how is she become a desolation, a place for beasts to lie down in! every one that passeth by her shall hiss, and wag his hand. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:15<version name="Darby">This is the rejoicing city that dwelt in security, that  said in her heart, I am, and there is none else beside me: how  is she become a desolation, a couching-place for beasts! Every  one that passeth by her shall hiss, shall wave his hand. </p><p /><br /></version>
2:15<version name="KJV">This is the rejoicing city that dwelt carelessly, that said in her heart, I am, and there is none beside me: how is she become a desolation, a place for beasts to lie down in! every one that passeth by her shall hiss, and wag his hand.</p><p /><br /></version>
2:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這是素來歡躍安居的城，她心婸﹛A惟有我，除我以外再沒有別的。她現在何竟荒涼，成為野獸躺臥之處！凡經過的人都必嗤笑，向她搖手。
3:1|ASV|Woe to her that is rebellious and polluted! to the oppressing city!
3:1|Darby|Woe to her that is rebellious and corrupted, to the  oppressing city!
3:1|KJV|Woe to her that is filthy and polluted, to the oppressing city!
3:1|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|這悖逆、污穢、欺壓的城有禍了！
3:2|ASV|She obeyed not the voice; she received not correction; she trusted not in Jehovah; she drew not near to her God.
3:2|Darby|She hearkened not to the voice; she received not correction;  she confided not in Jehovah; she drew not near her God.
3:2|KJV|She obeyed not the voice; she received not correction; she trusted not in the LORD; she drew not near to her God.
3:2|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|她不聽從命令，不領受管教，不信靠耶和華，不親近她的神。
3:3|ASV|Her princes in the midst of her are roaring lions; her judges are evening wolves; they leave nothing till the morrow.
3:3|Darby|Her princes in the midst of her are roaring lions; her  judges are evening wolves, that leave nothing for the morning.
3:3|KJV|Her princes within her are roaring lions; her judges are evening wolves; they gnaw not the bones till the morrow.
3:3|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|她中間的首領是吼叫的獅子。她的審判官是晚上的豺狼，一點食物也不留到早晨。
3:4|ASV|Her prophets are light and treacherous persons; her priests have profaned the sanctuary, they have done violence to the law.
3:4|Darby|Her prophets are vain-glorious, treacherous persons; her  priests profane the sanctuary, they do violence to the law.
3:4|KJV|Her prophets are light and treacherous persons: her priests have polluted the sanctuary, they have done violence to the law.
3:4|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|她的申言者是虛浮詭詐的人。她的祭司褻瀆聖所，強解律法。
3:5|ASV|Jehovah in the midst of her is righteous; he will not do iniquity; every morning doth he bring his justice to light, he faileth not; but the unjust knoweth no shame.
3:5|Darby|The righteous Jehovah is in the midst of her: he doeth no  wrong. Every morning doth he bring his judgment to light; it  faileth not: but the unrighteous knoweth no shame.
3:5|KJV|The just LORD is in the midst thereof; he will not do iniquity: every morning doth he bring his judgment to light, he faileth not; but the unjust knoweth no shame.
3:5|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華在她中間是公義的，斷不作不義的事，每早晨顯明祂的公平，從無失誤；只是不義的人不知羞恥。
3:6|ASV|I have cut off nations; their battlements are desolate; I have made their streets waste, so that none passeth by; their cities are destroyed, so that there is no man, so that there is no inhabitant.
3:6|Darby|I have cut off nations: their battlements are desolate; I  made their streets waste, that none passeth by; their cities  are destroyed, so that there is no man, so that there is no  inhabitant.
3:6|KJV|I have cut off the nations: their towers are desolate; I made their streets waste, that none passeth by: their cities are destroyed, so that there is no man, that there is none inhabitant.
3:6|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我耶和華已經剪除列國；他們的角樓毀壞；我使他們的街道荒涼，以致無人經過；他們的城邑毀滅，以致無人，也無居民。
3:7|ASV|I said, Only fear thou me; receive correction; so her dwelling shall not be cut off, according to all that I have appointed concerning her: but they rose early and corrupted all their doings.
3:7|Darby|I said, Only fear me, receive correction; so her dwelling  shall not be cut off, howsoever I may punish her. But they rose  early, they corrupted all their doings.
3:7|KJV|I said, Surely thou wilt fear me, thou wilt receive instruction; so their dwelling should not be cut off, howsoever I punished them: but they rose early, and corrupted all their doings.
3:7|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我說，你只要敬畏我，領受管教；如此，她的住處就不致照我所擬定的被除滅；只是他們從早起來，在一切所行的事上敗壞自己。
3:8|ASV|Therefore wait ye for me, saith Jehovah, until the day that I rise up to the prey; for my determination is to gather the nations, that I may assemble the kingdoms, to pour upon them mine indignation, even all my fierce anger; for all the earth shall be devoured with the fire of my jealousy.
3:8|Darby|Therefore wait ye for me, saith Jehovah, until the day that  I rise up to the prey; for my determination is to assemble the  nations, that I may gather the kingdoms together, to pour upon  them mine indignation, -- all my fierce anger: for all the  earth shall be devoured with the fire of my jealousy.
3:8|KJV|Therefore wait ye upon me, saith the LORD, until the day that I rise up to the prey: for my determination is to gather the nations, that I may assemble the kingdoms, to pour upon them mine indignation, even all my fierce anger: for all the earth shall be devoured with the fire of my jealousy.
3:8|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華說，因此你們要等候我，直到我興起擄掠的日子，因為我裁定要招聚列國，聚集列邦，將我的惱怒，就是我的烈怒，都傾倒在他們身上；因為在我嫉憤的火中，全地必被燒滅。
3:9|ASV|For then will I turn to the peoples of a pure language, that they may all call upon the name of Jehovah, to serve him with one consent.
3:9|Darby|For then will I turn to the peoples a pure language, that  they may all call upon the name of Jehovah, to serve him with  one consent.
3:9|KJV|For then will I turn to the people a pure language, that they may all call upon the name of the LORD, to serve him with one consent.
3:9|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時，我必使萬民改用純潔的語言，好叫他們都呼求我耶和華的名，同心合意的事奉我。
3:10|ASV|From beyond the rivers of Ethiopia my suppliants, even the daughter of my dispersed, shall bring mine offering.
3:10|Darby|From beyond the rivers of Cush my suppliants, the daughter  of my dispersed, shall bring mine oblation.
3:10|KJV|From beyond the rivers of Ethiopia my suppliants, even the daughter of my dispersed, shall bring mine offering.
3:10|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|向我祈求的，就是我所分散的女子，必從古實河外將素祭帶來給我。
3:11|ASV|In that day shalt thou not be put to shame for all thy doings, wherein thou hast transgressed against me; for then I will take away out of the midst of thee thy proudly exulting ones, and thou shalt no more be haughty in my holy mountain.
3:11|Darby|In that day thou shalt not be ashamed for all thy doings  wherein thou hast transgressed against me; for then I will take  away out of the midst of thee them that exult in thy pride, and  thou shalt no more be haughty because of my holy mountain.
3:11|KJV|In that day shalt thou not be ashamed for all thy doings, wherein thou hast transgressed against me: for then I will take away out of the midst of thee them that rejoice in thy pride, and thou shalt no more be haughty because of my holy mountain.
3:11|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當那日，你必不因所行一切得罪我的事，自覺羞愧；因為那時我必從你中間除掉那些高傲矜誇的人，在我的聖山上，你必不再狂傲。
3:12|ASV|But I will leave in the midst of thee an afflicted and poor people, and they shall take refuge in the name of Jehovah.
3:12|Darby|And I will leave in the midst of thee an afflicted and poor  people, and they shall trust in the name of Jehovah.
3:12|KJV|I will also leave in the midst of thee an afflicted and poor people, and they shall trust in the name of the LORD.
3:12|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我卻要在你中間，留下困苦貧寒的民；他們必投靠我耶和華的名。
3:13|ASV|The remnant of Israel shall not do iniquity, nor speak lies; neither shall a deceitful tongue be found in their mouth; for they shall feed and lie down, and none shall make them afraid.
3:13|Darby|The remnant of Israel shall not work unrighteousness, nor  speak lies; neither shall a deceitful tongue be found in their  mouth: but *they* shall feed and lie down, and none shall make  them afraid.
3:13|KJV|The remnant of Israel shall not do iniquity, nor speak lies; neither shall a deceitful tongue be found in their mouth: for they shall feed and lie down, and none shall make them afraid.
3:13|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|以色列所餘剩的人，必不作罪孽，不說謊言，口中也沒有詭詐的舌頭；因為他們必得草場躺臥，無人驚嚇。
3:14|ASV|Sing, O daughter of Zion; shout, O Israel; be glad and rejoice with all the heart, O daughter of Jerusalem.
3:14|Darby|Exult, O daughter of Zion; shout, O Israel; rejoice and be  glad with all the heart, O daughter of Jerusalem:
3:14|KJV|Sing, O daughter of Zion; shout, O Israel; be glad and rejoice with all the heart, O daughter of Jerusalem.
3:14|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|錫安的女子阿，應當歡呼！以色列阿，應當誇勝呼喊！耶路撒冷的女子阿，應當滿心歡喜快樂！
3:15|ASV|Jehovah hath taken away thy judgments, he hath cast out thine enemy: the King of Israel, even Jehovah, is in the midst of thee; thou shalt not fear evil any more.
3:15|Darby|Jehovah hath taken away thy judgments, he hath cast out  thine enemy; the King of Israel, Jehovah, is in the midst of  thee; thou shalt not see evil any more.
3:15|KJV|The LORD hath taken away thy judgments, he hath cast out thine enemy: the king of Israel, even the LORD, is in the midst of thee: thou shalt not see evil any more.
3:15|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華已經除去你的刑罰，趕走你的仇敵；以色列的王耶和華在你中間，你必不再看見災禍。
3:16|ASV|In that day it shall be said to Jerusalem, Fear thou not; O Zion, let not thy hands be slack.
3:16|Darby|In that day it shall be said to Jerusalem, Fear not; Zion,  let not thy hands be slack.
3:16|KJV|In that day it shall be said to Jerusalem, Fear thou not: and to Zion, Let not thine hands be slack.
3:16|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|當那日，必有話向耶路撒冷說，不要懼怕；錫安哪，手不要下垂。
3:17|ASV|Jehovah thy God is in the midst of thee, a mighty one who will save; he will rejoice over thee with joy; he will rest in his love; he will joy over thee with singing.
3:17|Darby|Jehovah thy God is in thy midst, a mighty one that will  save: he will rejoice over thee with joy; he will rest in his  love; he will exult over thee with singing.
3:17|KJV|The LORD thy God in the midst of thee is mighty; he will save, he will rejoice over thee with joy; he will rest in his love, he will joy over thee with singing.
3:17|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|耶和華你的神在你中間，是施行拯救的大能者；祂必因你歡欣喜樂，默然愛你，且因你喜樂而歡呼。
3:18|ASV|I will gather them that sorrow for the solemn assembly, who were of thee; to whom the burden upon her was a reproach.
3:18|Darby|I will gather them that sorrow for the solemn assemblies,  who were of thee: the reproach of it was a burden [unto them].
3:18|KJV|I will gather them that are sorrowful for the solemn assembly, who are of thee, to whom the reproach of it was a burden.
3:18|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|我必聚集那些屬你，為所定的大會愁煩的人，他們擔負了羞辱。
3:19|ASV|Behold, at that time I will deal with all them that afflict thee; and I will save that which is lame, and gather that which was driven away; and I will make them a praise and a name, whose shame hath been in all the earth.
3:19|Darby|Behold, at that time I will deal with all them that afflict  thee; and I will save her that halted, and gather her that was  driven out; and I will make them a praise and a name in all the  lands where they have been put to shame.
3:19|KJV|Behold, at that time I will undo all that afflict thee: and I will save her that halteth, and gather her that was driven out; and I will get them praise and fame in every land where they have been put to shame.
3:19|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時，我必懲辦一切苦待你的人，又拯救瘸腿的，聚集被趕出的。我必使他們在各地，就是在他們受羞辱之地，得稱讚，有名聲。
3:20<version name="ASV">At that time will I bring you in, and at that time will I gather you; for I will make you a name and a praise among all the peoples of the earth, when I bring back your captivity before your eyes, saith Jehovah. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:20<version name="Darby">At that time will I bring you, yea, at the time that I  gather you; for I will make you a name and a praise, among all  the peoples of the earth, when I shall turn again your  captivity before your eyes, saith Jehovah. </p><p /><br /></version>
3:20<version name="KJV">At that time will I bring you again, even in the time that I gather you: for I will make you a name and a praise among all people of the earth, when I turn back your captivity before your eyes, saith the LORD.</p><p /><br /></version>
3:20|&#24674;&#24489;&#26412;|那時我必領你們進來，那時我必聚集你們；因為我在你們眼前使你們被擄之人歸回的時候，必使你們在地上的萬民中有名聲，得稱讚。這是耶和華說的。
