<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Flow through me, Lord, a weak and earthly vessel</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Fulness of the Spirit&amp;mdash;As the Living Water</category>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="">Anonymous</author>
    <composer biodate="1809-1847" biolink="">Arranged from Felix Mendelssohn</composer>
  </creators>
  <meter>11.10.11.10.</meter>
  <hymncode>321543217132</hymncode>
  <key>Eb Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - - | F - - - | D7 - - - | G - - - | Dm/F - - - | Dm - - - | G7 - - - | C - - - | C - - - | Am - - - | Am - A/C# - | Dm - - - | Dm/F - - - | Dm - - - | G7 - - - | C - - - |</chords>
  <melody>| 3 - 2 1 | 5( 4) - 3 | 2 1 7_. 1 | 3 - 2 - (break) | 2 - 2 3 | 4 - - 2 | 6_. 7_. 3. 2/ | 1 - - - (break) | 3 - 2 1 | ._1 - - 7 | 6 5 4 3 | 6 - 2 - (break) | 2 - 2 3 | 4 - - 2 | 6_. 7_. 3. 2/ | 1 - - - |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>Flow through me, Lord, a weak and earth -- ly ves -- sel, Cleansed by Thy blood, and quick -- ened at Thy call. Flow through me, Lord, all ut -- ter -- ly a -- ban -- doned, To Thy dear serv -- ice, great, or high, or small.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="group">hymnal-subj087.xml</link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midi location="h" length="29">e0249_i.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Flow through me, Lord, a weak and earthly vessel,
  Cleansed by Thy blood, and quickened at Thy call.
Flow through me, Lord, all utterly abandoned,
  To Thy dear service, great, or high, or small.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Flow through me, Lord, with overflowing fulness,
  Make me to know Thine own deep love for souls.
Work in me, Lord, the faith that moveth mountains,
  As power, Almighty power, my being holds.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">Flow through me, Lord, till sin in all its blackness
  To captives bound by Satan is revealed.
Flow through me, Lord, till hearts are stricken, broken,
  And in Thy cleansing fountain saved and healed.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">Flow through me, Lord, till lagging souls are quickened,
  Till lives of failure sing the victory song,
Till praise from lips long dumb and silent, open,
  And join with rapture earth's glad, cleansed throng.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">Flow through me, Lord, till waters from Thy fountain
  Shall slake the thirst of souls in deserts drear.
Flow through me, Lord, till arid places blossom
  With roses fresh and sweet, and wondrous fair.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">Flow through me, Lord, set all my heart-strings thrilling,
  With Thine own love, so matchless, perfect, free.
Flow through me, Lord, till naught in earth or heaven,
  Can satisfy my being, Lord, but Thee.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
