<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Objective and subjective Christ is to us (Alternate Tune)</title>
  <category>Experience of Christ&amp;mdash;As the Subjective One</category>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="1905-1997" biolink="www.witnesslee.org">Witness Lee</author>
    <composer biodate="" biolink="">James E. Spilman</composer>
  </creators>
  <numbers><cebuano num="536"></cebuano><chinese num="398"></chinese><korean num="398"></korean><portuguese num="263"></portuguese><russian num="268"></russian><spanish num="239"></spanish><tagalog num="536"></tagalog></numbers>
  <meter>11.11.11.11.</meter>  <meter>11.11.11.11.D.</meter>
  <hymncode>511321156165</hymncode>
  <key>F Major</key>
  <time>3/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <melody>| 0 - 5_. | 1 1 3/( 2/) | 1 1 5_. | 6_. 1 6_. | 5_. - 5_. | 1 1 2 | 3 3 5 | 5 3 1 (break) | 2 - 5_. | 1 1 3/( 2/) | 1 1 5_. | 6_. 4 6_. | 5_. - 5_. | 1 1 2 | 3 (.5 4 | 5_. 5_. 7_. | 1 - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>Ob -- jec -- tive and sub -- jec -- tive Christ is to us, In heav -- en He's plead -- ing ob -- jec -- tive -- ly thus; Sub -- jec -- tive -- ly now in His mem -- bers He lives And in -- ward -- ly to them His be -- ing He gives.</singingstanza>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="group">hymnal-subj062.xml</link>
    <link type="lyrics" url="www.witness-lee-hymns.org/hymns/H0536.html">View Lyrics</link>
    <link type="relevant" category="h" num="536" />
  </links>
  <music>
    <midiref type="h" num="389"></midiref>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Objective and subjective Christ is to us,
In heaven He's pleading objectively thus;
Subjectively now in His members He lives
And inwardly to them His being He gives.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">In heaven He sits at the right hand of God,
Where as the High Priest He presented His blood;
Our Advocate, bearing our burdens above,
Our Surety, He careth for us in His love.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">He now is the Spirit, our spirit within;
He's there as our life, all things bringing with Him;
He's there as our strength and our grace every hour,
Our Paraclete in us, sustaining with pow'r.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">In heaven for us He's the glorified man,
The Forerunner entered, fulfilling God's plan;
Man into God bringing and making him one
With God in the heav'nlies, in Him as the Son.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">In us all the fulness of God dwells in Him;
As Spirit He brings God Himself thus within,
Revealing and making God real unto us,
God one with us building in life glorious.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">The Savior ascended in heaven now dwells,
And soon He's returning for us His Word tells;
Deliverer indwelling, He now in us lives,
And soon will transfigure, His glory to give.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="7">The day soon is coming when heaven and earth
Will mingle in one in that city of worth;
Objective and subjective will in that day
Be mingled within us in glory for aye.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
