<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Mine is the earth, the worlds in all their fulness</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Experience of Christ&amp;mdash;General</category>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="">Sister Eva of Friedenshort, adapted</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 5 - 3 4 | 6 - 5 - | 7 ._1 ._2 7 | ._1 - 5 - (break) | 6 - 4 6 | 5 - 6 - | 7 ._1 7 6 | 5 - - - (break) | 5 - 3 4 | 6 - 5 - | ._3 ._2 ._1 7 | ._2 - 6 - (break) | ._1 - 7 6 | 5 - ._1 - | ._1 7 6 7 | ._1 - - - |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>Mine is the earth, the worlds in all their ful -- ness; Mine, ev -- ery o -- cean, riv -- er, plain, and hill; Mine are the stars with -- in the heav -- en's still -- ness, Mine are the clouds that wan -- der at their will.</singingstanza>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="group">hymnal-subj067.xml</link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midiref type="h" num="420"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Mine is the earth, the worlds in all their fulness;
  Mine, every ocean, river, plain, and hill;
Mine are the stars within the heaven's stillness,
  Mine are the clouds that wander at their will.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Mine is the spring, when blossoms sweet are blowing,
  Wakened from slumb'ring neath the winter snow;
Mine, summer's wealth, with her bright colors glowing;
  Mine is the fruit rich autumn doth bestow.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">Mine, all the things created: praise the Giver!
  Fish, and all beasts, the birds upon the wing,
Sun-loving butterflies&amp;mdash;now and forever;
  Beauty and grace of every living thing.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">Mine, all things lovely, blessing every hour,
  Wealth of creation, over and around;
Mine is the sun, with its life-giving power,
  Mine is the music wonderful of sound.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">Mine are the pillars which cannot be shaken&amp;mdash;
  Truth in the Word, the Word that cannot fall.
Mine is the wisdom which great thoughts awaken
  In a man's soul, that this life is not all.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">Knowledge as needed, skill in all the doing,
  Mine, when kept closely for my Lord above;
Beauty and wisdom, living streams e'er flowing
  Fresh from the springs of God, the God of love.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="7">Mine are the battles, triumph-shouts e'er ringing&amp;mdash;
  Joy of the warriors for the truth and right;
Mine are the trophies God's brave ones are bringing,
  Heroes of faith and overcoming might.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="8">Mine, mercies granted, and each new awaking,
  Every experience, and each soul that's won;
Mine, the confessions sinners poor are making,
  Yea, I am joined with them, one in God's Son.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="9">One' Lord in all, and all one in His Spirit,
  Heavenly fellowship earth has not known;
Faith sees the riches we shall yet inherit,
  Glorious treasure laid up for His own.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="10">All in the bounds of earth and sea and heaven,
  Creation's wonders and Thy grace are stored:
Praise to Thee, Christ, for all the wealth Thou'st given!
  Poor in myself, but wealthy in my Lord!</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
