<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Not what I am, O Lord, but what Thou art</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Comfort in Trials&amp;mdash;By the Lord's Love</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="499"/><english num="672"/><french num="130"/><korean num="499"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="1808-1889" biolink="">Horatius Bonar</author>
    <composer biodate="" biolink="">T. Collins</composer>
  </creators>
  <meter>10.10.10.10.</meter>
  <hymncode>3243511721</hymncode>
  <key>F Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - F/C - | C - C/E - | F - G7 - | C - - - | C - D/A - | G/B - C - | G/D - D7 - | G - - - | C - G/B - | C - - - | C/E - C - | C/G - G - | F - G7/F - | C/E - F - | C/G - G7 - | C - - - |</chords>
  <melody>| 3 - 2 4 | 3 - 5 - | 1 1 7_. 2 | 1 - - - (break) | 3 - 3 4# | 5 - 3 - | 2 1 7_. 6_. | 5_. - - - (break) | 1 - 1 2 | 3 - 1 - | 5 5 4 3 | 3( - 2) - (break) | 6 - 5 4 | 3 5 4 2 | 1 - 7_. - | 1 - - - |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>Not what I am, O Lord, but what Thou art; That, that a -- lone, can be my soul's true rest; Thy love, not mine, bids fear and doubt de -- part, And stills the tem -- pest of my toss -- ing breast.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midi location="h" length="32">e0672_i.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Not what I am, O Lord, but what Thou art;
That, that alone, can be my soul's true rest;
Thy love, not mine, bids fear and doubt depart,
And stills the tempest of my tossing breast.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">It is Thy perfect love that casts out fear;
I know the voice that speaks the It is I,
And in these well-known words of heavenly cheer
I hear the joy that bids each sorrow fly.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">Thy Name is Love! I hear it from yon Cross;
Thy Name is Love! I read it in yon tomb:
All meaner love is perishable dross,
But this shall light me through time's thickest gloom.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">It blesses now, and shall for ever bless;
It saves me now, and shall for ever save;
It holds me up in days of helplessness,
It bears me safely o'er each swelling wave.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">'Tis what I know of Thee, my Lord and God,
That fills my soul with peace, my lips with song;
Thou art my health, my joy, my staff, my rod;
Leaning on Thee, in weakness I am strong.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">More of Thyself, Oh, show me, hour by hour;
More of Thy glory, O my God and Lord;
More of Thyself in all Thy grace and power;
More of Thy love and truth, Incarnate Word.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
