<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Lord, in Thy presence</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Prayer&amp;mdash;The Meaning</category>
  <numbers><cebuano num="764"/><chinese num="553"/><english num="764"/><german num="764"/><korean num="553"/><portuguese num="351"/><russian num="481"/><spanish num="326"/><tagalog num="764"/></numbers>
  <creators>
	<author biodate="1905-1997" biolink="www.witnesslee.org">Witness Lee</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 3 - 2 3 | 1 - - 1 | 2 3 4 5 | 3 - - - | 5 - 4 5 | 3 - 2 - | 1 1 1 1 | 7_. - - - (break) | 3 - 2 7_. | 1 - 5 - | 6 ._1 7. 4/ | 6( - 5) - | 6 - 4 3 | 3 5 4 6_. | 1 - 2 - | 1 - - - |</melody>
  <layout>
	<singingstanza>Lord, in Thy pre -- sence si -- lent I would be, That in the in -- most I to Thee may come; I would not in my own way pray to Thee, But let Thy prayer in me my prayer be -- come.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <links>
	<link type="group">icometotheedearlord.xml</link>
	<link type="group">hymnal-subj171.xml</link>
	<link type="lyrics" url="www.witness-lee-hymns.org/hymns/H0764.html">View Lyrics</link>
	<link type="orderinfo" url="www.livingstream.com/hymns/0736318135.html"></link>
  </links>
  <music>
	<midiref type="h" num="431"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
	<stanza type="verse" number="1">Lord, in Thy presence silent I would be,
That in the inmost I to Thee may come;
I would not in my own way pray to Thee,
But let Thy prayer in me my prayer become.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="2">It seems Thou art in heaven hearing me,
But right within my spirit Thou dost dwell;
It seems that I am praying unto Thee,
But really from Thyself the prayers do well.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="3">When, Lord, no words my burden can express,
My spirit with Thy Spirit deeply groans;
Not verbally I then my plea address,
But Thou dost pray within with words unknown.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="4">I would inhale Thee, Lord, e'en as I breathe,
And eat and drink Thee as my life supply.
A deeper fellowship with Thee bequeath
That Thou express Thyself through me thereby.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="5">Here in this fellowship Thy light doth shine,
Thy precious blood doth cleanse and make me clean;
May I not only, Lord, Thy light enshrine,
But may Thou be expressed and clearly seen.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="6">Thy oil anoints me here in every way,
Anointing Thee within unceasingly;
I more decrease, Thou more increase each day,
Thus full expression Thou shalt have through me.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="7">Myself I open that Thou may flow in;
Op'ning myself to others, Lord, flow out;
By such a stream, the fellowship within,
Thou, Lord, expressed will be my life throughout.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
