<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Prayer is the incense of a holy heart</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Prayer&amp;mdash;The Meaning</category>
  <numbers><cebuano num="762"/><chinese num="552"/><english num="762"/><korean num="552"/><tagalog num="762"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="1843-1919" biolink="">Albert Benjamin Simpson</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 1 - 2 3 | 4 - 3 - | 2 1 1 7_. | 1 - - - (break) | 3 - 4 5 | 6 - 5 - | 4 3 2 1 | 2 - - - (break) | 5 - 5 4 | 3 - 2 - | 3 5 5 4# | 5 - - - (break) | 3 - 2 1 | 7_. 1 2 4 | 3 - 2 - | 1 - - - |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>Prayer is the in -- cense of a ho -- ly heart Ris -- ing to God from bruised and brok -- en things, When kin -- dled by the Spir -- it's burn -- ing breath And up -- ward borne by faith's as -- cend -- ing wings.</singingstanza>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="group">hymnal-subj171.xml</link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midiref type="h" num="454"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Prayer is the incense of a holy heart
Rising to God from bruised and broken things,
When kindled by the Spirit's burning breath
And upward borne by faith's ascending wings.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Prayer is the perfume of the plants of grace,
The flowers of patience, faith, and suffering love,
Treasured in "vials full of odors sweet,"
God breathes their fragrance in His courts above.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">Prayer is th' ascending vapor which supplies
The showers of blessing, and the stream that flows
Through earth's dry places, till on every side
"The wilderness shall blossom as the rose."</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">Prayer is the heavenly telephone that brings
The distant near, till heaven to earth comes down,
And in our Father's ear and heart we may
Our burdens tell and all our sorrows drown.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">Prayer is the wireless telegraph that sends
Its heart throbs on the ether waves of heaven;
It finds the heart of God, and back to earth
The answering thrill to faith and love are given.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">Prayer is the golden pipes the Spirit fills,
Which feed the lamps of God with oil divine,
And, as with one accord we wait and pray,
The Spirit fills, the lamps with brightness shine.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="7">Prayer is the mightiest force of earth and heaven,
Prayer is the very dynamite of God;
It moves the hand that all things moves, and turns
The living wheels that sweep through earth abroad.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="8">Teach us to pray! Move on our hearts, O Lord,
Till Thine own passion all our being move!
Teach us! Pray in us, till our prayer shall be
Christ in us praying to the Christ above!</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="9">Teach us to pray! Reveal Thy will to us,
Till Thine own purpose all our being move!
Teach us! Pray in us, till our prayer shall be
God in us answering to the God above!</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
