<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>One sat alone beside the highway begging</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Gospel&amp;mdash;General</category>
  <numbers><english num="1078"/><french num="209"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="1889-1986" biolink="">Oswald Jeffrey Smith</author>
    <composer biodate="" biolink="">Homer Rodeheaver</composer>
  </creators>
  <meter>11.10.11.10.D.</meter>
  <hymncode>33212356354</hymncode>
  <key>C Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - - | C - A7 - | Dm - Dm/F - | G - G7/B - | C - - - | Cm - - - | C - A7 - | Dm - G7 - | C - A7 - | Dm - G7 - | C - A7 - | Dm - G7 - | C - - G7/D | C/E - C7 - | F - D7/F# - | C/G - G7 - | C F/C C - |</chords>
 <guitarChords>| C - - - | C - - - | Dm - - - | G - G7 - | C - - - | Cm - - - | C - - - | C - G7 - | C - - - | G - G7 - | C - - - | G - G7 - | C - - - | C - C7 - | F - - - | C - G7 - | C F C - |</guitarChords>
  <melody>| 0 - 0/ 3/ 3/ 2/ | 1. 2/ 3/ 5/ 6/ 3/ | 5 4. 4/ 4/ 3/ | 2. 3/ 4/ 5/ 2/ 4/ (break) | 3 - 0/ 1/ 1/ 1/ | 3b. 3b/ 3b/ 3b/ 2/ 1/ | 3 3 0/ 5/ ._1/ 3/ | 5. 3/ 4/ 4/ 3/ 2/ (break) | 1( - 1/) (Chorus) 5/ 6/ 3/ | 4. 5/ 7/ 6/ 5/ 4/ | 3 5 0/ 5/ 6/ 3/ | 4. 5/ 7/ 6/ 5/ 6/ (break) | 3( - 3/) 1/ 3/ 5/ | ._1. 3/ 3/ 3/ 4/ 5/ | 7 6. 6/ ._1/ 2/ | 5. 3/ 4/ 4/ 3/ 2/ | 1( - 1/) 0. |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>One sat a -- lone be -- side the high -- way beg -- ging, His eyes were blind, the light he could not see; He clutched his rags and shiv -- ered in the sha -- dows, Then Je -- sus came and bade his dark -- ness flee. When Je -- sus comes the tempt -- er's pow'r is brok -- en; When Je -- sus comes the tears are wiped a -- way. He takes the gloom and fills the life with glo -- ry, For all is changed when Je -- sus comes to stay.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <copyright>Copyright 1940. Rodeheaver Co., Owner. All Rights Reserved. Used by Permission.</copyright>
  <links>
    <link type="group">hymnal-subj098.xml</link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midi location="h" length="46">e1078_i.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">One sat alone beside the highway begging,
  His eyes were blind, the light he could not see;
He clutched his rags and shivered in the shadows,
  Then Jesus came and bade his darkness flee.</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">When Jesus comes the tempter's pow'r is broken;
  When Jesus comes the tears are wiped away.
He takes the gloom and fills the life with glory,
    For all is changed when Jesus comes to stay.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">From home and friends the evil spirits drove him,
  Among the tombs he dwelt in misery;
He cut himself as demon pow'rs possessed him,
  Then Jesus came and set the captive free.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">"Unclean! unclean!" the leper cried in torment,
  The deaf, the dumb, in helplessness stood near;
The fever raged, disease had gripped its victim,
  Then Jesus came and cast out every fear.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">Their hearts were sad as in the tomb they laid him,
  For death had come and taken him away;
Their night was dark and bitter tears were falling,
  Then Jesus came and night was turned to day.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">So men today have found the Savior able,
  They could not conquer passion, lust and sin;
Their broken hearts had left them sad and lonely,
  Then Jesus came and dwelt, Himself, within.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
