<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Jesus Lord, I'm captured by Thy beauty</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Experience of Christ&amp;mdash;Loving Him</category>
  <numbers><cebuano num="1159"/><chinese num="ts:305"/><dutch num="1"/><english num="1159"/><french num="115"/><german num="1159"/><korean num="831"/><lsmyp num="193"/><portuguese num="274"/><russian num="115"/><spanish num="278"/><tagalog num="1159"/></numbers>
  <creators>
	<author biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Ron Kangas">R. K.</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 0 - - 3/ 2/ | 1. 1/ 1/ 1/ 2/ 3/ | 3 2 0 2/ 1/ | 7_.. 7_./ 7_./ 1/ 2/ 7_./ (break) | 1 - 0 3/ 2/ | 1. 1/ 1/ 1/ 2/ 3/ | 3 2 0 2/ 1/ | 7_.. 7_./ 7_./ 1/ 2/ 7_./ (break) | 1 - 0 3./ 4// | 5. 5/ 5/ 5/ ._1/ 7/ | 7 6 0 2/ 3/ | 4. 4/ 4/ 6/ 5/ 4/ (break) | 3 - 0 3/ 2/ | 1. 1/ 1/ 1/ 2/ 3/ | 3 2 0 2/ 1/ | 7_.. 7_./ 7_./ 1/ 2/ 7_./ | 1 - 0 - |</melody>
  <layout>
	<singingstanza>Je -- sus Lord, I'm cap -- tured by Thy beau -- ty, All my heart to Thee I o -- pen wide; Now set free from all re -- li -- gious du -- ty, On -- ly let me in Thy -- self a -- bide. As I'm gaz -- ing here up -- on Thy glo -- ry, Fill my heart with ra -- dian -- cy di -- vine; Sat -- u -- rate me, Lord, I now im -- plore Thee, Min -- gle now Thy Spir -- it, Lord, with mine.</singingstanza>
	<columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <links>
	<link type="group">ivefoundtheoneofpeerlessworth.xml</link>
	<link type="group">hymnal-subj071.xml</link>
	<link type="orderinfo" url="www.livingstream.com/hymns/0736320504.html"></link>
  </links>
  <videos>
	<video title="" url=""/>
  </videos>
  <music>
	<midiref type="h" num="713"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
	<stanza type="verse" number="1">Jesus Lord, I'm captured by Thy beauty,
  All my heart to Thee I open wide;
Now set free from all religious duty,
  Only let me in Thyself abide.
As I'm gazing here upon Thy glory,
  Fill my heart with radiancy divine;
Saturate me, Lord, I now implore Thee,
  Mingle now Thy Spirit, Lord, with mine.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="2">Shining One&amp;mdash;how clear the sky above me!
  Son of Man, I see Thee on the throne!
Holy One, the flames of God consume me,
  Till my being glows with Thee alone.
Lord, when first I saw Thee in Thy splendor,
  All self-love and glory sank in shame;
Now my heart its love and praises render,
  Tasting all the sweetness of Thy name.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="3">Precious Lord, my flask of alabaster
  Gladly now I break in love for Thee;
I anoint Thy head, Beloved Master;
  Lord, behold, I've saved the best for Thee.
Dearest Lord, I waste myself upon Thee;
  Loving Thee, I'm deeply satisfied.
Love outpoured from hidden depths within me,
  Costly oil, dear Lord, I would provide.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="4">My Beloved, come on spices' mountain;
  How I yearn to see Thee face to face.
Drink, dear Lord, from my heart's flowing fountain,
  Till I rest fore'er in Thine embrace.
Not alone, O Lord, do I adore Thee,
  But with all the saints as Thy dear Bride;
Quickly come, our love is waiting for Thee;
  Jesus Lord, Thou wilt be satisfied.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
