<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>In the church the sound of life upon our ear is falling</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>The Church&amp;mdash;As Our Home and Rest</category>
  <numbers><cebuano num="1236"/><chinese num="ts:716"/><english num="1236"/><german num="1236"/><russian num="536"/><tagalog num="1236"/></numbers>
  <creators>
	<author biodate="" biolink="">Adapted</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| ._1. ._2/ ._1 6 | 5. 6/ 5 3 | 5. 6/ 5 4 | 3 5 - - | 6. 7/ ._1 6 | ._1. 5/ 5 ._1 | 6 ._2 ._2 ._3 | ._2 - - 0 (break) | ._1. ._2/ ._1 6 | 5. 6/ 5 3 | 5. 6/ 5 4 | 3 5 - - | 6. 7/ ._1 6 | 5 ._1 - ._4 | ._3 - ._2 - (break) | ._1 - - (Chorus) 5 | ._1 ._1 - 6./ 5// | ._1 ._1 - 3./ 4// | 5 5 5 5 | 5 - - 5 | 7 7 - 6./ 5// | ._1 ._3 - ._1 | 6 ._2 ._2 ._3 (break) | ._2 5 ._1 ._2 | ._3 ._3 - ._2./ ._1// | ._3 ._3 - ._2./ ._1// | ._2 ._1 6 ._1 | 5 5 3 4 | 5 ._1 - ._4 | ._3 - ._2 - | ._1 - - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
	<singingstanza>In the church the sound of life up -- on our ear is fall -- ing, Then we see the joy of Christ ex -- pressed on ev -- ery hand; Ba -- by -- lon and things of earth in vain to us are call -- ing. We are home for -- ev -- er in Christ our land. We're church -- ing in the Spir -- it On the church -- 's lo -- cal ground; We're church -- ing with our broth -- ers, Our fam -- ily we have found. Oh, yes, we're church -- ing with the church -- es, And we'll make the earth re -- sound With hal -- le -- lu -- jahs for Christ our land!</singingstanza>
	<columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <links>
	<link type="group">hymnal-subj196.xml</link>
  </links>
  <music>
	<midiref type="h" num="324"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
	<stanza type="verse" number="1">In the church the sound of life upon our ear is falling,
Then we see the joy of Christ expressed on every hand;
Babylon and things of earth in vain to us are calling.
  We are home forever in Christ our land.</stanza>
	<stanza type="chorus" number="">We're churching in the Spirit
On the church's local ground;
We're churching with our brothers,
Our family we have found.
Oh, yes, we're churching with the churches,
And we'll make the earth resound
  With hallelujahs for Christ our land!</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="2">Far away our background seems with all its gifts and teaching,
Farther still, the worldly things with all their foul demand;
As the love of Jesus Christ our inmost heart is reaching,
  Not a thing can move us from Christ our land.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="3">"I will build My church upon this rock," said the Lord Jesus,
And we see the building of His purpose and His plan;
Setting members in the Body as Himself it pleases,
  Building us together in Christ our land.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="4">Now the Lord's recovery is everywhere proceeding,
All the churches join in one to give the Lord command:
"Speed the day when all the earth will echo with pray-reading
  And with hallelujahs for Christ our land."</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
