<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Let's take the land! The land that God has given us</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Spiritual Warfare&amp;mdash;Taking the Land</category>
  <numbers><cebuano num="1287"/><chinese num="ts:243"/><english num="1287"/><german num="1287"/><lsmyp num="263"/><russian num="146"/><spanish num="404"/><tagalog num="1287"/></numbers>
  <creators>
	<author biodate="" biolink="">Adapted</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 0 - - 0./ 5// | ._1 ._1 ._1.. 5// | 6./ 5// 5./ 5// 6./ 5// 5./ 5// | ._2 ._2 ._2.. ._3// (break) | ._2./ ._1// 7./ 6// 5./ 0// 0./ 5// | ._3 ._3 ._3.. ._3// | ._3./ ._2// ._4./ ._3// ._2./ ._1// 7./ 6// | 5 ._1 ._1.. 5// (break) | ._3./ ._2// ._1./ 7// (.._1./ (Sisters:) 5// 6./ 7// | ._1 7 6 3 | 5 - 5./ 5// 6./ 7// | ._1 7 6 3 (break) | 4( - 4./) 2// 4./ 5// | 7 7 0./ 5// 7./ ._1// | ._2 ._2 0./ 2// 3./ 4// | 7 6 4 6 (break) | 5 - 0./ (Brothers:) 5// 6./ 7// | ._1 7 6 3 | 5 - 5./ 5// 6./ 7// | ._1 ._3 ._4 ._3 (break) | 6 - 0./ 5#// 6./ 7// | ._1 ._1 0./ 7// ._1./ ._2// | ._3 ._3 0./ 5// 5./ 5// | 6 ._4 ._3 ._2 | ._1 - - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
	<singingstanza>Let's take the land! The land that God has giv -- en us; In all our liv -- ing, Christ can be so much: To take this land, we have th'e -- quip -- ment that we need&amp;mdash; The blood, the Word, the Spir -- it, and the church. Let's take the land! O Christ -- ian broth -- ers, The land that God has giv -- en us. Be strong and take it, for we can make it And gain this land so glo -- ri -- ous! Let's take the land! O Christ -- ian sis -- ters, And to these things give earn -- est heed. The Lord im -- plores us; He's gone be -- fore us And giv -- en ev -- ery -- thing we need!</singingstanza>
	<columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <copyright>Lelia Naylor Morris, 1904 Frances M. Lunk, renewed by Haldor Lillenas 1932 or 1933 (also: Hope Publishing Co)</copyright>
  <links>
	<link type="group">hymnal-subj188.xml</link>
  </links>
  <music>
	<midiref type="h" num="1118"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
	<stanza type="verse" number="1">Let's take the land! The land that God has given us;
In all our living, Christ can be so much:
To take this land, we have th' equipment that we need&amp;mdash;
The blood, the Word, the Spirit, and the church.</stanza>
	<stanza type="chorus" number="">Sisters:
Let's take the land! O Christian brothers,
The land that God has given us.
Be strong and take it, for we can make it
  And gain this land so glorious!
Brothers:
Let's take the land! O Christian sisters,
And to these things give earnest heed.
The Lord implores us; He's gone before us
  And given everything we need!</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="2">We have the blood! Christ is our spotless offering,
Who gave Himself, our God to satisfy;
And so we come with boldness to the throne of grace,
And all day long, the precious blood apply.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="3">We have the Word! The written Word's our daily food;
We mix this Word with faith and say "Amen!"
Then thro' the day, the spoken Word will speak to us
And regulate our living from within.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="4">The Spirit's ours! The Spirit of reality,
He's independent of the way we feel;
He dwells in us, and teaches us to dwell in Him,
And guides us into everything that's real.</stanza>
	<stanza type="verse" number="5">We have the church! All saints are needed to possess
The fullness of this vast reality;
Together we will gain this all-inclusive Christ,
And He to us our everything will be.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
