<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Come let us speak till the kingdom</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Preaching of the Gospel&amp;mdash;Speaking the Word</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="ts:857"/><dutch num="96"/><english num="1294"/><lsmyp num="268"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="">Adapted</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 0 - 0/ 5/ 6/ 7/ | ._1 6/ 5/ ._1/ ._1/ 6/ 5/ | ._1 6/ ._1/( ._1/) 5/ 6/ 7/ (break) | ._1 ._1/ ._1/ ._1/ ._1/ ._1/ ._1/ | ._2 7/ 5/( 5/) 5/ 6/ 7/ (break) | ._1( - ._1/) ._1/ 7/ 7b/ | 6 - - 6/ 6/ | 5/ 5/ 5/ 5/ 5/ 5/ 5/ 5/ | 5/( 6/) 7/ ._1 0. |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>Come let us speak till the king -- dom of the Lord comes down. Yes, let us speak till the king -- dom of the Lord comes down. Why hold your peace? The Word re -- lease. Let us speak un -- til the king -- dom of the Lord comes down.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midiref type="h" num="1293"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Come let us speak till the kingdom of the Lord comes down.
Yes, let us speak till the kingdom of the Lord comes down.
  Why hold your peace?
  The Word release.
Let us speak until the kingdom of the Lord comes down.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Oh, loose the Word! It shall not return unto Him void.
Yes, loose the Word! It shall not return unto Him void.
  Let's sow the seed,
  This is our need;
Loose the Word, and it shall not return unto Him void!</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">It's gospel time! Let us spread the gospel all around.
Yes, gospel time! We will never fear the people's frown!
  God's done His work;
  Let us not shirk;
We're but pilgrims here, and we'll not fear the people's frown!</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">If we will speak, Christ will witness in the hearts of men.
If we will speak, Christ will witness in the hearts of men.
  Tell every man,
  Win all we can.
Through our speaking, Christ is speaking in the hearts of men!</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">The harvest's ripe! We are preaching the full gospel now!
The fields are white! We are preaching the full gospel now!
  For this men search&amp;mdash;
  Christ and the church!
Let us reap the harvest, preaching the full gospel now!</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
