<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>At the end of Luke's gospel, chapter twenty and two</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Spiritual Warfare&amp;mdash;In the Body</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="ts:760"/><english num="1291"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="">Adapted</author>
  </creators>
  <melody>| 0 - - 5/ 5/ | 3/ 3 3/ 2/ 1/ 1/ 3/ | 5/ 5 3/ 5 5/ 5/ | 6/( ._1) 6/ 5/ 3/ 2/ 1/ (break) | 3/ 2 3/ 2 5/ 5/ | 3/ 3 3/ 2/ 1/ 1/ 3/ | 5 5 6 6/ 7/ | ._1/ ._1 6/ 5/ 3/ 2/ 1/ (break) | 3/ 3 2/ (.1 (Chorus) 5/ 5/ | ._1/ ._1 ._1/ 6/ 5/ 3/ 4/ | 5/ 5 6/ 5 5/ 5/ | ._1/ ._1 ._1/ 6/ 5/ 3/ 1/ (break) | 3/ 2 3/ 2 5/ 5/ | 3/ 3 3/ 2/ 1/ 1/ 3/ | 5 5 6 6/ 7/ | ._1/ ._1 6/ 5/ 3/ 2/ 1/ | 3/ 3 2/ 1 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>At the end of Luke's gos -- pel, chap -- ter twen -- ty and two, The Lord says to Pet -- er, "Sa -- tan wants to sift you, But the Lord's in -- ter -- ced -- ing and His prayer is true, Hal -- le -- lu -- jah! He's prayed for us, we'll nev -- er sift through! Though there's all kinds of bat -- tles in our liv -- ing each day, And we al -- ways face tri -- als, life is or -- dered that way, Still, in all si -- tu -- a -- tions, as He in -- ter -- cedes, He in all things sup -- plies us and meets all of our needs.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <links>
    <link type="group">hymnal-subj186.xml</link>
    <link type="ref">Luke 22:31-32</link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midiref type="h" num="1194"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">At the end of Luke's gospel, chapter twenty and two,
The Lord says to Peter, "Satan wants to sift you,
But the Lord's interceding and His prayer is true,
Hallelujah! He's prayed for us, we'll never sift through!</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">Though there's all kinds of battles in our living each day,
And we always face trials, life is ordered that way,
Still, in all situations, as He intercedes,
He in all things supplies us and meets all of our needs.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Just a Christian alone, however strong he may be
Cannot withstand the sifting of the Lord's enemy;
Though he might sift one only, yet he'll ne'er sift two,
Hallelujah! Together we're too big to sift through!</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">What a wonderful purpose God has purposed for us,
To be transformed and reigning with His Son, glorious;
So it just doesn't matter what the foe might do&amp;mdash;
Hallelujah! The church is much too big to sift through!</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
