<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Drawn into Your Sweet, Loving Self</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Gospel&amp;mdash;General</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="ts:819"/><english num="6819"/></numbers>
  <meter>Peculiar Meter.</meter>
  <hymncode>321211354611</hymncode>
  <key>D Major</key>
  <time>3/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - | C - - | C7 - - | F - - | F - - | C - - | G - - | C - - | G7 - - | C - - | C7 - - | F - - | F - - | C/G - - | G7 - - | C - - | C - - | C - - | C7 - - | F - - | F - - | C - - | G - - | C - - | G7 - - | C - - | C7 - - | F - - | F - - | C/G - - | G7 - - | C - F/C | C - - ||</chords>
  <melody>| 0 - 3/ 2/ | 1. 2/ 1 | 1 3 5 | 4 6 ._1 (break) | ._1 - 7/ 6/ | 5. 4/ 3 | 2. 1/ 2 | 3( - - (break) | 3) - 3/ 2/ | 1. 2/ 1 | 1 3 5 | 4 6 ._1 (break) | ._1 - 7/ 6/ | 5. ._1/ 3 | 2. 1/ 2 | 1( - - (break) | 1) - 5/ 5/ | 5 3 5 | ._1 - 5/ 5/ | 6 4 6 (break) | ._1 - 7/ 6/ | 5. 4/ 3 | 2. 1/ 2 | 3( - - (break) | 3) - 3/ 2/ | 1. 2/ 1 | 1 3 5 | 4 6 ._1 (break) | ._1 - 7/ 6/ | 5. ._1/ 3 | 2. 1/ 2 | 1( - - | 1) - 0 ||</melody>
  <layout>
	<singingstanza>O -- ver hill, o -- ver val -- ley, we searched, but in vain, For the mean -- ing of our hu -- man life; We were just dis -- ap -- point -- ed a -- gain and a -- gain, Till we felt there was noth -- ing to find. But then one day You came, meet -- ing us in the way, And Your lov -- ing em -- brace did sur -- round; We were ful -- ly drawn in -- to Your sweet, lov -- ing self; The true mean -- ing of life we had found.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midi location="h" length="58">e6819_i.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Over hill, over valley, we searched, but in vain,
For the meaning of our human life;
We were just disappointed again and again,
Till we felt there was nothing to find.
But then one day You came, meeting us in the way,
And Your loving embrace did surround;
We were fully drawn into Your sweet, loving self;
The true meaning of life we had found.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">As we gaze, Your bright face risen glory displays,
But we know it was once topped with thorns;
To Your hands sweet and gracious we'll cling all our days,
In which nail prints are still clearly borne.
We're enjoying You here, Lord most loving and dear,
Daily sensing more reality;
As the water from rivers returns to the sea,
We are lost, more and more, Lord, in Thee.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
