<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>God, You are now rearranging my way</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Longings&amp;mdash;For Obedience to God</category>
  <numbers><chinese num="273"/><english num="8273"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="1903-1972" biolink="">Translated from Watchman Nee</author>
  </creators>
  <meter>10.10.10.10.D.</meter>
  <hymncode>3123211765</hymncode>
  <key>F Major</key>
  <time>6/8</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C. C7. | F. C. | C. Am. | D7. G. | C. C/E. | F - - | F. C/G. | G7. C. | C. C7/E. | F. Dm. | Em. Am. | D7. G. | C. C7/E. | F. D7/F#. | C/G. Am. | F G7/ C. |</chords>
  <melody>| 3/ 1/ 2/ 3/ 2/ 1/ | 1/ 7_./ 6_./ 5_.. | 5_./ 1/ 2/ 3/ 4/ 3/ | 3/ 2/ 1/ 2. (break) | 3/ 1/ 2/ 3/ 2#/ 3/ | 5/ 4/ 3/ 4 1/ | 1/ 7_./ 6_./ 5_./ 1/ 3/ | 2./ 1// 2/ 1. | (Chorus) 5/ 3/ 4/ 5/ 3/ 2/ | 1/ 7_./ 1/ 2/ 1/ 6_./ | 5_./ 1/ 2/ 3/ 4/ 3/ | 3./ 2// 1/ 2. (break) | 5/ 3/ 4/ 5/ 3/ 2/ | 1/ 7_./ 1/ 2/ 1/ 6_./ | 5_./ 1/ 2/ 3/ 4/ 3/ | 3 2/ 1. |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>God, You are now re -- ar -- rang -- ing my way. All I have built You're des -- troy -- ing to -- day. Those serv -- ing faith -- ful -- ly dai -- ly de -- crease. Dis -- hon -- est -- y, mis -- un -- der -- stand -- ings in -- crease. My eyes are tear -- y; I can't see You clear -- ly, As though all Your words aren't as real as be -- fore. You make me de -- crease, that You might thus in -- crease, To make Your will sweet -- er than e'er be -- fore.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midi location="h" length="48">e8273_i.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">God, You are now rearranging my way.
All I have built You're destroying today.
Those serving faithfully daily decrease.
Dishonesty, misunderstandings increase.</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">My eyes are teary; I can't see You clearly,
As though all Your words aren't as real as before.
You make me decrease, that You might thus increase,
To make Your will sweeter than e'er before.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">For Your hand stopping I'd almost implore,
When I feel I cannot take any more.
Yet You are God! Oh, how can You give way?
Please, Lord, do not give in; wait 'till I obey.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">If Your good pleasure and will should decree
That I must take suff'ring's yoke upon me,
Then may my heart's deepest joy be this thing&amp;mdash;
Obeying Your will to take the suffering.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">It seems the price that's required for Your joy
Is that I'm hindered and knocked down by You;
Therefore I'd welcome Your hindering pull,
If thus I could cause Your heart to be joyful.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">You've given chariots to others instead.
You have made them thus to ride o'er my head.
You stretch Your hand out my all now to take,
Yet please leave Your stripping hand here for my sake.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
