<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>I'm a beggar 'cause... I'm blind</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Gospel&amp;mdash;Light</category>
  <numbers><english num="ns:171"/><vsb num="3"/></numbers>
  <hymncode>33321423332167</hymncode>
  <key>Eb Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>100</tempo>
  <chords>| C - Em - | F - G7 - | C - Em - | F - G7 - | C - Dm - | F - G7 - | C - Am - | F - G7 - | C - Em - | F - G7 - | C - Em - | Dm7 - G7 - | C - G/B - | F/A - G7 - | C - Em - | F - G7 - |</chords>
  <melody>| 3 3 3/ 2/ 1( | 1) 4 2 - | 3 3 3/ 2/ 1( | 1) 6_. 7_. - (break) | 1 1/ 1/ 2/ 2/ 2( | 2) 4 2 - | 3 3 3/ 3/ 3( | 3) 4 5 - (break) | 5 - 5 5 | 6 5 5 - | 0 5 5 5 | {4 4 3} 2 - (break) | 0 3/ 3/ 2 2 | 1 1/ 1/ 2/ 1/ 7_./ 7_./ | 1( - - - | 1) - - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>I'm a beg -- gar 'cause... I'm blind So I take what I... can find I'm grop -- ing for re -- a... li -- ty On -- ly wish -- ing I... could see My par -- ents, they can see Why is this blind -- ness in me? All I know is I want to see re -- al -- i -- ty.</singingstanza>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midi location="ns" length="33">ns0171.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">I'm a beggar 'cause... I'm blind
So I take what I... can find
I'm groping for rea...lity
Only wishing I... could see
My parents, they can see
Why is this blindness in me?
All I know is I want to see reality.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Lord, I am sitting by... the road
Begging outside of Je...richo
Now, Lord I hear that You... pass by
Lord, Son of David... I cry
Lord, Son of David, I cry
Please, Christ, don't pass me by
I believe that you can open my eyes.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">You gave me life but where's... my sight?
I am still blind and that's... my plight
Blind lead the blind and then... both fall
So right now on You... I call
Jesus have mercy on me
Open my eyes that I might see
All I know is my only hope is in You.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">Lord I am rebuked by... the crowd
For You I cry out more... the loud
All the world wants to di...stract me
So I forget that I... can't see
Jesus don't leave me behind
You are the one I want to find
All I know is I just really need You.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="5">Still I'm afraid that You'll... go on
But joyful ears hear You... respond
What would you like for me... to do
Oh Christ I just want to see You
Open my eyes to... see You
Let me find what my spirit can do
All I know is I just want to see You.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="6">In my spirit I... can see
Because that's where You... touch me
By your touch dear Lord... I'm healed
All my sin and death... must yield
Now Lord, I am healed
In my spirit You are so real
All I know is I want to keep touching You.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="7">Lord my sight is for... one thing
So that I to You... can cling
I think I'm in love... with You
No one else for me... will do
Lord Christ let me follow You please
You're so real and so special to me
All I know is Lord I never want to leave.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
