<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>God's economy and His eternal plan</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Ultimate Manifestation&amp;mdash;God's Eternal Purpose</category>
  <numbers><english num="ns:181"/><vsb num="57"/></numbers>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Glenn Hwaung">G. H.</author>
    <composer biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Glenn Hwaung">G. H.</composer>
  </creators>
  <hymncode>55555554432</hymncode>
  <key>E Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>130</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - - | Em - - - | F - - - | G - - - | C - - - | Em - - - | F - - - | G - - C/E | F - - - | C - - - | E - E7/G# - | Am - C/G - | F - - - | C/E - - - | Dm - Dm7/F - | G - G7 - | C - - - | Em - - - | F - - - | G - - - | C - - - | Em - - - | F - - - | G - - C/E | F - - - | C - - - | E - E7/G# - | Am - C/G - | F - - - | C/E - - - | Dm - Dm7/F - | G - G7 - | C - - - | F/C - - - | C - - - | Em - - - | F - - - | G - - - | C - - - | Am - - - | Dm7 - - - | G7 - - - | C - - - | Em - - - | F - - - | G - - - | C - - - | Am - - - | Dm - Dm7/F - | G - G7 - | C - - - | F/C - - - | C - - - | Em - - - | F - - - | G - - - | C - - - | Em - - - | F - - - | G - - C/E | F - - - | C - - - | E - E7/G# - | Am - C/G - | F - - - | C/E - - - | Dm - Dm7/F - | G - G7 - | C - - - | Em - - - | F - - - | G - - - | C - - - | Em - - - | F - - - | G - - C/E | F - - - | C - - - | E - E7/G# - | Am - C/G - | F - - - | C/E - - - | Dm - Dm7/F - | G - G7 - | C - F/C - | C - - - |</chords>
  <melody>| (Verse_1) 5 5/ 5/( 5) 5 | 5 - - 5 | 5 4/ 4/( 4) 3 | 2 - - 1 | 5 5/ 5/( 5) 5/ 6/ | 6 5 - 5 | 4 4/ 6/( 6) 5 | 5 - - 1 | 6 6 6 6 | 5 3 - 3 | 3 4 3 2 | 1 - - 1 | 1 1/ 1/( 1) 2 | 1 5_./ 5_./( 5_.) 5_. | 1 1/ 1/( 1/)( 2/) 3 (break) | 2 - (Verse_2) 3 4 | 5 5 5 6 | 6 5 - 5/ 5/ | 5/ 4/ 4 4/ 4/ 3 | 2 - 3/ 3/ 4 | 5 - 5 6 | 6( 5) - 5 | 4 4/ 6/( 6) 5 | 5 - - 1 | 6 6 6 6 | 5 3 3 3 | 3 4 3 2 | 1 - - - | 1 1/ 1/( 1) 2 | 1 5_./ 5_./( 5_.) 5_. | 4 - 3 - | 2 - - 1 | 1( - - - | 1) - - 0 (break) | (Chorus) 5 - - - | 5 - 5 - | 6 - 5 - | 5 3 3 4 | 0 - 5 6 | 3 2/ 1/( 1) 3 | 4 - 3 - | 2 - - 1 | 5 - - 5 | 5 - 5 5 | 6 6/ 6/( 6) 5 | 5 - 3 4 | 5 - 5 6 | 3 2/ 1/( 1) 3 | 4 - 3 - | 2 - - 1 | 1( - - - (break) | 1) - (Verse_3) 3 4 | 5 5 5 6/ 6/( | 6) 5 - 5/ 5/ | 5/ 4/ 4/ 4/ 4/ 3. | 2 - 3 4 | 5 5/ 5/( 5) 6 | 6 5 - 5 | 4 4/ 6/( 6) 5 | 5 - - 1 | 6 6 6 6 | 5 3/ 3/( 3) 3 | 3 4 3 2 | 1 - - 1/ 1/ | 1 1/ 1/( 1) 2 | 1 5_./ 5_./( 5_.) 5_. | 1 1/ 1/( 1/)( 2/) 3 (break) | 2 - (Verse_4) 3 4 | 5 5 5 6 | 6 5 - 5 | 5 4/ 4/( 4) 3 | 2 - - 1 | 5 5/ 5/( 5) 6 | 6 5 - 5 | 4 4/ 6/( 6) 5 | 5 - - 1 | 6 6 6 6 | 5 - - 3 | 3 4 3 2 | 1 - - 1 | 1 1/ 1/( 1) 2 | 1 5_. - 5_. | 4 - 3 - | 2 2/ 1/( 1) 7_. | 1( - - - | 1) - - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza end="-1">God's e -- con -- o -- my and His e -- ter -- nal plan, His heart's de -- sire and in -- ten -- tion is to be one with man. Yet man has failed com -- plete -- ly through -- out all his -- to -- ry. But hal -- le -- lu -- jah! Praise the Lord! God's life is now in me. Now this life in me is flow -- ing as the riv -- er of wa -- ter of life, Wash -- ing a -- way all my sins, my cares, and all my strife. This life is o -- ver -- com -- ing si -- tu -- a -- tions in my day. Hal -- le -- lu -- jah! Praise the Lord! For this is what I pray: Lord Je -- sus, I love You! I give You the pre -- em -- i -- nence in what I do. En -- joy -- ing You is the o -- ver -- com -- ing way. Thank You for Your re -- cov -- er -- y; Your Word we will o -- bey. Thank You for our si -- tu -- a -- tions and the en -- vi -- ron -- ments we are in. That we'd turn to You in all things, and turn a -- way from sin. We'd drop all our anx -- i -- e -- ties and put our trust in You. And ex -- pe -- ri -- ence this liv -- ing One whose life is ev -- er new. Now the church life is so pre -- cious with all the saints so dear. En -- joy -- ing all Your rich -- es, our vi -- sion is so clear, That all would proph -- e -- sy of Christ from what they've seen, Ac -- cord -- ing to Your scrip -- ture in First Co -- rin -- thi -- ans four -- teen.</singingstanza>
    <globalstaffsize>13.5</globalstaffsize>
    <topmargin>0.25</topmargin>
    <bottommargin>0.25</bottommargin>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midi location="ns" length="158">ns0181.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">God's economy and His eternal plan,
His heart's desire and intention is to be one with man.
Yet man has failed completely throughout all history.
But hallelujah! Praise the Lord! God's life is now in me.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Now this life in me is flowing as the river of water of life,
Washing away all my sins, my cares, and all my strife.
This life is overcoming situations in my day.
Hallelujah! Praise the Lord! For this is what I pray:</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">Lord Jesus, I love You!
I give You the preeminence in what I do.
Enjoying You is the overcoming way.
Thank You for Your recovery; Your Word we will obey.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">Thank You for our situations and the environments we are in.
That we'd turn to You in all things, and turn away from sin.
We'd drop all our anxieties and put our trust in You.
And experience this living One whose life is ever new.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">Now the church life is so precious with all the saints so dear.
Enjoying all Your riches, our vision is so clear,
That all would prophesy of Christ from what they've seen,
According to Your scripture in First Corinthians fourteen.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
