<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>There are three kinds of life in our existence today</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Various Aspects of the Inner Life&amp;mdash;The Three Lives</category>
  <numbers><english num="ns:208"/><vsb num="119"/></numbers>
  <melody>| 0 - - 5/ 5/ | 3/ 3 3/ 2/ 1/ 1/ 3/ | 5/ 5 3/ 5 5/ 5/ | 6/ ._1 6/ 5/ 3/ 2/ 1/ | 3/ 2 3/ 2 5/ 5/ (break) | 3/ 3 3/ 2/ 1/ 1/ 3/ | 5 5 6 6/ 7/ | ._1/ ._1 6/ 5/ 3/ 2/ 1/ (break) | 3/ 3 2/ (.1 (Chorus) 5/ 5/ | ._1/ ._1 ._1/ 6/ 5/ 3/ 4/ | 5/ 5 6/ 5 5/ 5/ (break) | ._1/ ._1 ._1/ 6/ 5/ 3/ 1/ | 3/ 2 3/ 2 5/ 5/ (break) | 3/ 3 3/ 2/ 1/ 1/ 3/ | 5 5 6 6/ 7/ | ._1/ ._1 6/ 5/ 3/ 2/ 1/ | 3/ 3 2/ 1 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>There are three kinds of life in our ex -- is -- tence to -- day: There is Bi -- os, the phy -- si -- cal, and soul- -- life, Psu -- che; Now the third life is God's life and its called Zo -- e; And we all have to choose what life we'll live by to -- day. Oh, it's God in Christ Je -- sus, through the Spir -- it to -- day, Who is flow -- ing with -- in us, flow -- ing through us this way. We don't care for the Bi -- os; we don't want Psu -- che; All we want is God's Zo -- e life to fill us to -- day.</singingstanza>
  </layout>
  <music>
    <midiref type="h" num="1194"/>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">There are three kinds of life in our existence today:
There is Bios, the physical, and soul-life, Psuche;
Now the third life is God's life and its called Zoe;
And we all have to choose what life we'll live by today.</stanza>
    <stanza type="chorus" number="">Oh, it's God in Christ Jesus, through the Spirit today,
Who is flowing within us, flowing through us this way.
We don't care for the Bios; we don't want Psuche;
All we want is God's Zoe life to fill us today.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">We don't care for the Bios, we don't care for the soul.
We don't care for the cares of life, world's pleasure and show.
We don't care for the pride of life, the flesh and sin&amp;mdash;
We say, "No!" to the soul life, we'll take God's life within.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">Do you know what God's life is? Well, just listen to this:
It is God in Christ Jesus through the Spirit&amp;mdash;no less!
He is flowing within us, He is flowing through&amp;mdash;
Hallelujah! He's moving to make everything new.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">We have this Life within us, in our spirit today;
To our spirit we turn, O Lord, and take You this way.
We can overcome Bios and the Psuche too;
Hallelujah, the Spirit of the Lord takes us through.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
