<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hymn xmlns="http://www.hymnal.net/hymn">
  <title>Lord Jesus, I long in Thy presence to live</title>
  <index>true</index>
  <category>Longings&amp;mdash;For Living in the Lord's Presence</category>
  <creators>
    <author biodate="1903-1972" biolink="www.watchmannee.org">Watchman Nee</author>
    <composer biodate="" biolink="" fullname="Eric Ching">E. C.</composer>
  </creators>
  <hymncode>55554434523</hymncode>
  <key>D Major</key>
  <time>4/4</time>
  <tempo>110</tempo>
  <chords>| C - - - | C - - - | Dm - G7 - | C - - - | C - - - | F - - - | G7 - - - | C - - - | C7 - - - | F - - - | G - - - | Em - E/G# - | Am - C/G - | F - - - | Dm7 - - - | G - - - | G7 - C/E - | F - - - | G - - - | C - Em - | Am - C/G - | F - - - | G7 - - - | C - G7/D - | C/E - C7 - | F - - - | G - G7/F - | C/E - - - | F - C/E - | Dm - - - | G7 - - - | F/C - - - | C - - - |</chords>
  <melody>| 0 - - 0/ 5/ | 5 5 - 5 | 4 4/ 3/ 4/ 5/( 5/) 2/ | 3( - - - | 3) - - 0/ 1/ | 6 6/ 6/ 6/ 6 6/ | 6 5 - 4 | 3( - - - (break) | 3) - 0/ 3/ 4/ 5/ | 6 6 6 6 | 6/ 5/ 5/ 5/( 5) - | 3 4 3 2 | 2 1 - - | 1 - - 2 | 1 - 3 2( | 2)( - - - (break) | 2) - - 0/ 1/ | 6 6 - 6 | 6( 5) - - | 3 3 3/ 5/( 5/) 3/ | 1 - - 0/ 1/ | 6 6 - 6 | 6( 5) - 4 | 3 3 3 4 | 5 - - 0/ 1/ | 6 6 - 6 | 6 7 - 7 | ._1 - ._1 5 | 6 - 0/ 1/ 2/ 3/ | 3 4/ 2/( 2) - | 0 3/ 2/ 1 7_. | 1( - - - | 1) - - 0 |</melody>
  <layout>
    <singingstanza>Lord Je -- sus, I long in Thy pre -- sence to live, From morn -- ing to eve -- ning my one world Thou art; O let not my heart be con -- tent -- ed or rest When lov -- ing or seek -- ing what with Thee doth part. Each mo -- ment, each day, through -- out suf -- f'ring and pain, When nought in the world can give com -- fort or cheer, When sigh -- ing and weep -- ing en -- com -- pass -- es me, Lord, still all my sigh -- ing and wipe ev -- ery tear.</singingstanza>
    <columns>2</columns>
  </layout>
  <date>June, 2002</date>
  <links>
    <link type="relevant" category="h" num="389"></link>
  </links>
  <music>
    <midi location="nt" length="71">e0389_new.mid</midi>
  </music>
  <lyrics>
    <stanza type="verse" number="1">Lord Jesus, I long in Thy presence to live,
From morning to evening my one world Thou art;
O let not my heart be contented or rest
When loving or seeking what with Thee doth part.
Each moment, each day, throughout suff'ring and pain,
When nought in the world can give comfort or cheer,
When sighing and weeping encompasses me,
Lord, still all my sighing and wipe every tear.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="2">Each time when I dream of the goodness of life,
I pray Thee, dear Lord, that Thou in it may be;
O do not allow me to choose by myself,
Nor seek any pleasure that's other than Thee.
Each night when alone in the stillness I lie,
I pray Thee, Lord Jesus, that Thou wilt be near;
Each morning ere dawn comes, while still in my sleep,
Then whispering call me and open my ear.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="3">Each time, Lord, when reading in Thy holy Word,
I pray that Thy glory may shine on each line,
That clearly I'll see what a Savior I have
And how great salvation that Thou hast made mine.
When helpless I come, Lord, to kneel at Thy throne,
I pray Thee to hear me and grant me Thy grace;
If thru my shortcomings Thou hear not my prayer,
Withdraw not Thy presence, O hide not Thy face.</stanza>
    <stanza type="verse" number="4">Each time when of heavenly blessings I think,
O let my heart long to be raptured to Thee;
My only hope here is Thy coming again,
My only joy there, Lord, Thy presence will be.
Lord, teach me each day in Thy presence to live,
From morning to evening my one world Thou art;
O let not my heart be contented or rest
When loving or seeking what with Thee doth part.</stanza>
  </lyrics>
</hymn>
